<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-18075</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034417</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary genetics</subject>
              <subject>Paleontology</subject>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Haplotypes</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Paleontology</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Population biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Earth sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Paleontology</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Paleoanthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ancient DNA from Hunter-Gatherer and Farmer Groups from Northern Spain Supports a Random Dispersion Model for the Neolithic Expansion into Europe</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Neolithisation in Northern Spain</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hervella</surname>
            <given-names>Montserrat</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Izagirre</surname>
            <given-names>Neskuts</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Alonso</surname>
            <given-names>Santos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Fregel</surname>
            <given-names>Rosa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Alonso</surname>
            <given-names>Antonio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cabrera</surname>
            <given-names>Vicente M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>de la Rúa</surname>
            <given-names>Concepción</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Genetics, Physical Anthropology and Animal Physiology, University of the Basque Country, Bizkaia, Spain</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Genetics, University of La Laguna, La Laguna, Santa Cruz de Tenerife, Spain</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Biology, National Institute of Toxicology and Forensic Sciences, Madrid, Spain</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hofreiter</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of York, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">conchi.delarua@ehu.es</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MH NI SA RF AA VMC CR. Performed the experiments: MH NI SA RF AA VMC CR. Analyzed the data: MH NI SA RF AA VMC CR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MH NI SA RF AA VMC CR. Wrote the paper: MH NI SA RF AA VMC CR.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e34417</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hervella et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background/Principal Findings</title>
          <p>The phenomenon of Neolithisation refers to the transition of prehistoric populations from a hunter-gatherer to an agro-pastoralist lifestyle. Traditionally, the spread of an agro-pastoralist economy into Europe has been framed within a dichotomy based either on an acculturation phenomenon or on a demic diffusion. However, the nature and speed of this transition is a matter of continuing scientific debate in archaeology, anthropology, and human population genetics. In the present study, we have analyzed the mitochondrial DNA diversity in hunter-gatherers and first farmers from Northern Spain, in relation to the debate surrounding the phenomenon of Neolithisation in Europe.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methodology/Significance</title>
          <p>Analysis of mitochondrial DNA was carried out on 54 individuals from Upper Paleolithic and Early Neolithic, which were recovered from nine archaeological sites from Northern Spain (Basque Country, Navarre and Cantabria). In addition, to take all necessary precautions to avoid contamination, different authentication criteria were applied in this study, including: DNA quantification, cloning, duplication (51% of the samples) and replication of the results (43% of the samples) by two independent laboratories. Statistical and multivariate analyses of the mitochondrial variability suggest that the genetic influence of Neolithisation did not spread uniformly throughout Europe, producing heterogeneous genetic consequences in different geographical regions, rejecting the traditional models that explain the Neolithisation in Europe.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The differences detected in the mitochondrial DNA lineages of Neolithic groups studied so far (including these ones of this study) suggest different genetic impact of Neolithic in Central Europe, Mediterranean Europe and the Cantabrian fringe. The genetic data obtained in this study provide support for a random dispersion model for Neolithic farmers. This random dispersion had a different impact on the various geographic regions, and thus contradicts the more simplistic total acculturation and replacement models proposed so far to explain Neolithisation.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was partly supported by grants CGL-2004-03300, CGL-2007-65515, and a FPI pre-doctoral fellowship for MH (BES-2005-6925) from the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation; and grant IT542-10 from the Basque Government for Research Groups in the Basque University System. No additional external funding received for this study. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The phenomenon of Neolithisation refers to the transition from a hunter-gatherer way of life to an agro-pastoralist lifestyle, involving crop farming and livestock herding. There is consensus on the origin of the agro-pastoralist lifestyle associated with the Neolithic in the Near East, from where it spread throughout Europe. Yet, there is no such agreement on the mechanisms and means of transmission of farming to Europe. Traditionally, the spread of crop farming and livestock herding in Europe during the Neolithic has been framed within a dichotomy based either on an acculturation phenomenon or on a demic diffusion process.</p>
      <p>The demic diffusion model describes a migratory process based on a population expansion from the Near East into Europe, whose consequence was the assimilation of the genetic pool of the indigenous hunter-gatherer groups by the expanding of the farming community <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Ammerman1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Sokal1">[6]</xref>. On the other hand, the acculturation model posits that this transition occurred through the adoption of the agro-pastoralist system by local indigenous groups, without receiving any genetic input <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Dennell1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards1">[9]</xref>. Between these two models there are others that suggest a varying intensity of the genetic impact from the Neolithic farming communities that spread throughout Europe from the Near East <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards2">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Zvelebil1">[11]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The analysis of the genetic composition of present-day populations in Europe and the Near East, has tried to establish the origin of their extant genetic variability. Based on classical genetic markers, Ammerman and Cavalli-Sforza <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Ammerman1">[1]</xref>, proposed the wave-of-advance model, whereby the demic diffusion from the Near East towards Europe contributed to the genetic composition of present-day populations. Nevertheless, based on modern European patterns of mitochondrial diversity, Richards et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards1">[9]</xref> argued that this mitochondrial diversity had a predominantly Paleolithic origin, with a small Neolithic contribution (12%), which would favour the cultural diffusion model. Subsequent studies applying new methodologies have allowed quantifying the contribution of Neolithic farmers to the genetic pool of present-day European populations at 23% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards3">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards4">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Several studies on the variability of the non-recombining region of the Y chromosome (NRY) have detected the presence of a southeast-northwest gradient in Eurasia, which has been interpreted as the genetic fingerprint of Neolithic expansion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Rosser1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Semino1">[15]</xref>. A recent analysis of the variability of the Y chromosome in more than 2,500 samples taken from present-day European population revealed that, the diversity of haplogroup R1b1b2 (the most common one in Europe) is best explained by the spread from a single source in the Near East via Anatolia during the Neolithic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Balaresque1">[16]</xref>. This proposal contradicts prior studies, which consider this haplogroup to be a marker of the Mesolithic re-expansion from the glacial refuge in the Franco-Cantabrian region, the Balkans and the Alps <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Rosser1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Semino1">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The analysis of the DNA recovered from ancient human remains has highlighted a more complex pattern than the one revealed by the studies of contemporary populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Alzualde1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Fregel2">[22]</xref> (amongst others). Studies hitherto conducted on ancient DNA (aDNA) from European Neolithic populations indicate two routes to explain the Neolithic dispersion to Europe: one, supporting an acculturation model that followed a route of dispersion through the North-Central Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak2">[23]</xref>, and a second one, supporting a demic diffusion model through a Mediterranean route <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Sampietro1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Lacan1">[25]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Ancient DNA studies of hunter-gatherers from Scandinavia and Central Europe have pointed to a genetic discontinuity between hunter-gatherer and Neolithic populations in these two geographic regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Malmstrm1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Bramanti1">[27]</xref>. The analysis of mtDNA in the first Neolithic farmers of Central Europe (7.5–7 kya) showed a high frequency of haplogroup N1a (15%), which is rarely found in present-day populations (0.2%) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak2">[23]</xref>. On the other hand, these first farmers showed a genetic affinity with the present-day populations from the Near East and Anatolia, supporting a major genetic input from this area during the advent of farming in Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak2">[23]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The mtDNA analysis from the Neolithic site of the Iberian Mediterranean region named, “<italic>Camí de Can Grau</italic>” in Catalonia (5.5–5 kya), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Sampietro1">[24]</xref> has provided results that are different to those published by Haak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak2">[23]</xref>. The absence of haplogroup N1a and the presence of mitochondrial lineages typical of present-day populations from this European Mediterranean area, led Sampietro et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Sampietro1">[24]</xref> to propose a demic diffusion only in Mediterranean area of Europe.</p>
      <p>Likewise, the combined analysis of the mtDNA and NRY variability in 29 individuals from a French Mediterranean region, named “<italic>Cave I of Treilles</italic>” in Aveyron, (5 kya), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Lacan1">[25]</xref> reaffirmed the aforementioned proposal, based mainly on the absence of the mitochondrial haplogoup N1a and the R1b of the NRY, considered Neolithic dispersion markers through Central Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Balaresque1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak2">[23]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In view of the debate surrounding the phenomenon of Neolithisation in Europe, we have carried out a genetic analysis of Paleolithic hunter-gatherer and Neolithic samples recovered from nine sites in the North of the Iberian Peninsula (Basque Country, Navarre and Cantabria), whose chronologies date from the Upper Paleolithic through to the Bronze Age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t001">Table 1</xref>). The aim of this study is to explain the Neolithisation process along the Iberian Cantabrian fringe within the context of European populations.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0034417-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Geographic location of the ancient human remains analysed in the present study.</title>
          <p>All sites are located in the North of the Iberian Peninsula.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0034417-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>Chronology, subsistence pattern and geographical origin of the prehistoric samples analysed in the present study.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0034417-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SITES</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NOMENCLATURE</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SUBSISTENCE PATTERN</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CHRONOLOGY</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MNI</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">REFERENCES</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">La Pasiega (Cantabria)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PS</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hunter-Gathering(<bold>HG_CANT</bold>)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper Paleolithic (Magdalenian)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-GonzlezEchegaray1">[44]</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">La Chora (Cantabria)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hunter-Gathering (<bold>HG_CANT</bold>)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper Paleolithic (Magdalenian)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-GonzlezEchegaray2">[45]</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Erralla (Gipuzkoa)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ERR</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hunter-Gathering (<bold>HG_CANT</bold>)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Upper Paleolithic (Magdalenian) (12,310 BP)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-delaRa1">[46]</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aizpea (Navarre)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AZ</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hunter-Gathering (<bold>HG_CANT</bold>)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mesolithic (6,600±65 BP)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-delaRa2">[47]</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Los Cascajos (Navarre)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Early Neolithic farming (<bold>NEO_NAVARRE</bold>)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neolithic (6,185–5,185 BP)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-GarcaGazlaz1">[48]</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paternanbidea (Navarre)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAT</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Early Neolithic farming (<bold>NEO_NAVARRE</bold>)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neolithic (6,090−5,960 BP)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-GarcaGazlaz2">[49]</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marizulo (Gipuzkoa)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MZ</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neolithic farming</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neolithic (5,285 BP)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Basabe1">[50]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Alday1">[51]</xref></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fuente Hoz (Álava)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FH</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neolithic farming</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neolithic (5,240–5,160 BP)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Basabe2">[52]</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urtiaga (Gipuzkoa)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">URT</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wild and domestic resources</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bronze Age (3,475−3,430 BP)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Altuna1">[53]</xref>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p>Minimal number of individuals at each sites (MNI), number of individuals analysed (N).</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Authenticity of the results</title>
        <p>We have successfully analyzed 49 out of 54 individuals recovered from the nine prehistoric sites analyzed in the present study; four sites correspond to hunter-gatherer groups (La Chora, La Pasiega, Erralla and Aizpea), another four to the Neolithic period (Los Cascajos, Paternanbidea, Marizulo and Fuente Hoz) and the last one to the Bronze Age (Urtiaga). Out of these 49 individuals, 30 (61% of the individuals) were analysed in duplicate in our laboratory; in addition, a third sample from each of 22 individuals (44% of the individuals) was replicated at an independent laboratory (some in the University of La Laguna and others in the INTCF of Madrid, Spain).</p>
        <p>The number of molecular targets (mtDNA copy number) was quantified for each extract by means of quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR). The results showed that the number of molecules per μl in the extracts ranged between 100–12,000 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s001">Table S1</xref>). These values are within the limits proposed for reproducibility in aDNA studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Handt1">[28]</xref>.</p>
        <p>In addition, a total of 69 PCR products from 49 individuals were cloned. A minimum of ten clones per PCR product were amplified and sequenced. The results were used to determine the coincidence between the consensus sequence obtained from the clones and the sequence obtained by direct sequencing of the initial PCR product. A mean of 4.20 mutations per fragment cloned (∼100 bp) were rejected, as these mutations were found in single clones, possibly as consequence of post-mortem damage to the aDNA molecules (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s002">Table S2</xref>).</p>
        <p>In order to identify any possible contamination that might have occurred in the different stages of the laboratory work, at least two extraction controls and several PCR negative controls were included in each amplification. If any contamination was detected, the results obtained were discarded.</p>
        <p>Finally, the mtDNA HVR-I segment from the researchers and archaeologists that handled the samples was sequenced in order to rule out any possible contamination (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s003">Table S3</xref>). A comparison between the haplotypes of the researchers/archaeologists and those obtained in the aDNA samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">Table 2</xref>) produced two cases of coincidence, one with the rCRS haplotype, which is the most frequent one in European populations, and the other with haplogoup K (ht18: 92-224-311), which is widely present not only throughout the whole of the Iberian Peninsula <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Crespillo1">[29]</xref> and the Canary Islands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-MacaMeyer1">[30]</xref>, but also Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards3">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards4">[13]</xref> and North Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Rando1">[31]</xref>. HVR-II sequencing was performed on those prehistoric samples that coincided with the haplotypes of the researchers and/or archaeologists in order to discard a complete coincidence between them.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Analysis of mtDNA variability in the prehistoric samples</title>
        <p>We have successfully analyzed 49 individuals from nine prehistoric sites and obtained 25 different mitochondrial haplotypes belonging to eight mitochondrial haplogroups (H, U, K, J, HV, I, T and X) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">Table 2</xref>). Haplogroup H is the major one, showing a frequency of 45% in the ancient samples analysed. This figure is similar to that observed in some present-day European populations including the North of the Iberian Peninsula <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards4">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Larruga1">[32]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Pereira1">[34]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The second most frequent haplogroup was haplogroup U (34.7%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">Table 2</xref>), being the Neolithic populations of Navarre (Los Cascajos and Paternanbidea) the ones that showed the highest frequencies for this haplogroup (29.6% and 11.1%, respectively). A special mention should be made of sub-haplogroup U5, as it is one of the oldest found in Europe (∼36.9 kya), and has been linked to the colonisation of Europe by anatomically modern <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (AMHS) in the Early Upper Paleolithic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards4">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Achilli2">[35]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Soares2">[37]</xref>. The average frequency of U5 in the present study was 12%, considering hunter-gatherer samples (Erralla and Aizpea), Neolithic samples (Los Cascajos and Marizulo) and the Bronze Age sample (Urtiaga) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>Haplogroup J exhibited a frequency of 4.08% in the samples analysed, being found in two individuals from Los Cascajos, with two different haplotypes: ht7 and ht12 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>Finally, haplogroup K was only found in the Neolithic sites of Navarre (Los Cascajos and Paternanbidea), showing an average frequency of 8.2%. All the other haplogroups (HV, I, T and X) had a frequency of around 2% each, with haplogroups HV and I being only found in Paternanbidea, and haplogroups T and X in Los Cascajos (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0034417-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>Distribution of the frequencies (%) of the mtDNA haplotypes (HT) and haplogroups (HG) obtained in the prehistoric samples from the present work (see nomenclature in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t001">Table 1</xref>).</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0034417-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAMPLES</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HT</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HVS-I-II</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HG</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-21</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-33; CAS-182; CAS-497; PAT-1E3; PAT-2E1; FH-6; URT-1; PS-1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rCRS</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.163</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-48, CAS-90, CAS-196</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73-146-263-285-309.1C-310.1T-312-313</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.061</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-173; CAS-222; CAS-341</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16129</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.061</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-194; CAS-193S</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht11</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16311</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.041</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAT-1E4, PAT-4E2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht16</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16209</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.041</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAT-1E5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16092-16311</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FH-3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht23</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16093</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CH-1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht24</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16093-16362</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-70; CAS-216; CAS-254; CAS-258; PAT-1E1; FH-1; FH-4; FH-5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73-146-263-285-309.1-310.1-312-313</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.163</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-148</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16278-16311</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-204</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht13</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16270-16311</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ERR-1; MZ-1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht21</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16270</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.041</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FH-2; URT-2;</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht22</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16192-16270</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.041</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U5a</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-183</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16163</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-517</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht15</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16365</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AIZ-1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht25</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16051-16093-16189-16192-1270</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U5b1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.69</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-181; CAS-191; CAS-202</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16224-16311</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.061</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">K1a</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAT-2E2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht18</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16092-16224-16311</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">K</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.163</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-179</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16069-16126-16195</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">J</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-203</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16069-16129</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">J</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.082</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAT-3E2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht19</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16311</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HV</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.041</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAT-4E1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht20</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16129-16233</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.041</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-180</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16126-16294-16296</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">T2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.041</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAS-257</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ht14</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16183-16189-16233-16278</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.041</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>rCRS: revised Cambridge Reference Sequence</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Statistical and multivariate analysis of the mitochondrial variability of prehistoric populations</title>
        <p>The prehistoric populations analysed in this study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t001">Table 1</xref>) were compared with other present-day populations from the Iberian Peninsula, Europe and the Near East, as well as with those prehistoric populations reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s004">Table S4</xref>).</p>
        <p>In order to evaluate the differences between the populations compared, genetic distances have been calculated using the <italic>F<sub>ST</sub></italic> statistic (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s005">Table S5</xref>). The three groups of hunter-gatherers considered in this analysis (from Scandinavia, Central Europe and the Cantabrian fringe on the Iberian Peninsula) did not show statistically significant differences between one another. However, the hunter-gatherers from Scandinavia (<sc>hg</sc>_<sc>sca</sc>) and those from Central Europe (<sc>hg</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>) showed statistically significant differences with other Neolithic, Chalcolithic and present-day populations. The hunter-gatherer group in the Cantabrian fringe (<sc>hg</sc>_<sc>cant</sc>) did not show statistically significant differences with any other populations in the comparison, due probably to its small sample size (n = 4), for this reason it was not included in the MDS analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>The Neolithic populations from Catalonia (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc>), France (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>) and Navarre (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cas</sc> and <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>pat</sc>), did not show statistically significant differences either between each other or with present-day populations. However, the Neolithic population from Central Europe (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>) showed statistically significant differences with the Neolithic populations from Navarre (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cas</sc> and <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>pat</sc>), as well as with present-day populations in both Europe and the Near East (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s005">Table S5</xref>).</p>
        <p>The samples from Los Cascajos and Paternanbidea (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>) were merged as they did not show statistically significant differences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s005">Table S5</xref>) and because the sites were very close in terms of chronology, culture and location (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>Concerning the Chalcolithic populations in the Basque Country (San Juan ante Portam Latinam (SJaPL), Pico Ramos and Longar), they did not show statistically significant differences with any of the populations in the comparison set (except with hunter-gatherer groups) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s005">Table S5</xref>).</p>
        <p>Regarding present-day populations, statistically significant differences were apparent between those in the Near East and those in Europe, indicating a genetic differentiation between these two geographic regions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s005">Table S5</xref>).</p>
        <p>A Multidimensional Scaling (MDS) analysis was carried out providing a two-dimensional view of the <italic>F<sub>ST</sub></italic> distance matrix (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>). This analysis showed an RSQ of 0.980 and a stress of 0.0260. The results of the MDS clarified some of the results obtained in previous <italic>F<sub>ST</sub></italic> pair-wise comparisons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s005">Table S5</xref>) and in Principal Component Analysis (PCA) (data not shown), as it is the difference between the hunter-gatherers (<sc>hg</sc>_<sc>sca</sc> and <sc>hg</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>) and the rest of populations. The hunter-gatherer samples showed the highest frequency values for haplogroup U (50%–80%) than any other present-day population (this haplogroup occupied one end of the first axis in PCA, data not shown). The Neolithic groups are heterogeneous, setting the Neolithics of Central Europe (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>) apart from the rest of Neolithic groups (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>, <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc>, and <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>). This is because they showed a high frequency for haplogroup N1a, that is absent in other Neolithic populations. The Neolithic sample of France (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>) is closer to present-day populations in the Near East, because it shows similar frequencies for haplogroups TX, W, J, H and U (the ones with the highest correlation for the first axis in the PCA, data not shown). However, the Neolithic populations from the Iberian Peninsula (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc> and <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>) are located between the variability of present-day European populations and those in the Near East. Likewise, the Chalcolithic populations in the Basque Country (Longar, SJaPL and Pico Ramos) occupied a similar position to the Neolithic groups of the Iberian Peninsula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0034417-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Multidimensional Scaling (MDS), considering the Fst genetic differences calculated according to the distribution of the mtDNA haplogroup frequencies of different populations; Chalcolithics in the Basque Country (purple), Neolithics (green), present-day Near East and northern Caucasus (orange) and Europeans (blue).</title>
            <p>Abbreviations for populations. Hunter-gatherer groups: Scandinavia (HG_SCA), Central Europe (HG_CE) and Cantabrian fringe (HG_CANT: La Chora, La Pasiega, Aizpea and Erralla). <bold>Neolithic populations:</bold> Catalonia (NEO_CAT), Central Europe (NEO_CE), France (NEO_FR) and Navarre (Los Cascajos and Paternanbidea) (NEO_NAVARRE). <bold>Chalcolithic</bold> <bold>populations in the Basque Country:</bold> Longar, SJaPL and Pico Ramos. <bold>Present-day populations in Europe:</bold> Eastern Mediterranean (MdE), Central Mediterranean (MdC), Western Mediterranean (MdW), Northeast Europe (NE), North-Central Europe (NC), Northwest Europe (NW), Southeast Europe (SE), Scandinavia (SCA), Alps (ALP), Iberian Peninsula (Ib_Pen), and Cantabrian Fringe populations (Cant_F) (that includes the Basque Country)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Phylogenetic analysis of ancient samples</title>
        <p>We have constructed a Median Joining Network (MJN) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g003">Figure 3</xref>) with the HVR-I sequences of the ancient samples obtained in this study, together with a set of sequences of European hunter-gatherer and farming individuals published to date (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s004">Table S4</xref>). Given the high mutation rate of HVR-I, we applied the substitution rates obtained by Meyer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Meyer1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Meyer2">[39]</xref> to establish varying mutational weights ranging from 0 to10. The resulting MJN is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g003">Figure 3</xref>, where the central node is represented by the rCRS, which is shared by all the population groups included in the analysis.</p>
        <p>The hunter-gatherer groups in Scandinavia (pink), Central Europe (orange) and Cantabrian fringe (dark blue) share a high number of haplotypes, located in the nodes of the network corresponding to haplogroup U. This figure confirmed the close phylogenetic relationship between the three groups which show the same subsistence pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
        <p>The sequences corresponding to haplogroup N1a have been found only in the Neolithic groups in Central Europe (purple) and in one individual of a Neolithic site in northwest France (Prissè-la-Chorrière, Deux-Sèvres) (brown), where only three individuals were recovered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Deguilloux1">[40]</xref>. This indicates that haplogroup N1a, which has a high frequency in the first Neolithic farmers in Central Europe, is also present in northwest France associated to a late Neolithic group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
        <p>Furthermore, we have found shared haplotypes for the Neolithic groups from the Cantabrian fringe (blue), the French Mediterranean area (white) and Catalonia (green). Moreover, we have also found relationship between these three Neolithic groups and the hunter-gatherers from the Iberian Peninsula (dark blue) and Europe (pink and orange). This indicates the presence of shared haplotypes between hunter-gatherers and Neolithic groups from different regions and timeframes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0034417-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Median Joining Network of European Paleolithic, Neolithic and Bronze Age sequences.</title>
            <p>Data encompass mtDNA HVR-I (nps 15999-16399). <bold>Hunter-gatherer groups</bold>: Scandinavia (HG_SCA) in pink, Central Europe (HG_CE) in orange, and the Cantabrian fringe (HG_CANT: La Chora, La Pasiega, Aizpea and Erralla) in blue. <bold>Neolithic populations</bold>: Catalonia (NEO_CAT) in green, Central Europe (NEO_CE) in purple, Northwest France (NEO_FR_NW) in brown, South of France (NEO_FR) in white, and the Cantabrian fringe (NEO_Cant_F: Los Cascajos, Paternanbidea, Fuente Hoz and Marizulo) in light blue. Urtiaga (Bronze Age) in black.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We have carried out the analysis of the mtDNA variability of a sample of 49 (out of 54) individuals recovered from nine archaeological sites in the north of the Iberian Peninsula (Navarre, Basque Country and Cantabria), with a chronological range from the Upper Paleolithic to the Bronze Age (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t001">Table 1</xref>). Our goal was to evaluate the model of transition from hunter-gathering to farming in the Cantabrian fringe.</p>
      <p>These 49 individuals provided 25 different mitochondrial haplotypes, which indicates high genetic variability (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">Table 2</xref>). Both Paleolithic and Neolithic individuals and even present-day populations along the Cantabrian fringe, share haplotypes albeit at a different proportion between populations.</p>
      <p>The mitochondrial variability found in the prehistoric samples analysed here was classified into eight haplogroups: H, U, K, J, I, HV, T, and X, which are amongst the most frequent mitochondrial haplogroups in Europe (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">Table 2</xref>). Nevertheless, the distribution of these haplogroups is different to that in present-day European populations.</p>
      <p>The <italic>F<sub>ST</sub></italic> test indicated that European hunter-gatherer groups (<sc>hg</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>, <sc>hg</sc>_<sc>sca</sc> and <sc>hg</sc>_<sc>cant</sc>) did not show statistically significant differences between them, but they are significantly different from any population compared, because to the high frequency of haplotypes within the haplogroup U (50%–80%) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s005">Table S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g003">Figure 3</xref>). On the other hand, it was noted some differences within the European Neolithic groups, with the Neolithic group in Central Europe (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>) showing the highest number of statistically significant differences in <italic>F<sub>ST</sub></italic> test, whereas the Neolithics from France and Catalonia (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc> and <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc>) showed the lowest number of statistically significant differences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s005">Table S5</xref>). The differentiation of the Neolithic group in Central Europe (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>) is due largely to its high frequency of haplogroup N1a (15%).</p>
      <p>Haplogroup N1a was proposed by Haak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak1">[8]</xref> as a possible genetic marker for the first Neolithic farmers who lived in Central Europe 7,500 years ago <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak2">[23]</xref>. This haplogroup was also found in one individual recovered from a Neolithic burial site in northwest France, confirming its spread to another geographic region in addition to Central Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Rando1">[31]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Nonetheless, haplogroup N1a was absent in the Neolithic groups analysed here (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>), as well as in other Neolithic samples from the Mediterranean area (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc> and <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Sampietro1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Lacan1">[25]</xref>, which might suggest that the genetic influence of Neolithic groups from the Near East in Central Europe was different to that in the western Mediterranean area. This proposal fits well with the lack of simple patterns detectable in the mtDNA data that are available so far.</p>
      <p>Haplogroup J, also proposed as a marker for the spread of Neolithic farmers from Near East <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Richards4">[13]</xref>, in the present study has been found only in the ancient Neolithic groups from Navarre (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>), with a frequency of 6.25%. This value is the lowest of those described for Neolithic populations studied so far, which showed heterogeneous frequencies (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>: 20%, <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc>: 18% and <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>: 9.5%) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Haak2">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Lacan1">[25]</xref>. Regarding those lineages belonging to haplogroup J, their influence was not so important in the sites from Navarre compared to other European regions. This result highlights the complex biological patterns resulting from Neolithisation in contrast with the simpler and more evident cultural patterns.</p>
      <p>The differences in the genetic composition of Neolithic groups in Europe (including those analysed here) are also evidenced from their respective frequencies for other mitochondrial haplogroups (H, U, I, K, HV, V, T and X). We would like to highlight the absence of haplogroup V, proposed as a marker of the post-glacial recolonization from Franco-Cantabrian refuge <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Torroni1">[41]</xref>. The 49 prehistoric samples analysed in the present study, have not produced a single individual belonging to haplogroup V, which is consistent with previous aDNA studies carried out in the Basque Country <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Izagirre2">[42]</xref>. This may suggest the existence of a sub-structuration in populations from Cantabrian Fringe during Paleolithic period that it is maintained up to the present, given the variation of frequencies of haplogroup V in the present-day population from this geographic region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Izagirre2">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Garca1">[43]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The MDS analysis revealed the difference between the hunter-gatherers and all the other populations compared, as well as the heterogeneity of European Neolithic groups (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>, <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>, <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc>, <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Moreover, it is highlighted the unique position of Central Europe (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>ce</sc>) in relation to their southern counterparts (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>, <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc> and <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>). This difference seems to indicate that the human groups associated with the spread of agriculture in the region of Central Europe had a different genetic composition to those that followed a Mediterranean route, which were devoid of haplogroup N1a.</p>
      <p>The distances observed between the Neolithic groups from the Mediterranean area (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>, <sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc>) and Navarre (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>) are also explained by their different frequencies for certain mitochondrial haplogroups, with haplogroups J, U and H standing out (the ones with the highest correlation for the first two axes of the PCA, date not shown). The distances observed between these Neolithic groups could be due to a different genetic impact of Neolithic farmers from Near East into the indigenous populations in the different regions of Europe. This genetic influence could be greater in southern France (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>fr</sc>) than in the Iberian Peninsula. The sites of Los Cascajos and Paternanbidea (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>), from Early Neolithic, although they showed a substantial Neolithic cultural influence, they seem to show a lower genetic contribution of female migrants from the original areas where Neolithic first developed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>In this regards, the Chalcolithic populations in the Basque Country, dated towards the end of the fifth millennium (SJaPL, Pico Ramos and Longar), showed similar distances with the Neolithic groups in Catalonia (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>cat</sc>) and in Navarre (<sc>neo</sc>_<sc>navarre</sc>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>). This may be due to the demographic stabilisation of human groups from the Neolithic onwards, which would have attenuated the genetic variations existing during the Paleolithic and first stages of the Neolithic.</p>
      <p>In sum, the differences between Hunter-Gatherer and Neolithic groups in Europe can be attributed to the restructuring of their genetic make-up due to the incoming gene flow from the Near East. The genetic data obtained in this mtDNA study contradicts the total acculturation and replacement models proposed for explaining the phenomenon of Neolithisation. Whereas in Central Europe-Northern France a Neolithic clinal gradient can not be discarded from aDNA data so far, the differences in the mtDNA found between Neolithic sites at the Mediterranean area provide support for a random dispersion model. Maritime colonization, transporting small and different Neolithic groups from the Near East pool could contribute to explain the difference.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>This study presents a genetic analysis of 49 out of 54 individuals recovered from nine sites located in the north of the Iberian Peninsula (Basque Country, Navarre and Cantabria). Four of those sites correspond to Paleolithic hunter-gatherer populations: La Chora (Cantabria), La Pasiega (Cantabria), Erralla (Gipuzkoa) and Aizpea (Navarre), another four to the Neolithic period: Los Cascajos (Navarre), Paternanbidea (Navarre), Marizulo (Gipuzkoa) and Fuente Hoz (Alava), and the last one to the Bronze Age: Urtiaga (Gipuzkoa) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g001">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t001">Table 1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-GonzlezEchegaray1">[44]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Altuna1">[53]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The Neolithic sites from Navarre (Paternanbidea and Los Cascajos) provide the largest samples in this study and are of considerable importance, as on the one hand, they are dated to the Early Neolithic (6.2–5.2 kya) and, on the other, they are found in association with archaeological evidence of fully Neolithic lifestyle (settlements, agriculture and livestock herding) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-GarcaGazlaz1">[48]</xref>. All the other sites are exceptional in terms of their antiquity and cover an ample spectrum of the geography along the Cantabrian fringe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
      <p>The entire excavation process involved strict precautions designed to avoid contamination. Furthermore, the anthropological remains were immediately removed, without undergoing washing, often still embedded in the sediment, and taken to our laboratory where cleaning was performed in dry conditions. The samples analysed in this paper are mostly dental pieces, which constitute the most isolated system in skeletal remains and, therefore, are less liable to outside contamination.</p>
      <p>The processing of the samples in the laboratory involved the application of a series of strict criteria for the authentication of results. We used some of the criteria detailed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Cooper1">[54]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Gilbert1">[57]</xref>, such as DNA quantification, cloning, duplication and replication of the results by two independent laboratories. In addition, the extraction and preparation of the PCR were undertaken in a positive-pressure sterile chamber, physically separated from the laboratory where post-PCR processes were carried out. All the work surfaces were cleaned regularly with sodium hypochlorite and irradiated with UV light. Suitable disposable clothing was worn (lab coat, mask, gloves and cap). Contamination controls were applied in both the extraction and amplification processes. In this study, we did not use racemisation of the ancient samples, as several authors have showed this method does not provide efficient information on the reproducibility of the aDNA results <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Collins1">[58]</xref>.</p>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Collection, Selection and Preparation of Ancient Samples</title>
        <p>We have selected those teeth without caries or deep fissures that might extend into the pulp. Whenever possible, more than one tooth was taken from each individual for duplicate analysis, with the duplicates being analysed in different sessions at the University of the Basque Country (UPV/EHU). In addition, a third sample from some individuals was analysed in independent laboratories (either University of La Laguna or National Institute of Toxicology and Forensic Sciences (INTCF), Spain). When dental pieces could not be obtained, bone tissue from long bones was collected (14 samples).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Extraction of DNA Using Phenol/Chloroform</title>
        <p>In order to eliminate surface contamination, the teeth were subjected to a process of depurination using acids, and the entire surface was irradiated with ultraviolet light <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Ginther1">[59]</xref>. In the case of bone-based extraction, the external part of the bone was cleaned by physical scraping, with a piece of bone being then removed and powdered (Freezer Miller Spex 6770, Edison N.J.). The extraction process followed the protocol described by Hagelberg et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Hagelberg1">[60]</xref>: the tissue was incubated with stirring for 2 hours at 56°C in a lysis buffer (5 ml) (0.5 M EDTA pH 8.0–8.5; 0.5% SDS; 50 mM Tris HCl pH 8.0; 0.01 mg/ml proteinase K). The DNA was recovered using phenol and chloroform and then concentrated and purified (Centricon-30, Amicon). Each extraction session involved two contamination controls that were applied to the entire process, except no dental or bone tissue was added.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Analysis of the variability of mtDNA</title>
        <p>Sequencing of mtDNA HVR-I, nucleotide positions (nps) 15,998–16,400, and mtDNA HVR-II, nps 16504-429 as per <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Andrews1">[61]</xref>, was undertaken in six overlapping fragments, each with a length of approximately 100 bp (base pair). HVR-II sequencing was carried out in samples with no polymorphic positions in HVR-I (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s006">Table S6</xref>). Similarly, the fragment between primers 8F and 8R (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s006">Table S6</xref>) was amplified in all samples to determine position 73 of HVR-II. The PCRs were performed in 25 μl of reaction mixture containing 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.3; 2 mM of MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1 μM of each dNTP, 0.4 μM of each primer, 5 units of AmpliTaq Gold (Applied Biosystems) and 10 μl of diluted DNA (1 μl of DNA extract in 10 μl of 1 mg/ml BSA). Cycling parameters were 95°C for 10 min; followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 10 sec, annealing temperature for 30 sec, 72°C for 30 sec; and a final step of 72°C for 10 min. The annealing temperatures of the primers of HVR-I were as follows: 60°C for the A1/A1R primer pair, 58°C for 2F/2R and 4F/4R, 57°C for 1F/1R and 55°C for 3F/3R and 5F/5R, the primer sequences are listed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Alonso1">[62]</xref>. The sequence and annealing temperatures of the HVR-II primers are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s006">Table S6</xref>. The amplification of each fragment was undertaken in independent PCRs and each fragment was amplified and sequenced twice from two independent DNA extract. In the case of positive amplification and the absence of contamination, the amplifications were purified by ExoSAP-IT (USB Corporation), with subsequent sequencing in an ABI310 automatic sequencer using chemistry based on dRhodamine. The results obtained were edited with BioEdit software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/BioEdit/bioedit.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/BioEdit/bioedit.html</ext-link>) and the sequences were aligned manually.</p>
        <p>In order to classify the mitochondrial variability of the individuals analyzed in this study, we proceeded to amplify 11 markers, which are required for defining the 10 Caucasian haplogroups described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Macaulay1">[63]</xref>. The protocol and primers are described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Alzualde1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Izagirre1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Izagirre2">[42]</xref>. The digestion patterns were verified using a fragment Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Authentication Methods</title>
        <p>In addition to the precautions taken to avoid contamination, other authentication criteria such as quantification, cloning and sequencing were applied.</p>
        <sec id="s4d1">
          <title>Duplication</title>
          <p>61% of individuals were analyzed in duplicated at different times and by different researchers at the University of the Basque Country (UPV/EHU).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4d2">
          <title>Replication</title>
          <p>The HVR-I of a sub-sample of 21 individuals (43% of the samples) was replicated; almost all of them at the University of La Laguna (Tenerife, Spain) (20 individuals) and the remaining one at the INTCF (Madrid, Spain).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4d3">
          <title>Quantification of target DNA</title>
          <p>We have quantified the target DNA analysing by quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR), a PCR fragment of 113 bp length of HVR-I, by means of SYBR Green. The methodology is a modification of the one described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Alonso2">[64]</xref>. A segment of 113 bp of HVR-I was amplified using primers <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-CACCATTAGCACCCAAAGCT-3′</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">5′-ACATAGCGGTTGTTGATGGG-3′</named-content> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Alonso2">[64]</xref> in a final volume of 30 μl containing: 2×Power SYBR Green Master Mix (Applied Biosystem), 5 mM of each primer and 10 μl of DNA (dilution 1/10 BSA). Cycling conditions were 1 cycle at 95°C for 10 min, 40–45 cycles at 95 °C for 15 sec and 60°C for 1 min, and a denaturation cycle of 60°C to 96°C. Four replicates were performed for each sample. The standard curve was drawn using eight serial dilutions of a fragment of 405 bp length of the HVR-I, which included the fragment to be quantified. There were four replicates for each dilution obtaining typical values of efficiency (101%) and r<sup>2</sup> (0.988). In each qPCR, we included the corresponding extraction and amplification controls.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4d4">
          <title>Cloning</title>
          <p>In order to detect possible heterogeneities in the PCR products that may correspond to either post-mortem damage and/or mixed contamination, a fragment of HVR I was cloned in a sub-sample of 10 individuals by means of the TOPO TA Cloning® Kit (Invitrogen). Linkage to the vector pCR®2.1-TOPO® and chemical transformation of the cells TOP10F' (One Shot® <italic>E. coli</italic>) were performed following the supplier's instructions. After culturing the cells overnight at 37°C in a selective environment, 10 blank cultures were collected and each one cultured in a non-selective environment. Five μl of purified product (using a QIAprep Spin Mini prep Kit, QIAGEN) of each clone were used for the sequencing reaction.</p>
          <p>We determined the HVR-I and HVR-II sequence of the mtDNA of the researchers and archaeologists who handled the samples in order to discard possible contamination (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s003">Table S3</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Genetic diversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Nei1">[65]</xref> and genetic distances (F<sub>ST</sub> distances by Reynolds) were calculated on the basis of haplogroup frequencies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s004">Table S4</xref>) using Arlequin 3.11 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Schneider1">[66]</xref>.</p>
        <p>In addition, the distance matrix was calculated between the populations studied and those existing in the literature by means of Arlequin 3.11 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0034417-Schneider1">[66]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0034417.s004">Table S4</xref>). This distance matrix has been depicted in two dimensions by means of a Multidimensional Scaling (MDS) analysis (SPSS 17 Software) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Furthermore, a Median-Joining Network has been constructed using the 175 sequences of hunter-gatherer and farming individuals that have so far been published (including the samples in this study), using the Network 4.6.0.0 program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fluxus-engineering.com" xlink:type="simple">www.fluxus-engineering.com</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0034417.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Summary of results of quantification, replication and cloning from the samples analyzed in the present study (see nomenclature in </bold>
            <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t001">
              <bold>Table 1</bold>
            </xref>
            <bold> and </bold>
            <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t002">
              <bold>Table 2</bold>
            </xref>
            <bold>).</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0034417.s002" mimetype="application/x-excel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Mitochondrial DNA sequences of the clones from the samples analyzed in the present study (.xls).</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0034417.s003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Mitochondrial haplotypes (HVR-I and HVR-II) of researchers and archaeologists that handled the samples analyzed in the present study.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0034417.s004" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Prehistoric and present populations compiled from literature that constitutes the database of HVR-I sequences of mtDNA for the present study.</bold> Abbreviations of the populations (Abbrev), number of individuals analyzed (N), number of haplotypes (HT), number of polymorphic sites (s), haplotype diversity (Hd), Variance of Hd, standard deviation of Hd (sd Hd), average number of nucleotide differences (k), Haplogroup (HG) and gene diversity calculated from the frequencies of mitochondrial haplogroups. See abbreviations in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>; * see chronology in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0034417-t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0034417.s005" mimetype="application/x-excel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Results of F<sub>ST</sub> analysis.</bold> F<sub>ST</sub> values (upper the diagonal) and <italic>p</italic>-values with standard deviation (p±de) (under the diagonal) based on haplogroup frequencies (P&lt;0.0001, in gray). See abbreviations in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0034417-g002">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0034417.s006" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0034417.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Primer sequences and annealing temperatures used to amplify the HVR-II of mtDNA, in the present study.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful to the archaeologists and to the Institutions that granted permission for human remains (the Government of Navarra, Cultural Heritage Dept. of the Basque Government, the Archaeology and Paleontology Heritage Centre of Gipuzkoa, the Museum of Archaeology of Alava and the Museum of Prehistory and Archaeology of Cantabria).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Ammerman1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ammerman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalli-Sforza</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1984</year>             <article-title>The Neolithic Transition and the Genetics of Populations in Europe.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Barbujani1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbujani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokal</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oden</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Indo-European origins: a computer-simulation test of five hypotheses.</article-title>             <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source>             <volume>96</volume>             <fpage>109</fpage>             <lpage>132</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-CavalliSforza1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalli-Sforza</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Paleolithic and Neolithic lineages in the European mitochondrial gene pool.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>61</volume>             <fpage>247</fpage>             <lpage>254</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Chikhi1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chikhi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbujani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Y genetic data support the Neolithic demic diffusion model.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>99</volume>             <fpage>11008</fpage>             <lpage>11013</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Chikhi2">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chikhi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stro-Bisol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertorelle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascali</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbujani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Clines of nuclear DNA markers suggest a largely neolithic ancestry of the European gene pool.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>95</volume>             <fpage>9053</fpage>             <lpage>9058</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Sokal1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokal</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oden</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Genetic evidence for the spread of agriculture in Europe by demic diffusion.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>351</volume>             <fpage>143</fpage>             <lpage>145</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Dennell1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennell</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1985</year>             <article-title>Neolithic Advances: The Neolithic Transition and the Genetics of Populations in Europe.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>227</volume>             <fpage>1331</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Haak1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haak</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bramanti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Ancient DNA from the first European farmers in 7500-year-old Neolithic sites.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>310</volume>             <fpage>1016</fpage>             <lpage>1018</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Richards1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corte-Real</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson-Herbots</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>Paleolithic and neolithic lineages in the European mitochondrial gene pool.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>59</volume>             <fpage>185</fpage>             <lpage>203</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Richards2">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>The Neolithic transition in Europe: archaeological models and genetic evidence.</article-title>             <source>Documenta Praehistorica XXX, Neolithic Studies</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>159</fpage>             <lpage>167</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Zvelebil1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zvelebil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Looking back at the Neolithic transition in Europe.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Archaeol</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>183</fpage>             <lpage>190</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Richards3">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Phylogeography of mitochondrial DNA in western Europe.</article-title>             <source>Ann Hum Genet</source>             <volume>62</volume>             <fpage>241</fpage>             <lpage>260</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Richards4">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Tracing European founder lineages in the Near Eastern mtDNA pool.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>67</volume>             <fpage>1251</fpage>             <lpage>1276</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Rosser1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosser</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zerjal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurles</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adojaan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alavantic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Y-chromosomal diversity in Europe is clinal and influenced primarily by geography, rather than by language.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>67</volume>             <fpage>1526</fpage>             <lpage>1543</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Semino1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semino</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Passarino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oefner</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>The genetic legacy of Paleolithic Homo sapiens sapiens in extant Europeans: a Y chromosome perspective.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>290</volume>             <fpage>1155</fpage>             <lpage>59</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Balaresque1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balaresque</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>A predominantly neolithic origin for European paternal lineages.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>e1000285</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Alzualde1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alzualde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izagirre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rúa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Temporal mitochondrial DNA variation in the Basque Country: influence of post-neolithic events.</article-title>             <source>Ann Hum Genet</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>665</fpage>             <lpage>79</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Alzualde2">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alzualde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izagirre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albarran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Insights into the "isolation" of the Basques: mtDNA lineages from the historical site of Aldaieta (6th-7th centuries AD).</article-title>             <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source>             <volume>130</volume>             <fpage>394</fpage>             <lpage>404</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Alzualde3">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alzualde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izagirre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azkarate</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Influences of the European Kingdoms of Late Antiquity on the Basque Country: An Ancient DNA Study.</article-title>             <source>Curr Anthropol</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>155</fpage>             <lpage>62</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Izagirre1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Izagirre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alzualde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Rare haplotypes in mtDNA: applications in the analysis of biosocial aspects of past human populations.</article-title>             <source>Hum Biol</source>             <volume>77</volume>             <fpage>443</fpage>             <lpage>56</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Fregel1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fregel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pestano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The maternal aborigine colonization of La Palma (Canary Islands).</article-title>             <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>1314</fpage>             <lpage>1324</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Fregel2">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fregel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusmao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Demographic history of Canary Islands male gene-pool: replacement of native lineages by European.</article-title>             <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>181</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Haak2">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haak</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balanovsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koshel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaporozhchenko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Ancient DNA from European early neolithic farmers reveals their near eastern affinities.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Biol</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>e1000536</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Sampietro1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampietro</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lao</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caramelli</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Palaeogenetic evidence supports a dual model of Neolithic spreading into Europe.</article-title>             <source>Proc R Soc B</source>             <volume>274</volume>             <fpage>2161</fpage>             <lpage>2167</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Lacan1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricaut</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brucato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duranthon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Ancient DNA reveals male diffusion through the Neolithic Mediterranean route.</article-title>             <source>Pro Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>9788</fpage>             <lpage>9791</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Malmstrm1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malmström</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandstrom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stora</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Ancient DNA reveals lack of continuity between neolithic hunter-gatherers and contemporary Scandinavians.</article-title>             <source>Curr Biol</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>1758</fpage>             <lpage>62</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Bramanti1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bramanti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haak</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unterlaender</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jores</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P</surname></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Genetic discontinuity between local hunter-gatherers and Central Europe's first farmers.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>326</volume>             <fpage>137</fpage>             <lpage>140</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Handt1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Handt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krings</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pääbo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>The retrieval of ancient human DNA sequences.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>59</volume>             <fpage>368</fpage>             <lpage>376</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Crespillo1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crespillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luque</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paredes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA sequences for 118 individuals from northeastern Spain.</article-title>             <source>Int J Legal Med</source>             <volume>114</volume>             <fpage>130</fpage>             <lpage>132</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-MacaMeyer1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maca-Meyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pestano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA transit between West Asia and North Africa inferred from U6 phylogeography.</article-title>             <source>BMC Genet</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>15</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Rando1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA analysis of northwest African populations reveals genetic exchanges with European, near-eastern, and sub-Saharan populations.</article-title>             <source>Ann Hum Genet</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <fpage>531</fpage>             <lpage>550</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Larruga1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA characterisation of European isolates: the Maragatos from Spain.</article-title>             <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>708</fpage>             <lpage>16</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Achilli1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Achilli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fornarino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA Variation of Modern Tuscans Supports the Near Eastern Origin of Etruscans.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>80</volume>             <fpage>759</fpage>             <lpage>768</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Pereira1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McEvoy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Genetic Signatures of a Mediterranean Influence in Iberian Peninsula Sheep Husbandry.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>1420</fpage>             <lpage>6</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Achilli2">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Achilli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rengo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scozzari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Saami and Berbers--an unexpected mitochondrial DNA link.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>76</volume>             <fpage>883</fpage>             <lpage>886</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Soares1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ermini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mormina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Correcting for purifying selection: an improved human mitochondrial molecular clock.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>84</volume>             <fpage>740</fpage>             <lpage>759</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Soares2">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achilli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Semino</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The archaeogenetics of Europe.</article-title>             <source>Curr Biol</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>R174</fpage>             <lpage>R183</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Meyer1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Identifying site-specific substitution rates.</article-title>             <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>182</fpage>             <lpage>89</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Meyer2">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Pattern of nucleotide substitution and rate heterogeneity in the hypervariable regions I and II of human mtDNA.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>152</volume>             <fpage>1103</fpage>             <lpage>10</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Deguilloux1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deguilloux</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pemonge</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scarre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joussaume</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>News from the west: ancient DNA from a French megalithic burial chamber.</article-title>             <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source>             <volume>144</volume>             <fpage>108</fpage>             <lpage>118</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Torroni1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torroni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruciani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>A signal, from human mtDNA, of postglacial recolonization in Europe.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>69</volume>             <fpage>844</fpage>             <lpage>852</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Izagirre2">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Izagirre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rúa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>An mtDNA analysis in ancient Basque populations: implications for haplogroup V as a marker for a major paleolithic expansion from southwestern Europe.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>65</volume>             <fpage>199</fpage>             <lpage>207</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Garca1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fregel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fregel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Using mitochondrial DNA to test the hypothesis of a European post-glacial human recolonization from the Franco-Cantabrian refuge.</article-title>             <source>Heredity</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>37</fpage>             <lpage>45</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-GonzlezEchegaray1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>González-Echegaray</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1952</year>             <article-title>Hallazgos en la cueva de La Pasiega.</article-title>             <source>In Ampurias XV-XVI</source>             <volume>Barcelona.43–65</volume>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-GonzlezEchegaray2">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>González-Echegaray</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García-Guinea</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gegines</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1963</year>             <article-title>Cueva de La Chora.</article-title>             <source>Excavaciones Arqueológicas de España,</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>43</fpage>             <lpage>65</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-delaRa1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rúa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1985</year>             <article-title>Restos humanos de Erralla. Cazadores recolectores en la cueva de Erralla (Cestona, País Vasco).</article-title>             <source>Munibe</source>             <volume>37</volume>             <fpage>195</fpage>             <lpage>198</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-delaRa2">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rúa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baraybar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iriondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izagirre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Estudio antropológico del esqueleto mesolítico del yacimiento de Aizpea.</article-title>             <source>Anejos de Veleia-Series maior</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>363</fpage>             <lpage>429</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-GarcaGazlaz1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>García-Gazólaz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sesma</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J</surname></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Los enterramientos en el poblado Neolitico de Los Cascajos (Los Arcos).</article-title>             <source>In La tierra te sea leve, Arqueología de la muerte en Navarra</source>             <volume>Pamplona.49–58</volume>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-GarcaGazlaz2">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>García-Gazólaz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sesma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Los enterramientos neolíticos del yacimiento de Paternanbidea (Ibero).</article-title>             <source>In La tierra te sea leve, Arqueología de la muerte en Navarra</source>             <volume>Pamplona.59–65</volume>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Basabe1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basabe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1971</year>             <article-title>Restos humanos del yacimiento de Marizulo (Urnieta, Guipúzcoa).</article-title>             <source>Munibe</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>105</fpage>             <lpage>124</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Alday1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alday</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cava</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mujika</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>El IV milenio en el País Vasco: transformaciones culturales.</article-title>             <source>Rubicatum</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>745</fpage>             <lpage>756</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Basabe2">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basabe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennassar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1983</year>             <article-title>Estudio antropológico del yacimiento de Fuente Hoz (Anúcita, Álava).</article-title>             <source>Estudios de Arqueología Alavesa</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>77</fpage>             <lpage>119</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Altuna1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altuna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rúa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Dataciones absolutas de los cráneos del yacimiento prehistórico de Urtiaga.</article-title>             <source>Munibe</source>             <volume>41</volume>             <fpage>23</fpage>             <lpage>28</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Cooper1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Ancient DNA: do it right or not at all.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>289</volume>             <fpage>1139</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Hofreiter1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofreiter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaenicke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haeseler Av</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pääbo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>DNA sequences from multiple amplifications reveal artifacts induced by cytosine deamination in ancient DNA.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>4793</fpage>             <lpage>99</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Pbo1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pääbo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaenicke-Despres</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Genetic analyses from ancient DNA.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Genet</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>645</fpage>             <lpage>79</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Gilbert1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willerslev</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Authenticity in ancient DNA studies.</article-title>             <source>Med Scold</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>701</fpage>             <lpage>723</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Collins1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penkman</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohland</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobberstein</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Is amino acid racemization a useful tool for screening for ancient DNA in bone?. Proc Biol Sci.</article-title>             <volume>1669</volume>             <fpage>2971</fpage>             <lpage>2977</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Ginther1">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ginther</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Issel-Tarver</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>Identifying individuals by sequencing mitochondrial DNA from teeth.</article-title>             <source>Nat Genet</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>135</fpage>             <lpage>38</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Hagelberg1">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagelberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Isolation and characterization of DNA from archaeological bone.</article-title>             <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>             <volume>244</volume>             <fpage>45</fpage>             <lpage>50</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Andrews1">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubacka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chinnery</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lightowlers</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Reanalysis and revision of the Cambridge reference sequence for human mitochondrial DNA.</article-title>             <source>Nat Genet</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>147</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Alonso1">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albarran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Multiplex-PCR of short amplicons for mtDNA sequencing from ancient DNA.</article-title>             <source>International Congress Series</source>             <volume>1239</volume>             <fpage>585</fpage>             <lpage>88</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Macaulay1">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruciani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>The emerging tree of West Eurasian mtDNAs: a synthesis of control-region sequences and RFLPs.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>64</volume>             <fpage>232</fpage>             <lpage>49</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Alonso2">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albarran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Real-time PCR designs to estimate nuclear and mitochondrial DNA copy number in forensic and ancient DNA studies.</article-title>             <source>Forensic Sci Int</source>             <volume>139</volume>             <fpage>141</fpage>             <lpage>49</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Nei1">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1987</year>             <article-title>Molecular evolutionary Genetics.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0034417-Schneider1">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Estimation of past demographic parameters from the distribution of pairwise differences when the mutation rates vary among sites: application to human mitochondrial DNA.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>152</volume>             <fpage>1079</fpage>             <lpage>89</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>