<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-24191</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051106</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Computational biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population modeling</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Population biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population dynamics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Mathematics</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Applied mathematics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Complex systems</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Physics</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Interdisciplinary physics</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Paleoanthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Archaeology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Historical archaeology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Sociology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Demography</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Computational Biology</subject>
          <subject>Physics</subject>
          <subject>Mathematics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Space Competition and Time Delays in Human Range Expansions. Application to the Neolithic Transition</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Space Competition &amp; Time Delay in Human Expansions</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Isern</surname>
            <given-names>Neus</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Fort</surname>
            <given-names>Joaquim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vander Linden</surname>
            <given-names>Marc</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Departament de Prehistòria, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Cerdanyola del Vallès, Spain</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Complex Systems Lab, Departament de Física, Universitat de Girona, Girona, Catalonia, Spain</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Institute of Archaeology, University College London, London, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Caramelli</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>University of Florence, Italy</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">Neus.Isern@uab.cat</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Wrote the paper: NI. Assembled the Neolithic database: MVL. Devised the model: NI JF. Did the computations: NI. Made suggestions: JF MVL..</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <elocation-id>e51106</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Isern et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Space competition effects are well-known in many microbiological and ecological systems. Here we analyze such an effect in human populations. The Neolithic transition (change from foraging to farming) was mainly the outcome of a demographic process that spread gradually throughout Europe from the Near East. In Northern Europe, archaeological data show a slowdown on the Neolithic rate of spread that can be related to a high indigenous (Mesolithic) population density hindering the advance as a result of the space competition between the two populations. We measure this slowdown from a database of 902 Early Neolithic sites and develop a time-delayed reaction-diffusion model with space competition between Neolithic and Mesolithic populations, to predict the observed speeds. The comparison of the predicted speed with the observations and with a previous non-delayed model show that both effects, the time delay effect due to the generation lag and the space competition between populations, are crucial in order to understand the observations.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was funded by the Ministry of Science (grants SimulPast-Consolider-CSD-2010-00034 and FIS-2009-13050) and the Generalitat de Catalunya (Grup Consolidat 2009-SGR-374). The Neolithic database was assembled as part of the project Formation of Europe prehistoric population dynamics and the roots of socio-cultural diversity, funded by the European Commission (NEST-028192). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Reaction-diffusion equations have been widely applied to model biological and cross-disciplinary systems where there is an expanding front, such as in population dispersals, tumor growth or virus infections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort1">[1]</xref>. In this paper we develop a reaction-diffusion model with time delay and space competition that we apply to predict the spread of the Neolithic transition in Europe.</p>
      <p>The Neolithic transition is the change from a foraging way of subsistence (Mesolithic) to a farming lifestyle (Neolithic). Neolithization is considered a crucial process in human history as it involved a global socioeconomic change, and thus has been subject of numerous studies from different disciplines, such as archaeology, anthropology, genetics or mathematical modelling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Barker1">[2]</xref>. In Europe, the analysis of datings for early Neolithic sites shows that farming arrived from the Near East, the Fertile Crescent, and spread throughout the continent between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> years ago <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel1">[4]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The mechanisms for this spread have been traditionally regarded from two contrasting points of view. The demic diffusion model considers that the Neolithic expansion was mainly a demographic process, i.e. farming was spread by the dispersion of farmers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel2">[5]</xref>. On the other hand, the cultural diffusion model assumes that the adoption of the new culture and techniques by the indigenous populations is the main mechanism for the Neolithic expansion, entailing the spread of ideas rather than individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-VanderLinden1">[6]</xref>.</p>
      <p>There are archaeological analyses of Neolithic datings that support the idea of a mostly demic diffusion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Ammerman1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Collard1">[9]</xref>, but it is specially relevant that several recent genetic studies also agree with the demic diffusion scenario, both from the analysis of modern European populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Chikhi1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Balaresque1">[11]</xref>, as well as from the DNA of ancient remains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Haak1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Gamba1">[14]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Thus, assuming that Neolithization was basically a demic process, one can apply reaction-diffusion equations to model its expansion in Europe. The first attempt to mathematically model the Neolithic transition in Europe was led by Ammerman and Cavalli-Sforza in 1973 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Ammerman2">[15]</xref> applying the wave of advance model initially proposed by Fisher to predict the spread of advantageous genes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fisher1">[16]</xref>. Since then, other authors have developed more complex reaction-diffusion models to try to better explain the Neolithic expansion, for example, by including the effect of the time delay between successive migrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort2">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern1">[18]</xref>. Fisher's model considers that there is no time delay between two successive migrations, however, when modelling human beings it is reasonable to assume that children will stay with their parents until they reach adulthood and migrate to form their own families. Thus there is a time span between the migration of the parents and that of their children that, when taken into account, yields slower speeds than Fisher's model, and which are consistent with the observations for the Neolithic transition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Besides human population dispersals, there exist other biological systems in which the inclusion of a time delay between migrations has also proved to be of great importance to predict rates of expansion, such as the range expansion of some avian species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-OrtegaCejas1">[19]</xref> (where the time delay is due to the reproduction time) or viral infections of bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort3">[20]</xref> or mammalian cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Amor1">[21]</xref> (where the time delay there would correspond to the elapsed time between the virus adsorption and the release of its progeny).</p>
      <p>Another important effect that neither Fisher's model nor the time-delayed models take into account is the space competition between the colonizing farmers (Neolithic populations) and the indigenous hunter-gatherers (Mesolithic populations). Space competition between populations has been widely studied in ecological <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Murray1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Reynolds1">[23]</xref> and microbiological systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Gause1">[24]</xref>. On the spread of human populations, the interaction between different cultural groups can also have an important effect. In recent years, several authors have developed reaction-diffusion models that tackle the interaction between farmers and hunter-gatherers when studying the Neolithic transition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fedotov1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref>. Here we will focus on the models developed in references <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref> that were applied to predict the observed slowdown of the Neolithic transition in Northern Europe in terms of the space competition between Neolithic and Mesolithic populations. Archaeological literature points out that this slowdown may be caused by an increase on the Mesolithic population density near the North Sea <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Price1">[29]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-LouweKooijmans1">[31]</xref>. Other theoretically possible causes for the slowdown, such as the genetic adaptation of crops to the different climatic conditions, have been considered negligible as, according to Coward et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Coward1">[32]</xref>, apparently the crops that were not productive enough were dropped for the other more productive ones. Then, we have a system in which one population (Neolithic) colonizes an already populated region where the indigenous population density (Mesolithic) is not homogeneously distributed. The interaction between the two populations modifies the rate of spread of the invading population. It has been shown that the space competition between the two populations can be mathematically modelled by considering that the interaction has two effects. First, a limiting effect on the Neolithic population (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) growth dynamics, due to the competition for space and resources. So, besides the self-limiting term usually introduced in the logistic growth equation (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Murray1">[22]</xref>, one must also add a limitation term due to the fraction of space already occupied by the Mesolithic populations (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). As shown in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref>, then the usual logistic growth function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is replaced by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). On the other hand, the dispersion is also affected by the presence of Mesolithic populations and can be described through a non-homogeneous dispersion probability depending on the Mesolithic population density <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at each direction. In this way, the probability to move towards a certain direction depends on the space available (or free space <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) in that direction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref>. Using these ansätze one can predict modifications on the front speed dependent on the distribution of the Mesolithic populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref>.</p>
      <p>However, these previous models do not take into account the effect of the time delay between successive migrations (and neither do the other models with interaction mentioned above <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fedotov1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Patterson1">[26]</xref>). In this paper we want to develop a more general model including both effects, namely, the interaction between populations and the time delay between successive migrations. We will apply this model to predict the slowdown of the Neolithic transition in Europe and compare the results with the observations from a comprehensive Early Neolithic database for Europe containing 902 Early Neolithic datings (included as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s001">Table S1</xref>). In the next sections we will introduce a model where both effects (the interaction between populations and the time delay) are considered, and see that it can give a better account of the observed front speeds.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Observed front speeds</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Figure 1</xref> shows an interpolation of 902 Early Neolithic datings (included as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s001">Table S1</xref>), obtained using a natural neighbor interpolation method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Sibson1">[33]</xref>, and the location of the archaeological sites. This map gives an idea of how the Neolithic spread throughout the continent. From the interpolation map one can already qualitatively perceive a slower rate of expansion at the Atlantic coast, obvious by the fact that the distance advanced in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (distance between isochrones) is smaller there than at lower latitudes.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0051106-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Chronology of arrival times of the Neolithic transition in Europe.</title>
            <p>The circles correspond to the 902 datings (included as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s001">Table S1</xref>) used for this natural neighbor interpolation. The delimited corridor defines the region studied here, where the Neolithic expansion took place mainly in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> direction. The origin of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> coordinate is also defined on the map.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref> we use <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> intervals for clarity, but we calculate the front speed from the interpolated results every <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The front speed is calculated using a geometrical method (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>) for a corridor that goes from the Balkans to the North Sea, as indicated by the straight lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. The axis of this corridor roughly corresponds to one of the main known axis of diffusion of farming across Europe and encompasses, in the South-East, some of the earliest occurrences of farming in Europe, and in the North-West some of the latest (the latest are located in Northern Scandinavia, which is actually excluded here). The calculated front speeds are represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Figs. 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">3a and 3b</xref> (squares), with the first value corresponding to the period between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Cal yr BP; earlier periods have been left out in order to avoid the sea travel effect near the Mediterranean. (Note that this first value is located at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, rather than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The origin of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> coordinate, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, was defined as the position of the first archaeologically-measured value in references <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref>, but as we are using a newer database here, the position of the first value does not lie in the same position as before. However, we still conserve the same origin as with the older database, for the sake of comparability.)</p>
        <fig id="pone-0051106-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>a) Variation of the Mesolithic population density in the region of study. The triangles correspond to the archaeological data and the lines to the best fit (solid line) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref>, and the upper and lower <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> confidence bands (dotted and dashed lines respectively). (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the best fit, solid line, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the upper band, dotted line, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the lower band, dashed line.) b) Estimated and predicted speeds for the slowdown of the Neolithic transition. Symbols (squares): measured front speed from archaeological data for the region delimited in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> wide) and using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> intervals. Lines: Prediction from a time-delayed reaction diffusion-model with space competition between populations (solid line) and from a non-delayed model with space competition (dash-dotted line) when considering the best fit for the Mesolithic data, and when using the upper and lower bands for the Mesolithic population density (dotted and dashed lines respectively) from (a). (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0051106-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Parameter sensitivity of the models.</title>
            <p>Symbols (squares): Measured front speed from archaeological data. Lines: Upper and lower error bands (dotted and dashed lines respectively) predicted when considering the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> C.L. intervals for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for (a) the time-delayed model and (b) the non-delayed model. The solid line in (a) and the dash-dotted line in (b) correspond to the mean prediction, i.e., they are the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>. (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The measured front speeds show that the expansion was, at first, approximately constant at a rate of about <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (at central Europe), which agrees with the mean front speed values obtained by Gkiasta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Gkiasta1">[8]</xref> and Pinhasi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>, but later there is a clear slowdown on the expanding speed as Northern regions are reached, mostly between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see, e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>).</p>
        <p>The results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Figs. 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">3a and 3b</xref> have been calculated using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> intervals, but changing the interval duration does not change the observed results significantly, and neither does changing the width of the studied regions to a wider corridor (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s002">Fig. S1</xref>). Changing the interpolation method (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref> corresponds to a Natural Neighbor interpolation) modifies slightly the values of the front speed, but not significantly enough as to change the conclusions in this paper (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s003">Figs. S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s004">S3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Mathematical model</title>
        <p>When considering both effects (namely, the interaction with the Mesolithic populations and the time delay between migrations) the reaction-diffusion equation that describes the evolution at the leading edge of the Neolithic front (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) can be expressed as follows (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>),<disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e044"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e044" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the Neolithic population density at position <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the Mesolithic population density upon the arrival of the Neolithic transition (for simplicity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is considered to change only along the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> direction, as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the maximum Mesolithic population density in the region, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the Neolithic generation time, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the Neolithic diffusion coefficient and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the modified growth rate for the Neolithic populations due to the presence of Mesolithic populations (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> being the Neolithic intrinsic growth rate).</p>
        <p>The interaction with Mesolithic populations is clearly taken into account in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">Eq. (1)</xref> by the use of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> instead of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (limiting the population growth due to the competition for space and resources) and the term proportional to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> where the Mesolithic population density <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> appears explicitly (backwards advection term that hinders the expansion rate due to encountering Mesolithic populations). Taking into account the time delay entails the appearance of the second-order derivatives in time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort2">[17]</xref>, which in the reaction-diffusion <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">equation (1</xref>) correspond to the second term on the left-hand side and the terms proportional to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> on the right-hand side (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> for the detailed derivation). Conversely, when only taking into account the space competition, but not the time delay (such as in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref>) the reaction-diffusion equation would be<disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e061"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e061" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula></p>
        <p>The predictions for the Neolithic expansion obtained from the new reaction-diffusion <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">equation (1</xref>) will be calculated below with the following equation for the front speed along the direction <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> for details)<disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e063"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e063" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>where we have defined<disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e064"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e064" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e065"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e065" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Predicted Neolithic front speeds and parameter sensitivity</title>
        <p>In order to apply <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e063">Eq. (3)</xref> to the Neolithic transition we need to assign realistic values the Neolithic parameters and to define the equation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the Mesolithic population density. For the Neolithic populations we use the following parameter values obtained from preindustrial farming populations (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> C.L. interval) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern4">[34]</xref>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Ammerman3">[35]</xref> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> C.L. interval <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort4">[36]</xref> (the value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has little effect on the front speeds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort2">[17]</xref>).</p>
        <p>The distribution of the Mesolithic population density upon the arrival of the Neolithic populations is unknown, but it is reasonable to assume that this will be proportional to the density of archaeological sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel3">[37]</xref>. In Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref> an estimation of the density of Mesolithic sites was performed from archaeological data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Vermeersch1">[38]</xref>, obtaining an increase of the population density at Northern latitudes (triangles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2a</xref>). The best fit to the Mesolithic data along the direction <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-shaped function<disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e077"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e077" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> C.L. intervals). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2a</xref> shows the best fit (solid line) and the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> confidence bands (dashed and dotted lines). (Note that the lower band in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2a</xref> corresponds to using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the upper band to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.)</p>
        <p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref> we show the front speeds predicted when applying the time-delayed model developed here, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e063">Eq. (3)</xref>, as well as the previous non-delayed model given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e061">Eq. (2)</xref>, namely <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref><disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e086"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e086" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>Comparing first the results when applying mean parameter values (solid and dash-dotted lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>) we see that, for both models, the predicted font speed at central Europe (i.e. the first <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is mostly constant, but while the time-delayed model (solid line) predicts a front speed similar to the observations (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) for this region, the non-delayed model (dash-dotted line) predicts a significantly faster speed (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). At Northern regions, both models predict a significant slowdown on the front speed similar to the observations, though somewhat less abrupt, with the non-delayed speeds always faster than those from the archaeological data; so the time-delayed model does also provide a better approximation for this region. In fact, if considering the whole range of distances, one obtains that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the time-delayed model, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e063">Eq. (3)</xref>, while for the previous non-delayed model, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e086">Eq. (7)</xref>, the fit is poorer, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>Besides the prediction when considering the best fit to the Mesolithic population density, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref> also shows the predicted front speeds when considering <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> defined by the upper and lower confidence bands in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2a</xref>. We can see that changing the values of the parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e077">Eq. (6)</xref> basically affects the abruptness of the slowdown, while the predicted front speeds near the origin are mostly unchanged. Then, for a more steep increase in the Mesolithic population density taking place at a southern region (dotted line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2a</xref>, corresponding to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), the predicted front speed also shows a more abrupt change (dotted lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>). In fact, we see from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref> that this case would offer a better fit to the archaeological data, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the time delayed-model, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e063">Eq. (3)</xref>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the previous non-delayed model, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e086">Eq. (7)</xref>. (All results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref> have been calculated using the mean values of the Neolithic parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.)</p>
        <p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">Figs. 3a and 3b</xref> we analyze the errors introduced in the predicted speeds due to the uncertainties on the Neolithic parameters. The upper and lower bounds in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">Fig. 3</xref> have been calculated using the extreme values of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> C.L. intervals for the initial growth rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and the diffusion coefficient <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We see that, in this case, varying the Neolithic parameters modifies the predicted front speeds specially for the Southern regions (low values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Also, it is in this Southern region where there is a more significant difference between the predictions from the time-delayed model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">Fig. 3a</xref>) and the non-delayed one (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">Fig. 3b</xref>). We see in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">Fig. 3a</xref> that the time delayed-model developed here, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e063">Eq. (3)</xref>, predicts a narrower window of front speeds as compared to the non-delayed model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">Fig. 3b</xref>). At Southern latitudes (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), the archaeologically-measured speeds (squares) lie in the middle of the range predicted by the new delayed model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">Fig. 3a</xref>) but only at the lower end of the range predicted by the previous non-delayed model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">Fig. 3b</xref>). But even in the most favorable case for the non-delayed model (minimum values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), the prediction is not better that the one from the delayed model for the same set of parameters (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for both models in these conditions). Thus, even when considering the uncertainties on the Neolithic demographic parameters, the time-delayed model, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e063">Eq. (3)</xref>, provides a better prediction of the observed data.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Previously, the Neolithic transition in Europe was modelled by taking into account the role of a delay time due to the generation lag time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort2">[17]</xref>. Here we have also included the effect of the space competition between Neolithic and Mesolithic populations. We see from the results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Figs. 2b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">3</xref>) that the new model combining both effects, when applied to predict the slowdown of the Neolithic transition, provides a good approximation to the observed slowdown on the front speed.</p>
      <p>In this paper we have compared the results from our models to a newer archaeological database (included as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s001">Table S1</xref>) than the one used in previous studies dealing with the slowdown of the Neolithic at Northern Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref> (the older database can be found in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>). This new database is more complete (902 European Early Neolithic datings, versus 765 Early Neolithic datings for Europe and the Near East) and has been carefully prepared and audited as to provide a reliable vision of Early Neolithic in Europe. Details on the data selection can be found in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort5">[39]</xref> and the entire database will be published as Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-VanderLinden2">[40]</xref>. Consistent with the older database, a slowdown is observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The analysis of this newer and more detailed database for the corridor in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref> provides front speed values (squares in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Figs. 2</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">3</xref>) that differ significantly from the predictions made by the previous model (see, e.g., the three upper lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>). This problem is solved here by including the effect of the time delay between successive migrations.</p>
      <p>The need of space-competition models when modelling the Neolithic transition has been noted only recently. It is true that the Mesolithic population densities at the time were rather low at most of the continent. In fact, according to Shennan and Edinborough <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Shennan1">[41]</xref>, the Mesolithic population density just before the Neolithization process was lower than in previous periods (and much lower than the Neolithic population densities reached upon the consolidation of the Neolithic culture) (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel4">[42]</xref>). The estimation of the Mesolithic population density for our region of interest performed in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref> (triangles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2a</xref>) also yields very low values of Mesolithic population density at central Europe (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Certainly, low Mesolithic population densities would have had little effect on the front speed, which is consistent with the mostly constant front speed both measured from he Neolithic database (squares in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>) and predicted by the models at the first <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the studied region. Thus, except in Northern Europe, it seems reasonable to neglect the interaction between Mesolithic and Neolithic populations when modelling at large scales. Conversely, in the particular case studied here (Northern Europe), the space competition between populations seems to be of utmost importance. Indeed, taking into account the presence of non-homogeneously distributed Mesolithic populations, and the interaction of these indigenous populations with the Neolithic individuals, yields in our model a slowdown on the expanding front, similar to the observations. In addition, we have seen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>) that the way in which the slowdown predicted by the models takes place depends highly on the shape of the function for the Mesolithic density <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The results have been calculated taking into account the uncertainties in the parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e077">Eq.(6)</xref>, and we have seen that while the best fit to the Mesolithic data obtained in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref> provides a reasonable account for the measured variation in the front speeds, an earlier and more abrupt increase in the Mesolithic population density (such as when considering the upper <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> confidence band from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2a</xref>) would be able to provide a better fit to the observed front speeds.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, when modelling dispersions of human populations there is a time delay between the migration of the parents and the time in which their children can migrate away and create their families. Fisher-type models do not take into account such a delay. When included in the mathematical models (by including second-order time derivatives at the reaction-diffusion equation) this delay yields significantly slower front speeds, as can be easily seen by comparing, e.g., the results from the delayed and non-delayed models in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>. When comparing the mean predictions from the models (solid and dash-dotted lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Figs. 2b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">3</xref>) with the archaeological data (squares) we see that, in the particular case studied here, taking into account the time delay can provided a significantly better prediction of the measured front speed. This is specially obvious for the first <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the studied region where the mean error of the prediction is about <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the delayed model while for the non-delayed model the mean error is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. But also when considering the whole region, the time-delayed model provides a better prediction for the front speed, as shown by the lower value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> obtained when comparing the archaeological data with the models.</p>
      <p>When working with archaeological and anthropological data, the uncertainties in the parameters and measurements can have an important effect on the predicted results. We have discussed above how taking into account the uncertainties of the parameters defining the function for the Mesolithic affects the predicted results, but in this paper we have also studied the importance of the uncertainties in the demographic parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Taking into account the extreme values of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> C.L. interval for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> provides a fairly wide range of possible predicted speeds, specially at the first <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In the case of the time-delayed model developed here, for this initial region, the range of predictions is mostly centered around the archaeological estimates. The non-delayed model, on the other hand, provides a wider window of possible results, from speeds marginally consistent with the observations in the slower case, to speeds up to a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> faster that the observations for the first <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. However, even though the previous non-delayed model could be considered marginally consistent with the measured data given certain conditions of low diffusivity and population growth (i.e., due to the parameter uncertainties), this prediction is not better that the one from the delayed models in the same conditions. Thus, even taking into account the effect of the uncertainties, the time-delayed model can still provide a better prediction of the measured front speeds for the slowdown of the Neolithic transition.</p>
      <p>Therefore, the new model developed here with space competition and time delay effects provides a better prediction of the measured slowdown of the Neolithic transition than previous approximations taking into account only one of these effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref>. So, in this paper we see that (i) reaction-diffusion models taking into account the space competition with indigenous groups (or species) can predict variations in the front speed (a deceleration in this case) related with inhomogeneities on the indigenous population distribution and (ii) that including the time delay effect due to a generation lag can provide much better descriptions of observations.</p>
      <p>In future work, it would be of interest to perform numerical simulations to check that the theoretical front speed predicted here is actually obtained within the domain, given the finite time and length scales imposed by the archaeological dates and geographical region analyzed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Speed from archaeological data</title>
        <p>In this paper we have compared the results from our models with archaeological speeds estimated from an Early Neolithic database with 902 sites, which is included as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s001">Table S1</xref> (details on the data selection can be found in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort5">[39]</xref>). The database includes information on the location, dating, dating method and dated material. To calculate the front speed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2</xref> we have calibrated the 902 dates from the database using CALIB Radiocarbon Calibration 5.0.1 software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Stuiver1">[43]</xref>, and interpolated the calibrated dates using a natural neighbor interpolation system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Sibson1">[33]</xref> with ArcGIS 10. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref> shows the chronology of arrival times for the Neolithic transition thus obtained. Setting the isochrones at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> intervals, for each <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> interval we have defined a polygon delimited by two isochrones and the limits of the studied region. Computing the area of each of these polygons we know the region covered by the Neolithic population expansion during each <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> interval within the studied region. Thus, assuming that the expansion took place mainly in the direction <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref> we can estimate the mean front speed from the area, the width of the considered region (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and the time interval (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with the following expression<disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e136"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>In order to plot these results, for each area we have also calculated the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> coordinate of its centroid (by using the corresponding built-in function from ArcGIS). In this way, for each <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> interval we have a value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and a mean front speed.</p>
        <p>We have also applied the same method to estimate front speeds when considering <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> intervals, as well as for a wider region (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e141" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). They all provide approximately the same results as can be observed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s002">Fig. S1</xref>. We have also preformed similar calculations using a kringing interpolation method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Oliver1">[44]</xref> with a spherical semivariogram (see map and estimated front speeds in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s003">Figs. S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0051106.s004">S3</xref>). In this case the front speeds are slightly different than with the natural neighbor interpolation method, but the conclusions for this paper remain unchanged.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Mathematical model: Analytic front speed</title>
        <p>The reaction-diffusion model developed here, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">Eq. (1)</xref>, can be obtained from the following evolution equation that gives the Neolithic population density after a time interval <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e142" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (a generation) due to the reaction (population growth) and dispersal processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref><disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e143"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e143" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula>The function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the dispersion probability distribution that provides the probability for the Neolithic individuals to move from the position <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> during one generation. We have defined this probability distribution as dependent on the density of Mesolithic populations <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> present at each position. Assuming that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> varies only on the direction <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> we have <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref><disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e150"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e150" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the probability distribution corresponding to the dispersion in an unpopulated space, with all directions equally probably, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> corresponds to the reproduction process and gives the increase in population density due to the birth-death balance during one generation. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can be expressed as a Taylor series of the population growth function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>,<disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e157"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e157" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>We have defined the population growth function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> similarly to the logistic growth equation, but taking into account the additional limiting effect to the Neolithic population growth due to competition for space and resources with the Mesolithic populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern2">[27]</xref><disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e159"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e159" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula></p>
        <p>Linearizing and Taylor-expanding <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e143">Eq. (8)</xref> up to second order in time and space, we obtain the reaction-diffusion equation that describes this system including the interaction between populations and the time delay effect, i.e., <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">Eq. (1)</xref>. Due to the linearization, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">Eq. (1)</xref> is valid only at the leading edge of the front (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), which is where we want to compute the expansion speed. We calculate the front speed by assuming that for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the front is locally planar, with the local speed <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> parallel to the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> direction when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Then, we look for constant shaped solutions with the form <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. As <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has to be real, this yields the following constraint for the front speed<disp-formula id="pone.0051106.e168"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e168" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are defined in Eqs. (4) and (5). As the speed is a positive value, from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e168">Eq. (12)</xref> one obtains that the real speed is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>,with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the positive root to the quadratic equation obtained when the equality in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e168">Eq. (12)</xref> holds. From variational analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Mndez1">[45]</xref> one can also obtain an upper bound that happens to be the same value, thus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the exact front speed for a system described by the reaction diffusion <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">equation (1</xref>), and this front speed can be expressed mathematically by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e063">Eq. (3)</xref> in the Results section.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Parameter values</title>
        <p>To predict the Neolithic front speed we have used the following Neolithic parameter values: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e174" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e175" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e176" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> C.L. interval) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern4">[34]</xref>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e177" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Ammerman3">[35]</xref> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e179" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> C.L. interval <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref>) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e180" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort4">[36]</xref> (the value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e181" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> has little effect on the front speeds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort2">[17]</xref>). All these ranges have been estimated from modern ethnographical data of preindustrial populations as we summarize below.</p>
        <p>The range above for the intrinsic growth rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e182" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was estimated in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern4">[34]</xref> from data on the evolution of the population number for human populations established in previously unpopulated space (Pitcairn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Birdsell1">[46]</xref>, Furneaux <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Birdsell1">[46]</xref> and Tristan da Cunha <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Roberts1">[47]</xref> islands, and the fist colonization of the United States). The intrinsic growth rate has also been estimated by Guerrero et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Guerrero1">[48]</xref> directly from archaeological remains based on the rise in fertility (which was detected due to the rise in the proportions of immature skeletons in early Neolithic cemeteries), obtaining <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e183" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which lies within the range above (that was estimated from modern pre-industrial farming populations).</p>
        <p>The other two parameters used here, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e184" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e185" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, were estimated from ethnographical data from the agriculturalist Majangir people in Ethiopia. The generation time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e186" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, defined as the mean age difference between parents and one of their children (not necessarily the eldest), was estimated previously (see note <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Gause1">[24]</xref> in reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort4">[36]</xref>). The diffusion coefficient has been calculated from the expression <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e187" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort2">[17]</xref>, and the mobility range was estimated in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">[3]</xref> from the distance moved by individuals during one generation for three Majangir groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Ammerman3">[35]</xref>.</p>
        <p>To include the space competition between populations, we need the Mesolithic population density upon the arrival of the Mesolithic front. The actual Mesolithic population density is unknown, but as only the relative density is necessary, it is reasonable to assume that it will be proportional to the density of archaeological sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel3">[37]</xref>. The relative density of Mesolithic sites was estimated in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Isern3">[28]</xref> using data from the INQUA database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Vermeersch1">[38]</xref>, for a region <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e188" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> wider than the one delimited in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref>. The best fit to these data yield the following expression <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e189" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e190" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e191" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The behavior of this function corresponds to a relative Mesolithic populations density <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e192" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e193" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, which increases following a <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e194" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-shaped curve with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e195" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e196" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Fig. 2a</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0051106.s001" mimetype="application/x-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Information about 902 Early Neolithic sites: latitude/longitude, radiocarbon date, calibrated date, and additional archaeological information <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0051106-Fort5">[39]</xref>.</p>
          <p>(XLS)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0051106.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Front speeds estimated from the archaeological data interpolated with a natural neighbor method and using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e197" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (squares, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Figs. 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">3a–b</xref>) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e198" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (triangles) intervals for a corridor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e199" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) wide, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e200" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (stars) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e201" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (crosses) intervals for a corridor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e202" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> wide. The solid line corresponds to the delayed model with space competition (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">Eq. (1)</xref>), i.e., it is the same as the solid line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Figs. 2b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">3a</xref>.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0051106.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Chronology of the Neolithic expansion calculated with a kringing interpolation method with a spheric semivariogram. The circles correspond to the 902 datings used for this interpolation. The delimited corridor defines the region studied here, where the Neolithic expansion took place mainly in the direction <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e203" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The origin of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e204" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> coordinate is also defined on the map.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0051106.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Front speeds estimated from the archaeological data interpolated with a kringing method and using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e205" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (squares) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e206" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (triangles) intervals for a corridor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0051106.e207" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> wide (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The solid line corresponds to the delayed model with space competition (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0051106.e044">Eq. (1)</xref>), i.e., it is the same as the solid line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g002">Figs. 2b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0051106-g003">3a</xref>.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Fort1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Progress in front propagation research</article-title>. <source>Rep Prog Phys</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>086001</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Barker1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Barker G (2006) The agricultural revolution in prehistory: why did foragers become farmers? Oxford: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Pinhasi1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinhasi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ammerman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Tracing the origin and spread of agriculture in Europe</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e410</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocquet-Appel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vander Linden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlowski</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Detection of diffusion and contact zones of early farming in Europe from the space-time distribution of 14C dates</article-title>. <source>J Archaeol Sci</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>807</fpage>–<lpage>820</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel2">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocquet-Appel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>When the world's population took off: The springboard of the Neolithic demographic transition</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>333</volume>: <fpage>560</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-VanderLinden1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Vander Linden M (2011) In constant motion? Recent advances in mathematical modelling and radiocarbon chronology of the neolithisation of Europe. In: Hadjikoumis A, Robinson E, Viner S, editors, Dynamics of neolithisation in Europe. Studies in honour of Andrew Sherratt, Oxford: Oxbow. pp. 25–45.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Ammerman1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ammerman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalli-Sforza</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Measuring the rate of spread of early farming in Europe</article-title>. <source>Man (NS)</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>674</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Gkiasta1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gkiasta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shennan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Neolithic transition in Europe: the radiocarbon record revisited</article-title>. <source>Antiquity</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Collard1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edinborough</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shennan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Radiocarbon evidence indicates that migrants introduced farming to Britain</article-title>. <source>J Archaeol Sci</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>866</fpage>–<lpage>870</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Chikhi1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chikhi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbujani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Y genetic data support the Neolithic demic diffusion model</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>11008.11013</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Balaresque1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balaresque</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A predominantly Neolithic origin for European parental lineages</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1000285</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Haak1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haak</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balanovsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koshel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaporozhchenko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ancient DNA from European Early Neolithic farmers reveals their Near Eastern ancestors</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1000536</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Skoglund1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skoglund</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malmström</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raghavan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Storå</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Origins and genetic legacy of Neolithic farmers and hunter-gatherers in Europe</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>336</volume>: <fpage>466</fpage>–<lpage>469</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Gamba1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamba</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>tirado</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deguilloux</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pemonge</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Ancient dna from Early Neolithic Iberian population supports a pioneer colonization by first farmers</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Ammerman2">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ammerman AJ, Cavalli-Sforza LL (1973) A population model for the diffusion of early farming in Europe. In: Renfrew C, editor, The explanation of culture change, London: Duckworth. pp. 343–357.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Fisher1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1937</year>) <article-title>The wave of advance of advantageous genes</article-title>. <source>Ann Eugen</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Fort2">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Méndez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Time-delayed theory of the Neolithic transition in Europe</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>870</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Isern1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isern</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Time-delayed reaction-diffusion fronts</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>057103</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-OrtegaCejas1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega-Cejas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Méndez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The role of the delay time in the modelling of biological range expansions</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Fort3">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Méndez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Time-delayed spread of viruses in growing plaques</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev Lett</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>178101</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Amor1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amor</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Virus infection speeds: Theory versus experiment</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>061905</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Murray1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Murray JD (2002) Mathematical Biology, volume 1. Berlin: Springer-Verlag, 3 edition.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Reynolds1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Details of the geographic replacement of the red squirrel (Sciurus vulgaris) by the grey squirrel (Sciurus carolinensis) in Eastern England</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Gause1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gause GF (1934) The Struggle for Existence. Baltimore: The Williams &amp; Wilkins Company.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Fedotov1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedotov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Stochastic model for population migration and the growth of human settlements during the Neolithic transition</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>026107</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Patterson1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarson</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shukurov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Modelling the Neolithic transition in a heterogeneous environment</article-title>. <source>J Archaeol Sci</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>2929</fpage>–<lpage>2937</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Isern2">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isern</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Anisotropic dispersion, space competition and the slowdown of the Neolithic transition</article-title>. <source>New J Phys</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>123002</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Isern3">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isern</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Cohabitation effect on the slowdown of the Neolithic expansion</article-title>. <source>Europhys Lett</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>58002</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Price1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Price TD (2003) The arrival of agriculture in Europe as seen from the North. In: Ammerman AJ, Biagi P, editors, The Widening harvest: the Neolithic transition in Europe : looking back, looking forward, Boston: Archaeological Institute of America. pp. 273–294.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Zvelebil1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zvelebil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rowley-Conwy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Transition to farming in northern Europe: A hunter-gatherer perpective</article-title>. <source>Norw Arch Rev</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-LouweKooijmans1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Louwe Kooijmans</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The agency factor in the process of neolithisation? a Dutch case study</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Archaeology in Low Countries</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Coward1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coward</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shennan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colledge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conolly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The spread of Neolithic plant economies from the Near East to northwest Europe: a phylogenetic analysis</article-title>. <source>J Archaeol Sci</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Sibson1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sibson R (1981) A brief description of natural neighbour interpolation. In: Arnett V, editor, Interpreting Multivariate Data, New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons. pp. 21–36.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Isern4">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isern</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez-Losada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Realistic dispersion kernels applied to cohabitation reaction-dispersion equations</article-title>. <source>J Stat Mech - Theor Exp</source> <volume>2008</volume>: <fpage>P10012</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Ammerman3">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ammerman AJ, Cavalli-Sforza LL (1984) The Neolithic Transition and the Genetics of Populations in Europe. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Fort4">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jana</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Humet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Multidelayed random walks: theory and application to the Neolithic transition in Europe</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>031913</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel3">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocquet-Appel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demars</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noiret</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrowsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Estimates of Upper Palaeolithic meta-population size in Europe from archaeological data</article-title>. <source>J Archaeol Sci</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1656</fpage>–<lpage>1668</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Vermeersch1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Vermeersch PM, Boon J (2010). Radiocarbon Paelolithic Europe database, version 10. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ees.kuleuven.be/geography/projects/14c-palaeolithic/" xlink:type="simple">http://ees.kuleuven.be/geography/projects/14c-palaeolithic/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Fort5">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vander Linden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Modelling the Neolithic transition in the Near East and Europe</article-title>. <source>Am Ant</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-VanderLinden2">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vander Linden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>in prep</year>) <article-title>The many dates of farming: assessing the radiocarbon record of the Mesolithic-Neolithic transition in Europe</article-title>. <source>Eur J Archaeol</source></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Shennan1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shennan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edinborough</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Prehistoric population history: from the late glacial to the late Neolithic in central an northern Europe</article-title>. <source>J Archaeol Sci</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>1339</fpage>–<lpage>1345</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-BocquetAppel4">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocquet-Appel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vander Linden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Understanding the rates of expansion of the farming system in Europe</article-title>. <source>J Archaeol Sci</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>546</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Stuiver1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Stuiver M, Reimer PJ, Reimer R (2010). CALIB Radiocarbon Calibration, version 5.0.1. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://calib.qub.ac.uk/calib/" xlink:type="simple">http://calib.qub.ac.uk/calib/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Oliver1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Kriging: a method of interpolation for geographical information systems</article-title>. <source>Int J Geogr Inform Syst</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Mndez1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Méndez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farjas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Speed of wave-front solutions to hyperbolic reaction-diffusion equations</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev E</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>5231</fpage>–<lpage>5243</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Birdsell1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Birdsell</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>1957</year>) <article-title>Some population problems involving Pleistocene man</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Roberts1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>Genetic effects of population size reduction</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>220</volume>: <fpage>1084</fpage>–<lpage>1088</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0051106-Guerrero1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Guerrero E, Naji S, Bocquet-Appel JP (2008) The signal of the Neolithic demographic transition in the Levant. In: Bocquet-Appel JP, Bar-Yosef O, editors, The Neolithic demographic transition and its consequences, Berlin: Springer. pp. 57–80.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>