<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-01115</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035431</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Reproductive system</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary processes</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Evolutionary selection</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Organismal evolution</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Human evolution</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary genetics</subject>
              <subject>Evolutionary theory</subject>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Heredity</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genotypes</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Human genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Reproductive system</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Reproductive physiology</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Obstetrics and gynecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Female subfertility</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Women's health</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biological anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Physiology</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
          <subject>Women's Health</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>How Contemporary Human Reproductive Behaviors Influence the Role of Fertility-Related Genes: The Example of the P53 Gene</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Human Reproductive Behaviors and P53 Gene</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Corbo</surname>
            <given-names>Rosa Maria</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gambina</surname>
            <given-names>Giuseppe</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Scacchi</surname>
            <given-names>Renato</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Biology and Biotechnology “Charles Darwin,” La Sapienza University, Rome, Italy</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Alzheimer's Disease and Other Dementias Center, Division of Neurology, Hospital of Verona, Verona, Italy</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>CNR Institute of Molecular Biology and Pathology, Rome, Italy</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>Shree Ram</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">National Cancer Institute, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">rosamaria.corbo@uniroma1.it</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RMC GG RS. Performed the experiments: RS. Analyzed the data: RMC RS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RS GG. Wrote the paper: RMC.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e35431</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Corbo et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <p>Studies on human fertility genes have identified numerous risk/protective alleles involved in the occurrence of reproductive system diseases causing infertility or subfertility. Investigations we carried out in populations at natural fertility seem to suggest that the clinical relevance that some fertility genes are now acquiring depends on their interaction with contemporary reproductive behaviors (birth control, delayed childbearing, and spacing birth order, among others). In recent years, a new physiological role in human fertility regulation has emerged for the tumor- suppressor p53 gene (P53), and the P53 Arg72Pro polymorphism has been associated with recurrent implantation failure in humans. To lend support to our previous observations, we examined the impact of Arg72Pro polymorphism on fertility in two samples of Italian women not selected for impaired fertility but collected from populations with different (premodern and modern) reproductive behaviors. Among the women at near-natural fertility (n = 98), the P53 genotypes were not associated with different reproductive efficiency, whereas among those with modern reproductive behaviors (n = 68), the P53 genotypes were associated with different mean numbers of children [Pro/Pro = 0.75&lt;Pro/Arg = 1.7&lt;Arg/Arg = 2, (p = 0.056)] and a significant negative relationship between the number of children and P53 Pro allele frequencies (p = 0.028) was observed. These results are consistent with those of clinical studies reporting an association between the P53 Pro allele and recurrent implantation failure. By combining these findings with previous ones, we suggest here that some common variants of fertility genes may have become “detrimental” following exposure to modern reproductive patterns and might therefore be associated with reduced reproductive success. Set within an evolutionary framework, this change could lead to the selection of a set of gene variants fitter to current reproductive behaviors as the shift to later child-bearing age in developed countries.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by La Sapienza University, Progetti AST 2009 (to RMC). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="5"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Human fertility is a complex trait determined by gene-environmental interactions in which genetic factors represent a significant component <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kohler1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kosova1">[2]</xref>. Fertility is regulated by a large number of genes acting in various different steps to establish both male and female fertility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Layman1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Matzuk1">[4]</xref>. Besides the numerous rare mutations associated with infertility, many polymorphic variants (alleles) have also been identified in fertility genes, but how these alleles affect human fertility remains unclear <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Layman1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Matzuk1">[4]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Different alleles at a locus are usually thought to be associated only with small fertility differences (or no differences at all) and contribute very little to overall fitness, otherwise selection would lead to their fixation or elimination <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Fisher1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Rodgers1">[6]</xref>. This scenario would fit well with the complex trait model proposed for fertility which predicts the contribution of many genes, each with a small effect. In recent investigations we were able to examine the way the variation of some fertility-related genes may influence reproductive efficiency in natural (or near-natural) fertility populations (i.e. in the absence of deliberate birth control) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Corbo1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Corbo2">[8]</xref> and could confirm the absence of a relevant effect of gene variants on total fertility (i.e., fertility of subjects at the end of their reproductive lifetime). Other recent studies on fertility candidate genes have identified risk/protective alleles involved in the occurrence of reproductive system diseases causing infertility or subfertility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Simoni1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Yoon1">[12]</xref>. More recently, some of these polymorphisms have been studied also in relation to their role in positive outcomes after <italic>in vitro</italic> fertilization (IVF) or other assisted reproductive technology (ART) procedures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Sundarrajan1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Altme2">[15]</xref>. The emerging picture seems to indicate that fertility genes represent a set of genes whose role is changing, and acquiring clinical relevance, a phenomenon we hypothesize may be due to their interaction with the present environmental context, i.e., modern reproductive patterns (e.g., birth control, family planning, delayed childbearing, and spacing birth order) followed in many of today's industrialized countries.</p>
      <p>Whether for economic, social, or educational reasons, young couples have begun to postpone starting a family and reduce family size, and women to delay having first childbirth or decide to remain childless. In Western Europe, the mean age at which women deliver their first child rose from 22–25 years in 1950 to 27–30 years in 2003 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Frejka1">[16]</xref>, i.e., later in life when fertility starts to decline. Studies on age-related female fertility indicate that it begins to decline at age 30 years and then more rapidly after age 35. While the decline in male fertility is also age-dependent, it becomes significant only after age 45 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-teVelde1">[17]</xref>. Furthermore, postponement of first childbirth is accompanied by increased serious health risks for mothers and their children. A major effect of this shift in reproductive behaviors is a progressive reduction of fertility. Across Europe, total fertility rates ([TFR], average number of children per woman) decreased dramatically from 2·6 between 1960 and 1964 to 1·5 between 2004 and 2005, a value well below 2·1, the TFR needed for generation replacement, i.e. the level of fertility at which a population exactly replaces itself from one generation to the next (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/employment_social/social_situation/docs/sec_2007_638_en.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://ec.europa.eu/employment_social/social_situation/docs/sec_2007_638_en.pdf</ext-link>; last accessed February 23, 2012).</p>
      <p>To verify the hypothesis that exposure to different reproductive behaviors may influence the action of fertility-related genes, we examined the role of another fertility gene, P53, in two samples of the Italian population with different reproductive patterns. The tumor-suppressor p53 gene (P53) has a pivotal role in tumor prevention and DNA damage response. In response to a variety of cellular stresses, the p53 protein (p53) is able to activate target genes to induce cell cycle arrest, apoptosis, and senescence. Through these mechanisms, p53 promotes DNA repair or the elimination of damaged cells, thus contributing to tumor suppression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Levine1">[18]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the last years, a new physiological role has emerged for p53 as a fertility regulator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Hu1">[19]</xref>. In mice maternal reproduction p53 was found to control the implantation of fertilized eggs, a function p53 exerts by activating leukemia inhibitory factor (LIF), an essential gene for blastocyst implantation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Hu2">[20]</xref>. So too in humans LIF appears to be involved in egg implantation, given that LIF levels are significantly decreased in women with unexplained infertility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Hu3">[21]</xref>. The role of p53 in the regulation of female fertility has been confirmed by more recent observations of how other members of the p53 family (p63 and p73) participate in the control of human maternal reproduction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Levine2">[22]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Many single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) of P53 have been identified in human populations, but the one most extensively studied is rs1042522, located in codon 72 of exon 4, where the change CGC→CCC results in an Arg/Pro substitution. The Pro and Arg alleles at codon 72 are not functionally equivalent: Pro72 encodes a weaker p53 isoform than that encoded by Arg72 to induce apoptosis and suppress transformation, while it is better at favoring cell cycle arrest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Jeong1">[23]</xref>. The two alleles at P53 codon 72 differ also in their transcriptional activity toward a subset of p53-responsive genes. Notably, cells containing P53 Arg72 produce twice as much LIF as those containing the Pro72 allele <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kang1">[24]</xref>. A growing body of epidemiological data is consistent with these <italic>in vitro</italic> studies: the P53 Pro72 allele was found at increased frequencies among women undergoing <italic>in vitro</italic> fertilization (IVF) and, among such women, it was associated with higher implantation failure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kang1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kay1">[25]</xref>. This clinical observation confirms that p53 regulates maternal reproduction in humans as well.</p>
      <p>So far, the P53 Arg72Pro polymorphism has been found to influence human reproduction in a pathological context. We examined it in two samples of women not selected for impaired fertility and collected from populations with different reproductive patterns. The first was collected from a rural population from Southern Italy, which, according to population and sample fertility rate, has reproduced with a pre-modern or near-natural reproductive pattern. The second was collected from an urban population from northeastern Italy whose fertility rate indicates a pattern of reproduction typical of modern societies where birth control is practiced.</p>
      <p>The aim of the present study was to examine the role of P53 polymorphism in fertility at the population (not clinical) level and the possible effects different reproductive behaviors may have on it.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The characteristics of the samples are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0035431-t001">Table 1</xref>. The observed fertility rate for the women in the Southern Italian sample was 3.7±2.3 children (range, 0–11). This value was intermediate with respect to the range of 4.8-3.1 reported for cohorts of women born in the same geographic area and in the same period (1900–1930) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Istituto1">[26]</xref>. The fertility rate for the women in the Northern Italian sample was 1.8±0.97 children (range, 0–4). This value was near the lower end of the range of 2.4–1.7 reported for cohorts of women born in the same geographic area and in the same period (1921–1953) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Istituto2">[27]</xref>. Spontaneous abortion rates were calculated as the ratio between the number of abortions and the number of children. No population data concerning cohorts of women of the same periods are available for a comparison with the sample data; however, the abortion rates (abortion/livebirths) reported for the same geographic areas (Northern Italy, 0.13) and (Southern Italy, 0.12) are available for the period 1997–2001 [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www3.istat.it/dati/catalogo/asi2004/PDF/Cap3.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www3.istat.it/dati/catalogo/asi2004/PDF/Cap3.pdf</ext-link>, last accessed February/27/2012].</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0035431-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035431.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>Characteristics of the two study samples.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0035431-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035431.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Southern Italy</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Northern Italy</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Age (yrs)</bold>
                <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.2±6.0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.3±9.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Total no. of children</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">342</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Mean no. of children</bold>
                <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7±2.3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8±0.97</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Total no. of abortions</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Abortion/children ratio</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.19</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Childless subjects (%)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.7</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.8</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label>*</label>
            <p>Plus-minus value is equal to plus-minus standard deviation.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>The P53 Arg72Pro polymorphism was examined in the Southern Italian (n = 152) and the Northern Italian (n = 102) samples. The observed genotype frequencies (Southern Italy: Pro/Pro 0.112, Pro/Arg 0.382, Arg/Arg 0.507; Northern Italy: Pro/Pro 0.069, Pro/Arg 0.363, Arg/Arg 0.568) agreed with those expected according to the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. The P53 Pro allele frequencies of the two samples were 0.250 (Northern Italy) and 0.303 (Southern Italy), similar to those reported for the Italian population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Tenti1">[28]</xref>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0035431-t002">Table 2</xref> reports the mean number of children associated with P53 genotypes in the two samples. Among the women in the Southern Italian sample, the P53 genotypes were not found to be associated with a different number of children. In contrast, among the women in the Northern Italian sample, the P53 genotypes were associated with different numbers of children, with a trend among the genotypes (from the lowest number of children to the highest) Pro/Pro&lt;Pro/Arg&lt;Arg/Arg (p = 0.056). The power calculation of this analysis is low (1-β&lt;0.80) and the probability to make a type II error is high (β&gt;0.20). We calculated that we would need to have approximately 50 subjects in each class to reach a statistical power of 0.80. But because of the P53 Pro allele frequency, we would have to collect about 800 subjects to find about 50 Pro/Pro homozygotes.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0035431-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035431.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
          <title>Mean number of children (±SD) according to P53 genotype. The number of subjects is given in brackets.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0035431-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035431.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P53 genotype</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Southern Italy</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Northern Italy</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Pro/Pro</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6±2.2(11)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75±1.0 (4)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Pro/Arg</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.6±2.1 (30)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67±0.9 (21)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>Arg/Arg</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.7±2.6 (50)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.95±1.0 (38)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>p</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.056</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
      <p>A statistically significant result was achieved with a different approach: the subjects were grouped into different classes according to the number of children, and the P53 allele frequencies were calculated for each class (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0035431-t003">Table 3</xref>). The chi square test for trend of proportions showed a significant negative relationship between the number of children and P53 Pro allele frequencies (chi square = 4.9,d.f. = 1, p = 0.028) only in the Northern Italian sample, where the highest Pro allele frequencies were found in the class with no children (0.438) and the lowest in the class with two or more children. No significant trend was observed among the women in the Southern Italian sample (chi square = 0.11,d.f. = 1, p = 0.74). In neither sample were differences observed in the mean number of spontaneous abortions associated with the P53 genotypes (Southern Italian sample, p = 0.40; Northern Italian sample, p = 0.62) (data not reported).</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0035431-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035431.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
          <title>P53 allele frequencies in subjects grouped according to number of children.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0035431-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035431.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of children</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Northern Italy</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Southern Italy</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of subjects</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pro freq.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. of subjects</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pro freq.</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>0</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.438</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.214</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>1</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.231</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.231</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>2</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.224</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.389</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>3</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.136</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.324</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>4</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.250</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>&gt;4</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.287</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>p</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.027</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.74</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This study examined the association of the P53 Arg72Pro polymorphism with fertility at the population level, specifically in women not selected for fertility disorders. The data show that in the sample of women at near-natural fertility, the P53 genotypes are not associated with differential fertility. Conversely, in the sample of women with modern reproductive behaviors, the P53 genotypes are associated with a different reproductive efficiency, with the lowest fertility occurring among the Pro/Pro genotype carriers. The observation of a reduced fertility associated with the Pro allele was confirmed by subsequent chi square for trend of proportions test that shows a significant inverse relationship between Pro allele frequency and classes according to number of children.</p>
      <p>These results should be interpreted with caution. The size of the samples is relatively small and, fertility being a complex trait, numerous other genetic and environmental factors, including male fertility, could have contributed to determine the phenotype “number of children” we examined. Nevertheless, the results obtained in the sample of women with a modern reproductive pattern are consistent with those of clinical studies reporting an excess of P53 Pro/Pro genotypes in women with unexplained infertility undergoing IVF and, among these, in women with higher implantation failure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kang1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kay1">[25]</xref>. The observation that P53 genotypes are not associated with different numbers of spontaneous abortions, which, by definition, represent the end of an established pregnancy, is not unexpected, given that P53 is involved in egg implantation instead.</p>
      <p>It is interesting to observe how the phenotypic effects of P53 genotypes vary according to reproductive environments. In women from the population at near-natural fertility, P53 genotypes do not influence fertility, suggesting that the possible small reduction of fertility associated with the P53 Pro allele could have been offset by the pre-modern reproductive behavior (little or no birth control, lower age at first birth, etc.). In the sample from the population where modern reproductive behaviors began to be followed, the P53 genotype effect begins to shift toward differential fertility. Set within the broader context of contemporary society, the role of P53 genotypes eventually tends to acquire clinical relevance, being associated with infertility and the successful/or not outcome in women undergoing IVF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kang1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Kay1">[25]</xref>.</p>
      <p>These findings are similar to what we have observed for other fertility-related genes. One gene we studied was ESR1, which encodes estrogen receptor alpha <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Corbo1">[7]</xref>. We examined the association of two ESR1 polymorphisms (rs 2234693, rs9340799) with fertility in two populations at near-natural (Italian) and natural (Afro-Ecuadorian) fertility and observed that the effects of ESR1 genotypes on fertility varied according to the reproductive environment: in the women from the African-Ecuadorian populations ESR1 genotypes (<italic>pp</italic> and <italic>xx</italic>) influenced the fertility level, predisposing to have an elevated number of children (higher than the median value). In the Italian women, the same genotypes showed an association with a low rate of spontaneous abortions, but without any impact on total fertility. In today's industrialized societies, however, the effects of the ESR1 genotype manifest as a successful outcome in women undergoing IVF <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Sundarrajan1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Altme1">[14]</xref> or predisposing to premature ovarian failure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Yoon1">[12]</xref>, or exerting a protective effect against azoospermia or idiopathic oligospermia in men <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-OFlynn1">[11]</xref>. In other words, in populations with pre-modern reproductive patterns, the ESR1 genotypes influence at most the number of children, whereas within the context of modern reproductive behaviors, they seem to be associated instead with having children or not.</p>
      <p>Another example is the angiotensin I-converting enzyme (ACE) gene. Recently, the ACE I/D polymorphism was found associated with recurrent spontaneous miscarriages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Fatini1">[29]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-DossenbachGlaninger1">[31]</xref>. We analyzed the relationship between the ACE I/D polymorphism and the number of spontaneous abortions, the number of pregnancies and completed fertility in a sample of Italian women at near-natural fertility <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Corbo2">[8]</xref>. We were able to tease out in this population sample an association between an ACE genotype (DD) and recurrent miscarriages, as previously reported in case-control studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Fatini1">[29]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-DossenbachGlaninger1">[31]</xref>; however, no difference in completed fertility was observed among the women carrying the different ACE genotypes, as those carrying the ACE risk genotype and prone to miscarriage overcame the problem by counterbalancing it with a greater number of pregnancies. In contrast, published data on contemporary women appear to indicate that the ACE genotype could now be associated with reduced reproductive success, presumably because of their shorter reproductive lifespan due to postponement of childbearing. Similarly, other fertility related genes which do not seem to have any effects on fertility in populations with pre-modern reproductive patterns have been recently associated with infertility or ovarian stimulation outcome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Lussiana1">[32]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Corbo3">[33]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0035431-t004">Table 4</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0035431-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035431.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
          <title>Fertility related polymorphic genes which have been investigated for their role in populations with different reproductive patterns.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0035431-t004-4" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0035431.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Phenotypes</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ref</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Premodern pattern</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Modern pattern</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>ESR1</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">fertility level</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IVF outcome; POF<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7, 12–15</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>FSHR</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IVF outcome</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,32, unpubl.data.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>CYP19</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IVF/COH<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>; POF<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,33</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>P53</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">infertility; IVF outcome</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Present invest.,24, 25</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                <bold>ACE</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">none (see text)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">recurrent miscarriages.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8, 29–31</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt102">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>POF:premature ovarian failure; COH: controlled ovarian hyperstimulation.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>The emerging picture of the interactions between fertility genes and contemporary reproductive behaviors suggests that fertility genes may represent a further example of genes “rendered detrimental by progress”. The hypothesis for a “genotype rendered detrimental by progress” was first advanced by J.V. Neel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Neel1">[34]</xref> in 1962 in an attempt to explain the emergence of diabetes epidemics in the United States and other technologically advanced societies. He speculated the existence of a “thrifty genotype”, i.e., a set of genes shaped for our hunter-gatherer ancestors to survive on an intermittent and unpredictable food supply and with elevated physical activity. Such a genotype would be exceptionally efficient in the utilization of food and allow the storage of fat reserves in times of plenty for later times of shortage. Once highly advantageous for ensuring survival, these thrifty genes have become detrimental in modern societies where food is plentiful or overabundant and overall physical activity has declined. Moreover, they may be identified with susceptibility genes for complex diseases like type 2 diabetes or obesity. The notion that an “ancient” genotype could increase disease susceptibility has been put forth to account for the growing prevalence of such complex disorders as hypertension, coronary heart disease and Alzheimer's disease. Some 30 years later, in 1998 Neel suggested broadening the original concept to include the “civilization syndromes” or the “altered lifestyle syndromes” for diseases which can be explained by a similar evolutionary framework <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Neel2">[35]</xref>. This hypothesis, originally based on disease physiology and epidemiology, found recent support from population genetic studies showing that, for several susceptibility polymorphisms for common disease, the risk allele is the ancestral allele, the result of an ancient adaptation no longer advantageous in the modern environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-DiRienzo1">[36]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Taken together, our data seem to indicate that fertility genes might easily fit within the “altered lifestyle syndromes” hypothesis, and, at least for the P53 and ACE genes, in the ancestral susceptibility model as well, given that both the Pro allele of P53 and the D allele of ACE are the ancestral alleles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-DiRienzo1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Sucheston1">[37]</xref>. There is, however, an important difference between fertility genes and other genes “rendered detrimental by progress”: the latter are mostly susceptibility genes for diseases occurring in post-reproductive age (coronary heart disease, hypertension, Alzheimer's disease, among others) and therefore escape selection, while the natural fertility gene variants may be associated with differential fitness and, hence, be under selective pressure. This process could promote the selection of a set of gene variants fitter to the current reproductive patterns, thus favoring, for example, reproduction at a later age as well.</p>
      <p>On the whole, the picture we have outlined suggests the occurrence of complex interactions between genetic factors and reproductive environments and that fertility genes are a further set of genes whose functions are influenced by the lifestyle changes of modern societies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Study populations</title>
        <p>The Southern Italian population sample included 152 apparently healthy unrelated women in the post-reproductive age collected for a population survey of the elderly population of Cilento, a rural area in the district of Salerno, Southern Italy. All subjects were born before 1930 (1900–1930) and lived in a society where the demographic transition (increase in life expectancy and declining fertility) had just started <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Ulizzi1">[38]</xref>. In Italian women born in the same geographic area and in the same year range, the mean age at marriage was 22.4 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Istituto1">[26]</xref>, and the fertility rate was well over the replacement level (range, 4.8-3.1). All subjects were recruited consecutively without selection criteria, except age (&gt;70 years) and birthplace. Fertility data (number of children) were ascertained by interviews and were collected for only 98 women. Written informed consent was obtained from all subjects. The protocol for the collection of biological material for the scientific studies was approved by the institutional committees (Local Health Unit ASL SA 3).</p>
        <p>The Northern Italian population sample comprised 102 healthy unrelated women recruited as a control sample during an epidemiological study on Alzheimer's disease (AD) carried out at the Verona Hospital. All subjects were born between 1921/1953 in the urban area of Verona, northeastern Italy, and lived in a society where the demographic transition was already under way. In the Italian women born in the same geographic area in the same year range, the mean age at marriage was 25.2 years and the fertility rate was near/below the replacement level (range, 2.4-1.7) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Istituto2">[27]</xref>. All subjects were recruited consecutively without selection criteria, except age that matched that of AD patients (&gt;60 years) and birthplace (Verona province). Fertility data (number of children) were ascertained by interviews and were collected for only 63 women. Written informed consent was obtained from all subjects. The protocol for the collection of biological material for the scientific studies was approved by the institutional ethics committee (Hospital of Verona, Ethical Committee protocol no. 1268/131/2006). The study was approved by the Department Board (12/06/2009 session) of the former “Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology” of La Sapienza University, Rome.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Laboratory Methods</title>
        <p>Venous blood was drawn in ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) from all subjects after overnight fasting. High-molecular-weight DNA was extracted from whole blood according to the procedure described by Miller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Miller1">[39]</xref>. The P53 SNP (rs1042522) was investigated by an allele-specific PCR according to Giannoudis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Giannoudis1">[40]</xref>. In brief, P53 Arg and Pro sequences were amplified in a single reaction with an allele-specific primer pair: P53 Arg sequences were detected using the primer pair p531, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">58-GTCCCCCTTGCCGTCCCA-38</named-content>, and Arg–, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">58-CTGGTGCAGGGGCCACGC-38</named-content>, amplifying a 137-bp fragment; P53 Pro sequences were detected using the primer pair Pro1, <named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">58-GCCAGAGGCTGCTCCCCC-38</named-content> and p53–,<named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">8-GGAAGCCAGCCCCTCAGG-38</named-content>, amplifying a 206-bp fragment. Visualization of the PCR product on agarose gel revealed three different genotypic patterns.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>Allelic frequencies were determined by the gene-counting method. The agreement of the genotype distribution with Hardy–Weinberg expectations was verified with the chi square test. Comparisons between the mean number of children associated with different P53 genotypes were performed using analysis of variance (ANOVA). Estimates of statistical power (1-β) were calculated according to Cohen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Cohen1">[41]</xref> i.e. we calculated the probability of rejecting the null hypothesis, when the null is false. In this analysis the null hypothesis is that the P53 genotypes are associated with the same number of children. The Cochran-Armitage chi square test for trend of proportions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0035431-Armitage1">[42]</xref> was used to verify the presence of a linear trend between the number of children and P53 allele frequencies.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful to K.A. Britsch for reviewing the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Kohler1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skytthe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Bio-social determinants of fertility.</article-title>             <source>Int J Androl</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>46</fpage>             <lpage>53</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Kosova1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ober</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Colloquium papers: Heritability of reproductive fitness traits in a human population.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>107:</volume>             <supplement>Suppl 1</supplement>             <fpage>1772</fpage>             <lpage>8</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Layman1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Layman</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Human gene mutations causing infertility.</article-title>             <source>J Med Genet</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>153</fpage>             <lpage>161</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Matzuk1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matzuk</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>The biology of infertility: research advances and clinical challenges.</article-title>             <source>Nat Med</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>1197</fpage>             <lpage>1213</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Fisher1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1958</year>             <source>The genetical theory of natural selection</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Dover Publications Inc</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Rodgers1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doughty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Genetic influence helps explain variation in human fertility: evidence from recent behavioral and molecular genetic studies.</article-title>             <source>Cur Dir Psychol Sci October</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>184</fpage>             <lpage>188</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Corbo1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corbo</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulizzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piombo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Labarga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Stefano</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Estrogen receptor alpha polymorphisms and fertility in populations with different reproductive patterns.</article-title>             <source>Mol Hum Reprod</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>537</fpage>             <lpage>540</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Corbo2">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corbo</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulizzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piombo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scacchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Association of ACE I/D polymorphism and recurrent miscarriages in an Italian population with a pre-modern reproductive pattern.</article-title>             <source>Ann Hum Biol</source>             <volume>38</volume>             <fpage>102</fpage>             <lpage>105</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Simoni1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tempfer</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Destenaves</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauser</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Functional genetic polymorphisms and female reproductive disorders: Part I: Polycystic ovary syndrome and ovarian response.</article-title>             <source>Hum Reprod Update</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>459</fpage>             <lpage>484</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Tempfer1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tempfer</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Destenaves</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauser</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Functional genetic polymorphisms and female reproductive disorders: part II–endometriosis.</article-title>             <source>Hum Reprod Update</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>97</fpage>             <lpage>118</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-OFlynn1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Flynn</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The genetic causes of male factor infertility: a review.</article-title>             <source>Fertil Steril</source>             <volume>93</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>12</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Yoon1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Estrogen receptor {alpha} gene polymorphisms in patients with idiopathic premature ovarian failure.</article-title>             <source>Hum Reprod</source>             <volume>25</volume>             <fpage>283</fpage>             <lpage>287</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Sundarrajan1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundarrajan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Association of oestrogen receptor gene polymorphisms with outcome of ovarian stimulation in patients undergoing IVF.</article-title>             <source>Mol Hum Reprod</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>797</fpage>             <lpage>802</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Altme1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altmäe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hovatta</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavreus-Evers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Allelic estrogen receptor 1 (ESR1) gene variants predict the outcome of ovarian stimulation in in vitro fertilization.</article-title>             <source>Mol Hum Reprod</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>521</fpage>             <lpage>526</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Altme2">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altmäe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hovatta</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavreus-Evers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salumets</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Genetic predictors of controlled ovarian hyperstimulation: where do we stand today?</article-title>             <source>Hum Reprod Update</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>813</fpage>             <lpage>828</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Frejka1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frejka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sardon</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>First birth trends in developed countries: A cohort analysis.</article-title>             <source>Demographic research</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>147</fpage>             <lpage>180</lpage>             <comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.demographic-research.org/" xlink:type="simple">www.demographic-research.org/</ext-link>. Accessed 28 February 2012</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-teVelde1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>te Velde</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>The variability of female reproductive ageing.</article-title>             <source>Hum Reprod Update</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>141</fpage>             <lpage>54</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Levine1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>The P53 pathway: what questions remain to be explored?</article-title>             <source>Cell Death Differ</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>1027</fpage>             <lpage>1036</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Hu1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The role of p53 gene family in reproduction.</article-title>             <source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>a001073</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Hu2">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teresky</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>p53 regulates maternal reproduction through LIF.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>450</volume>             <fpage>721</fpage>             <lpage>724</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Hu3">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atwal</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>p53: a new player in reproduction.</article-title>             <source>Cell Cycle</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>848</fpage>             <lpage>52</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Levine2">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomasini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKeon</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>The p53 family: guardians of maternal reproduction.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>             <volume>12</volume>             <fpage>259</fpage>             <lpage>65</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Jeong1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belyi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabadan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Differential levels of transcription of p53-regulated genes by the arginine/proline polymorphism: p53 with arginine at codon 72 favors apoptosis.</article-title>             <source>FASEB J</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>1347</fpage>             <lpage>1353</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Kang1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atwal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Single-nucleotide polymorphisms in the p53 pathway regulate fertility in humans.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>9761</fpage>             <lpage>9766</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Kay1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeyendran</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulam</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>p53 tumour suppressor gene polymorphism is associated with recurrent implantation failure.</article-title>             <source>Reprod Biomed Online</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>492</fpage>             <lpage>496</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Istituto1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">Istituto Centrale di Statistica</collab>             <year>1974</year>             <article-title>Indagine sulla fecondita' della donna.</article-title>             <source>Note e Relazioni</source>             <volume>50</volume>             <fpage>96</fpage>             <lpage>97</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Istituto2">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">Istituto Nazionale di Statistica</collab>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>La fecondità nelle regioni italiane. Analisi per coorti.</article-title>             <source>Informazioni</source>             <volume>35</volume>             <fpage>59</fpage>             <lpage>69</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Tenti1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tenti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vesentini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondo Spaudo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zappatore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Migliora</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>p53 codon 72 polymorphism does not affect the risk of cervical cancer in patients from northern Italy.</article-title>             <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>435</fpage>             <lpage>438</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Fatini1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gensini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Battaglini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prisco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cellai</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme DD genotype, angiotensin type 1 receptor CC genotype, and hyperhomocysteinemia increase first trimester fetal-loss susceptibility.</article-title>             <source>Blood Coagul Fibrinolysis</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>657</fpage>             <lpage>662</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Buchholz1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogenhofer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pihusch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Polymorphisms in the ACE and PAI-1 genes are associated with recurrent spontaneous miscarriages.</article-title>             <source>Hum Reprod</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>2473</fpage>             <lpage>2477</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-DossenbachGlaninger1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dossenbach-Glaninger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Trotsenburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberkanins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopmeier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>ACE I/D polymorphism and recurrent first trimester pregnancy loss: interaction with SERPINE1 4G/5G and F13 Val34Leu polymorphisms.</article-title>             <source>Br J Haematol</source>             <volume>141</volume>             <fpage>269</fpage>             <lpage>271</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Lussiana1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lussiana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Restagno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massobrio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Mutations and polymorphisms of the FSH receptor (FSHR) gene: clinical implications in female fecundity and molecular biology of FSHR protein and gene.</article-title>             <source>Obstet Gynecol Surv</source>             <volume>63</volume>             <fpage>785</fpage>             <lpage>795</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Corbo3">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corbo</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulizzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Positano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scacchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Association of CYP19 and ESR1 pleiotropic genes with human longevity.</article-title>             <source>J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci</source>             <volume>66</volume>             <fpage>51</fpage>             <lpage>55</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Neel1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neel</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1962</year>             <article-title>Diabetes mellitus: a “thrifty” genotype rendered detrimental by “progress”?</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>353</fpage>             <lpage>362</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Neel2">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neel</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The “thrifty genotype” in 1998.</article-title>             <source>Nutr Rev</source>             <volume>57</volume>             <fpage>S2</fpage>             <lpage>S9</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-DiRienzo1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Rienzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>An evolutionary framework for common diseases: the ancestral-susceptibility model.</article-title>             <source>Trends Genet</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>596</fpage>             <lpage>601</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Sucheston1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sucheston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witonsky</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Natural selection and functional genetic variation in the p53 pathway.</article-title>             <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>             <volume>20</volume>             <fpage>1502</fpage>             <lpage>1508</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Ulizzi1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulizzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>San Martini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terrenato</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1979</year>             <article-title>Changes of selection opportunities with a changing environment: regional heterogeneity in Italy.</article-title>             <source>Ann Hum Genet</source>             <volume>43</volume>             <fpage>137</fpage>             <lpage>141</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Miller1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dykes</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polesky</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>A simple salting out procedure for extracting DNA from human nucleated cells.</article-title>             <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>             <volume>16</volume>             <fpage>1215</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Giannoudis1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannoudis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrington</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>p53 codon 72 ARG/PRO polymorphism is not related to HPV type or lesion grade in low- and high-grade squamous intra-epithelial lesions and invasive squamous carcinoma of the cervix.</article-title>             <source>Int J Cancer</source>             <volume>83</volume>             <fpage>66</fpage>             <lpage>69</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Cohen1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <source>Statistical power analysis for behavioural sciences. 2<sup>nd</sup> Edition</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0035431-Armitage1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1994</year>             <source>Statistical Methods in Medical Research, 3rd edn</source>             <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Blackwell Science</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>