<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-08643</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleobiology</subject><subject>Vertebrate paleontology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleobiology</subject><subject>Vertebrate paleontology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Earth sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleobiology</subject><subject>Vertebrate paleontology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological anthropology</subject><subject>Paleoanthropology</subject><subject>Physical anthropology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Handedness in Neandertals from the El Sidrón (Asturias, Spain): Evidence from Instrumental Striations with Ontogenetic Inferences</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Handedness in Neandertals from El Sidrón Cave</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Estalrrich</surname><given-names>Almudena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><addr-line>PaleoAnthropology Group, Department of Paleobiology, Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales (MNCN-CSIC), Madrid, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalueza-Fox</surname><given-names>Carles</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Institut de Biologia Evolutiva - Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">aestalrrich@mncn.csic.es</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AE AR. Performed the experiments: AE. Analyzed the data: AE. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AE AR. Wrote the paper: AE AR.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e62797</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Estalrrich, Rosas</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The developed cognitive capabilities for <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> seems to be the result of a specialized and lateralized brain, and as a result of this, humans display the highest degree of manual specialization or handedness among the primates. Studies regarding its emergence and distribution within the genus <italic>Homo</italic> show that handedness is present very early. The mode in which it was articulated and spread across the different species during the course of human evolution could provide information about our own cognitive capacities. Here we report the manual laterality attributed to eleven 49,000 old Neandertal individuals from El Sidrón cave (Spain), through the study of instrumental or cultural striations on the anterior dentition. Our results show a predominant pattern addressed to right-handers. These results fit within the modern human handedness distribution pattern and provide indirect evidence for behavior and brain lateralization on Neandertals. They support the early establishment of handedness in our genus. Moreover, the individual identified as Juvenile 1 (6–8 years old at death), displays the same striation pattern as the adult Neandertals from the sample, and thereby the ontogenic development of manual laterality in that Neandertal population seems to be similar to that of living modern humans.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This research is funded by the Spanish Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad (Projects CGL2009-09013 and CGL2012-36682). El Sidrón site is being excavated with the support of the Consejería de Cultura of the Asturias Autonomous Government. A.E. has the benefit of a predoctoral FPI fellowship of the Spanish Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad (BES-2010-033914) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mineco.gob.es/portal/site/mineco/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mineco.gob.es/portal/site/mineco/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Handedness is the tendency to display left- or right-hand task preference, and modern humans show a high frequency of right hand specialization compared to all great apes, meaning that such pattern of manual laterality should have been developed only in our actual lineage.</p>
<p>In order to understand and define how and when handedness evolved at population-level, several studies have been carried out through the paleoanthropological record employing different methodologies like stone tool production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Oll1">[1]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Steele1">[2]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Bargall1">[3]</xref>, the analysis of cut mark orientation on bones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Bromage1">[4]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Pickering1">[5]</xref>, brain lateralization from endocasts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Holloway1">[6]</xref>, asymmetries in hominid upper limb skeletons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Cashmore1">[7]</xref>, and the orientation of scratches striating the labial surface of anterior teeth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>.</p>
<p>As a result it is acknowledged that during Middle Pleistocene, <italic>Homo heidelbergensis</italic> had an exclusively right-handed preference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Oll1">[1]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LozanoRuiz1">[9]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano1">[10]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano2">[11]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Frayer1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>For Neandertals, widespread evidence from France to Spain to Croatia, beginning at least 130,000 years ago shows that they followed a right-handed pattern close to that characteristic to modern <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>. Studies by Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>, Trinkaus <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Trinkaus1">[13]</xref>, Lalueza-Fox and Frayer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lalueza1">[14]</xref>, Frayer <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Frayer2">[15]</xref> and Volpato <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Volpato1">[16]</xref> on skeletal evidence, indicate that although there is a predominant right-hand use at species-level, at least two individuals with a left-handed preference have been identified, showing a frequency of 93% right-handers to 7% left-handers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Volpato1">[16]</xref>. Thus, Neandertals show a frequency identical to modern human populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Faurie1">[17]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Uomini1">[18]</xref>.</p>
<p>This study analyzes the directionality of the instrumental or cultural striations present on the anterior teeth of eleven individuals of known sex and age from El Sidrón cave (Asturias, Spain), substantially increasing the Neandertal sample.</p>
<sec id="s1a">
<title>El Sidrón Cave</title>
<p>The sample comprises teeth from the Neandertal fossils of El Sidrón cave, which are housed at the Department of Paleobiology at National Museum of Natural History (MNCN- CSIC) in Madrid, Spain. The age of the bone assemblage has been estimated at ∼49 kya <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-TorresT1">[19]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Wood1">[20]</xref>. At the moment, the minimum number of individuals (MNI) identified at the site is 13, including seven adults, three adolescents, two juveniles and one infant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox1">[21]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Rosas1">[22]</xref>. We have genetic profiles for each individual, so we are reasonably certain of the sex, based on presence (or absence) of Y chromosome markers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox1">[21]</xref>. So, unlike other studies which estimates sex based on size or robusticity, we approached the sex-estimation also from paleogenetics. The combined results show that the sample comprises at least 3 adult females, 3 adult males, 2 adolescent males, and 1 juvenile possible male. For 4 individuals it was not possible to retrieve genetic material and the skeletal evidence was not enough to fairly conclude the estimation. In addition, several human remains show evidence that they were subject to cannibalism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Rosas1">[22]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Rosas2">[23]</xref>.</p>
<p>The dental fossil sample selected for this study comprises 66 teeth (62 are permanent teeth while 4 are deciduous teeth) corresponding to 11 of the 13 individuals identified at the El Sidrón cave. A complete list of the specimens here analyzed with their catalogue number, anatomical identification and individuals assignment is provided on supplementary materials (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0062797.s001">Table S1</xref>). The individuals infant 1 and juvenile 2 do not have associated teeth. No taphonomical, excavation or preparation damage have been observed on the teeth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Rosas1">[22]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Rosas2">[23]</xref>. All dental modifications observed on teeth are clearly related to both masticatory and non-mastication wear (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062797-g001">Figure 1</xref> as an example of the good preservation of dental surface). Posterior teeth show no evidence of buccal (or labial) striations.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062797-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Cultural or Instrumental striation morphology.</title>
<p>200× picture of SD-355 (RI<sub>2</sub>) associated to individual Adult 4. Cut mark features are indicated on the image. Directionality is from cervix to the incisal edge.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s1b">
<title>Instrumental or Cultural Striations</title>
<p>Instrumental or cultural striations are cut marks associated with the use of teeth as a third hand, known as the “stuff-and-cut” behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Brace1">[24]</xref>. Brace <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Brace1">[24]</xref> used this term to describe differential, heavy wear on Neandertal incisors and canines compared to their premolars and molars. When an individual holds some material between the teeth with one hand pulling and the opposite hand cutting the material, scratches are sometimes left on the labial surface of incisors and canines when the lithic tool accidentally glances the tooth surface. Experimental work using teeth from dental extractions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LozanoRuiz1">[9]</xref> has produced cut marks on enamel similar to those found on original Neandertal teeth.</p>
<p>Several authors have characterized the morphology of cultural striations on Pleistocene hominids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LozanoRuiz1">[9]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano1">[10]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano2">[11]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lalueza1">[14]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Frayer2">[15]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Volpato1">[16]</xref>, among others). The scratches appear mostly on the labial surface of the central and lateral incisors and are more common in the central area than the mesial or distal sides of the teeth. On the canine they most commonly occur near the mesial surface. Their length varies between 1 to 4 mm and the width varies from 20 to 100 microns. These striations exhibit the same morphological features of the cut marks on bone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Bromage1">[4]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Shipman1">[25]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Bromage2">[26]</xref>, <italic>i.e.</italic>, Hertzian cones, grooves with a “V”- shaped section, and microscratches at the bottom, which vary depending on the stone tool that produced the striation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LozanoRuiz1">[9]</xref>, and, at least, linear and parallel borders. Because of this morphology it is possible to establish the directionality of the cut mark <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Bromage2">[26]</xref> and infer the manual laterality of the individual who has made the cut mark.</p>
<p>Based on these features, Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>, Lalueza-Fox and Frayer, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lalueza1">[14]</xref> and Lozano-Ruíz <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LozanoRuiz1">[9]</xref>, linked the orientation and directionality of the cultural striation with a preferred hand movement, leading to the establishment of a direct relation between the individual’s hand movement and the directionality of the cultural striation. Once a statistical significance was reached, it allowed the assignment of handedness to individuals.</p>
<p>Instrumental striations have been reported on Middle and Late Pleistocene fossil hominids from the sites of La Quina <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Martin1">[27]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox2">[28]</xref>, L’Hortus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-deLumley1">[29]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>, Cova Negra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>, Shanidar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Trinkaus2">[30]</xref>, Krapina <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lalueza1">[14]</xref>, Vindija <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Frayer2">[15]</xref>, Regourdou <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Volpato1">[16]</xref>, Tabun I <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox2">[28]</xref>, Broken Hill <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox2">[28]</xref>, Boxgrove <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Hillson1">[31]</xref> and Sima de los Huesos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LozanoRuiz1">[9]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano1">[10]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Frayer1">[12]</xref>, as well as in several modern human populations, such as the Chalcolithic individuals from Pakistan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lucaks1">[32]</xref>, Neolithic from Spain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox3">[33]</xref> and Sweden <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Molnar1">[34]</xref>, Paleoindian from North America <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Green1">[35]</xref>, Australian Aborigines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano1">[10]</xref>, and Fueguians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox3">[33]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Each tooth was inspected under binocular lens and Environmental Scanning Electron Microscope (ESEM Fei- Quanta 200 <sup>©</sup> located in the National Museum of Natural History (MNCN-CSIC). All teeth were examined at 25.0 kv accelerating voltage and low vacuum mode. The magnification observations ranged from 40× to 1000× in some instances.</p>
<p>As 21 teeth were found <italic>in situ</italic> (in their respective <italic>alveoli</italic> on both the maxilla and mandible), it has been necessary to perform high-resolution replicas of them, due to the limited dimensions of the microscope’s chamber. Following the procedures described elsewhere in detail, a hydrophilic vinyl polysiloxane resin was employed to make the negative cast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Bromage2">[26]</xref>, and a polyurethane resin to make the replica <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-MartnezMaza1">[36]</xref>. Using a low viscosity variety it is possible to produce replicas of great resolution and the details on the negative impression can last more than a year; polyurethane has a moderately fast drying time, excellent viscosity and fluidity that allow faithfully details reproduction of the enamel surface. Finally, the replicas were covered with a thin layer of metallic gold (Sputter Coater, EMITECH K550Y®) to allow the ESEM visualization.</p>
<p>The orientation of the <italic>striae</italic> to the occlusal plane was measured directly on digital images (NIH Image J, Image Processing and Analysis in Java; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Rasband1">[37]</xref>). In this study, we have considered the instrumental striations that have an undoubted cut-mark morphology, that is: we did not count the scratches that appear worn (cut-mark morphology is almost removed, and thus we cannot be sure about their origin) or the ones that are short and thin (thinner than 20 microns and length less than 1 mm, as was described before according to the results on the Krapina Neandertals sample <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lalueza1">[14]</xref>), and could be confused with dietary dental microwear. Orientation's classification was made following Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref>. X<sup>2</sup> tests were performed to examine the significance (p&lt;0.05) of the striations' distribution on each individual.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>All individuals studied at the El Sidrón site present instrumental striations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062797-g002">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062797-g003">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062797-g004">4</xref>). The results of the characterization of the orientation for each tooth associated to an individual are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062797-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062797-t002">2</xref>. Considering them as a group, the preferred orientation is right-oblique (58% of the total number of cultural striations analyzed), followed by the horizontal orientation (17% of the total). Vertical (14%) and left-oblique (11%) orientations are also present in all the individuals but their frequencies are not high.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062797-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Instrumental striations present on the El Sidrón Adolescents.</title>
<p>Left: LI<sub>2</sub> from Adolescent 1. Right: LI<sup>1</sup> belonging to Adolescent 2. All instrumental striations are distinguishable, and some are also still slightly covered by sediment, that reinforces their ancient origin. M = mesial; D = distal.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0062797-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Instrumental striations present on two El Sidrón Adult females.</title>
<p>Scanning Electron Microscope images of the instrumental striations identified on the left upper canine on Adult 3 (Left) and on the right lower lateral incisor from Adult 4 (Right). M = mesial; D = distal.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0062797-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Instrumental striations present on one El Sidrón Adult males.</title>
<p>ESEM micrographs of the labial surface of the upper right central incisor and upper right canine belonging to Adult 1. M = mesial; D = distal.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0062797-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Instrumental striations on the El Sidrón adult Neandertals.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062797-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">MAXILLARY DENTITION</td>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">MANDIBULAR DENTITION</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INDIVIDUAL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADULT 1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADULT 2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADULT 3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADULT 4</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADULT 5</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 23</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADULT 6</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADULT 7</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>In this table are the results for the analysis of the total number of instrumental striations counted per tooth (n) and the number of scratches depending on their orientation. RC: right canine; RI2: right lateral incisor; RI1: right central incisor; LI1: left central incisor; LI2: left lateral incisor; LC: left canine. RO: right-oblique orientation; LO: left-oblique orientation; V: vertical orientation; H: horizontal orientation; n:.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0062797-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Instrumental striations on the El Sidrón immature Neandertals.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062797-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">MAXILLARY DENTITION</td>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">MANDIBULAR DENTITION</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INDIVIDUAL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RI1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LC</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADOLESCENT 1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADOLESCENT 2</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ADOLESCENT 3</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = O</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>JUVENILE 1</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 6*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 14*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 18*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n = 7*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RO = 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H = 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LO = 2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V = 1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>The results for the analysis of the number of instrumental striations (n) counted on each tooth and the number according to their orientation through the occlusal/incisal plane on the El Sidrón adolescent and juvenile Neandertals. * Indicate deciduous teeth. RC: right canine; RI2: right lateral incisor; RI1: right central incisor; LI1: left central incisor; LI2: left lateral incisor; LC: left canine. RO: right-oblique orientation; LO: left-oblique orientation; V: vertical orientation; H: horizontal orientation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The tooth with the highest number of cultural striations registered in the sample belongs to adolescent 2, followed by adult 1 and adults 3 and 4. Regarding the strations' measurements on the sample, the mean length is 2.063 mm (SD = 0.147) and the mean width is 43.5 microns (SD = 16 microns), similar to the Krapina Neandertals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lalueza1">[14]</xref>.</p>
<p>Juvenile 1 has several instrumental striations, whose morphology has been carefully studied, and coincide with the cultural striations pattern, like the adult Neandertals from the sample, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062797-g005">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062797-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Instrumental striations on one El Sidrón Adult and the juvenile Neandertal.</title>
<p>Morphological comparison between the instrumental striations found on: Left: a mandibular right deciduous lateral incisor (SD-1600c) from Juvenile 1; and Right: a mandibular right lateral incisor belonging to Adult 5 (SD-1327a). M = mesial; D = distal.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The X<sup>2</sup> analyses comparing the number of right vs left scratches reveal that all X<sup>2</sup> values exceed the table value of 7.815 (at 3 degrees of freedom and p&lt;0.00001). Based on this we can reject the null hypothesis of a random distribution in favor of the hypothesis the striations are showing a preferred orientation on every El Sidrón Neandertal (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062797-t003">Table 3</xref>), which is right-oblique.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0062797-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Comparison of number of right vs left scratches.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062797-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chi-square</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.64</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescent 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescent 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.80</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescent 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juvenile 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;.0000001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>The results of the X<sup>2</sup> analysis (x<sup>2</sup> values exceed the table value of 7.815 at 3 degree of freedom) show that all values accept a preferred orientation regarding the instrumental striations' distribution, and in this sample is oblique to the right.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>As said, all individuals analyzed from the El Sidrón individuals have cut marks on their erupted anterior dentition. Our results show a predominantly right-oblique orientation of the instrumental striations, typically ascribed to right-handers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lalueza1">[14]</xref>. The results match with the modern human handedness pattern, and provide additional indirect evidence for Neandertal brain lateralization. This handedness pattern, together with the asymmetries on cranial dural sinuses and blood drainage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-PeaMelin1">[38]</xref>, the morphology of hyoid bone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Arensburg1">[39]</xref> and the same derived FOXP2 variant of modern humans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Krause1">[40]</xref> as part of the basis for human speech capability, reinforces a modern brain asymmetry pattern in Neandertals.</p>
<p>In our sample we found a substantial number of vertical striations (177 out of 1233, or 14% of the total striations counted). The vertical marks have been associated with the processing of plant fibers in Paleoindian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Bax1">[41]</xref> and according to the authors, it is not possible to address a manual preference on the sample they studied. Since the marks described by Bax and Ungar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Bax1">[41]</xref> display the characteristic cut mark morphology associated to the instrumental striations here considered, and are also shorter and thinner, we consider that the behavior responsible for the scratch formation is different in both samples. Therefore, it is not recommended to analyze all the anterior scratches to address handedness in past populations.</p>
<p>Individual adult 2 presents almost the same number of right and left-oblique striae, but the left ones are covering the right oriented striations. This pattern appears on both mandibular and maxillary dentition, but is more evident on the lower teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062797-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Despite this, the interpretation of X<sup>2</sup> results show that this individual is right-handed. The presence of a severe oral pathology on the left side on his mandible <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Prieto1">[42]</xref> plus dental calculus deposits on the occlusal molar surface, suggest that this individual may have changed his hand orientation to avoid the pain on his mouth, and can explain the fact that the left-oriented striations appear new when compared with the right ones. We propose that chewing with the left and even the action of holding materials for processing could be painful. That could have motivated the individual to start using the right side of his teeth to seize materials and later cut them, adapting his manual laterality to his actual circumstances. According to the well-preserved striae's morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0062797-g006">Figure 6</xref>), this change may have happened fast, and since no postcranial elements have been associated to this individual yet, we propose the pathological condition as the most plausible explanation.</p>
<fig id="pone-0062797-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>The peculiar case found on El Sidrón Adult 2.</title>
<p>ESEM image showing the left-oblique striations covering the right-oblique on a RI<sub>1</sub> from Adult 2. M = mesial; D = distal. R = right; L =  left.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Juvenile 1 displays the same striation pattern as the other adult Neandertals from the sample, although the number of scratches is slightly below the adults. The number of scratches varies depending on how many times the individual have repeated the action <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano1">[10]</xref>. So, despite the juvenile seems to have performed this task less often than adults, the number indicates that it could be an habitual behavior, and he left enough cut marks on his front teeth to describe him as a right-handed individual.</p>
<p>Previous studies dealing with those scratches were done on adult Neandertals, so this is the first time that handedness has been found in a juvenile Neandertal. The estimated age for this individual is about 6–8 years old, so it seems that the ontogenic development of manual laterality in that Neandertal population is similar to that of actual modern humans. In this specie an unimanual hand use for reaching objects has been detected early on infants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Nelson1">[43]</xref>, although manual laterality preference when performing complex tasks and bimanual actions appear on later age <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Sacrey1">[44]</xref> and it is completely established around seven years of age <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Fennell1">[45]</xref>.</p>
<p>Bermúdez de <italic>Castro et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1">[8]</xref> and Lozano <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano1">[10]</xref> presented results of handedness for subadult individuals (mostly adolescents) for the SH sample. On their results, they show evidence for right-handedness on adolescent individuals, and even on one individual with an estimated age at death of 3–4 years old. This individual has only 2 cut marks on one tooth, so we are not sure if it could indicate an incipient establishment of handedness or maybe its number is underrepresented because the individual's anterior dentition has not been recovered.</p>
<p>According to our results, the El Sidrón individuals are all right-handed, and when comparing to other Neandertals described in the literature, the distribution of manual laterality coincides with the handedness distribution at the Vindija cave and Atapuerca-Sima de los Huesos site, whose population appears to consist exclusively of right-handed individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-LozanoRuiz1">[9]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lozano1">[10]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Frayer1">[12]</xref>. At the Neandertal sites of Hortus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-deLumley1">[29]</xref> and Krapina <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Lalueza1">[14]</xref> the dominant trend is the same, oblique to the right, but two specimens (KDP 4 and Hortus VII) have an oblique to the left predominant orientation, which is characteristics of left-handed individuals. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062797-t004">Table 4</xref> summarizes the findings regarding manual lateralization in Neandertals by the study of cultural striations, including the last findings at the El Sidrón fossils. At population level in Neandertals, the distribution of handedness based on this feature is 27 right-handers to 2 left-handers, or 93% to 7% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Volpato1">[16]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Uomini1">[18]</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0062797-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>List of Neanderthal sites where handedness has been identified from cultural striations.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062797-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INDIVIDUAL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HANDEDNESS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REFERENCES</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cova Negra</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hortus VII</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">de Lumley, 1973; Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hortus VIII</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">de Lumley, 1973; Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hortus IX</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">de Lumley, 1973; Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hortus XI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">de Lumley, 1973; Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hortus XII</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">de Lumley, 1973; Bermúdez de Castro <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KDP 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalueza-Fox &amp; Frayer, 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KDP 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalueza-Fox &amp; Frayer, 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KDP 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalueza-Fox &amp; Frayer, 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KDP 17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalueza-Fox &amp; Frayer, 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KDP 18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalueza-Fox &amp; Frayer, 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KDP 29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalueza-Fox &amp; Frayer, 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KDP Q</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lalueza-Fox &amp; Frayer, 1997</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Le Régourdou 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R*</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volpato <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vindija 206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frayer <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vindija 288</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frayer <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vindija 289</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frayer <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vindija 290</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frayer <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adult 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adult 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adult 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adult 4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adult 5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adult 6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adult 7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adolescent 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adolescent 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Adolescent 3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sidrón Juvenile 1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>On the left column are the specimens that have been studied, and the references of the study (column on the right). The identification as a right- (R) or left-hander (L) is on the central column. KDP: Krapina Dental Person <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Radovi1">[47]</xref>. This table extends the data provided by Uomini <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Uomini1">[18]</xref>, considering only data from the analysis of labial scratches. * =  data also from humeral morphology.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>This is consistent with the distribution of manual dexterity in modern humans, which in any population, left-handed individuals are expected to be between 3% and 25% of the total, while right-handed individuals could be between 97% and 75% of the population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Faurie1">[17]</xref>. This is a highly variable range, but indicates that the most probable manual laterality in one population is the right-handed one <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Faurie1">[17]</xref>. In our case, all individuals identified match with right-handed individuals, as was expected in a human population.</p>
<p>Regarding the behavioral consequences derived from the manual laterality, a recent model proposed by Abrams and Panaggio <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062797-Abrams1">[46]</xref>, states that the high prevalence of the same manual laterality pattern at the populational level, may suggest a collaborative society with low level of intra-society violence. This was the first model to make a clear correlation between population-level handedness and social behavior and, if we apply its conclusions to the extreme frequency of right-handedness in Neandertals it may suggest a cooperative society, or at least among groups such as the El Sidrón group.</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Individuals identified from the El Sidrón dental sample present a predominant right-oblique orientation of their instrumental striations, typically related to right-handed individuals. The results enhance the knowledge of Neandertal manual laterality and provide additional indirect evidence for Neandertal brain lateralization.</p>
<p>One individual, identified as adult 2, presents evidence for a change in his manual motion, probably as a result to avoid pain on his unhealthy mouth. This could suggest a rapid adaptative behavior in this group.</p>
<p>The handedness' distribution in Neandertals and its ontogenetic development match within the modern human laterality pattern at population level, and may have behavioral and social applications to this fossil species. In addition, those results are giving information about the evolutionary development and establishment of our own asymmetric hand use, indicating that the achievement of this pattern may be shared with our common ancestor.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0062797.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062797.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>List of the El Sidrón specimens analyzed in this study, with their catalogue number, anatomical identification and individuals assignment.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are deeply grateful to D. W. Frayer for helpful comments and discussion on this research topic, and M. Lozano and N. T. Uomini for their helpful reviews on this manuscript. We also want to thank A. García-Tabernero, B. Fernández Cascón, the remainder members of the PaleoAnthropology Group from the MNCN-CSIC and the El Sidrón Cave excavation team for their amazing work directed by Marco de la Rasilla.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Oll1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ollé A (2003) Variabilitat i patrons funcionals en els sistemes tècnics de mode 2. Anàlisi de les deformacions d’ús en els conjunts lítics del Riparo Esterno de Grotta Paglicci (Rignano Garganico, Foggia), Aridos (Arganda, Madrid) i Galeria-TN (Atapuerca,Burgos). Ph.D. Dissertation, Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Tarragona, Spain.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Steele1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Steele J, Uomini NT (2005) Humans, tools and handedness In: Roux V, Bril B, editors. Stone knapping: The necessary conditions for a uniquely hominin behaviour. Cambridge: McDonald Institute for Archaeological Research. 217–239.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Bargall1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bargalló A, Mosquera M (2013) Hand Laterality and Stone Lithics. Poster presented at the Tarragona Laterality Conference (Spain).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Bromage1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bromage</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Microscopic Criteria for the Determination of Directionality of Cutmarks on Bone</article-title>. <source>Amer J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Pickering1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hensley-Marschand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cutmarks and hominid handedness</article-title>. <source>J Arch Sci</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Holloway1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Holloway RL, Sherwood CC, Hof PR, Rilling JK (2009) Evolution of the Brain in Humans-Paleoneurology. In: Binder MD, Hirokawa N, Windhorst U, editors. The New Encyclopedia of Neurosciences. New York: Springer. 1326–1338.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Cashmore1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cashmore</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uomini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chapelain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The evolution of handedness in humans and great apes: A review and current issues</article-title>. <source>J Anthrop Sci</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-BermdezdeCastro1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bermúdez de Castro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bromage</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Jalvo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Buccal striations on fossil human anterior teeth: evidence of handedness in the middle and early Upper Pleistocene</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-LozanoRuiz1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano-Ruiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bermúdez de Castro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinón-Torres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Cutmarks on fossil human anterior teeth of the Sima de los Huesos site (Atapuerca, Spain)</article-title>. <source>J Archaeol Sci</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1127</fpage>–<lpage>1135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Lozano1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bermúdez de Castro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carbonell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arsuaga</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Non-Masticatory uses of the anterior teeth of Sima de los Huesos individuals (Sierra de Atapuerca, Spain)</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>728</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Lozano2"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosquera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bermúdez de Castro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arsuaga</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carbonell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Right handedness of <italic>Homo heidelbergensis</italic> from Sima de los Huesos (Atapuerca, Spain) 500,000 years ago</article-title>. <source>Evol Hum Behav</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Frayer1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frayer</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bermúdez de Castro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carbonell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arsuaga</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>More than 500,000 years of right handedness in Europe</article-title>. <source>Laterality</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Trinkaus1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trinkaus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Postcranial robusticity in <italic>Homo.</italic> II: Humeral bilateral asymmetry and bone plasticity</article-title>. <source>Amer J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Lalueza1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalueza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frayer</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Non-dietary marks in the anterior dentition of the Krapina Neanderthals</article-title>. <source>Int J Osteoarch</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Frayer2"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frayer</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalueza-Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radovčić</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bondioli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Right handed Neanderthals: Vindija and Beyond</article-title>. <source>J Anthropol Sci</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Volpato1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Volpato V, Macchiarelli R, Guatelli-Steinberg D, Fiore I, Bondioli L, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2012) Hand to Mouth in a Neandertal: Right-Handedness in Regourdou 1. PlosOne 7: e43949 <comment>Doi <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/101371/journalpone0043949" xlink:type="simple">101371/journalpone0043949</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Faurie1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faurie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <collab xlink:type="simple">Schiefenhövel W, Le Bomin S, Billiard S, Raymond M</collab> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Variation in the frequency of left-handedness in traditional societies</article-title>. <source>Curr Anthropol</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Uomini1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Uomini N (2011) Handedness in Neandertals In: Conard NJ, Richter J, editors. Neanderthal Lifeways, Subsistence and Technology: One Hundred Fifty Years of Neanderthal Study. Heidelberg: Springer. 139–154.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-TorresT1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres T</surname><given-names>de</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grün</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eggins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valladas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Dating of the hominid <italic>Homo neanderthalensis</italic> remains accumulation from El Sidrón Cave Piloña, Asturias, North Spain: an example of multi-methodological approach to the dating of Upper Pleistocene sites</article-title>. <source>Archaeometry</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>680</fpage>–<lpage>705</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Wood1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>TFG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Torres</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tisnérat-Laborde</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valladas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A new date for the neanderthals from El Sidrón cave (Asturias, Northern Spain)</article-title>. <source>Archaeometry</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalueza-Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estalrrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gigli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García-Tabernero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic evidence for patrilocal mating behaviour among Neandertal groups</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Rosas1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estalrrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García-Tabernero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bastir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García-Vargas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Les Néandertaliens d’El Sidrón (Asturies, Espagne) Actualisation d’un nouvel échantillon</article-title>. <source>L'Anthropologie</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Rosas2"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Maza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bastir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García-Tabernero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalueza-Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Paleobiology and comparative morphology of a late Neandertal sample from El Sidrón, Asturias, Spain</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>19266</fpage>–<lpage>19271</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Brace1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brace</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Comment on “Did La Ferrasie I use his teeth as tools?”</article-title>. <source>Curr Anthropol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>809</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Shipman1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shipman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Early hominid hunting, butchering, and carcass processing behaviours: Approaches to the fossil record</article-title>. <source>J Anthropol Archaeol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Bromage2"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bromage</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The scanning electron microscopy replica technique and recent applications to the study of fossil bone</article-title>. <source>Scanning Electron Microscopy</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Martin1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Martin H (1923) L'Homme fossile de la Quina. Paris: Doin. 260p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox2"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalueza-Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez- Pérez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Cutmarks and post-mortem striations in fossil human teeth</article-title>. <source>Hum Evol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-deLumley1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Lumley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>L’Homme de l’Hortus</article-title>. <source>Étude Quat</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Trinkaus2"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Trinkaus E (1983) The Shanidar Neandertals. New York: Academic Press. 528p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Hillson1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillson</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parfitt</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Two hominin incisor teeth from the middle Pleistocene site of Boxgrove, Sussex, England</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Lucaks1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucaks</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pastor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Activity-Induced Patterns of Dental Abrasion in Prehistoric Pakistan: Evidence From Mehgarh and Harappa</article-title>. <source>Amer J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-LaluezaFox3"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalueza-Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Information obtained from a microscopic examination of cultural striations</article-title>. <source>Int J Osteoarch</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Molnar1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molnar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dental wear and oral pathology: possible evidence and consequences of habitual use of teeth in a Swedish Neolithic sample</article-title>. <source>Amer J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>431</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Green1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Titmus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The Buhl Burial: A Paleoindian Woman from Southern Idaho</article-title>. <source>Am Antiq</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-MartnezMaza1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-Maza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García-Vargas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estalrrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rasilla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Bone remodelling in Neanderthal mandibles from the El Sidrón site (Asturias, Spain)</article-title>. <source>Biol Lett</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Rasband1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rasband WS (1997–2008) ImageJ, U. S. National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland, U S A. Image J. Image Processing and Analysis in Java. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/" xlink:type="simple">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>. Accessed 2009 Dec 19.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-PeaMelin1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peña-Melián</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>García-Tabernero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bastir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rasilla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Paleoneurology of two new neandertal occipitals from El Sidrón (Asturias, Spain) in the context of <italic>Homo</italic> endocranial evolution</article-title>. <source>Anat Rec</source> <volume>294</volume>: <fpage>1370</fpage>–<lpage>1381</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Arensburg1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arensburg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tillier</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vandermeersch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duday</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schepartz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>A Middle Palaeolithic human hyoid bone</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>338</volume>: <fpage>758</fpage>–<lpage>760</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Krause1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalueza-Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enard</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The derived FOXP2 variant of modern humans was shared with Neandertals</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1908</fpage>–<lpage>1912</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Bax1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bax</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ungar</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Incisor Labial surface wear striations in Modern Humans and their implications for handedness in Middle and Late Pleistocene Hominids</article-title>. <source>Int J Osteoarchaeol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Prieto1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Hallazgos paleopatológicos en la mandíbula SDR-7–8 del Sidrón</article-title>. In: <source>Madrid: Monografías del Museo de Altamira</source> <name name-style="western"><surname>Montes-Barquín</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lasheras-Corruchaga</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, editors. Neandertales cantábricos: estado de la cuestión. <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Nelson1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Unimanual to bimanual: Tracking the development of handedness from 6 to 24 months</article-title>. <source>Infant Behav Dev</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Sacrey1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sacrey LA, Arnold B, Whishaw IQ, Gonzalez CL (2012) Precocious hand use preference in reach-to-eat behavior versus manual construction in 1- to 5-year-old children. Dev Psychobiol <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/dev.21083" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/dev.21083</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Fennell1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fennell EB (1986) Handedness in neuropsychological research. In: Hannay JH, editors. Experimental Techniques in Human Neuropsychology. New York: Oxford University Press. 15–44.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Abrams1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Abrams DM, Panaggio MJ (2012) A model balancing cooperation and competition can explain our right handed world and the dominance of left-handed athletes. J R Soc Interface <comment>DOI:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2012.0211" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rsif.2012.0211</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062797-Radovi1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Radovčić J, Smith F, Trinkaus E, Wolpoff M (1988) The Krapina Hominids. An Ilustrated Catalog of Skeletal Collection. Croatian National History Museum. 118p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>