<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-43774</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093294</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA modification</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular cell biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary systematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Phylogenetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Epigenetics</subject><subject>Gene expression</subject><subject>Human genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Ethnicities</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographic and national differences</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Demography</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Multiple Ethnic Origins of Mitochondrial DNA Lineages for the Population of Mauritius</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Multiple Origins of mtDNA Lineages in Mauritius</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fregel</surname><given-names>Rosa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seetah</surname><given-names>Krish</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Betancor</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suárez</surname><given-names>Nicolás M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calaon</surname><given-names>Diego</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Čaval</surname><given-names>Saša</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janoo</surname><given-names>Anwar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pestano</surname><given-names>Jose</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¶</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Genetics, Faculty of Medicine, University of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Las Palmas, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Genetics, Faculty of Biology, University of La Laguna, La Laguna, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Anthropology, Stanford University, Stanford, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Forensic Genetics Laboratory, Institute of Legal Medicine of Las Palmas, Las Palmas, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>IDEAS Interdepartmental Centre, Ca'Foscari University, Venice, Italy</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Department of History, University of Mauritius, Reduit, Mauritius</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petraglia</surname><given-names>Michael D.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Oxford, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn id="fn1" fn-type="other"><p>¶ Senior author.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">rfregel@gmail.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RF KS EB NMS DC SC AJ JP. Performed the experiments: RF EB NMS JP. Analyzed the data: RF KS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KS JP. Wrote the paper: RF KS EB NMS DC SC AJ JP.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<elocation-id>e93294</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Fregel et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article reports on the first genetic assessment of the contemporary Mauritian population. Small island nodes such as Mauritius played a critical role in historic globalization processes and revealing high-resolution details of labour sourcing is crucial in order to better understand early-modern diaspora events. Mauritius is a particularly interesting case given detailed historic accounts attesting to European (Dutch, French and British), African and Asian points of origin. Ninety-seven samples were analysed for mitochondrial DNA to begin unravelling the complex dynamics of the island's modern population. In corroboration with general demographic information, the majority of maternal lineages were derived from South Asia (58.76%), with Malagasy (16.60%), East/Southeast Asian (11.34%) and Sub-Saharan African (10.21%) also making significant contributions. This study pinpoints specific regional origins for the South Asian genetic contribution, showing a greater influence on the contemporary population from northern and southeast India. Moreover, the analysis of lineages related to the slave trade demonstrated that Madagascar and East Asia were the main centres of origin, with less influence from West Africa.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Since prehistoric times, the Indian Ocean has provided the backdrop for major maritime expansion events, resulting in the exchange of crops, stocks and languages among African, South Asian and Island Southeast Asian populations, and catalysing extensive cross-cultural interaction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Fuller1">[1]</xref>.</p>
<p>At the western edge of the Indian Ocean, African and Austronesian communities inhabited Madagascar and the Comoro Archipelago before European colonization. Other islands in this region, such as Réunion Island and Mauritius, although visited by the Arabs during the Islamic expansion, were not permanently occupied until the arrival of Europeans. Consensus suggests that in all cases, Europeans first imported sub-Saharan African and Malagasy slaves for labour provision and later, indentured workers from South and Southeast Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Allen1">[2]</xref>. However, the complexity of this situation is highlighted by historical interrogations of extant records <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Allen1">[2]</xref>. The present day multi-ethnic population structure of these islands reflects their idiosyncratic histories.</p>
<p>Early molecular genetic studies of the haploid characteristics of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) have been used to confirm the presence of Austronesian female lineages in Madagascar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Soodyall1">[3]</xref>. Subsequent research revealed the complex nature of settlement on this island, with the inclusion of at least three putative parental populations of African, Indonesian and Indian origin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dubut1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Hurles1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Razafindrazaka1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Tofanelli1">[7]</xref>. A similar result was obtained for the Comoro Archipelago <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Gourjon1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Msaidie1">[9]</xref>. In relation to Réunion Island, phylogeographic analysis not only detected strong founder effects and gender asymmetrical gene flow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-BerniellLee1">[10]</xref> but also tracked the most probable origins of the <italic>Malbar</italic> and <italic>Zarab</italic> ethnic groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dubut2">[11]</xref>.</p>
<p>This study initiates a process to disentangle the mtDNA genetic composition of Mauritius. Together with Réunion and Rodrigues, these islands form the Mascarene Archipelago, situated approximately 700 km off the eastern coast of Madagascar. From a genetic point of view, Mauritius is particularly interesting as it underwent complex and multi-scalar processes of European colonization. Visited by the Portuguese in 1510, the first permanent settlement was by the Dutch in 1638. The number of Dutch settlers was low; however, they brought hundreds of slaves to the island, mainly of Malagasy origin. A century later the Dutch abandoned the island with a contingent of their slaves. As with other enclaves marked by slavery, runaways were common and the Dutch left a group of such <italic>maroons</italic> on the island upon their departure. During the next century, the French occupied Mauritius. Slaves accompanied the first French settlers and grew steadily in size during the 18th century, reaching 75–85% of the island's population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Allen1">[2]</xref>. These slaves were mainly imported from Madagascar and Mozambique and it was estimated that 160,000 slaves were brought to Mauritius and Réunion between 1670–1810: 45% being Malagasy, 40% East African, 13% Indian and 2% West African <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Filliot1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>In 1810, the British captured Mauritius. Although this coincided with the Act of Abolition of the Trade in Slaves, it is suspected that some 30,000 slaves were imported to the island by the early 1820 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Allen1">[2]</xref>. In spite of this illegal trade, the emancipation of slaves and the high mortality rate due to cholera and malaria epidemics reduced the number of men capable of heavy agricultural work. This led to the “Great Experiment”, a trail by the British to use imported indentured labour, mainly from India. The situation is far from simple as African indentured labourers, as well as other Asian ethnic groups, were also recruited throughout this period <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Allen1">[2]</xref>. By 1846, Indian immigrants represented more than 35% of the population; by 1871 this figure had risen to two thirds, a proportional representation that has remained constant to present day <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Allen1">[2]</xref>. The partial admixture of these groups gave rise to the contemporary Creole population, and a highly plural society that retains features, such as polyglot language traditions, from its diverse founder populations.</p>
<p>In the present research we use the non-recombining characteristics of the mtDNA molecule and its well-known phylogeographic structure to identify the maternal sources and present day proportions of this admixed population.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>Ethical approval was provided by the Truth and Justice Commission, Port Louis, Mauritius, Chaired by Prof. Alex Borain. Written consent was recorded from all participants prior to partaking in the study. Consent was documented on a form, copies of which were lodged with the Truth and Justice Commission, Mauritius. The ethics committee at the Truth and Justice Commission approved, sanctioned and fully endorsed this mode of consent recording.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Samples</title>
<p>Ninety-seven samples were taken from anonymous unrelated Mauritian donors and all collaborators gave their informed consent to this project. These miscellaneous samples derived from all geographic zones on the island (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093294-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Ethnic affiliation and place of birth were obtained in order to determine the suitability of the sample for reflecting the whole Mauritian diversity.</p>
<fig id="pone-0093294-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Map showing the geographical origin of samples.</title>
<p>Mauritius, with the capital, Port Louis, starred. Figures in brackets represent number of individual samples taken per district.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>For comparative purposed, mtDNA sequences from Mauritian putative parental populations were retrieved from published data: Madagascar (n = 170), South Asia (n = 6504), East Asia (n = 9074), Southeast Asia (n = 4293), Africa (n = 9780) and Europe (n = 2913). Samples from Austronesia (n = 4451) and Réunion Island (n = 303) were also obtained (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s006">Table S1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s007">Table S2</xref>). For interregional comparison within South Asia, the Indian samples were subdivided in five distinct geographical areas: North, Southwest, Southeast, West and East. For assessing the geographical origins of lineages related with the transatlantic slave trade, the African samples were classified into West Africa, West Central Africa and East Africa groups.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>MtDNA analysis</title>
<p>Samples consisted in all cases of buccal swabs. DNA extraction was carried out using QIAmp DNA Mini Kit (QIAgen), following manufacturer recommendations. The complete hypervariable region (HVR) was amplified using the primers L15676 and H00945, previously described by Maca-Meyer et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer1">[13]</xref>. The PCR was carried out in 50-μl volumes, containing 1X Tris–HCl buffer, 200 μM of each dNTP, 2.5 mM MgCl2, 50 pmoles of each primer and 3 U of Taq polymerase (Bioline). The amplification was carried out in an Applied Biosystems 2720 Thermal Cycler with the following conditions: 30 amplification cycles with denaturation at 94°C for 30 s, annealing at 55°C for 30 s, and extension at 72°C for 90 s.</p>
<p>HVR haplotypes were classified into haplogroups based on the mtDNA tree (Build 15) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-vanOven1">[14]</xref>. For those haplotypes that could not be classified based solely on HVR sequence, several SNPs (1473, 1888, 3432, 10295, 10556, 12285, 12561, 14308, 14569, 15287, 15355, 15431, 15497 and 15968) were analysed by sequencing using PCR primer pairs and published protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer1">[13]</xref>. The coding region mtDNA sequence was obtained for nine samples by amplifying five PCR fragments using the primer pairs L923 – H3108 (fragment A), L3073 – H5306 (fragment B), L5278 – H8861 (fragment C), L8799 – H12603 (fragment D) and L12572 – H15720 (fragment E) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer1">[13]</xref>. The PCR was carried out in 50-μl volumes, containing 1X Tris–HCl buffer, 200 μM of each dNTP, 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 pmoles of each primer and 5 U of Taq polymerase (Bioline). The amplification was carried out in an Applied Biosystems 2720 Thermal Cycler with the following conditions: 30 amplification cycles with denaturation at 94°C for 30 s, annealing at different temperatures (56°C, 52°C, 55°C, 59°C and 57°C for A, B, C, D and E fragment respectively) for 30 s, and extension at 72°C for 4 min.</p>
<p>Sequencing reactions were performed using the BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit v3.1 (Applied Biosystems). The HVR fragment was sequenced using L15676, H16401, L16340, H00408 and H00945 primers. The PCR fragments for SNP typing were sequenced with both forward and reverse primers. Finally, the coding region sequencing was carried out using both the amplification and internal primers. All the primers used for sequencing were previously described by Maca-Meyer et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer1">[13]</xref>. The sequencing products were run on an ABI 3130xl Genetic Analyser (Applied Biosystems) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. Sequences were analysed with the Sequencing Analysis software v 5.2 (Applied Biosystems) and manually inspected using FinchTV ver. 1.4.0 software (Geospiza, Inc.; Seattle, WA, USA; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geospiza.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.geospiza.com</ext-link>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>The Mauritian sample was compared with its putative parental populations (South Asia, Madagascar, East Asia, Southeast Asia, Africa and Europe) and with other islands at the western fringe of the Indian Ocean (Réunion Island and Madagascar). The Reunionese sample from Berniell-Lee et al. (2008) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-BerniellLee1">[10]</xref> was used only for match analysis as it is not comparable with our miscellaneous sample from Mauritius due to founding events affecting its mtDNA diversity and its low representativeness of the whole population of Réunion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dubut2">[11]</xref>. The sample from the Dubut et al. (2009) study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dubut2">[11]</xref> could only be used for determining differences between Indian influences as it is based on the characterization of two concrete ethnic groups of Indian origin, the <italic>Malbar</italic> and the <italic>Zarab</italic>.</p>
<p>For comparison purposes, the mtDNA range used was 16065–16365 and all were reclassified into haplogroups according to their geographical adscription as in Dubut et al. 2009 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dubut2">[11]</xref>. Pair-wise F<sub>ST</sub> genetic distances <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Slatkin1">[15]</xref> based on haplogroup frequencies and diversity indices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Nei1">[16]</xref> were calculated as implemented in ARLEQUIN ver. 3.5.1.2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Schneider1">[17]</xref>. Multidimensional scaling (MDS) analysis of pair-wise F<sub>ST</sub> distances was performed using the SPSS statistical program v.19 (SPSS, Inc.). Matches for Mauritian sequences with other areas were distributed following the most probable contributor hierarchical order, in such a way that, when a match occurred with India or Madagascar, it was removed from consideration as a match in other areas. The first hierarchical priority was given to India, following by Madagascar, sub-Saharan Africa and finally the remaining areas, according to demographic and historical data that place India as the main contributor followed by Malagasy and sub-Saharan African slaves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Allen1">[2]</xref>. The origin of the Mauritian putative Indian lineages was assigned using the Bayesian approach proposed by Mendizábal et al. 2008 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Mendizabal1">[18]</xref>. The same method was applied to the analysis of African and Malagasy lineages with the aim of assessing the influence of the slave trade. For admixture analyses, m<sub>y</sub> and m<sub>L</sub> estimators were calculated using ADMIX 2.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dupanloup1">[19]</xref> and WLSAdmix (kindly provided by Dr. Jeffrey Long) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Long1">[20]</xref> programs, respectively. The phylogenetic trees were constructed using median-joining networks as implemented in Network version 4.6.1.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Bandelt1">[21]</xref>, and subsequently refined manually to resolve reticulations.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Mauritian mtDNA complete sequences</title>
<p>All the Mauritian coding region sequences (GenBank accession numbers: KJ411336–KJ411423) could be assigned to 72 haplogroups and subhaplogroups (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s008">Table S3</xref>). However, to accomplish this affiliation, the complete mtDNA genome sequencing of nine samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s001">Figure S1</xref>) was necessary (GenBank accession numbers: KC577353–KC577361). Sample Ma-82 belongs to M5b haplogroup (with the 8784T defining mutation), samples Ma-70 and Ma-79 belong to the H13a2a haplogroup (sharing the 709, 1008, 2259 and 14872 diagnostic transitions), sample Ma-84 to the D4a subhaplogroup (sharing 152 3206 8473 14979 16129 diagnostic motif) and sample Ma-44, although it does not have the 16189 mutation, is classified as B4'5 as it has 8281–8289del. Some of these sequences have allowed us to define new subhaplogroups. Sample Ma-46 is classified as M42 (9156). This sequence defines a new branch of M42 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Kumar1">[22]</xref>, named M42b2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s002">Figure S2</xref>), and characterized by 1053 4197 15241 15562 and 16278 mutations. Sample Ma-66 is classified as R6 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s003">Figure S3</xref>). This sequence redefines R6a1b subhaplogroup (12133 15067 16266!) and its sub-branches R6a1b1 (5894 16213) and R6a1b1a (15100), and also redefines the branch R6a1 (228 11075 14058 16274!), R6a1a (6305 8584 8650 16318 16320) and its sub-branch R6a1a1 (195! 373 961 7316). We also defined a new branch R6a2 (7202 9449 14470 16172). Ma-19 belongs to M49 haplogroup as it has 3780 and 16234 mutations; however, its further classification into subsequent clades remained unclear because it has the 10514 mutation in common with M49c, and the 11542 with M49d, but no other defining mutations for any subhaplogroup. Finally, sample Ma-12 is classified as M* as it does not share any subhaplogroup defining mutation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Phylogenetic analysis of Mauritian mtDNA lineages</title>
<p>In our dataset of 97 Mauritian sequences we detected 89 distinct haplotypes, 79 of which (81.44%) are unique to the sample. Measures of gene diversity indicate that Mauritian values (99.46% ± 0.24%) are within the range of its putative parental populations: South (99.61% ± 0.02%), East (99.43% ± 0.03%) and Southeast Asia (99.35% ± 0.03%), Madagascar (92.86% ± 1.03%) and Africa (99.42% ± 0.03%). The majority of Mauritian lineages are either Indian (M2, M3, M5, M6, R6, U7, U2, etc.) or African specific (L1c, L2a, L3b, L3d and L3e). There are also moderate frequencies of East or Southeast Asian lineages (B4, B5, D4a, F1a, etc.). Finally, the Mauritian sample contains some clear Malagasy (B4a1a, F3b, M7c3 and M23) as well as possible European types (K1, U3 and T2). The H13a2 samples have been assigned to an Indian influence, as H13 is a Near Eastern, not a European variant of haplogroup H <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Roostalu1">[23]</xref>. Indeed, the H13a2a haplogroup have been observed in 5.9% of the Indian B'nei Israel community <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Behar1">[24]</xref>. In the same vein, although in principle we have considered the K1, U3 and T2 lineages as a potential European input, the fact that two of those lineages are found both in India and Europe (the other lineage does not showed any match in the whole database) does call for caution. Furthermore, the only H lineages found in Mauritius belonging to the Near Eastern H13 haplogroup, when it is related to other H13 complete sequences, clusters with Indian, not European or Near Eastern, sequences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s004">Figure S4</xref>). It is worth mentioning that H lineages account for 50% in continental Europe but the only ones detected in the Mauritian sample belong to an Indian branch, indicating a potential South Asian origin for these and other putative European lineages (K1, U3 and T2).</p>
<p>Furthermore, considering the importance of Madagascar as the labour source for Réunion and Mauritius, we should not rule out that some East African lineages present in Mauritian could be an indication of indirect gene flow from these regions through Madagascar. In this way, the 45% of the sub-Saharan lineages could be the result of direct gene flow from Madagascar. Additionally, the two Polynesian B4a1a1a samples from Mauritius carry the “Malagasy motif” (1473 3432A) described by Razafindrazaka et al. 2010 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Razafindrazaka1">[6]</xref>, confirming Madagascar as their origin. In summary, the Indian component in Mauritius could reach 58.76%, rendering the European contribution almost negligible (3.09%). The Malagasy, sub-Saharan African and East-Southeast Asian influences are then 16.60%, 10.21% and 11.34%, respectively.</p>
<p>The Slatkin's F<sub>ST</sub> distances (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093294-t001">Table 1</xref>) between Mauritius and its putative parental populations are in agreement with the phylogenetic analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093294-g002">Figure 2</xref>). South Asia is the nearest Mauritian parental population (0.0183), followed by East and Southeast Asia (0.0330 and 0.0313, respectively), Madagascar (0.0414), and Africa (0.1185), with Europe (0.1366) being the farthest. Within South Asia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093294-t002">Table 2</xref>), the lower F<sub>ST</sub> distance values have been shown to be with North India (0.0022), West India (0.0031) and Southeast India (0.0033).</p>
<fig id="pone-0093294-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>MDS plot based on haplogroup F<sub>ST</sub> distances (MAU  =  Mauritius; MAD  =  Madagascar; IND  =  India; EAS  =  East Asia; SEA  =  Southeast Asia; AFR  =  Africa; AUS  =  Austronesia; EUR  =  Europe).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0093294-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Linearized F<sub>ST</sub> distances between Mauritius and its parental populations (MAU  =  Mauritius; MAD  =  Madagascar; IND  =  India; EAS  =  East Asia; SEA  =  Southeast Asia; AFR  =  Africa; EUR  =  Europe).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0093294-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IND</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EAS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0414</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0183</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0330</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0313</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1185</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1366</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0414</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0720</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0682</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0617</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1421</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0554</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2374</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IND</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0183</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0720</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0412</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0414</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1901</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1126</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1061</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EAS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0330</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0682</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0412</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0125</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1818</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0940</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1526</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0313</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0617</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0414</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0125</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1883</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0871</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1537</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1185</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1421</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1901</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1818</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1883</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2674</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3352</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0554</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1126</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0940</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0871</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2674</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2378</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1366</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2374</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1061</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1526</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1537</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3352</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2378</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0093294-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Linearized F<sub>ST</sub> distances between Mauritius and the different South Asian sub-regions (MAU  =  Mauritius; PWI  =  Pakistan and West India; SWI  =  Southwest India; NI  =  North India; SEI  =  Southeast India; BEI  =  Bangladesh and East India).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0093294-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PWI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SWI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BEI</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAU</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0031</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0082</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0022</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0033</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0057</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PWI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0031</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0060</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0015</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0024</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0051</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SWI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0082</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0060</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0056</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0052</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0096</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0022</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0015</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0056</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0018</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0042</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0033</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0024</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0052</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0018</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0058</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BEI</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0057</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0051</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0096</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0042</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0058</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Admixture analyses of the Mauritian population</title>
<p>Addressing exact haplotypic matches and linking these with the putative parental populations following the hierarchical order based on historical data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093294-t003">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s009">Table S4</xref>), the highest value was found with South Asia (63.46%). Outside South Asia, the greatest number of matches was with Madagascar (15.38%), followed by East Asia (9.62%), Africa (7.69%), and Southeast Asia (3.85%). The European putative lineages have exact matches in India confirming that maternal contributions directly from Europe could be considered negligible. In fact, at present, there are no direct, unique, matches with the Europe database from the Mauritian sample.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0093294-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Summarized matches analysis results comparing Mauritius with its parental populations (IND  =  India; MAD  =  Madagascar; AFR  =  Africa; EAS  =  East Asia; SEA  =  Southeast Asia; EUR  =  Europe).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0093294-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total matches</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique matches</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matches assignation following hierarchical order</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IND</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6065</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.46%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MAD</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.38%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AFR</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9780</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.69%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EAS</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9074</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.62%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SEA</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4293</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EUR</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2913</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>32295</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>52</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>24</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>52</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100%</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>More formal admixture measures based on haplogroup frequencies (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093294-t004">Table 4</xref>) and using two distinct estimation programs (ADMIX 2.0, and WLSAdmix), show similar results to the phylogeographic analysis. The most important parental population for Mauritius is South Asia, with a contribution of 52.97%–48.47%. Other important contributions to the maternal lineages, which ostensibly derive from the slave trade, with admixture values of 23.07%–17.51% and 11.11%–7.20% are from Africa and Madagascar, respectively. The contribution of East and Southeast Asia is 10.12%–5.51% and 11.91%–5.91% respectively. Finally, the European input (3.82%–2.38%) is practically negligible. These contribution values based on haplogroup frequencies partly resemble the values obtained using haplotypic matches (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093294-t003">Table 3</xref>). This indicates that our hierarchical order of most probable contributor, based on the historical data, provides congruent results, although it overestimated South Asian, and underestimated African, contributions respectively.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0093294-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Admixture estimations for Mauritian population (MAD  =  Madagascar; IND  =  India; EAS  =  East Asia; SEA  =  Southeast Asia; AFR  =  Africa; EUR  =  Europe).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0093294-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IND</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EAS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">m<sub>L</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Long1">[20]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.11±0.36%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.97±0.54%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.12±0.45%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91±0.40%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.51±0.35%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38±0.27%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">m<sub>y</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dupanloup1">[19]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20±0.63%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.47±1.07%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.51±1.08%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.92±0.97%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.07±0.61%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82±0.76%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Interregional origin of Indian and African lineages in Mauritius</title>
<p>Previous research from Réunion Island <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dubut2">[11]</xref>, demonstrated that Southeast India was the main contributor to <italic>Malbar</italic> and <italic>Zarab</italic> ethnic group. In order to compare these results with that observed in Mauritius, we repeated the admixture calculation based on haplogroup frequencies with lineages of Indian adscription only. The major Indian contributor area to Mauritius was North India (49.23%). Other contributions came from Southeast (31.50%), and West India (19.26%). The contributions from Southwest and East India were negligible. The intraregional analysis of Mauritian haplotypic matches within India using a Bayesian estimator showed that Southeast (37.88% ± 0.99%) and North India (32.26% ± 1.02%) were the main manual labour origin source followed by West India (18.55% ± 1.21%), with Southwest (7.88% ± 1.05%) and East India (3.51% ± 1.04%) being minor contributors.</p>
<p>We also performed an intraregional analysis of sequences of African origin, which, indicated that African influence derived from Madagascar and East Africa (47.97% ± 2.39% and 26.40% ± 2.50%), with a West African input also detected (25.64% ± 2.44%). The admixture Bayesian estimator based on haplotypic matches corroborates Madagascar (76.75%) and East Africa (14.82%) as the main points of origin, with minor influences from West Central (5.25%) and West Africa (3.19%).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The analysis of complete genome sequences from Madagascar revealed an autochthonous linage named M23 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dubut1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Ricaut1">[25]</xref>. Our complete mtDNA study also discovered an unidentified M type that only shares the common M mutations. The presence of this rare lineage on Mauritius has to be the result of historical migrations, most probably from India or East-Southeast Asia. Future analysis within these regions should provide its most probably origin.</p>
<p>The mitogenomes presented here redefine R6a and M42b subhaplogroups. Haplogroup R6 is a clear Indian haplogroup associated with the demographic expansion event during an interglacial period before the Last Glacial Maximum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Metspalu1">[26]</xref>. We defined a new branch R6a1b1 based on our R6 Mauritian lineage within the R6a haplogroup previously defined by Chaubey et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Chaubey1">[27]</xref>. In order to determine if it is possible to track the precise origin of this lineage we determine its frequency in the different regions of India based on its HVRI motif (16129 16213 16266! 16274! 16362). The entire frequency of R6a1b1 in India is only 0.33% (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s007">Table S2</xref>). Within the different geographical areas the frequency is ∼0.30%, with the highest value in west India and Pakistan (0.48%) and the lowest in southwest India (0.15%). We also performed a network of the R6a1b1 HVRI data and observed that the Mauritian sample does not cluster with any Indian sample and splits directly from the basal motif (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s005">Figure S5</xref>). More phylogenetic analysis of R6 haplogroup would be necessary in the future to refine the R6 phylogenetic tree and determine the precise origin of the Mauritian sequence.</p>
<p>Although M42 was previously considered as an Australian aborigine lineage, complete sequences from relic tribes of India showed that the M42 haplogroup presents two branches with clear geographical adscription <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Kumar1">[22]</xref>. M42a is restricted to aboriginal people from Australia, whereas M42b is a clear Indian lineage. The coalescence time estimated for the divergence of M42 Indian and Australian lineages (∼55 Kya) is consistent with the archaeological evidence regarding the first human arrival to Australia. Our Mauritian sequence defines a new branch M42b2 within the Indian M42 branch (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s002">Figure S2</xref>) reinforcing the importance of Indian ancestry in Mauritius. As the M42b2 HVRI motif is defined only by mutations common to other haplogroups (16189 16223 16278) it was discarded to obtain conclusions from HVRI data (16065–16385).</p>
<p>Historically, the parental populations of Mauritius have been identified as deriving from India, sub-Saharan Africa, Madagascar, China and Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Allen1">[2]</xref>. The complex demographic history of Mauritius is clearly reflected by its high genetic diversity (99.46%) that could be explained by the successive founder events motivated by labour sourcing initiated by the different European colonizers: Dutch, French and British. The complexity of Mauritius' demography is also reflected in its diverse genetic composition. The important migration of indentured workers brought from India is confirmed by the high frequency of Indian-specific lineages in the Mauritian maternal genetic pool. Furthermore, all the data analysis comparing Mauritius with its putative parental populations corroborates that India is the main source of Mauritian lineages. In fact, the majority of lineages from Mauritius were classified as Indian-specific haplogroups, reaching 58.76%, with the island showing its lowest value for Slatkin's F<sub>ST</sub> genetic distance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093294-t001">Table 1</xref>) with this region. Furthermore, the matches and admixture analyses place India as the main contributor with 64.3% of exact matches and an averaged contribution of approximately 50%.</p>
<p>Focusing on the Indian lineages, the lower F<sub>ST</sub> values of the Mauritian sample derived from North, West and Southeast India (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0093294-t002">Table 2</xref>). As expected, these regions also show the highest percentage of exact matches and the higher genetic contribution within India. In fact, admixture analysis suggests that the Indian specific lineages could be explained solely by North, Southeast and West India contributions (49.23%, 31.50% and 19.26%, respectively). This result is congruent with the historical record of worker recruitment in India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Carter1">[28]</xref>. It is known that Calcutta (North India) was an important port of embarkation of indentured labourers to Mauritius between 1834 and 1910. By the middle of the 19<sup>th</sup> century, Bihar (North India) had become the centre of recruitment. Many labourers also came from other specific regions of the Northwestern provinces. The apparently better physical constitution of South Indian workers, and lower mortality rate during transportation, made this region another important source of labourers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Carter1">[28]</xref>.</p>
<p>The other significant contributor to the Mauritian population derived from the historic slave trade, both from Africa and Madagascar. The values of exact matches (15.4%) and the admixture values (11–7%) indicate that Madagascar provided a remarkable amount of maternal lineages to Mauritius. In the same manner, 7.7% of exact matches and a contribution estimation of approximately 20% evidence the existence of a direct sub-Saharan slave trade from the continent. These results emphasize the contribution of Malagasy and sub-Saharan slaves to the modern Mauritian gene pool in spite of high mortality within these populations from hard working conditions and disease. A more refined admixture analyses based on haplogroup frequencies and haplotypic matches revealed a more significant contribution from Madagascar and East Africa (75%–90%) whereas a lower percentage come from West Africa (10%–25%). The differences in Malagasy-sub-Saharan Africa contributions using exact matches and Bayesian estimations, and those obtained using admixture calculations based on haplogroup frequencies seems to be caused by the presence of Malagasy-specific haplotypes on Mauritius and their absence on the African continent, slightly overestimating the real contribution of Madagascar.</p>
<p>The genetic impact of manual workers, and in later years merchants, from China is also detected by the presence of East Asian lineages. East and Southeast Asia showed a percentage of 9.6% and 3.9% of exact matches with the Mauritian sample, respectively. The admixture analysis points to an estimated genetic contribution of 10.0–5.5% and 11.9–5.9% for East and Southeast Asia respectively.</p>
<p>Finally, although French and British colonizers settled Mauritius, only a 2.4–3.8% European contribution has been detected. This could be explained by the fact that European colonizers were mainly men and the few European females did not mix with local males.</p>
<p>Mauritius and Réunion had similar historical backgrounds and the same putative parental populations and this is reflected in the match analysis. The two multi-ethnic populations present exact haplotypic matches in lineages present both in India (10) and Madagascar/Africa (5) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s009">Table S4</xref>). Mauritius and Réunion share one haplotypic match in one lineage of the M43b Indian haplogroup <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Thangaraj1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Chandrasekar1">[30]</xref> that has not been observed in the parental population. This result highlights the similarities of their genetic histories. However, evaluations of the exact origin of Indian lineages also reveal important differences. Dubut et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dubut2">[11]</xref> determine the origin of the Indian lineages of the <italic>Malbar</italic> and <italic>Zarab</italic> ethnic groups, as well as other haplotypes with South Asian origin and conclude that these lineages were contributed mainly from Southeastern India (63%). For Mauritius, an important portion of lineages came from Northern India, whereas only 15% of Reunionese Indian descendants derive from the North. This points to differences in the main recruitment centres of indentured labourers for Mauritius and Réunion, probably due to the fact that they belonged to Britain and France, respectively. After the abolition of slavery in 1848, the French administration for Réunion started to recruit workers from India, primarily from the colony in Pondicherry, located in Southeast India, and this was likely the principal area of origin of indentured labourers brought to Réunion Island <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Dupon1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Lacpatia1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Singhvi1">[33]</xref>. France reached a convention with the British that allowed the recruitment of 6,000 Indian indentured labourers per year. Between 1848 and 1860, around 40,000 Indian manual labourers were brought to Mauritius, most of them originating from Tamil Nadu. Curiously, the results from Dubut et al. indicates that Andhra Pradesh contributed more to Réunion than Tamil Nadu, contradicting the historical records.</p>
<p>From a genetic perspective, it is clear that the diverse human movements around the Indian Ocean have shaped the demographic composition of the islands situated at its western edge. Madagascar and the Comoros archipelago's genetic compositions have mainly been determined by ancient human migrations from Austronesia and East Africa, a result of the Bantu expansion. The Mascarene archipelago, although uninhabited at the time of its discovery, show a complex demographic structure due to continuous waves of human migration motivated by the need for manual labour during European expansion. Although the French and British controlled these islands, their genetic impact was insignificant, at least from the mtDNA point of view.</p>
<p>Given both the location and role as a ‘labour island’, a key focus of future research should be archaeological samples, as performed on other admixed populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer2">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer3">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0093294-Fregel1">[36]</xref>. This should aim to investigate differential geneflow over time, their admixture, and sex-specific dichotomy. The comparison of ancient DNA results with those obtained from current populations would provide valuable information regarding the temporal evolution of human populations in the island.</p>
<p>Finally, the present research potentially has implications beyond assessment of the island's past. Modern populations on Mauritius have a remarkably high prevalence of specific non-communicable diseases, particularly type 2 diabetes. Determining the genetic structure of small island populations, such as Mauritius, is the first step to forging links between the molecular causes of illnesses and their impacts on specific populations, particularly as these diseases appear to have significantly greater relative impact on these small communities.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Phylogenetic tree of complete Mauritian sequences.</bold> Number along links refers to nucleotide changes, whereas “d” and “i” indicate deletions and insertions, respectively. GenBank accessions and geographic origin are referred for each complete sequence. Red numbers correspond to recurrent mutations (309iC, 315iC, 522dCA, 523iCA, 16182C, 16183C and 16519) not taken into account during tree construction. Exclamation marks indicate retromutations. Mutations highlighted in light blue correspond to newly defined or redefined branches.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Phylogenetic tree of complete haplogroup M42 sequences.</bold> Codes as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s001">Figure S1</xref>.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Phylogenetic tree of complete haplogroup R6a sequences.</bold> Codes as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s001">Figure S1</xref>. Underlined numbers correspond to recurrent mutations within R6 haplogroup.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Phylogenetic tree of complete haplogroup H13a2 sequences.</bold> Codes as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s001">Figure S1</xref>.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S5</label><caption>
<p><bold>HVRI network of R6 sequences.</bold> Star corresponds to CRS haplotype. Codes as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093294.s001">Figure S1</xref>.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s006" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Populations used for comparison in this study.</bold></p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s007" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Haplogroup frequencies for the comparison database (MAU  =  Mauritius; MAD  =  Madagascar; IND  =  India; PWI  =  Pakistan and West India; SWI  =  Southwest India; NI  =  North India; SEI  =  Southeast India; BEI  =  Bangladesh and East India; EAS  =  East Asia; SEA  =  Southeast Asia; AFR  =  Africa; WAF  =  West Africa; EAF  =  East Africa; AUS  =  Austronesia; EUR  =  Europe).</bold></p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s008" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Partial (HVRI and HVRII) mtDNA haplotypes, haplogroups and coding region mutations observed for the Mauritian samples analyzed in this study.</bold> The GenBank accesion numbers are indicated in the last column.</p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0093294.s009" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0093294.s009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Detailed matches information (MAU  =  Mauritius; REU  =  Réunion Island; MAD  =  Madagascar; IND  =  India; PWI  =  Pakistan and West India; SWI  =  Southwest India; NI  =  North India; SEI  =  Southeast India; BEI  =  Bangladesh and East India; EAS  =  East Asia; SEA  =  Southeast Asia; AFR  =  Africa; WAF  =  West Africa; EAF  =  East Africa; EUR  =  Europe).</bold></p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are grateful to Almudena Ramos and Yessica Lara for technical assistance. KS gratefully acknowledges the assistance of Allan Charlotte, Amirchandsingh Teerbohan and Ruud Stelten for their support in the field, and Will Goodwin, University of Central Lancashire (UK) for his initial consultative role. Special thanks are due to Vijaya Teelock, University of Maurius, for facilitating the early stages of this project. KS would also like to express sincere thanks to the directorates of the Aapravasi Ghat Trust Fund, Le Morne Heritage Trust Fund, Mauritius Museum Council and the Truth and Justice Commission (Mauritius) for supporting this project. RF would like to acknowledge Dr. Vicente Cabrera for his helpful comments on the manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Fuller1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>DQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoogervorst</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allaby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Across the Indian Ocean: the prehistoric movement of plants and animals</article-title>. <source>Antiquity</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Allen1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Allen RB (1999) Slaves, freedmen and indentured laborers in colonial Mauritius. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Soodyall1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soodyall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoneking</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>‘Polynesian’ mtDNA in the Malagasy</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Dubut1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubut</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cartault</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Payet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thionville</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murail</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Complete mitochondrial sequences for haplogroups M23 and M46: insights into the Asian ancestry of the Malagasy population</article-title>. <source>Hum Biol</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Hurles1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurles</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jobling</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The dual origin of the Malagasy in Island Southeast Asia and East Africa: evidence from maternal and paternal lineages</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>894</fpage>–<lpage>901</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Razafindrazaka1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razafindrazaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricaut</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mormina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dugoujon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Complete mitochondrial DNA sequences provide new insights into the Polynesian motif and the peopling of Madagascar</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>581</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Tofanelli1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tofanelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertoncini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luiselli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calafell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>On the origins and admixture of Malagasy: new evidence from high-resolution analyses of paternal and maternal lineages</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2109</fpage>–<lpage>2124</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Gourjon1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gourjon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boetsch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Degioanni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Gender and population history: sex bias revealed by studying genetic admixture of Ngazidja population (Comoro Archipelago)</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>660</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Msaidie1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Msaidie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ducourneau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boetsch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longepied</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genetic diversity on the Comoros Islands shows early seafaring as major determinant of human biocultural evolution in the Western Indian Ocean</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-BerniellLee1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berniell-Lee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plaza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calafell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jourdan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Admixture and sexual bias in the population settlement of La Reunion Island (Indian Ocean)</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Dubut2"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubut</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murail</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pech</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thionville</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cartault</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Inter- and extra-Indian admixture and genetic diversity in reunion island revealed by analysis of mitochondrial DNA</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Genet</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Filliot1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Filliot JM (1974) La traite des esclaves vers la Mascareignes au XVIIIe siecle. Paris: ORSTOM.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maca-Meyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Major genomic mitochondrial lineages delineate early human expansions</article-title>. <source>BMC Genet</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-vanOven1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Oven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Updated comprehensive phylogenetic tree of global human mitochondrial DNA variation</article-title>. <source>Hum Mutat</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>E386</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Slatkin1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slatkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>A measure of population subdivision based on microsatellite allele frequencies</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>462</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Nei1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nei N (1987) Molecular evolutionary genetics. New York: Columbia University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Schneider1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Schneider S, Roessli D, Excoffier L (2000) Arlequin ver. 2000: A software for population genetics data analysis. Geneva, Switzerland: Genetics and Biometry Laboratory, University of Geneva.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Mendizabal1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendizabal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berniell-Lee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calafell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genetic origin, admixture, and asymmetry in maternal and paternal human lineages in Cuba</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Dupanloup1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupanloup</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertorelle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Inferring admixture proportions from molecular data: extension to any number of parental populations</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>672</fpage>–<lpage>675</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Long1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The genetic structure of admixed populations</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Bandelt1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Median-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Kumar1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ravuri</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koneru</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urade</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Reconstructing Indian-Australian phylogenetic link</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Roostalu1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roostalu</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kutuev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loogvali</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tambets</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Origin and expansion of haplogroup H, the dominant human mitochondrial DNA lineage in West Eurasia: the Near Eastern and Caucasian perspective</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>436</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Behar1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kivisild</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosset</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tzur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Counting the founders: the matrilineal genetic ancestry of the Jewish Diaspora</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e2062</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Ricaut1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricaut</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Razafindrazaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dugoujon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guitard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A new deep branch of eurasian mtDNA macrohaplogroup M reveals additional complexity regarding the settlement of Madagascar</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Metspalu1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kivisild</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hudjashov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Most of the extant mtDNA boundaries in south and southwest Asia were likely shaped during the initial settlement of Eurasia by anatomically modern humans</article-title>. <source>BMC Genet</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Chaubey1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaubey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karmin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selvi-Rani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography of mtDNA haplogroup R7 in the Indian peninsula</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Carter1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Carter M (1995) Servants, sirdars, and settlers: Indians in Mauritius, 1834–1874. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Thangaraj1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thangaraj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaubey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kivisild</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selvi Rani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Maternal footprints of Southeast Asians in North India</article-title>. <source>Hum Hered</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Chandrasekar1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrasekar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sreenath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urade</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Updating phylogeny of mitochondrial DNA macrohaplogroup m in India: dispersal of modern human in South Asian corridor</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e7447</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Dupon1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupon</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Les immigrants indiens de La Reunion: Evolution et assimilation d'une population</article-title>. <source>Cah Cent Univ La Réunion</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Lacpatia1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lacpatia F (1982) Les Indiens de La Réunion 1: Origine et recrutement. Saint-Denis (Réunion): Bibliothèque Départementale.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Singhvi1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Singhvi LM, Bhatia RL, Hiremath JR, Baleshwar A, Agrawal B, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2001) Réunion. In: Division NRIPoIO, editor. Report of the high level committee on Indian diaspora. New-Delhi: Ministry of External Affairs. pp. 61–70.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer2"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maca-Meyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fregel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA diversity in 17th–18th century remains from Tenerife (Canary Islands)</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-MacaMeyer3"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maca-Meyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rando</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ancient mtDNA analysis and the origin of the Guanches</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0093294-Fregel1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fregel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gusmao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Demographic history of Canary Islands male gene-pool: replacement of native lineages by European</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>