<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-41887</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085673</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Heredity</subject><subject>Human genetics</subject><subject>Population genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Theoretical biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Applied mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Complex systems</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ethnic groups</subject><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Ethnobiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Demography</subject><subj-group><subject>Ethnic groups</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational sociology</subject><subject>Culture</subject><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Let My People Go (Home) to Spain: A Genealogical Model of Jewish Identities since 1492</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Genealogical Model of Jewish Identities since 1492</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weitz</surname><given-names>Joshua S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><addr-line>School of Biology and School of Physics, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Solé</surname><given-names>Ricard V.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Spain</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">jsweitz@gatech.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The author has declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JSW. Performed the experiments: JSW. Analyzed the data: JSW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JSW. Wrote the paper: JSW.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<elocation-id>e85673</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
    <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Joshua S Weitz</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The Spanish government recently announced an official fast-track path to citizenship for any individual who is Jewish and whose ancestors were expelled from Spain during the inquisition-related dislocation of Spanish Jews in 1492. It would seem that this policy targets a small subset of the global Jewish population, that is, restricted to individuals who retain cultural practices associated with ancestral origins in Spain. However, the central contribution of this manuscript is to demonstrate how and why the policy is far more likely to apply to a very large fraction (i.e., the vast majority) of Jews. This claim is supported using a series of genealogical models that include transmissible “identities” and preferential intra-group mating. Model analysis reveals that even when intra-group mating is strong and even if only a small subset of a present-day population retains cultural practices typically associated with that of an ancestral group, it is highly likely that nearly all members of that population have direct genealogical links to that ancestral group, given sufficient number of generations have elapsed. The basis for this conclusion is that not having a link to an ancestral group must be a property of all of an individual’s ancestors, the probability of which declines (nearly) superexponentially with each successive generation. These findings highlight unexpected incongruities induced by genealogical dynamics between present-day and ancestral identities.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>Joshua S. Weitz holds a Career Award at the Scientific Interface from the Burroughs Wellcome Fund. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="6"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Present-day Jews predominantly self-identify as either Sephardic or Ashkenazi. Origins of Sephardic Jews are generally attributed to the Jewish community based in Spain and Portugal that was expelled from the Iberian peninsula in the late 15th century, whereas Ashkenazi Jews generally attribute their origins to Central and Eastern Europe, pre-dating the expulsion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Telushkin1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Zohar1">[2]</xref>. These divisions are, at least culturally, considered to be long-standing, for example, the protagonist of the classic 19th century farce “The King of Schnorrers” (which is set in the late 18th century) – Manasseh Bueno Barzillai Azevedo da Costa – reacts in horror at the prospect of his daughter marrying an Ashkenazi, rather than a Sephardic, Jew: “A Sephardi cannot marry a Tedesco [Ashkenazi]! It would be a degradation” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Zangwill1">[3]</xref>. The conditions for the fast-track naturalization announced by the Spanish government in November 2012, follow along these traditional designations of ethnic identity: (i) the petitioner must be Jewish; (ii) the petitioner must “certify” their Spanish Jewish origins. Indeed, the announcement and subsequent media coverage of this change to Spanish civil law highlighted its intended target to be self-identified Sephardic Jews <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Minder1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Anonymous1">[5]</xref> – a minority of the global Jewish population. It would seem that being a direct descendant of an individual expelled from Spain in 1492 would be a necessary condition for fast-track naturalization, however, it remains unclear as to whether this will be a sufficient condition. Here, the following question is asked: to what extent should <italic>any</italic> Jew living today expect to have one (or more) Jewish ancestors expelled from Spain in 1492.</p>
<p>Although identities may indeed be exclusive and even strongly retained inter-generationally, this does not preclude the fact that individuals of one identity may have one (or more) ancestors of a different identity. Irrespective of identity, the number of ancestors that any individual has grows quite rapidly, exponentially at first and then increasing (albeit at a slower-than-exponential rate) with each successive prior generation. Hence, a present-day individual that self-identifies as Jewish would have a direct genealogical link to the expelled Spanish Jewish community if one (or more) of their deceased forebears in 1492 was a member of that community. Here, the main contribution is to develop a simple genealogical model (and intuition) to explain how having ancestors of diverse “types” is extremely common even when cross-“type” mating is rare.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Model of Genealogical Dynamics with Assortative Mating</title>
<p>Consider the genealogical dynamics of a population of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> individuals where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the ancestral population of interest (e.g., the number of Jews living in Spain in 1492) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes each successive prior generation such that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes the present. In this model, given an initial population size, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, then <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> pairs of parents are selected at random from the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> individuals present in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-th generation, forming a history of genealogical links between each generation. The value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is then incremented iteratively from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In this model, individuals can be selected more than once and no information on male/female identities are retained. These dynamics correspond to the forward version of standard models of genealogical dynamics with sexual reproduction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Chang1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Derrida1">[7]</xref>. Statistical properties of genealogical dynamics at the population scale have previously been found to be highly robust to this apparent lack of realism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Manrubia1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Brunet1">[10]</xref>.</p>
<p>Next, consider a modified version of the standard model of genealogical dynamics with sexual reproduction to distinguish between individuals with two exclusive traits, type <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or type <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, e.g., Sephardic (type-1) or Ashkenazi (type-2) These traits need not be genetically encoded. In this framework, each generation can be described in terms of a population-wide distribution of traits, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The fraction of type-1 individuals is denoted as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Individuals of different traits may prefer to mate with individuals with the same trait. A generalized mating preference parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can account for preferential mating, such that the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> parents of individuals in generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> will be selected from a multinomial distribution with probabilities: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the proportion of type-1 individuals in generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Hence, when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, mating occurs exclusively amongst individuals of the same type, i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, mating probabilities depend on population proportions exclusively, i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Intermediate values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> provide a continuum between these limits, consistent with models of varying degrees of assortative mating in population genetics. The model further presumes that children of two type-1 parents self-identify as type-1 individuals, and that children of two type-2 parents self-identify as type-2 individuals. Finally, the model assumes that children of a type-1 and a type-2 parent self-identify as either type-1 or type-2 with equal probability.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Individuals have Ancestors with Multiple Identities, even when Mating is Strongly-preferred among Individuals of the Same Identity</title>
<p>Trait-associated genealogical dynamics were simulated in the modified model, described above, for three values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085673-g001">Figure 1</xref>). When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, then the identities of ancestors must match that of present-day individuals, since there is no reproduction among individuals of different identities. In this limit, the fraction of present-day individuals with no type-1 ancestors remains relatively constant (near <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Whereas, when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, then reproduction occurs irrespective of identity. Hence, it is highly likely that individuals have ancestors of both identities. Notably, the same phenomenon is observed even when preferences are strong for intra-type reproduction, e.g., when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The reason is occasional (even rare) instances of cross-identity reproduction among an exponentially growing number of ancestors (and matings) lead to frequent instances of type-1 individuals with type-2 ancestors and vice-versa. Moreover, once a type-1 individual has at least one type-2 ancestor, then the mating preferences reinforce this history, ensuring that type-1 individuals often have many type-2 ancestors (and vice versa). These exploratory simulations reveal that individuals can have ancestors with identities other than their own, even when individuals strongly prefer to reproduce with individuals of the same identity.</p>
<fig id="pone-0085673-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Genealogical history with mating preferences.</title>
<p>Each panel illustrates the ancestors of two focal individuals given <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (top-middle-bottom). Initially, at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, there are 20% type-1 individuals (red circles) and 80% type-2 individuals (blue circles). Ancestors are denoted by red and blue lines, respectively. When viewing the process retrospectively from the present-day (top line in each panel, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), it is apparent that all ancestors share the same identity as the focal two individuals when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. However, when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> then one (or more) ancestors may have a different identity than that of the focal individual.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>The Likelihood of having an Ancestor with an Identity Different than One's Own Increases (Nearly) Super-exponentially with Prior Generations</title>
<p>Introducing the concept of <italic>genealogical identity</italic> will prove useful to explore the phenomenon of having ancestors with identities different than that of a focal individual, Let <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represent whether or not any of a focal <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>-th individual's ancestors had a particular identity of interest. In this study system, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes that none of an individual's ancestors was of type-1, whereas <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denotes that at least one ancestor of a focal individual was of type-1. Hence, the state of an individual can be described in terms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Due to the definition of identity transfer in the model, there are three possible states of individuals: (i) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - a type-1 individual with at least one type-1 ancestor; (ii) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - a type-2 individual with no type-1 ancestors; (iii) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - a type-2 individual with at least one type-1 ancestor. The genealogical identity <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of children is equal to 1 when either parent is of type <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and equal to 0 only when both parents are of type <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Analysis of genealogical dynamics yield a closed form prediction for the fraction of individuals with at least one type-1 ancestor:<disp-formula id="pone.0085673.e055"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e055" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>(see derivation in the Methods). The fraction of individuals with at least one type-1 ancestor rapidly approaches one, given that the probability of having no type-1 ancestors declines (nearly) super-exponentially. This prediction can be evaluated for different values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in a large population simulation where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Quantitative agreement is found even when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085673-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Indeed, even when the vast majority of sexual reproductions occur between individuals of the same identity as occurs when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the fraction of individuals with at least one type-1 ancestor, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, converges rapidly from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0085673-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Rapid increase in frequency of genealogical link to a previously minority identity.</title>
<p>Solid lines with symbols denote theory of Eq. (1) (colored based on initial frequency of type-1 individuals) while circles denote simulation. The simulated population has <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e064" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> individuals.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Nearly All Present-day Jews are Likely to have at least One (if not many more) Ancestors Expelled from Spain in 1492</title>
<p>The modified genealogical model with mating preferences can be evaluated in a parameter regime inspired by that of transmission of Sephardic and Ashkenazi identities. This regime includes the assumptions that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, spanning an approximately 500 year time frame, corresponding to approximately 20 generations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Botticini1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-DellaPergola1">[12]</xref>. Further, the application of the model assumes that the Sephardic community was approximately 20% of the global Jewish population in 1492 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Botticini1">[11]</xref>. Mating preference data spanning this historical period is not available in a comprehensive fashion. Instead, consider a highly conservative (and highly biased) mating scenario where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, corresponding to a 1000∶1 relative likelihood given one type-1 individual to mate with another type-1 individual rather than a type-2 individual. Note that analysis of the 1995 Israeli national census finds that marriages between Sephardic and Ashkenazi individuals is reported to occur approximately 10-fold less frequently than within-type marriages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Rubinstein1">[13]</xref>. Such modern estimates suggest that strong inter-type preferences continue to have persisted into the 20th century. Simulations reveal that, despite an extreme preference for in-group mating, it takes only 15 generations for all individuals to have at least one direct genealogical link to a Sephardic in the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> generation (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085673-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). This occurs despite the fact that Sephardic identity remains a minority throughout the simulation (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085673-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). The frequency of individuals with at least one type-1 ancestor, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, agrees with theoretical predictions (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085673-g003">Figure 3C</xref>), further substantiating the generality of the present mechanism for the spread of genealogical identity in constant and in varying populations. These results are highly robust to changes in initial population fractions, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, population sizes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and mating preferences <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0085673-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Nearly all modern-day Jews are likely to have many ancestors expelled from Spain in 1492.</title>
<p>Genealogical dynamics are simulated using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in a population of initial size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at generation 0 that is of size <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at generation 20. The choice of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> corresponds to a relative preference of in-group mating of 1000∶1 relative to out-group mating. (A) Population-state of identities, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where the identities (red for Type-1, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and blue for Type-2, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) are displayed for each individual (column) in each generation (row). (B) Population-state of genealogical identities, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where the identities (red for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and blue for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) are displayed for each individual (column) in each generation (row). (C) Comparison of theoretical prediction (red circles) of the fraction of individuals with at least one Sephardic ancestor, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> simulations (all variation contained in black shaded region). The identity information in panels (A) and (B) are downsized by a factor of 1000∶1 for the purposes of visualization.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Claims regarding the diversity of ancestral identities can be extended using the same model framework. Specifically, the model predicts that individuals are not only likely to have at least one ancestor of an identity different that their own (as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085673-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085673-g003">3</xref>), but are likely to have <italic>many</italic> such ancestors. To illustrate this concept, consider a type-1 individual in generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> who has one type-2 ancestor in generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Then, the type-1 individual would be a direct genealogically descendant of many type-2 ancestors in generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> via this (rare) link, subsequently reinforced by assortative mating. A quantitative metric can be introduced to characterize this phenomenon: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> - the fraction of ancestors in generation 0 who are of type 1 for an individual living in generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> whose identity is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Simulations reveal that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> converges to that of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> over time. This implies that individuals of different identities both share many, and eventually, all ancestors of a focal identity (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0085673-g004">Figure 4</xref>). This claim is consistent with prior analysis of panmictic populations in which there is a rapid (i.e., scaling independently of population size) and recent (i.e., scaling with the logarithm of population size) transition, in terms of generations, over which two randomly chosen individuals are likely to switch from sharing very few to nearly all of their ancestors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Derrida1">[7]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0085673-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Individuals have many ancestors with different identities than their own.</title>
<p>The results are from a simulation of a population with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. (Left) Fraction of ancestors in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that are type 1, for individuals who at generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> self-identify as type 1 (red) or type 2 (blue); (Right) Fraction of individuals with at least one type-1 ancestor, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Generations increase from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> along the y-axis in both panels.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In summary, a series of simplified genealogical models have been proposed and analyzed in which individuals retain a set of identities. Nearly all model variants lead to dynamics in which present-day individuals who identify with one identity have at least one, and typically many, ancestors of a different identity in a relatively recent generation. As is apparent, the model formulation is generic rather than specifically parameterized for the detailed and complex structure of present-day and historical Jewish populations - which inspired the present analysis. Hence, extensions are warranted that include population structure, mating with other “groups” (e.g., those who do not transmit or retain the cultural practices associated with the identity), loss of identity, and other demographic structure that may change both the baseline expectation and variation for identity dynamics as described by the present model. Nonetheless, given the super-exponential nature of the process, it would require significant changes to the model structure to substantively modify the overall conclusion: given occasional mating between individuals of different identities, then a small number of generations is likely required for individuals to have a subset of their ancestors with identities different than their own. This notion is strongly consistent with landmark work on the genealogical ancestry of all living humans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Rohde1">[9]</xref> and population genomics research on the related ancestry of individuals from seemingly disparate European populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Ralph1">[14]</xref>.</p>
<p>Returning to the inspiration for this model, note that the Spanish government's fast track to citizenship was ostensibly meant to target Sephardic Jews, a minority of the global Jewish population. Extrapolating from the model analysis, it would seem that, to the contrary, the far more likely baseline hypothesis is that the vast majority of present-day Jews have one or more direct genealogical forebears in the Jewish community expelled from Spain in 1492. The current analysis does not consider the policy implications of such a hypothesis. However, it is worth noting that the fast-track naturalization process announced in November 2012 has yet to be implemented (as of May 2013) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Minder2">[15]</xref> and that Portugal has also recently announced a similar policy modeled on the Spanish framework <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Krich1">[16]</xref>. Instead, the model can be used to point out that policies linked to the identity of (distant) ancestors should be approached cautiously, given that the number of ancestors grows (nearly) exponentially. As a consequence, the identity-associated characteristic of ancestors need not be congruent with the identities of present-day individuals. In the words of Manasseh Bueno Barzillai Azevedo da Costa, the protagonist of The King of Schnorrers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0085673-Krich1">[16]</xref>, “Never before have I sat at the table of a Tedesco [Ashkenazi] – but you – you are a man after my own heart. Your soul is a son of Spain.”</p>
</sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>The dynamics of genealogical identity can be derived as follows. Consider a population of individuals each with state <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Denote <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as the population wide probability of a randomly selected individual to have the state denoted in the subscript, e.g., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For convenience, define the time-varying fraction of type-2 individuals with no type-1 ancestors as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Initially, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In generation <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is equal to the fraction of individuals both of whom had type-2 parents, i.e., <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In subsequent generations, some type-2 individuals themselves have type-1 ancestors. Of the type-2 individuals born to parents who are both type-2, only a fraction, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, are a product of reproduction involving parents with no type-1 ancestors. Hence, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Recall that the genealogical dynamics modeled here preserves the fraction of typed individuals, on average, a result leveraged by assuming that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Therefore, the predicted discrete-time population dynamics of the system can be written, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as:<disp-formula id="pone.0085673.e120"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pone.0085673.e121"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pone.0085673.e122"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>In this framework,<disp-formula id="pone.0085673.e123"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
<p>But, recalling that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, this can be simplified as:<disp-formula id="pone.0085673.e125"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e125" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Eq. 2 can be solved recursively, implying that the subpopulation of type-2 individuals with no type-1 ancestors declines superexponentially so long as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e127" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Finally, the fraction of individuals with at least one type-1 ancestor is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, as stated in the main text. Simulation code used to generate figures in this manuscript is available as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0085673.s001">File S1</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0085673.s001" mimetype="application/zip" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0085673.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>File S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Software for simulating assortative ancestries.</bold></p>
<p>(ZIP)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The author thanks M. Cortez, J. Dushoff, D. Goldman, M. Goodisman, S. Levin, S. Manrubia, S. Strogatz, R. Weitz-Shapiro, and A. Zangwill for many helpful comments and suggestions.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Telushkin1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Telushkin J (2008) Jewish Literacy: The Most Important Things to Know About the Jewish Religion, Its People and Its History. New York: William Morrow.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Zohar1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zohar Z (2005) Sephardic and Mizrahi Jewry: From the Golden Age of Spain to Modern Times. New York City: NYU Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Zangwill1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zangwill I (1893) The King of Schnorrers. New York: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Minder1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Minder R (2012) Spain: citizenship process eased for Sephardic Jews. New York Times. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/23/world/europe/spain-citizenship-process-eased-for-sephardic-jews.html?_r=0" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/23/world/europe/spain-citizenship-process-eased-for-sephardic-jews.html?_r=0</ext-link>. Accessed 2013 Dec 27.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Anonymous1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Anonymous (2012) La condición de sefardí dará derecho automático a la nacionalidad Española. El Pais. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2012/11/22/actualidad/1353599231_756068.html" xlink:type="simple">http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2012/11/22/actualidad/1353599231_756068.html</ext-link>. Accessed 2013 Dec 27.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Chang1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Recent common ancestors of all present-day individuals</article-title>. <source>Adv Appl Probab</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1002</fpage>–<lpage>1026</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Derrida1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derrida</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manrubia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zanette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>On the genealogy of a population of biparental individuals</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source> <volume>203</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Manrubia1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manrubia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Derrida</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zanette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genealogy in the era of genomics</article-title>. <source>American Scientist</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>158</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Rohde1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>DLT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Modelling the recent common ancestry of all living humans</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>431</volume>: <fpage>562</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Brunet1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brunet E, Derrida B (2013) Genealogies in simple models of evolution. J Stat Mech: P01006.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Botticini1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botticini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eckstein</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>From farmers to merchants, conversions and diaspora: human capital and Jewish history</article-title>. <source>Journal of the European Economic Association</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>926</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-DellaPergola1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">DellaPergola S (2012) World Jewish Population, 2012. In: Dashefsky A, DellaPergola S, Sheskin I, editors, American Jewish Year Book, 2012, North American Jewish Data Bank, Current Jewish Population Reports.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Rubinstein1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rubinstein Y, Brenner D (2013) Pride and prejudice: using ethnicsounding names and inter-ethnic marriages to identify labor market discrimination. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ceplseacuk/pubs/download/dp1180pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://ceplseacuk/pubs/download/dp1180pdf</ext-link>. In press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Ralph1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The geography of recent genetic ancestry across Europe</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>e1001555</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Minder2"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Minder R (2013) Many of Spain's Sephardic Jews still waiting for citizenship. New York Times. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/20/world/europe/many-of-spains-sephardic-jews-still-waiting-for-citizenship.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/20/world/europe/many-of-spains-sephardic-jews-still-waiting-for-citizenship.html</ext-link>. Accessed 2013 Dec 27.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0085673-Krich1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Krich J (2013) Jews win a right of return to Portugal five centuries after inquisition. Time. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://world.time.com/2013/09/04/jews-win-a-right-of-return-to-portugal-five-centuries-after-inqusition/" xlink:type="simple">http://world.time.com/2013/09/04/jews-win-a-right-of-return-to-portugal-five-centuries-after-inqusition/</ext-link>. Accessed 2013 Dec 27.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>