<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-29562</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053724</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavioral ecology</subject>
              <subject>Biodiversity</subject>
              <subject>Evolutionary ecology</subject>
              <subject>Population ecology</subject>
              <subject>Terrestrial ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Evolutionary processes</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Adaptation</subject>
                <subject>Sexual selection</subject>
                <subject>Sexual conflict</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Organismal evolution</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Animal evolution</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal behavior</subject>
              <subject>Behavioral ecology</subject>
              <subject>Evolutionary ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Population biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Population dynamics</subject>
              <subject>Population ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biological anthropology</subject>
              <subject>Physical anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Psychology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavior</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Till Death (Or an Intruder) Do Us Part: Intrasexual-Competition in a Monogamous Primate</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Intra-Sexual Aggression in Owl Monkeys</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Fernandez-Duque</surname>
            <given-names>Eduardo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Huck</surname>
            <given-names>Maren</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
            <sup>¤</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Anthropology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Centro de Ecología Aplicada del Litoral, Conicet, Argentina</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gursky-Doyen</surname>
            <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Texas A&amp;M University, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">eduardof@sas.upenn.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: EFD. Performed the experiments: EFD. Analyzed the data: MH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: EFD MH. Wrote the paper: EFD MH.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff">
          <label>¤</label>
          <p>Current address: Department of Behavioural Ecology and Sociobiology, German Primate Centre, Göttingen, Germany</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e53724</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Fernandez-Duque et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Polygynous animals are often highly dimorphic, and show large sex-differences in the degree of intra-sexual competition and aggression, which is associated with biased operational sex ratios (OSR). For socially monogamous, sexually monomorphic species, this relationship is less clear. Among mammals, pair-living has sometimes been assumed to imply equal OSR and low frequency, low intensity intra-sexual competition; even when high rates of intra-sexual competition and selection, in both sexes, have been theoretically predicted and described for various taxa. Owl monkeys are one of a few socially monogamous primates. Using long-term demographic and morphological data from 18 groups, we show that male and female owl monkeys experience intense intra-sexual competition and aggression from solitary floaters. Pair-mates are regularly replaced by intruding floaters (27 female and 23 male replacements in 149 group-years), with negative effects on the reproductive success of both partners. Individuals with only one partner during their life produced 25% more offspring per decade of tenure than those with two or more partners. The termination of the pair-bond is initiated by the floater, and sometimes has fatal consequences for the expelled adult. The existence of floaters and the sporadic, but intense aggression between them and residents suggest that it can be misleading to assume an equal OSR in socially monogamous species based solely on group composition. Instead, we suggest that sexual selection models must assume not equal, but flexible, context-specific, OSR in monogamous species.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>EFD acknowledges financial support from the Wenner-Gren Foundation, the L.S.B. Leakey Foundation, the National Geographic Society, the National Science Foundation (BCS- 0621020), the University of Pennsylvania Research Foundation and the Zoological Society of San Diego, and MH from the German Science Foundation (HU 1746-2/1). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="5"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The relationships between sexual selection, aggression, operational sex ratio (OSR, the ratio of fertilizable females to sexually active males at any given time), sexual dimorphism, mating system, and population structure are well recognized <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Emlen1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Kvarnemo1">[5]</xref>. For example, as the operational sex ratio becomes more biased, competition and aggression increase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Emlen1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Weir1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-CluttonBrock1">[6]</xref>. Generally, polygynous species are more sexually dimorphic than monogamous ones, and sexual dimorphism in body and canine size increases with increased competition in polygynous species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Plavcan1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Thoren1">[9]</xref>. Although the mating system can only partly explain the strength of intra-sexual competition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Plavcan1">[7]</xref>, it has been assumed that species with a monogamous mating system will have similar OSRs given that there is only one reproducing male and female in each group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Emlen1">[1]</xref>. The potential reproductive rate, however, will also be influenced by parental investment, which can bias the OSR towards the less caring sex <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Kvarnemo1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-CluttonBrock1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Fitze1">[10]</xref>. Additionally, for some mammals, and particularly primates, monogamy has been assumed to imply low frequency, low intensity intra-sexual competition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Plavcan1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Setchell1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Heske1">[12]</xref>, whereas more pronounced intra-sexual competition is predicted when there are stronger deviations from an equal OSR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Weir1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Kvarnemo1">[5]</xref>. Nevertheless, high rates of intra-sexual selection and competition among both males and females of monogamous species have been theoretically predicted, and have been described for various taxa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-CluttonBrock1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Heske1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Mitani2">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Owl monkeys are one of the few pair-living and genetically monogamous mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Wright1">[17, Huck, Babb, Schurr, &amp; Fernandez–Duque, unpubl. data]</xref>. They live in small social groups that include one pair of reproducing adults. They show little sexual dimorphism in morphological, behavioural and life-history traits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Huck1">[19]</xref>. Males are prominently involved in infant care and nursing and carrying of the infant by both parents last approximately six months <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Rotundo1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Dixson1">[23]</xref>. Given that parents are both strongly involved in infant care, that reproduction is seasonal and that owl monkeys reproduce once a year, potential reproductive rates ( i.e., “times in” and “times out”, sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-CluttonBrock1">[6]</xref>) for males and females are the same. In other words, at a population level, they have an equal adult sex ratio <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Huck2">[21]</xref> and therefore the population-wide OSR can be considered un-biased <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Kvarnemo1">[5]</xref>. Within-group aggression is rare, and although interactions with neighbouring groups can be intense, they do not normally include physical contact. On the other hand, groups routinely interact, sometimes aggressively, with a significant number of solitary “floating” individuals who range over a wide area rather than a fixed territory after having dispersed from their natal groups, and are usually sub-adults or young adults (ca. 3–5 years old) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque3">[24]</xref>.</p>
      <p>We present the results of an examination of the relationship between pair-bond duration, intra-sexual competition, and OSR in a population of pair-living Azara's owl monkeys (<italic>Aotus azarai</italic>) in the Argentinean Chaco. Comparing the reproductive success of individuals with one or more partners, we first evaluated the hypothesis that the break-up of pairs is an adaptive strategy for the remaining pair-mate, as is the case in various birds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-GarcaNavas1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Dubois1">[27]</xref>. We then examined potential reasons for pair-bond termination, which can include both intrinsic (e.g., incompatibility of mates) and extrinsic factors (e.g., solitary individuals) to the pair <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Choudhury1">[26]</xref>. Finally, since the relationship between intra-sexual aggression in both sexes and the mating system are contradictory for socially monogamous species that are generally assumed to have an un-biased OSR (see above), we also discuss the term OSR, based on the system found in owl monkeys.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>Owl monkey groups have been monitored regularly at the Estancia Guaycolec, Formosa, Argentina (58°11′W, 25°58′S) since 1997. During these 16 years, we collected demographic data from 18 groups. Thus, we were able to establish replacement dates often to the exact date and sometimes within a range of a few weeks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Huck3">[28]</xref>. Animals (n = 154) have been captured regularly since 2000 for a complete physical exam and fitted with radio or bead collars for individual identification <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque4">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Jurez1">[30]</xref>. We used here only data on identified pairs. We considered cases where a former pair-mate died or disappeared before a new individual was seen in the group as deaths. If a new individual was seen in the group before the former resident disappeared, or if the former resident was later found to range solitary, the replacement was considered an expulsion. We used survival analysis with Weibull distribution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Crawley1">[31]</xref> and we considered censored data to determine individual or pair tenure lengths.</p>
      <p>To evaluate the hypothesis that the break-up is an adaptive strategy for at least one of the original partners, we determined for each individual the number of partners and the number of offspring they had, and calculated the number of infants per 10 years of tenure length (infants/10ytl) or pair length (infants/10ypl). We compared the number of infants/10ytl for individuals that had only one with those that had two or more partners using a general linear model (after inspecting visually for deviations from normality) with number of partners (one or more) and sex as fixed factors. Since any effect found in that analysis could be related to the duration of pair-bonds, we used a linear mixed effect model with female and male identity as random factors to investigate the relationship between duration of a pair and the number of infants/10ytl. We checked the suitability of the model using graphical methods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Zuur1">[32]</xref>, and we ran a Shapiro-Wilk test to confirm that there was no statistically significant deviation from normality in the residuals (W = 0.97, p = 0.64). During the physical exam of individuals we scored wounds at the ears on a scale from 0 (no wounds) to 3 (badly damaged ears), and noted the number of scars, missing teeth and broken canines. We compared the scores of adult animals who were still resident in a breeding group (‘residents’) with those of adults that had been expelled from their group in two ways: using a Mann-Whitney U-test, and matching five residents with five expelled individuals of similar age in a Wilcoxon matched-pair test. Matched individuals had no more than two months of age difference and the mean age for both residents and expelled individuals was 103 months. All analyses were two-tailed and conducted in R 2.13 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-R1">[33]</xref>. We used package lme4 for the mixed effect model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Bates1">[34]</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Owl monkeys did not pair for life; both males and females were regularly replaced by intruding adult individuals, with both males and females being replaced equally often. The intruders had been floaters, relatively young adults who had dispersed from their natal groups. We recorded 27 female and 23 male replacements (including ‘double replacements’ when occasionally two or three replacements occurred in quick succession) during 149 group-years in 18 groups between 2001 and 2011 (G-test with William's correction, G<sub>corr</sub> = 0.32, df = 1, p = 0.57). Median pair-duration of 26 pairs that stayed long enough together to produce at least one offspring was 9.1 years (survival analysis taking censored data into account), and individuals had a median number of two partners during their reproductive lives. The proportion of individuals with one or more partners did not differ between males and females. Nine females had only one partner during their tenure, and 12 females had more than one. Ten males had only one partner, whereas 15 males had more than one (G-test, G<sub>corr</sub> = 0.04, df = 1, p = 0.85). Males and females with more than one partner had on average 2.2 partners. Since these estimates were obtained using censored tenure length, the actual proportion of individuals that never had more than one partner during the entire life is probably even lower.</p>
      <p>The change of partner reduced the reproductive success of the remaining individual. On average, an owl monkey who only had one partner produced 25% offspring more per decade of tenure than an individual with two or more partners (7.9 vs 6.3, glm, N<sub>1</sub> = 19, N<sub>≥2</sub> = 27, t = −2.1, p = 0.038; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053724-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). This result was not significantly different for the sexes (glm, t = 0.42, p = 0.67). The difference in reproductive success was the consequence of a delay in reproduction following the formation of a new pair. The median inter-birth interval (IBI) of established pairs was 13.1 months (N = 22 pairs, 59 IBIs), whereas the mean delay between pair formation and first birth was 15.5 months (median: 14.4, N = 15 pairs). Since births are seasonal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque1">[16]</xref>, when a pair dissolved, the remaining partner skipped a year of breeding, while stable pairs normally reproduced once a year. Only four of 22 pairs produced an offspring within the first year of pair-formation.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0053724-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053724.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Number of infants per decade of tenure length (infants/10ytl).</title>
          <p>The boxplot show medians (solid line), means (dotted line) and interquartile ranges for individuals with one or with two or more partners during their tenure. The whiskers give the range except for “outliers” that are more than ±1.5 times the inter-quartile range larger or smaller than the median.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053724.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>There were no intrinsic factors clearly associated with pair-bond termination. Shorter pair durations were not associated with pairs that had fewer offspring per year (linear mixed model, t = −0.25, p = 0.81; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053724-g002">Fig. 2</xref>), nor were break-ups more common after particularly long inter-birth intervals. Indeed, the median time between the birth of the last infant and break-up was 10.1 months, shorter than the average inter-birth interval reported above, not longer as would be expected if break-ups were triggered by failures to reproduce.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0053724-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053724.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Correlation between the number of offspring per decade of pair duration and the total length a pair lasted.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053724.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>On the other hand, break-ups were strongly associated with factors extrinsic to the pair. In a majority of cases with detailed known circumstances (63%, 12/19 cases), one of the former residents was clearly expelled by the intruding individual. Among these cases there were five (four females, one male) when we either witnessed a fight resulting in wounds and limping, or we found the expelled individuals limping or with serious bite wounds shortly after the replacement; in one case this resulted in the death of the animal one day later. In about a third of the cases (37%, 7/19), the death of a former resident preceded the intrusion of a new individual, and never did a male or a female leave their partner (i.e., “divorced”). Secondary dispersal is infrequent; only two males of 50 expelled individuals successfully immigrated for a second time into a new group. Non-widowed owl monkey pairs clearly terminated their bond following the aggressive intrusion of a new individual. Ear wounds were more frequent among expelled individuals than among resident ones; all five expelled individuals showed ear wounds whereas only sixty-eight percent of 74 adults still resident as breeders had damaged ears. Furthermore, the degree to which ears were wounded differed markedly between residents and expelled individuals (average scores of 2.2 and 1.3 respectively; Mann-Whitney U-test: W = 279, N<sub>1</sub> = 5, N<sub>2</sub> = 72, p = 0.04), a difference that persisted when comparing residents and expelled individuals of matched age (Wilcoxon matched-pair test: W = 23, N = 5, p = 0.025; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053724-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). There were no pronounced differences between the sexes in the average ear-wound scores (median<sub>female</sub> = 2.0, median<sub>male</sub> = 2.0; Mann-Whitney U-test: W = 669, N<sub>female</sub> = 41, N<sub>male</sub> = 36, p = 0.45).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0053724-g003" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053724.g003</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Ear wound score for adult owl monkeys.</title>
          <p>Ages for individuals that were still resident (♦) in a breeding group or recently expelled (○) are matched.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0053724.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Life-time reproductive success is highest for owl monkeys that do not change partners during their lifetime. A 25% increase during the life-time reproductive period should be a strong selective force. There could be other possible costs, potentially associated with the replacement of one of the parents, like reduced infant survivorship or early dispersal of juveniles and subadults. However, in our population, infant survival and age of dispersal did not change following replacements <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Huck3">[28]</xref>. Our findings differ from those reported for some monogamous birds, where remaining life-time reproductive success (i.e., the expected future gains) of the individual that initiates or tolerates a ‘divorce’ was higher than if it remained with its initial partner. For example, in kittiwakes (<italic>Rissa tridactyla</italic>) and many other pair-living birds, but also in some human societies, it is sometimes advantageous to ‘divorce’, if partners prove incompatible <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-GarcaNavas1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Dubois1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-BorgerhoffMulder1">[35]</xref>. In contrast, our data strongly indicate that break-ups were associated with factors extrinsic to the pair, and that partners did not voluntarily leave or “divorce” as it has been reported for birds, gibbons, and (in at least one case) brown titi monkeys (<italic>Callicebus brunneus</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-GarcaNavas1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Dubois1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Palombit1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Lawrence1">[37]</xref>. On the other hand, in some species (oystercatchers, <italic>Haematopus ostralegus</italic>), the reproductive success of stable pairs is not only higher, but there are also accrued benefits with increased duration of the pair-bond, independent of effects of age or experience <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-vandePol1">[38]</xref>. This was not the case for owl monkeys, since the number of offspring produced did not change with increased duration of the pair-bond (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053724-g002">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>Our results show that the owl monkey social system can be described as long-term serial monogamy. What remains to be carefully examined is the extent to which partners who have an interest in long-term stable bonds help his or her mate to repel intruders. We have shown that competition for breeding positions can be surprisingly fierce, sometimes leading to the death of one of the contestants. Thus, it is possible that the loss of fitness due to one missed breeding season is still lower than the potential costs of severe injuries during fights.</p>
      <p>Similar findings of replacements through intense intra-sexual aggression have also been anecdotally reported for titi monkeys, another primate whose social organization is most similar to owl monkeys <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Lawrence1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Rodman1">[39]</xref>. These data also support earlier findings that, despite the relatively smaller canines of <italic>Aotus</italic> compared to most other primate species with high levels of intra-sexual aggression, the canines are substantially larger than those of closely related species with low intensity levels of aggression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Plavcan1">[7]</xref>. Monomorphism in this socially and genetically monogamous, bi-parental-care species might therefore be due to intra-sexual competition in both males and females, rather than to a lack of competition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Plavcan1">[7]</xref>. High potential levels of aggression among females, as well as among males are also found in gibbons (<italic>Hylobates muelleri</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Mitani2">[15]</xref>. While it has been suggested that aggression among female birds might be over resources rather than mates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-LeBas1">[40]</xref>, the replacements in owl monkeys seem to indicate that they are due to competition, for mates and a territory, at similar rates in females and males. Aggression has been shown to be beneficial in the context of female-female competition in other taxa as well, such as tree swallows (<italic>Tachycineta bicolor</italic>), European starlings (<italic>Sturnus vulgaris</italic>), and chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Rosvall1">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Pusey1">[43]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In populations where defensible territories are stable over some extended time, individuals are expected to fight fiercely over them since access to territories will highly affect their reproductive success <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Grafen1">[44]</xref>. The pressure to hold a territory should be particularly high if the survival of floaters is strongly reduced compared to group-living territory holders. As we have shown, all these conditions hold in our owl monkey population. Thus, we argue that our findings raise the question of whether the operational sex ratio, both theoretically and empirically linked to the degree of intra-sexual competition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Emlen1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Weir1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-CluttonBrock1">[6]</xref>, can be assumed to be 1∶1 in pair-living species, even if males and females have similar potential reproductive rates. Rather, our data show that at each replacement event, several floaters of the same sex that roam solitarily, and without fixed home-ranges among the territories of established pairs, will compete for reproductive positions. In our population, both females and males can be affected by this process; but not necessarily at the same time or location (i.e., group). Thus, depending on whether we estimate the OSR for the whole population, only for established pairs, or for one particular group, we may conclude that the OSR is balanced, male-biased or female-biased.</p>
      <p>In many species, it is very difficult to assess the floater population, or how many same-sexed individuals without established territories might at a given time compete with each other, since floaters tend to behave less conspicuously than established groups (pers. obs.). The potential presence of floaters of both sexes, and the subsequent context-specific OSRs that will result from their presence are usually neglected in sexual selection models, even when the influence of density-effects on the evolution of aggressiveness are well known <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Knell1">[4]</xref>. In conclusion, given that it has long been recognized that OSRs can be time and place specific <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-CluttonBrock1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-Grant1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0053724-deJong1">[46]</xref>, the incorporation into sexual selection models of flexible, context-specific OSRs may help explain why many monogamous species are monomorphic, but, at least occasionally, also ferociously aggressive competitors.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Bellamar Estancias continuously supported the Owl Monkey Project. The study has the approval of the Formosa Province Council of Veterinarian Doctors, the Directorate of Wildlife, the Subsecretary of Ecology and Natural Resources and the Ministry of Production. At the national level, the procedures were approved by the National Wildlife Directorate in Argentina and by the IACUC committees of the Zoological Society of San Diego (2000–2005) and of the University of Pennsylvania (2006–2011). We would like to thank those who helped with data collection. T. Clutton-Brock, S. Blaffer Hrdy, P. Kappeler, R. Seyfarth, C. Valeggia, and two anonymous reviewers provided valuable comments on earlier drafts of the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Emlen1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emlen</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oring</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Ecology, sexual selection, and the evolution of mating systems</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>197</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Weir1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>JWA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchings</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The influence of operational sex ratio on the intensity of competition for mates</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>177</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-WestEberhard1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>West-Eberhard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Sexual selection, social competition, and speciation</article-title>. <source>Q Rev Biol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Knell1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knell</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Population density and the evolution of male aggression</article-title>. <source>J Zool</source> <volume>278</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Kvarnemo1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kvarnemo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahnesjö</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The dynamics of operational sex ratios and competition for mates</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>404</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-CluttonBrock1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Potential reproductive rates and the operation of sexual selection</article-title>. <source>Q Rev Biol</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>456</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Plavcan1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plavcan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Schaik</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Competition, coalitions and canine size in primates</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Mitani1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gros-Louis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Sexual dimorphism, the operational sex ratio, and the intensity of male competition in polygynous primates</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>966</fpage>–<lpage>980</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Thoren1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thoren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindenfors</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic analyses of dimorphism in primates: Evidence for stronger selection on canine size than on body size</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Fitze1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitze</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Galliard</surname><given-names>JFo</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Operational sex ratio, sexual conflict and the intensity of sexual selection</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>432</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Setchell1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Setchell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Selection in relation to sex in primates</article-title>. <source>Adv Stud Behav</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Heske1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heske</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostfeld</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Sexual dimorphism in size, relative size of testes, and mating systems in North American voles</article-title>. <source>J Mammal</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>510</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Wittenberger1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wittenberger</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tilson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>The evolution of monogamy: hypotheses and evidence</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Ecol Syst</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Stockley1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bro-Jørgensen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Female competition and its evolutionary consequences in mammals</article-title>. <source>Biol Rev</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Mitani2">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>The behavioral regulation of monogamy in gibbons (<italic>Hylobates muelleri</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fernandez-Duque E (2011) Aotinae: Social monogamy in the only nocturnal anthropoid. In: Campbell CJ, Fuentes A, MacKinnon KC, Bearder SK, Stumpf R, editors. Primates in Perspective. 2nd ed. Oxford: Oxford University Press. pp.139–154.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Wright1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wright PC (1981) The night monkeys, genus <italic>Aotus</italic>. In: Coimbra-Filho A, Mittermeier RA, editors. Ecology and Behavior of Neotropical Primates. Rio de Janeiro: Academia Brasileira de Ciencias. pp.211–240.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque2">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Duque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Rensch's rule, Bergmann's effect and adult sexual dimorphism in wild monogamous owl monkeys (<italic>Aotus azarai</italic>) of Argentina</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Huck1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rotundo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Duque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Growth and development in wild owl monkeys (<italic>Aotus azarai</italic>) of Argentina</article-title>. <source>Int J Primatol</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1133</fpage>–<lpage>1152</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Rotundo1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotundo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Duque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Infant development and parental care in free-ranging <italic>Aotus azarai azarai</italic> in Argentina</article-title>. <source>Int J Primatol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1459</fpage>–<lpage>1473</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Huck2">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Huck M, Fernandez-Duque E (2012) When dads help: male behavioral care during primate infant development. In: Clancy KBH, Hinde K, Rutherford JN, editors. Building Babies: Primate Development in Proximate and Ultimate Perspective. New York: Springer. pp.361–385.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Wright2">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wright PC (1984) Biparental care in <italic>Aotus trivirgatus</italic> and <italic>Callicebus moloch</italic>. In: Small MF, editor. Female Primates: Studies by Women Primatologists. New York: Alan R. Liss. pp.59–75.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Dixson1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixson</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Parental behaviour and infant development in owl monkeys (<italic>Aotus trivirgatus griseimembra</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Zoology, London</source> <volume>194</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque3">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Duque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Natal dispersal in monogamous owl monkeys (<italic>Aotus azarai</italic>) of the Argentinean Chaco</article-title>. <source>Behaviour</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-GarcaNavas1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>García-Navas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Females call the shots: breeding dispersal and divorce in blue tits</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>932</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Choudhury1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Divorce in birds: a review of the hypotheses</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Dubois1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cézilly</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Breeding success and mate retention in birds: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Huck3">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Duque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Children of divorce: effects of adult replacements on previous offspring in Argentinean owl monkeys</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>517</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-FernandezDuque4">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Duque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rotundo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Field methods for capturing and marking azarai night monkeys</article-title>. <source>Int J Primatol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>–<lpage>1120</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Jurez1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juárez</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rotundo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Duque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Costs and benefits of radio-collaring on the behavior, demography and conservation of owl monkeys (<italic>Aotus azarai</italic>) in Formosa, Argentina</article-title>. <source>Int J Primatol</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Crawley1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Crawley MJ (2007) The R Book. Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Zuur1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zuur A, Ieno EN, Walker NJ, Saveliev AA, Smith GM (2009) Mixed Effects Models and Extensions in Ecology with R. Heidelberg: Springer.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-R1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">R Development Core Team (2012) R: A language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Bates1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bates D, Maechler M, Bolker B (2011) lme4: Linear mixed-effects models using S4 classes. R package version 0.999375-42. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=lme4" xlink:type="simple">http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=lme4</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-BorgerhoffMulder1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgerhoff Mulder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Serial monogamy as polygyny or polyandry? Marriage in the Tanzanian Pimbwe</article-title>. <source>Hum Nature</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Palombit1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palombit</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Dynamic pair bonds in hylobatids: implications regarding monogamous social systems</article-title>. <source>Behaviour</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Lawrence1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lawrence JM (2007) Understanding the pair bond in brown titi monkeys (<italic>Callicebus brunneus</italic>): male and female reproductive interests [PhD thesis]: Columbia University. 157 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-vandePol1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van de Pol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruinzeel</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuijper</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verhulsta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Experimental evidence for a causal effect of pair-bond duration on reproductive performance in oystercatchers (<italic>Haematopus ostralegus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>982</fpage>–<lpage>991</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Rodman1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodman</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Fathers and stepfathers: familial relations of old and new males within groups of <italic>Callicebus brunneus</italic> in southeastern Perú [Abstract]</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>132, Issue S44</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-LeBas1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>LeBas</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Female finery is not for males</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Rosvall1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosvall</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Sexual selection on aggressiveness in females: evidence from an experimental test with tree swallows</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>1603</fpage>–<lpage>1610</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Sandell1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandell</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Exogenous testosterone increases female aggression in the European starling (<italic>Sturnus vulgaris</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Pusey1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pusey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallauer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wroblewski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Severe aggression among female <italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic> at Gombe National Park, Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Int J Primatol</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>949</fpage>–<lpage>973</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Grafen1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grafen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The logic of divisively asymmetric contests: respect for ownership and the desperado effect</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-Grant1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>JWA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foam</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Effect of operational sex ratio on female-female versus male-male competitive aggression</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>2242</fpage>–<lpage>2246</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0053724-deJong1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wacker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amundsen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forsgren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Do operational sex ratio and density affect mating behaviour? An experiment on the two-spotted goby</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>1229</fpage>–<lpage>1238</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>