<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-00335</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059805</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biological anthropology</subject>
              <subject>Economic anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Economics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microeconomics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Spatial economic analysis</subject>
                <subject>Supply and demand</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Economic anthropology</subject>
              <subject>Economic models</subject>
              <subject>Economic competition</subject>
              <subject>Economic development</subject>
              <subject>Information economics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Evolutionary Thinking in Microeconomic Models: Prestige Bias and Market Bubbles</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Prestige Bias and Market Bubbles</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bell</surname>
            <given-names>Adrian Viliami</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <addr-line>Department of Anthropology, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Huerta-Quintanilla</surname>
            <given-names>Rodrigo</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Cinvestav-Merida, Mexico</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">adrian.bell@anthro.utah.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and conducted the analysis: AVB. Wrote the paper: AVB.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <elocation-id>e59805</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Adrian Bell</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Evolutionary models broadly support a number of social learning strategies likely important in economic behavior. Using a simple model of price dynamics, I show how prestige bias, or copying of famed (and likely successful) individuals, influences price equilibria and investor disposition in a way that exacerbates or creates market bubbles. I discuss how integrating the social learning and demographic forces important in cultural evolution with economic models provides a fruitful line of inquiry into real-world behavior.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This author has no support or funding to report.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="5"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Cultural variation is widespread and important to economies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Alesina1">[1]</xref>. Cultural-prescribed behavioral diversity in domains such as commons institutions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Ostrom1">[2]</xref>, languages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-FoleyWA1">[3]</xref>, and the formation of ethnic groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Fearon1">[4]</xref> provide challenges and opportunities to economic development and governance. Interactions across linguistic or ethnic groups influence fairness preferences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Ferraro1">[5]</xref>, labor wage differentials, high communication costs may lead to bargaining breakdowns <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Grin1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Jones1">[7]</xref>, and diverse ethnic groups may undermine political bargaining leading to gridlock <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Hannan1">[8]</xref>. On the other hand, diverse communities may also promote production and innovation by the more frequent introduction of novel ideas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Hong1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Ottaviano1">[10]</xref>. Behavioral scientists must account for the origin of cultural diversity and change before arriving at an understanding important for policy makers and theoreticians alike.</p>
      <p>In this paper I discuss the gene-culture coevolutionary approach to explaining cultural variation and briefly introduce its theories of individual decision making. Since much of the theory is about the evolution of learning, it offers a simultaneous appeal to the ultimate origins of behavior as well as the proximate mechanisms behind behavioral change as actors adopt (or not) behaviors from others. After briefly reviewing the theoretical and empirical evidence for social learning biases, I show how actors engaging in a prestige bias, in particular, alter price equilibria using a stylized model of price dynamics.</p>
      <sec id="s1a">
        <title>Gene-culture Coevolution</title>
        <p>Among primates, humans are an anomaly for their ability to generate highly variable speech. Key to our ability is the much lower position of the larynx, or “voice box”, allowing us to easily produce a far more diverse repertoire of discriminable vocal tract resonances compared to other primates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Lieberman1">[11]</xref>. While there are a fair number of hypothesis for how this first arose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd1">[13]</xref>, it is highly plausible that the human vocal tract has been modified and maintained to enhance the capacity to acquire and use cultural information. In a like manner that human morphology was shaped by social influences, especially regarding cultural learning, selection is likely to have played a role in honing our ability to acquire cultural information in adaptive ways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd1">[13]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The human capacity for complex culture likely began 250,000 years ago <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-McBrearty1">[14]</xref>, and since then has generated adaptive culture that allowed human populations to expand to the most marginal regions of the world. Human populations have long faced a widely changing environment both spatially and temporally, and theoretical models show how natural selection would favor individuals to engage in optimal amounts of adaptive social learning and individual innovation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd1">[13]</xref>, chap. 4). For example, the turbulent Pleistocene environment presented the right conditions to favored the evolution of savy social learners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Richerson1">[15]</xref>, pp 131–139), and the relative stability of the Holocene may have favored accumulated cultural knowledge in plant innovations leading toward domestication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Richerson2">[16]</xref>. In fact, adherence to tradition can maximize utility better that Bayesian learning under certain conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd2">[17]</xref>. In a fluctuating environment, adaptive learners pay more attention to tradition as the environmental autocorrelation increases and the quality of environmental information decreases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059805-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0059805-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>When culture (tradition) is favored in a fluctuating environment.</title>
            <p>A result of an evolutionary model of learning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd1">[13]</xref>, chap. 4), plotted are three curves for three values of environmental autocorrelation (<italic>R</italic>). Higher values of <italic>R</italic> indicate more similar environments through time. This result extends to Bayesian learners and environmental heterogeneity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd2">[17]</xref>. Social learning (e.g. imitation or adherence to tradition) is favored by natural selection and will maximize utility as environments change less and individual learning becomes more error prone.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The consensus among many is that humans have an evolved psychology to learn. Evolutionary theoreticians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Richerson1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-CavalliSforza1">[18]</xref> and economists <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Schlag1">[19]</xref> together have motivated a number of social learning biases that, scaled to the population level, can lead to distinct cultural trajectories. Behind this theoretical foundation, a growing field of experimental and field studies are bringing us closer to a finer description of how actors adopt behaviors and beliefs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s1b">
        <title>Evidence for Learning Biases</title>
        <p>While the evidence clearly suggests our preference to imitate others is extraordinary among primates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Whiten1">[20]</xref>, there is a slow developing consensus on how and when humans learn socially. Experimental evidence in anthropology and psychology show that individuals have a propensity to imitate the successful in economic games <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-McElreath1">[21]</xref> and conform to majority behavior in other experimental tasks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Asch1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Efferson1">[24]</xref>. In a multi-armed bandit, McElreath et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-McElreath1">[21]</xref> show participants preferring to imitate those with higher payoffs. It is likely that actors employ a number of social learning strategies, with substantial heterogeneity within a group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Efferson1">[24]</xref>. Ethnographic accounts suggest individual biases in cultural learning are behind the persistent ethnic subcultures that maintain substantial differences in norms of violence, farming practices, and religious beliefs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Nisbett1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Salamon1">[26]</xref>.</p>
        <p>These findings suggest a subset of learning strategies may be especially important to microeconomic processes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0059805-t001">Table 1</xref>). One particularly salient bias is the copying of prestigious individuals, a Model-based bias, where actors adopt the behaviors or beliefs from those who receive a disproportionate amount of attention or deference from other learners (i.e. Warren Buffet). Perhaps a universal feature, human societies recognize the prestigious who are liable to be imitated by many. Evolutionary models suggest prestige biased learning as a broadly adaptive learning strategy as it provides a quick way for a naive learner to obtain optimal behaviors in the current environment (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Henrich1">[27]</xref> for a review of the theory and evidence). In an attempt for direct experimental evidence for a prestige bias, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Chudek1">[28]</xref> show that in certain conditions children preferentially learn from those who receive more bystander attention. Even among chimpanzees with relatively limited social learning abilities compared to humans, there is evidence of preferentially adopting solutions to a foraging problem from higher-ranked and older chimpanzees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Horner1">[29]</xref>. Clearly, this social learning “force” should be incorporated into our models of decision making.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0059805-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Plausible learning biases important to economic processes – decision-making and biased-transmission learning strategies (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Richerson1">[15]</xref>).</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0059805-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decision-making forces</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Guided variation.</bold> Nonrandom changes in cultural variants by individuals that are subsequently transmitted. This force results from transformations during social learning, or the learning, invention, or adaptive modification of cultural variants.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Biased-transmission</bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Content-based (or direct) bias.</bold> Individuals are more likely to learn or remember some cultural variants based on their content. Content-based bias can result from calculation of costs and benefits associated with alternative variants, or because the structure of cognition makes some variants easier to learn or remember.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Frequency-based bias.</bold> The use of the commonness or rarity of a cultural variant as a basis for choice. For example, the most advantageous variant is often likely to be the commonest. If so, a conformity bias is an easy way to acquire the correct variant.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Model-based bias.</bold> Choice of trait based on the observable attributes of the individuals who exhibit the trait. Plausible model-based biases include a predisposition to imitate successful or prestigious individuals, and a predisposition to imitate individuals similar to oneself.</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>To motivate the use of social learning forces in economics, I use a model to illustrate how biases in social learning can influence price dynamics in a market. First I consider a model of herding behavior by Lux <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Lux1">[30]</xref>, and show how biases in social learning can influence price equilibria. Then I show how a prestige bias can cause or exacerbate market bubbles. As a simple caricature of a complex problem, the goal is to highlight in a transparent fashion the effects of an evolutionary-motivated learning strategy on asset price and investor disposition equilibria.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Analysis</title>
      <p>Since prestige bias was likely a good learning strategy for much of our species history, lets assume that actors have a culturally and/or genetically reinforced propensity to learn from prestigious persons. Given this propensity, the goal is to see how trade price equilibria may significantly differ from their fundamental value as investors learn, then buy or sell.</p>
      <p>Investing in inflated markets through herding behavior has been modeled previously by Lux <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Lux1">[30]</xref>, and I will use this modeling framework to describe the effect of theoretically motived social learning strategies on market price equilibrium. Let <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> be the number of optimistic and pessimistic investors, respectively. By defining <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, then <italic>x</italic> is an index from −1 to 1 describing the average disposition of investors. Increasing lower and negative values indicate more pessimistic investors (sellers), increasing higher and positive values indicate more optimistic investors (buyers), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> indicates an equal number of buyers and sellers. Let <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> be the transition probability of investors who are pessimistic becoming optimistic, and those who are optimistic becoming pessimistic, respectively. Then a recursion describing the disposition of investors is:<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e009"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e009" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula></p>
      <p>For a model of price dynamics, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Lux1">[30]</xref>, assume that pessimistic investors enter the supply side by selling the asset and optimistic investors enter the demand side by buying additional units of the asset. Each trader buys or sells a fixed amount of stock (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and the total trading volume of speculative investors becomes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Then the net excess demand becomes:<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e012"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e012" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the total trading volume for this group of speculators. At this point, for all trades to be completed it is required that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Therefore a second group of traders is added that would buy or sell to speculators. Call these traders fundamentalists, such that excess demand of this group depends on the difference in the fundamental value of the asset (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and the actual price at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e018"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e018" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the total trading volume of this group. Assuming that prices respond to excess demand in supply, translated in price change by constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we can then derive recursions describing the price dynamics.</p>
      <p><disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e021"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e021" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>The full system of investor behavior and price dynamics then becomes:<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e022"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e022" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula></p>
      <p>Our analysis focuses on how how learning can affect price equilibria (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) from their fundamental price (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and the equilibrium disposition of investors (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The price equilibria,<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e026"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e026" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>depends on the final disposition of investors. The key learning process occurs in defining the transition probabilities from buyer to seller and vice versa (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). If we let the transition probabilities equal the current frequency of an investor strategy, i.e.,<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e028"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e028" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>then it is easy to see that the system (5) yields no change in x (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). This fundamental result in cultural evolution suggests that cultural change occurs when there are biases in social learning, such as actors assorting or learning preferentially from those with similar preferences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd1">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Instead of adopting the disposition of random individuals, assume that actors follow current market trends such that dispositions change depending on accurate projected directions of the trade price. An increase in the market value will more likely cause pessimistic speculators to become optimistic (buyers), and a decrease in market value will cause optimistic investors to more likely become pessimistic (sellers). Then the transition probabilities become:<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e030"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e030" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(8)</label></disp-formula></p>
      <p>The equilibrium, (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), following these transition probabilities is (0, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The eigenvalues of the linearized system (5) shows that this equilibrium (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is stable when one of the below two conditions are satisfied (see Supporting Information, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059805.s001">Derivations S1</xref>):<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e035"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e035" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(9)</label></disp-formula>or if,</p>
      <p><disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e036"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e036" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(10)</label></disp-formula>Remembering that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> translates the excess demand into a change in trade price and parameter <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> scales the effect of price projections on investor disposition, the above condition reflects the level of response to demand and price changes. This makes sense since <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Lux1">[30]</xref> shows (in the continuous time version) that an unstable equilibrium at (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e039" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e040" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) leads to limit cycles, and cycles generally depend on time lags – in this case responses to price and demand changes. Even when additional “mood of the market” parameters heighten the influence of social contagion that would potentially dampen the cycles, the cycles persist because price increases diminish and the market “loses confidence” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Lux1">[30]</xref>. Neither the state of pure optimism (or pessimism) can exist indefinitely <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Mitchell1">[31]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Finally, consider a prestige bias such that individuals adopt the behavior of successful individuals. Rather than follow market trends, actors may look toward prestigious individuals whose assets are higher valued. An indirect measure of this success may be how different the fundamental value of an asset is from the current price of the asset (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). The individuals with the high-valued asset, relative to the fundamental price, are viewed as opinion leaders that prescribe the pathway to success. When actors meet, they learn of others’ updated assets and assume the net increase in asset value to be the difference from the fundamental price. Actors compare this difference to a baseline difference, (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), that may represent a shared preference or some outside option. Given that an actor meets an individual with an opposite disposition, she may adopt a disposition depending on this difference scaled by a constant (<italic>a</italic>). The transition probabilities become:<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e043"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e043" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(11)</label></disp-formula></p>
      <p>This specification leads to the investor-price joint equilibria (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) as (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), and (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ). Equilibrium trade price in the state of pure optimism (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the “growing bubble” condition) depends on trade volume between our two groups and the fundamental price:<disp-formula id="pone.0059805.e049"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e049" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(12)</label></disp-formula></p>
      <p>This equilibrium has the potential to increase indefinitely as the fraction of trading originates from non-fundamentalist speculators. Under prestige-biased learning specified in (11), the equilibrium with only optimistic investors is stable when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (see Supporting Information, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0059805.s001">Derivations S1</xref>). The greater the relative trading volume for non-fundamentalist than fundamentalist investors, the greater the chance for most investors feeling optimistic about their assets in the long run. In other words, the more traders using prestige biased social learning the higher and more stable are inflated assets. This outcome is limited when assets in outside markets signal increasing high returns (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) from their own fundamental price. Note also that the pessimistic equilibrium is always stable and the unstable internal equilibrium, (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) = (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ), which determines the domain of attraction for the pessimistic and optimistic equilibrium, becomes increasing in favor of pessimism with a <italic>larger</italic> fraction of the trading coming from non-fundamentalists. In sum, if outside markets present minor “prestigious” gains relative to the current market and there is a precedence for optimism among investors, then prestige biased decision making among speculators can prolong an “irrational” state of optimism and lead to or exacerbate market bubbles.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <p>This model shows how an evolutionarily favored social learning strategy can cause an “irrational” inflated price equilibrium. Investors able to forecast market trends will keep price dynamics in the region of the fundamental price (perhaps cycling around it), thus controlling price inflation. Once actors imitate the disposition of prestigious individuals, along with control of a disproportionate share of the trading volume, prices inflate leading to a potential market collapse.</p>
      <p>Other explanations for market bubbles may fit into the intuitions of this model. One narrative argues that herding among traders is due to reputational effects and the relative performance of mutual fund managers. Dass et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Dass1">[32]</xref> found that managers that were payed on an absolute scale documented less herding effects than among fund managers evaluated on a relative scale with other managers. Along the same theme, DeMarzo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-DeMarzo1">[33]</xref> use a model to argue that rational actors with relative wealth concerns may not trade against the crowd. This result is driven by the fact that they include the wealth of others in their utility function.</p>
      <p>This model analysis further corroborates thinking on economic contagion that posits a number of mechanisms by which shocks propagate more than expected <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Edwards1">[34]</xref>, one of which emphasizes the role of incomplete and/or asymmetric information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Calvo1">[35]</xref>, e.g.). Here social information is predictive as investors follow “informed” market participants, subjecting the market to fads and rumors leading to herding behavior. As shown above, using social influence is broadly favored by natural selection when the cost of accurate information is high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059805-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Therefore, one or more of the social learning biases in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0059805-t001">Table 1</xref> may characterize how investors behave.</p>
      <p>Future work is needed to directly test empirically whether investors adopt the behaviors of prestigious individuals and therefore exacerbate market bubbles. An effective assessment would include broader theoretical development than presented here, as the above stylized model of markets is to motivate future theoretical work as well as empirical inquiry (i.e. when the fundamental price is difficulty to assess, as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Blanchard1">[36]</xref>). Also, since it is likely that humans may use a variety of different social learning strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Efferson1">[24]</xref>, e.g.) that may mitigate or further exacerbate market bubbles, models assuming heterogeneity in learning strategies would likely yield new insights and predictions for empirical testing. Further, proponents of the rational actor concept may derive conditions under which prestige bias, or any other evolutionary-motivated social learning strategy, yields rational decision-making.</p>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Integrating Other Evolutionary Insights</title>
        <p>Gene-cultural coevolution motivates social contagion behaviors often invoked in economic models. However, applying evolutionary theory may also move beyond the social learning preferences actors use, and consider other important parameters in gene-culture coevolutionary research. Population size, migration rates, and other demographic parameters have shown in theory to affect cultural variation. Especially in small groups, technology may be lost due to random loss of experts, especially for harder to learn objects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd1">[13]</xref> chap. 7, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Henrich2">[37]</xref>). Engineers may “disinvent” innovations, and a weak link in the chain of knowledge reproduction may result in the loss of innovations. Heavy migration may increase the effective size of the cultural traits available to learners, and may make populations more similar, depending on the learning strategies employed, migration patterns, and the strength of local adaptation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0059805-Boyd3">[38]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <p>This paper demonstrates the scope of the gene-culture coevolutionary approach to explaining economic behavior in markets. Through a simultaneous appeal to proximate mechanisms and ultimate origins, an analysis of market behavior provided novel results, suggesting further theoretical and empirical work on social learning strategies. Investors able to forecast market trends will keep price dynamics in the region of the fundamental price (perhaps cycling around it), thus controlling price inflation. However, once actors imitate the disposition of prestigious individuals, along with control of a disproportionate share of the trading volume, prices inflate leading to a potential market collapse. By integrating social learning strategies and other evolutionary forces into economic models, new avenues of inquiry are likely to open and provide new insights into complex economic phenomenon.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0059805.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0059805.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Derivations S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>This technical appendix reports the equilibria and stability conditions discussed in the main text.</bold> Further details can be requested from the author.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Peter Richerson, Joseph Henrich and multiple reviewers provided useful comments and references.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Alesina1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alesina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrara</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Ethnic diversity and economic performance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Literature</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>762</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Ostrom1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ostrom E (2005) Understanding Institutional Diversity. Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-FoleyWA1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">FoleyWA (1986) The Papuan languages of New Guinea. Cambridge Language Surveys. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Fearon1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Ethnic and cultural diversity by country</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Growth</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Ferraro1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraro</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cultural diversity, discrimination, and economic outcomes: An experimental analysis</article-title>. <source>Economic Inquiry</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Grin1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Grin F (2006) Economic Considerations in Language Policy, Malden: Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Jones1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jones EL (2000) The Case for a Shared World Language, New York: Springer.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Hannan1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Dynamics of formal political structure: An event-history analysis</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Hong1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Groups of diverse problem solvers can outperform groups of high-ability problem solvers</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>16385</fpage>–<lpage>16389</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Ottaviano1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ottaviano</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The economic value of cultural diversity: Evidence from U.S. cities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Geography</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Lieberman1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klatt</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>Vocal tract limitations on the vowel repertoires of rhesus monkey and other nonhuman primates</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>1185</fpage>–<lpage>1187</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Fitch1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitch</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The evolution of speech: a comparative review</article-title>. <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Boyd1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Boyd R, Richerson PJ (1985) Culture and the Evolutionary Process. London: The University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-McBrearty1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McBrearty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The revolution that wasn’t: a new interpretation of the origin of modern human behavior</article-title>. <source>Journal of Human Evolution</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>563</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Richerson1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Richerson PJ, Boyd R (2005) Not by genes alone: how culture transformed human evolution. University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Richerson2">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richerson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bettinger</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Was agriculture impossible during the pleistocene but mandatory during the holocene? a climate change hypothesis</article-title>. <source>American Antiquity</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Boyd2">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Boyd R, Richerson P (1993) Rationality, imitation, and tradition, New York: Oxford University Press. 131–149.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-CavalliSforza1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cavalli-Sforza LL, Feldman MW (1981) Cultural transmission and evolution : a quantitative ap- proach. Monographs in population biology: 16. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Schlag1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlag</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Why imitate, and if so, how?: A boundedly rational approach to multi-armed bandits</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Theory</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Whiten1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whiten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGuigan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall-Pescini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Emulation, imitation, over-imitation and the scope of culture for child and chimpanzee</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society (B)</source> <volume>364</volume>: <fpage>2417</fpage>–<lpage>2428</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-McElreath1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McElreath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Efferson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lubell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richerson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Beyong existence and aiming outside the laboratory: Estimating frequency-dependent and payoff-biased social learning strategies</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B</source> <volume>363</volume>: <fpage>3515</fpage>–<lpage>3528</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Asch1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1955</year>) <article-title>Opinions and social pressure</article-title>. <source>Scientific American</source> <volume>193</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Asch2">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asch</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name> (<year>1956</year>) <article-title>Studies of independence and conformity: I. a minority of one against a unanimous majority</article-title>. <source>Psychological Monographs</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Efferson1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Efferson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalive</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richerson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McElreath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lubell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Conformists and mavericks: the empirics of frequency-dependent cultural transmission</article-title>. <source>Evolution and Human Behavior</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Nisbett1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nisbett RE, Cohen D (1996) Culture of honor: the psychology of violence in the South. New directions in social psychology. Boulder, CO: Westview Press, 332 pp.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Salamon1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salamon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Ethnic origin as explanation for local land ownership patterns, Greenwich CT: JAI Press. p</article-title>. <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>161186</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Henrich1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gil-White</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The evolution of prestige - freely conferred deference as a mech- anism for enhancing the benefits of cultural transmission</article-title>. <source>Evolution and Human Behavior</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Chudek1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chudek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Prestige-biased cultural learning: bystander’s differential attention to potential models inuences children’s learning</article-title>. <source>Evolution and Human Behavior</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Horner1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnie</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whiten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>deWaal</surname><given-names>FBM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Prestige affects cultural learning in chimpanzees</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e10625</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Lux1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Herb behaviour, bubbles and crashes</article-title>. <source>The Economic Journal</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>881</fpage>–<lpage>896</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Mitchell1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mitchell WC (1923) Business Cycles, NBER.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Dass1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dass</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Massa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patgiri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mutual funds and bubbles: The surprising role of contractual incentives</article-title>. <source>The Review of Financial Studies</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-DeMarzo1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeMarzo</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaniel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Relative wealth concerns and _nancial bubbles</article-title>. <source>The Review of Financial Studies</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Edwards1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Contagion</article-title>. <source>World Economy</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>873</fpage>–<lpage>900</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Calvo1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Calvo GA, Mendoza EG (2000) Contagion, Globalization, and the Volatility of Capital Flows, University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Blanchard1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Blanchard OJ, Watson MW (1982) Bubbles, Rational Expectations and Financial Markets, Lex- ington, MA: D.C. Heathand Company. 295–316.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Henrich2">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Demography and cultural evolution: How adaptive cultural processes can produce maladaptive losses - the tasmanian case</article-title>. <source>American Antiquity</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0059805-Boyd3">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richerson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Voting with your feet: Payoff biased migration and the evolution of group beneficial behavior</article-title>. <source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source> <volume>257</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>339</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>