<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180009</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-34811</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Education</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical education</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical humanities</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical education</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Quality of life</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical humanities</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care providers</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical doctors</subject><subj-group><subject>Physicians</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Professions</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical doctors</subject><subj-group><subject>Physicians</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject><subj-group><subject>Anxiety</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject><subj-group><subject>Anxiety</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A cross-sectional study of sociodemographic factors and their influence on quality of life in medical students at Sao Paulo, Brazil</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Quality of life in medical students</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Serinolli</surname>
<given-names>Mario Ivo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4802-8446</contrib-id>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Novaretti</surname>
<given-names>Marcia Cristina Zago</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Health Administration Graduate Department, Universidade Nove de Julho, Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo, Brazil</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>Robert</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Institute of Psychiatry, UNITED KINGDOM</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p><list list-type="simple"><list-item>
<p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Data curation:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Investigation:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Methodology:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Project administration:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Resources:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Supervision:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Validation:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Visualization:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item><list-item>
<p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> MIS MCZN.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">marcianovaretti@uni9.pro.br</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>10</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e0180009</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>30</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>7</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Serinolli, Novaretti</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0180009"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Various sociodemographic factors can affect the quality of life of medical students and interfere in their ability to study. A deeper understanding of these factors may facilitate improvements in learning and retention of medical students.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>We conducted a cross-sectional study of 405 medical students, representing 65.3% of the total student body (years 1–6), at a private medical school in São Paulo, Brazil. Among the entire study group, 177 students (43.7%) were male, and 228 (56.3%) were female. The mean age was 23.55 years (SD = 3.98 years, range: 18–40). The World Health Organization Quality of Life-Biomedical Research and Education Facility (WHOQOL-BREF) scale was used to evaluate the following sociodemographic factors: age, sex, academic year, daily traveling time, housing conditions, smoking, weight, height, participant’s and his/her parents’ education background, students who had a degree or not and religious beliefs. The reliability of the WHOQOL-BREF was evaluated using Cronbach’s analysis, and the association of sociodemographic factors with quality of life was examined using multivariate regression analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Main Results</title>
<p>Quality of life was significantly higher in medical students with religious beliefs (β 0.14 for psychological domain; β 0.11 for environmental domain) when compared with that in those with no religious beliefs. BMI was negative associated with QOL in medical students (β -0.11 for physical domain; β -18.9 for the psychological domain). In both male and female students, longer daily traveling time was negative related to QOL (β -0.11 for environmental domain). Having at least one parent who was a doctor was associated with a better quality of life (β 0.17 for environmental domain). Male students presented with significantly higher mean scores for three of the four domains evaluated (β 0.20 for physical domain; β 0.25 for psychological domain; β 0.14 for social domain).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This study has provided novel insights into the effects of sociodemographic factors, physical traits, and religious beliefs on the quality of life of medical students. These findings may facilitate improvements in physical, psychological, and social support for medical students at a critical stage in their training, thereby providing tools for student better adjustment to medical school.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="0"/>
<table-count count="4"/>
<page-count count="13"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>In the 21st century, advances in medicine and in health technology have provided increased access to medical research databases, social networks, and apps, making it more difficult to be a medical student and ultimately a physician [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref001">1</xref>]. Medical students experience greater stress compared with university students in other fields due to the long hours of training, stringent academic demands, frequent examinations, and constant exposure to new and often stressful clinical experiences, all of which may lead to anxiety, depression, and burnout [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref002">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref003">3</xref>]. Moreover, the competitive environment persists after medical school and remains a substantial component of a physician’s life. Medical doctors are expected to deliver high-quality health care, possess strong communication skills, collaborate with other physicians, be accountable to the wider medical team, and adopt a patient-centered approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref004">4</xref>]. They function as educators, leaders, team members, managers, and policymakers. To prepare medical students for these challenges, Cruess <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref001">1</xref>] emphasized the need to reframe medical education and to transition from teaching the concept of professionalism to a concept of aligning medical professionalism with the student’s personal identity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref004">4</xref>].</p>
<p>Using various assessment tools, several studies demonstrated that medical education and training could negatively affect a student’s physical and mental health, thereby reducing their quality of life (QOL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref005">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref007">7</xref>]. Furthermore, the QOL of medical students can greatly change during the course of their academic medical training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref005">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref008">8</xref>]. Recently, Tempski <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref009">9</xref>] demonstrated that strategies designed to improve resilience among medical students might ameliorate the emotional distress associated with medical training. However, the effect of various factors that affect the QOL of the general population, such as obesity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref010">10</xref>] and religious beliefs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref011">11</xref>], on the QOL of medical students remains unclear.</p>
<p>This study was undertaken to evaluate the effect of various sociodemographic factors on the QOL of medical students, with the goal of improving learning and retention at medical school. We hypothesized that normal body index and religious beliefs are positively correlated with the QOL of medical students. We conducted a cross-sectional study of students at a private medical school in Sao Paulo, Brazil using the World Health Organization Quality of Life-Biomedical Research and Education Facility (WHOQOL-BREF) scale questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref012">12</xref>], a tool that facilitates international cross-cultural comparisons of the QOL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref012">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref013">13</xref>]. The questionnaire is available in several languages that are spoken in both developed and developing countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref007">7</xref>], and it has proven to be an effective tool to analyze the QOL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref012">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref013">13</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Study setting and population</title>
<p>Universidade Nove de Julho is a private University with more than 130,000 students. Among the total student body, 720 students are enrolled at the School of Medicine, with 60 new medical students enrolling each semester. Medical training takes at least 8 hours per day, 5 days a week. The Nove de Julho School of Medicine utilizes an innovative teaching strategy to achieve their mission of preparing future primary care physicians. The curriculum comprises 12 semesters of full-time training with 4 semesters of basic sciences, 2 semesters of module training, and 4 semesters of internship. The students begin interacting with patients in a primary care setting during their first semester. During the first 4 semesters, the students take anatomy, histology, biochemistry, physiology, molecular biology, epidemiology, medical ethics, pathology, pharmacology, embryology, statistics, microbiology, parasitology, scientific projects, and primary care. Each course consists of lectures, seminars, and extensive studying. The next phase of medical school is a 2-year period referred to as the modular step. The modular step consists of training in semiology, internal medicine, pediatrics, surgery, community medicine, gynecology and obstetrics, and an introduction to imaging. In addition, the medical students are encouraged to participate in medical rounds and outpatient consultations under close supervision. The last phase of medical school is the internship, in which students do rotations in pediatrics, internal medicine, surgery, psychiatry, gynecology and obstetrics, emergency care, and primary care. Patients with complex or unique conditions are the focus of interdisciplinary discussion with professors throughout the different phases of training.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Study design</title>
<p>We conducted a cross-sectional study from October to November 2014. Medical students at Universidade Nove de Julho in their 1st to 12th semesters voluntarily participated in the study. After the study participants provided informed consent to the authors (MIS or MCZN), they received access to an online survey through a link to the Informatics Laboratory of Universidade Nove de Julho, where each participant independently and anonymously completed a questionnaire comprising 45 questions. The students had 15 minutes to complete the questionnaire. The authors were available to clarify any questions during the entire data collection period. We specifically avoided administering the questionnaire around the time of academic assessments to minimize the potential influence of additional academic stress and/or anxiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref014">14</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>This study adhered to the guidelines of Resolution 466/12 of the Brazilian National Health Council for experiments with humans. It was approved by the Ethics Committee on Human Research of Universidade Nove de Julho under number 014341 in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration. Each participant was well informed of the content and the aim of the questionnaires. The participants had the option of declining to answer any or all questions if they did not wish to do so. All subjects provided written consent immediately prior to data collection. This was an anonymous survey, and the data obtained remain confidential.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Questionnaire</title>
<p>The questionnaire was composed of two sections. The first section collected the following sociodemographic data: age, gender, place of birth, place of residence, distance between residence and university, time spent getting to/from the university, weight, height, religious beliefs (no religion, or religion), and information regarding a participant’s and his/her parents’ education background, students who had a degree or not and habits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref014">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref015">15</xref>]. In the second section of the questionnaire, we administered a Brazilian/Portuguese version [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref016">16</xref>] of the WHOQOL-BREF, a widely used, generic QOL assessment tool provided by the World Health Organization (WHO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref013">13</xref>] that was validated by Fleck <italic>et al</italic>. in 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref017">17</xref>]. QOL assessment is based on answers to questions in four domains: physical health (7 questions), psychological health (6 questions), social relationships (3 questions), and environment (8 questions). Two additional questions assessing general health conditions and QOL satisfaction were included in the second section of the study questionnaire. Each answer is based on self-reported assessments using a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (very dissatisfied/very poor) to 5 (very satisfied/very good). The raw domain scores were transformed into a linear scale between 0 and 100 to facilitate comparisons with another questionnaire used to address QOL (the WHOQOL-100) in accordance with previously published guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref018">18</xref>]. Higher scores indicate greater QOL, with the exception of three questions used to assess a negative parameter.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>For continuous variables, the data are presented as mean ± standard deviation (SD). For categorical variables, the data are presented as frequencies and percentages, and data associated with non-normally distributed variables are presented as median values. Body mass index (BMI) was classified as overweight (25 &lt; BMI &lt;30), obese (BMI ≥ 30), or normal/underweight (BMI ≤ 24.9). Time to get to/from the university was classified as less than 30 minutes, &gt; 30 &lt; 60 minutes, &gt; 60 &lt; 120 minutes, &gt; 120 &lt; 180 minutes. We calculated Cronbach’s coefficient to determine the internal consistency reliability. We considered Cronbach alpha values over 0.70 as acceptable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref019">19</xref>]. To investigate a relationship between WHOQOL-BREF scores and sociodemographic factors, we compared QOL among the study participants using the Student’s t-test and one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). Multiple regression models were performed. Physical, Psychological, Social and Environmental domains were included as dependent variables. Age, gender, academic year, students’ hometown, BMI, parents background education, students’ prior degree, religion beliefs, smoking, time to get to/from university were analyzed as predictor variables. For each model, the standardized beta coefficient (β), p-value and the explained variance (R2) were calculated. A p-value &lt; 0.05 in the statistical analysis was considered significant. Statistical analyses were conducted using the SAS statistical software (version 9.3, SAS Institute, Cary, NC).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Socio-demographic characteristics of the study population</title>
<p>The study population comprised 405 medical students in their 1st through 12th semesters, representing 65.3% of the medical students at Universidade Nove de Julho. The study group included 177 (43.70%) males and 228 (56.30%) females. The mean age was 23.55 years (SD = 3.98, range: 18–40 years). There was no statistically significant difference in age between the male and female participants (p = 0.9379). An overview of sociodemographic characteristics of the study population is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180009.t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0180009.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Sociodemographic characteristics of the study population.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0180009.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Characteristics</th>
<th align="left">N (%)</th>
<th align="left">Mean</th>
<th align="left">SD<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">*</xref></th>
<th align="left">Minimum</th>
<th align="left">Maximum</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Age (years)</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>177 (43.70)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>23.57</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>4.13</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>18</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>40</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>228 (56.30)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>23.54</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>3.87</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>18</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>40</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>total</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>405 (100.00)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>23.55</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>3.98</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>18</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>40</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight (Kg)</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>177 (43.70)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>82.44</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>13.59</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>57</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>139</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>228 (56.30)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>60.76</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>11.22</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>43</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>115</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>total</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>405 (100.00)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>70.24</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>16.34</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>43</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>139</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Height (cm)</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>177 (43.70)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>177.90</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>5.87</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>162</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>197</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>228 (56.30)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>164.20</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>6.30</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>150</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>179</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>total</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>405 (100.00)</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>170.19</bold></td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>9.14</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>150</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>197</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>* SD: standard deviation</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Reliability</title>
<p>The Cronbach’s alpha coefficient of the complete WHOQOL-BREF questionnaire was 0.8998. The coefficients of the physical health, psychological health, social relations, and environmental domain were 0.7201, 0.7664, 0.7152, and 0.7415, respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>QOL according to academic year and gender</title>
<p>The number of years in medical school was not significantly associated with QOL (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180009.t002">Table 2</xref>). The highest mean WHOQOL-BREF QOL scores were observed in the social relations domain, whereas the lowest mean scores were observed in the environmental domain. Significantly higher mean scores for three out of the four domains evaluated were observed in males (physical health, p = 0.0035; psychological health, p = 0.0005; social relations, p = 0.0161). There was no significant difference between males and females with respect to the environmental domain of the questionnaire (p = 0.9832) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180009.t002">Table 2</xref>). After multiple separate regression analysis we also found that female gender was related to QOL in all domains, except for the environmental one. There was a moderate effect of gender in physical (<bold>β</bold> .20) and psychological (<bold>β</bold> .26) domains and a weak effect on social domain (<bold>β</bold> .15) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180009.t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0180009.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>QOL domain scores (mean and standard deviation) according to academic year and gender.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0180009.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Academic Year</th>
<th align="left">N (%)</th>
<th align="center">Physical Health (mean and standard deviation)</th>
<th align="center">Psychological Health (mean and standard deviation)</th>
<th align="center">Social Relations (mean and standard deviation)</th>
<th align="center">Environmental (mean and standard deviation)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>1st</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>86 (21.23)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>65.03±13.53</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>65.89±15.11</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>71.32±18.85</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>59.41±13.71</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>48 (55.81)</bold></td>
<td align="left">66.66<bold>±13.57</bold></td>
<td align="left">67.62<bold>±15.57</bold></td>
<td align="left">74.47<bold>±16.07</bold></td>
<td align="left">59.04<bold>±12.08</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>38 (44.19)</bold></td>
<td align="left">62.96<bold>±13.37</bold></td>
<td align="left">63.70<bold>±14.43</bold></td>
<td align="left">67.32<bold>±21.43</bold></td>
<td align="left">59.86<bold>±15.69</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>2nd</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>102 (25.19)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>61.97±15.33</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>64.82±14.00</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>70.42±20.63</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>57.01±14.95</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left">40 (39.22)</td>
<td align="left">64.37<bold>±14.98</bold></td>
<td align="left">67.81<bold>±12.62</bold></td>
<td align="left">72.70<bold>±17.29</bold></td>
<td align="left">55.00<bold>±14.37</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left">62 (60.78)</td>
<td align="left">60.42<bold>±15.47</bold></td>
<td align="left">62.90<bold>±14.60</bold></td>
<td align="left">68.95<bold>±22.54</bold></td>
<td align="left">58.31<bold>±15.28</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>3rd</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>97 (23.95)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>63.84±15.09</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>65.08±16.02</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>72.94±17.55</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>59.73±15.42</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left">38 (39.18)</td>
<td align="left">65.31<bold>±17.13</bold></td>
<td align="left">66.99<bold>±18.89</bold></td>
<td align="left">73.02<bold>±20.63</bold></td>
<td align="left">60.44<bold>±16.91</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left">59 (60.82)</td>
<td align="left">62.89<bold>±13.68</bold></td>
<td align="left">63.84<bold>±13.91</bold></td>
<td align="left">72.88<bold>±15.44</bold></td>
<td align="left">59.26<bold>±14.51</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>4th</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>59 (14.57)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>61.62±12.95</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>62.50±16.59</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>69.20±23.37</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>60.96±15.57</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left">27 (45.76)</td>
<td align="left">65.21<bold>±13.71</bold></td>
<td align="left">65.43<bold>±16.65</bold></td>
<td align="left">73.76<bold>±20.24</bold></td>
<td align="left">60.76<bold>±14.11</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left">32 (54.24)</td>
<td align="left">58.59<bold>±11.64</bold></td>
<td align="left">60.02<bold>±16.39</bold></td>
<td align="left">65.36<bold>±25.40</bold></td>
<td align="left">61.13<bold>±16.93</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>5th</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>35 (8.64)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>65.40±15.53</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>68.69±16.24</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>73.09±17.97</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>60.08±16.84</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left">14 (40.00)</td>
<td align="left">71.68<bold>±17.06</bold></td>
<td align="left">79.46<bold>±9.45</bold></td>
<td align="left">76.19<bold>±21.39</bold></td>
<td align="left">62.50<bold>±22.02</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left">21 (60.00)</td>
<td align="left">61.22<bold>±13.23</bold></td>
<td align="left">61.50<bold>±15.97</bold></td>
<td align="left">71.03<bold>±15.50</bold></td>
<td align="left">58.48<bold>±12.66</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>6th</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>26 (6.42)</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>67.54±17.09</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>64.90±15.68</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>65.71±19.76</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>56.85±16.97</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left">10 (38.46)</td>
<td align="left">67.50<bold>±19.00</bold></td>
<td align="left">67.08<bold>±17.50</bold></td>
<td align="left">71.66<bold>±10.54</bold></td>
<td align="left">59.37<bold>±13.50</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left">16 (61.54)</td>
<td align="left">67.41<bold>±16.43</bold></td>
<td align="left">63.54<bold>±14.86</bold></td>
<td align="left">61.97<bold>±23.36</bold></td>
<td align="left">55.27<bold>±19.08</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>TOTAL</bold></td>
<td align="left"><bold>405 (100.0)</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>male</bold></td>
<td align="left">177 (43.70)</td>
<td align="left">66.08±15.23</td>
<td align="left">68.10±15.81</td>
<td align="left">73.63±18.05</td>
<td align="left">58.98±15.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>female</bold></td>
<td align="left">228 (56.30)</td>
<td align="left">61.79±14.06</td>
<td align="left">62.79±14.70</td>
<td align="left">68.89±20.68</td>
<td align="left">59.01±15.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>p-test</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">0.0035</td>
<td align="left">0.0005</td>
<td align="left">0.0161</td>
<td align="left">0.9832</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>test used</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">t-student</td>
<td align="left">t-student</td>
<td align="left">t-student</td>
<td align="left">t-student</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0180009.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Associations between quality of life of medical students and predictor variables.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0180009.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Physical QoL</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Psychological QoL</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Social QoL</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Environmental</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">β <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></th>
<th align="left">p</th>
<th align="left">β</th>
<th align="left">p</th>
<th align="left">β</th>
<th align="left">p</th>
<th align="left">β</th>
<th align="left">p</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Academic year</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0522533</td>
<td align="char" char="."><bold>0.305</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0180772</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.716</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0148977</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.770</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0042333</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.932</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Gender</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.2024125</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.000</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.2598076</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.000</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.1474219</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.007</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0140499</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.792</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>At least one parent physician</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0070457</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.889</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.054317</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.271</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0475324</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.348</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.1752481</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Religion beliefs</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0683935</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.174</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.1489346</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.002</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0702851</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.162</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.1111119</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.025</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Time to get to /from</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0812605</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.151</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0418517</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.448</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.1227917</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.030</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.1883522</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Smoking</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0296317</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.553</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0245209</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.615</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.016941</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.735</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0040716</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.934</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Previous degree</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0093911</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.851</td>
<td align="char" char=".">.0355388</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.466</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0368284</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.462</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0755587</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.124</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Hometown</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0504292</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.374</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0680633</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.219</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0267316</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.638</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.1156196</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.038</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BMI</bold></td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.1118018</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.038</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.1872911</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.000</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0878492</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.103</td>
<td align="char" char=".">-.0610303</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.248</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>R2</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2">4.6%</td>
<td align="left" colspan="2">9.3%</td>
<td align="left" colspan="2">4.5%</td>
<td align="left" colspan="2">8.1%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>QOL = quality of life;</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p>*β = indicates standardized β coefficient</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>QOL according to sociodemographic factors</title>
<p>In this study, we evaluated the effect of sociodemographic factors on the QOL of medical students in Sao Paulo, Brazil. In this study, we found no statistical difference between students who had previously graduated compared with those who had not, or smokers compared with non-smokers. Nearly 67% of the study participants were from outside Sao Paulo. At first, we did not observe statistically significant differences in QOL scores in students living in Sao Paulo compared with students living outside of Sao Paulo, however we found a negative weak effect on the environmental domain (β -0.12) after multiple regression analysis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180009.t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<p>Higher mean psychological health scores were observed in students who held religious beliefs (p = 0.0068). In addition, participants with at least one parent who held a medical degree had higher mean scores in the environmental domain (p = 0.0004). A commute between home and university longer than two hours had a significant negative impact on the QOL with respect to the social relations and environmental domain (p = 0.0301 and p = 0.0299, respectively). Finally, a BMI ≥ 30 was associated with lower QOL scores in the psychological, social relations, and the physical health domain, but not in the environmental domain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180009.t004">Table 4</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0180009.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>QOL scores (mean and standard deviation) of medical students according to sociodemographic factors.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0180009.t004g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Academic Year</th>
<th align="left">N (%)</th>
<th align="justify">Physical Health (mean and standard deviation)</th>
<th align="justify">Psychological Health (mean and standard deviation)</th>
<th align="justify">Social Relations (mean and standard deviation)</th>
<th align="justify">Environmental (mean and standard deviation)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Hometown</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>São Paulo</bold></td>
<td align="left">134 (33.09)</td>
<td align="left">63.51±15.18</td>
<td align="left">65.60±16.75</td>
<td align="left">69.52±20.23</td>
<td align="left">59.30±16.35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>Other city</bold></td>
<td align="left">271 (66.91)</td>
<td align="left">63.74±14.51</td>
<td align="left">64.86±14.72</td>
<td align="left">71.67±19.42</td>
<td align="left">58.85±14.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Religious beliefs</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>Yes</bold></td>
<td align="left">315 (77.78)</td>
<td align="left">64.10±14.81</td>
<td align="left"><bold>66.21</bold>±14.75<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001">*</xref></td>
<td align="left">71.50±19.93</td>
<td align="left">59.76±14.62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>No</bold></td>
<td align="left">90 (22.22)</td>
<td align="left">62.14±14.39</td>
<td align="left"><bold>61.25</bold>±17.03</td>
<td align="left">69.07±20.91</td>
<td align="left">56.35±16.84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Previous Graduation</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>Yes</bold></td>
<td align="left">59 (14.57)</td>
<td align="left">63.74±15.83</td>
<td align="left">66.10±15.52</td>
<td align="left">68.50±19.39</td>
<td align="left">56.14±14.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>No</bold></td>
<td align="left">346 (85.43)</td>
<td align="left">63.65±14.55</td>
<td align="left">64.94±15.40</td>
<td align="left">71.39±19.74</td>
<td align="left">59.49±15.33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>At least one parent physician</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>Yes</bold></td>
<td align="left">88 (21.73)</td>
<td align="left">64.24±18.26</td>
<td align="left">67.23±16.42</td>
<td align="left">73.10±20.12</td>
<td align="left"><bold>64.02</bold>±16.87<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>No</bold></td>
<td align="left">317 (78.27)</td>
<td align="left">63.50±13.61</td>
<td align="left">64.52±15.08</td>
<td align="left">70.37±19.56</td>
<td align="left"><bold>57.61</bold>±14.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Time to get to/from university</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>&lt; 30 min</bold></td>
<td align="left">225 (55.56)</td>
<td align="left">63.89±14.18</td>
<td align="left">64.98±14.94</td>
<td align="left"><bold>73.07</bold>±18.90<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="left"><bold>60.72 (13.86)</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn004">****</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>30–60 min</bold></td>
<td align="left">83 (20.49)</td>
<td align="left">65.36±14.80</td>
<td align="left">65.76±14.48</td>
<td align="left"><bold>68.57</bold>±20.59</td>
<td align="left"><bold>58.62</bold>±17.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>60–120 min</bold></td>
<td align="left">56 (13.83)</td>
<td align="left">63.84±15.77</td>
<td align="left">68.38±15.38</td>
<td align="left"><bold>71.13</bold>±19.20</td>
<td align="left"><bold>56.14</bold>±13.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>120–180 min</bold></td>
<td align="left">41 (10.12)</td>
<td align="left">59.80±15.59</td>
<td align="left">60.06±18.73</td>
<td align="left"><bold>64.02</bold>±21.36</td>
<td align="left"><bold>54.27</bold>±18.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Smoking</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>Yes</bold></td>
<td align="left">47 (11.60)</td>
<td align="left">62.53±13.04</td>
<td align="left">63.65±14.53</td>
<td align="left">71.27±20.61</td>
<td align="left">57.51±14.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>No</bold></td>
<td align="left">358 (88.40)</td>
<td align="left">63.81±14.94</td>
<td align="left">65.30±15.52</td>
<td align="left">70.92±19.60</td>
<td align="left">59.20±15.27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BMI</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>18.5–24.9</bold></td>
<td align="left">273 (67.41)</td>
<td align="left"><bold>63.30</bold>±14.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn005"><sup>#</sup></xref></td>
<td align="left"><bold>65.64</bold>±14.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn006"><sup>##</sup></xref></td>
<td align="left"><bold>74.00</bold>±20.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn007"><sup>###</sup></xref></td>
<td align="left">59.39±15.35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>25–29.9</bold></td>
<td align="left">93 (22.96)</td>
<td align="left"><bold>67.97</bold>±14.32</td>
<td align="left"><bold>66.80</bold>±15.52</td>
<td align="left"><bold>73.66</bold>±18.07</td>
<td align="left">60.18±13.78</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"> <bold>≥30</bold></td>
<td align="left">39 (9.63)</td>
<td align="left"><bold>55.95</bold>±14.98</td>
<td align="left"><bold>57.37</bold>±17.74</td>
<td align="left"><bold>64.32</bold>±19.30</td>
<td align="left">53.53±16.46</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p>*p = 0.0068 (t-test),</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p>**p = 0.0004 (t-test),</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn003"><p>***p = 0.0301 (one-way ANOVA),</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn004"><p>****p = 0.0299 (one-way ANOVA),</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn005"><p><sup>#</sup>p = 0.0001 (ANOVA),</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn006"><p><sup>##</sup>p = 0.0034 (ANOVA),</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn007"><p><sup>###</sup>p = 0.0451 (ANOVA)</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Separate multiple linear regression analyses were performed to identify predictors variables for the physical, psychological, social and environmental QOL, as measured by the WHOQOL-BREF (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180009.t003">Table 3</xref>). In our study, although less than 10% of the variance in all domains evaluated was explained, we found some significant statistical p-value in the models. We found that two variables, gender (<bold>β</bold> .20) and BMI (<bold>β</bold> -.11) are the strongest predictors in the physical domain. For the psychological domain, gender (β 0.26) and BMI (β -.19) were the strongest predictors. Time spent to /from the university was negative associated to the social domain (β -.12). The strongest predictors in the environmental domain were time spent to /from the university (β -.19) and students parent with a medical degree (β.17).</p>
<p>Student´s parent with medical doctor degree was perceived as a positive predictor of QOL in the environmental domain. This result can be partially, explained by the fact that parents with a medical degree could influence their offspring for a better understanding of the medical school environment.</p>
<p>Religion beliefs were positive related to psychological and environmental domains, while time to get to to/from the university was identified as negative related to psychological and environmental domains. Students hometown out of São Paulo, where the medical school campus is located, was negative associated with environmental domain of QOL as well. Finally, BMI was negative related to QOL in physical and psychological domains.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This study was conducted to identify sociodemographic factors that potentially influence the QOL of medical students attending a private medical school in Sao Paulo, Brazil. Consistent with our initial hypothesis, we found that a normal BMI and religious beliefs were associated with greater QOL in medical students. In addition, we observed lower scores in the physical, social, and psychological domains of the QOL questionnaire in female students compared with male students.</p>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Obesity</title>
<p>The negative impact of obesity on the QOL in the general population has previously been described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref020">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref022">22</xref>]. The increasing prevalence of obesity worldwide is attributed to lifestyle changes, and this phenomenon is associated with an increased incidence of chronic diseases and mental disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref020">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref021">21</xref>]. The WHO estimated that approximately 13% of the world´s adult population were obese and 39% were overweight in 2013. If current trends continue, approximately 57.8% of the adult population will be classified as overweight/obese by 2030 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref023">23</xref>]. Malta <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref024">24</xref>] reported that an alarming 51.0% of Brazilian adults were overweight and 17.4% were obese in 2012, with an annual increase in these rates of 1.37% and 0.89%, respectively.</p>
<p>The proportion of medical students that are overweight ranges from 19.7% in American freshmen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref025">25</xref>] to 39.3% in Greek students [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref026">26</xref>]. Obesity was reported in 4.8% of American medical students [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref025">25</xref>] and in 10.2% of Pakistani medical students [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref027">27</xref>]. Furthermore, one study reported that the rates of obesity/overweight increased from 24.9% in the first year of medical school to 37.1% in the last year (p &lt; 0.005) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref028">28</xref>].</p>
<p>In this study, the rates of overweight (23.0%) and obesity (9.6%) were consistent with previous reports. Although a previous study evaluating Brazilian medical students attending a private university observed lower rates of obesity and overweight (1.4% and 16.4%, respectively), the study was conducted in 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref029">29</xref>].</p>
<p>Due to its reported impact on the QOL in the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref020">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref022">22</xref>], we analyzed the potential influence of obesity in the QOL of medical students. Our findings confirmed our hypothesis that obese medical students have a lower QOL compared with nonobese students. Lower QOL scores were observed in obese students with respect to two of the four domains evaluated (physical and psychological).</p>
<p>These results may reflect, in part, the discrimination, lack of acceptance, or social stigma associated with overweight and obese individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref030">30</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Religious beliefs</title>
<p>Religious beliefs and spirituality are reported in nearly 90% of the population worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref031">31</xref>]. The impact of spirituality and religious beliefs on the QOL, especially with respect to mental health, have been previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref032">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref033">33</xref>]. Several studies concluded that religious beliefs reduce the incidence of anxiety, depression, drug addiction, and suicide attempts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref031">31</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref033">33</xref>]. Religious beliefs are also associated with attitudes toward clinical interactions, assisted reproductive technologies, life and death concepts, and legalized abortion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref034">34</xref>].</p>
<p>A large cross-cultural study described the positive effect of spirituality, religion, and personal beliefs on components of the QOL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref032">32</xref>]. The authors observed the strongest correlations with the psychological and social domains.</p>
<p>Although physicians need to deal with patient expectations and personal beliefs, there is a scarcity of data on the religious beliefs of physicians. Recently, Kim and Roth reported that the incidence of depression was greater in Korean medical students without religious beliefs compared with religious students [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref035">35</xref>].</p>
<p>A large Brazilian study reported that 33.9% of medical students did not report a religious affiliation and that religious beliefs influence opinions on controversial medical ethics issues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref036">36</xref>]. A study of 275 medical students in New Zealand found that 42.5% of the study participants had no religion affiliation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref037">37</xref>].</p>
<p>Compared with previous studies, we observed a lower percentage of medical students with no religious beliefs (22.2%). This difference might reflect the study population, as the research conducted by Lucchetti <italic>et al</italic>. included public, private, rural, and cosmopolitan universities, thereby representing the heterogeneity of the Brazilian society [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref036">36</xref>].</p>
<p>In the present study, we identified an association between religious beliefs and improved QOL with respect to psychological health (β .15; p = 0.002) and to environmental domain (β .11; p = 0.0025). By contrast, Henning <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref037">37</xref>] did not observe a similar effect in medical students in New Zealand.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020">
<title>The effect of academic year on the QOL</title>
<p>Several publications have already reported the effect of academic year on the QOL in medical students [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref038">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref040">40</xref>]. In this study, we did not observe any effect of academic year on the QOL. This finding might be partially explained by the fact that Universidade Nove de Julho subscribes to the philosophy of empowerment education, as first described by Paulo Freire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref041">41</xref>]. Freire proposes that empowerment education promotes health in all aspects of life. His model suggests that active participation in group activities and dialogue enhances the ability to change the education process and to change one’s life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref041">41</xref>]. Students have free access to professors, coordinators, and the dean of the School of Medicine. In addition, the university makes efforts to periodically engage students in an open dialogue during regularly scheduled meetings. In these meetings, the students provide their own insights into approaches that might improve the quality of their medical education and their communication skills.</p>
<p>Zhang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref006">6</xref>] reported significant differences in the QOL according to academic year, particularly with respect to the psychological and physical domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref004">4</xref>]. Domantay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref002">2</xref>] described an association of some academic years with lower QOL in medical students. He attributed this effect to the specific challenges that arise during different academic years, such as adaptation during the first year and clinical clerkships during later years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref002">2</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>Gender effect</title>
<p>In previous centuries, medical students were predominantly male. In 2006, the WHO reported that the number of females attending medical school was increasing worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref042">42</xref>]. In the United States (US), women account for 47% of medical students; however, only 21% of full-time professors are women, indicating that this is still a relatively new trend [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref043">43</xref>]. Nevertheless, in some countries, including Great Britain, China, and Brazil, women have been outnumbering men in medical sciences in recent years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref044">44</xref>,, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref045">45</xref>]. This is a relatively new global phenomenon, and, although it has been gaining attention, the consequences of this shift remain unclear.</p>
<p>In 2012, a study of 150 Pakistani medical students reported that females had higher levels of anxiety. The authors attributed this observation to greater emotional vulnerability in female students, due in part to a patriarchal society that discourages women from pursuing higher education [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref046">46</xref>]. However, this explanation might not be relevant to the results described in our study as the Brazilian society is more liberal, and it promotes equal opportunities for men and women.</p>
<p>A systematic review of 40 studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref047">47</xref>] revealed that female medical students in the US and Canada experienced more personal distress. However, it was unclear if this finding was directly associated with medical education, and the authors emphasized that their results required further investigation.</p>
<p>Another recent systemic review reported that females are more prone to develop anxiety before or after academic assessments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref014">14</xref>]. However, this type of stress/anxiety cannot explain our results, as we avoided collecting data around the time of academic assessments.</p>
<p>Paro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref048">48</xref>] and Domantay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref002">2</xref>] also reported lower QOL scores for female medical students [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref002">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref003">3</xref>]. Furthermore, several authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref006">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0180009.ref049">49</xref>] reported lower QOL with respect to psychological and physical domains of the WHOQOL-BREF questionnaire in female medical students.</p>
<p>In our study, we observed lower QOL scores in the psychological, physical, and social relation domains in female medical students. These findings are consistent with a culture that encourages men to appear less emotional and to hide their feelings and weaknesses. However, additional research is required to address this hypothesis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec022">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Several limitations to our study must be noted. The results are limited to a single medical school in a developing country in one of the largest cities in the world. Consequently, external factors that might affect the QOL of the general population, such as heavy traffic and a high rate of violence, might also influence the participants of this study. Despite these limitations, the compelling data observed in this study might provide a basis for research in other localities.</p>
<p>In addition, strategies to help overcome the challenges associated with poor QOL identified in this study can be implemented. For example, promoting social activities and providing tutoring services might help overcome the observed differences between males and females. In addition, making healthy foods available and providing health services might reduce obesity rates.</p>
<p>The stress associated with a long commute between home and university might be alleviated by creating a department that helps students living in areas outside Sao Paulo find housing closer to the university.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec023">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This study has provided a deeper understanding of the effects of sociodemographic factors, physical traits, and religious beliefs on the QOL in medical students. These findings might inform strategies to improve physical, psychological, and social support for medical students at a critical stage in their training, thereby providing tools to a better adjustment to medical schools.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec024">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0180009.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 File</label>
<caption>
<title>The all quality of life of medical students results.</title>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0180009.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 File</label>
<caption>
<title>History of anxiety, panic attacks or depression and analysis of the impact on quality of life in medical students.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0180009.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0180009.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 File</label>
<caption>
<title>Impact of physical activity practice on quality of life of medical students, Nove de Julho University (Uninove).</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruess</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruess</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boudreau</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snell</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinert</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reframing medical education to support professional identity formation</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1446</fpage>–<lpage>1451</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1097/ACM.0000000000000427" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/ACM.0000000000000427</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25054423</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domantay</surname> <given-names>JAA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health-related quality of life of future physicians at a medical school in the Philippines: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>SAGE Open</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1177/2158244014545459" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/2158244014545459</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyrbye</surname> <given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Satele</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boone</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sloan</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Burnout among U.S. Medical students, residents, and early career physicians relative to the general U.S. Population</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1097/ACM.0000000000000134" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/ACM.0000000000000134</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24448053</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paro</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de C Bittencourt</surname> <given-names>ZZL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Qualidade de vida de graduandos da área da saúde</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Educ Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1590/s0100-55022013000300009" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/s0100-55022013000300009</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lun</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Quality of life of medical students in china: A study using the WHOQOL-BREF</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e49714</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0049714" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0049714</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23209595</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyrbye</surname> <given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Power</surname> <given-names>DV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durning</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moutier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Massie</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Burnout and serious thoughts of dropping out of medical school: A multi-institutional study</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1097/ACM.0b013e3181c46aad" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/ACM.0b013e3181c46aad</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20042833</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shareef</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Amodi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Khateeb</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abudan</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alkhani</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zebian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The interplay between academic performance and quality of life among preclinical students</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Educ</source>. 2015 <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tempski</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname> <given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enns</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perotta</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paro</surname> <given-names>HBMS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Relationship among medical student resilience, educational environment and quality of life</article-title>. <source>PLOS One</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e0131535</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0131535" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0131535</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26121357</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalali-Farahani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amiri</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname> <given-names>YS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Are physical activity, sedentary behaviors and sleep duration associated with body mass index-for-age and health-related quality of life among high school boys and girls?</article-title> <source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12955-016-0434-6" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/s12955-016-0434-6</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26921272</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names> <suffix>Jr</suffix></name>. <source>Revisiting the medical school educational mission at a time of expansion</source>. <collab>Josiah Macy Jr Foundation.</collab>, <publisher-loc>Charleston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Josiah Macy Jr Foundation</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krägeloh</surname> <given-names>CU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henning</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Billington</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawken</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The relationship between quality of life and spirituality, religiousness, and personal beliefs of medical students</article-title>. <source>Acad Psychiatry</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40596-014-0158-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s40596-014-0158-z</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25034953</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development of the World Health Organisation WHOQOL-BREF quality of life assessment. The WHOQOL Group</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9626712</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skevington</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lotfy</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Connell</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The world health organization’s WHOQOL-BREF quality of life assessment: psychometric properties and results of the international field trial. A report from the WHOQOL group</article-title>. <source>Qual Life Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1023/B:QURE.0000018486.91360.00" xlink:type="simple">10.1023/B:QURE.0000018486.91360.00</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15085902</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyndon</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strom</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alyami</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname> <given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The relationship between academic assessment and psychological distress among medical students: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Perspect Med Educ</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>418</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40037-014-0148-6" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s40037-014-0148-6</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25428333</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamali</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tofangchiha</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jamali</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nedjat</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narimani</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Medical students’ health-related quality of life: Roles of social and behavioural factors</article-title>. <source>Med Educ</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1001</fpage>–<lpage>1012</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/medu.12247" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/medu.12247</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24016170</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleck</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Louzada</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chachamovich</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Aplicação da versão em português do instrumento abreviado de avaliação da qualidade de vida “WHOQOL-bref”</article-title>. <source>Rev Saude Publica</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1590/s0034-89102000000200012" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/s0034-89102000000200012</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10881154</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleck</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chachamovich</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trentini</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development and validation of the Portuguese version of the WHOQOL-OLD module</article-title>. <source>Rev Saude Publica</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1590/s0034-89102006000600007" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/s0034-89102006000600007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17301899</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><article-title>The World Health Organization Quality of Life assessment (WHOQOL): position paper from the World Health Organization</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1403</fpage>–<lpage>1409</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8560308</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Portney</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></name>. <source><italic>Foundations of clinical research</italic>: <italic>applications to practice</italic></source>.<edition>3d</edition>. <publisher-loc>Upper Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>. p. <fpage>607</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>VH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forhan</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vigod</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of obesity on quality of life</article-title>. <source>Best Pract Res Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.beem.2013.04.004" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.beem.2013.04.004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23731876</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lubetkin</surname> <given-names>EI</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of obesity on health-related quality-of-life in the general adult US population</article-title>. <source>J Pub Health</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>164</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/pubmed/fdi025" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/pubmed/fdi025</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15820993</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ul-Haq</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackay</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fenwick</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pell</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Association between body mass index and mental health among Scottish adult population: a cross-sectional study of 37272 participants</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>2231</fpage>–<lpage>2240</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291713002833" xlink:type="simple">10.1017/S0033291713002833</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24274839</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">WHO. Obesity and overweight. World Health Organization. 2016. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs311/en/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs311/en/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malta</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Claro</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernal</surname> <given-names>RTI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trends in prevalence of overweight and obesity in adults in 26 Brazilian state capitals and the federal district from 2006 to 2012</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Epidemiol</source>.<year>2014</year>;<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1590/1809-4503201400050021" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/1809-4503201400050021</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phelan</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puhl</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dyrbye</surname> <given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dovidio</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeazel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The adverse effect of weight stigma on the well-being of medical students with overweight or obesity: Findings from a national survey</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1251</fpage>–<lpage>1258</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11606-015-3266-x" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11606-015-3266-x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26173517</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertsias</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mammas</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linardakis</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kafatos</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Overweight and obesity in relation to cardiovascular disease risk factors among medical students in Crete, Greece</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2458-3-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1471-2458-3-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12517305</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Assir</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shafiq</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jabeen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>High prevalence of preobesity and obesity among medical students of Lahore and its relation with dietary habits and physical activity</article-title>. <source>Indian J Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>206</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4103/2230-8210.176357" xlink:type="simple">10.4103/2230-8210.176357</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27042417</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavalle</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villarreal</surname> <given-names>JZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montes</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mancillas</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Change in the prevalence of metabolic syndrome in a population of medical students: 6-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>J Diabetes Metab Disord</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>14</volume>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s40200-015-0216-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/s40200-015-0216-4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26613078</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandão</surname> <given-names>CDG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neto</surname> <given-names>ANF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardo</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nascif</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Obesity and related risk factors in students of a private university in Vitoria-ES. Obesidade e fatores de risco em alunos de Medicina de uma faculdade privada de Vitória-ES</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Med</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>. [Portuguese].</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puhl</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brownell</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bias, discrimination, and obesity</article-title>. <source>Obes Res</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>788</fpage>–<lpage>805</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/oby.2001.108" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/oby.2001.108</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11743063</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koenig</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Research on religion, spirituality, and mental health: a review</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19497160</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonelli</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koenig</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mental disorders, religion and spirituality 1990 to 2010: A systematic evidence-based review</article-title>. <source>J Relig Health</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>673</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-013-9691-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10943-013-9691-4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23420279</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab>WHOQoL SRPB Group</collab>. <article-title>A cross-cultural study of spirituality, religion, and personal beliefs as components of quality of life</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1486</fpage>–<lpage>1497</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2005.08.001" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.socscimed.2005.08.001</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16168541</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curlin</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sellergren</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roach</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lantos</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The association of physicians Religious characteristics with their attitudes and self-reported behaviors regarding religion and spirituality in the clinical encounter</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>446</fpage>–<lpage>453</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16641663</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roh</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Depressive symptoms in medical students: prevalence and related factors</article-title>. <source>Korean J Med Educ</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3946/kjme.2014.26.1.53" xlink:type="simple">10.3946/kjme.2014.26.1.53</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25805080</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucchetti</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lucchetti</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Medical students and controversial ethical issues: Results from the multicenter study SBRAME</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Ethics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6939-15-85" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1472-6939-15-85</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25511565</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henning</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krägeloh</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sisley</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawken</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Religious affiliation, quality of life and academic performance: New Zealand medical students</article-title>. <source>J Relig Health</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-013-9769-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10943-013-9769-z</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24005316</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leahy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newbury</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tonkin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbull</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Distress levels and self-reported treatment rates for medicine, law, psychology and mechanical engineering tertiary students: cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Aust NZ J Psychiatr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>608</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjeldstadli</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyssen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finset</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hem</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gude</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gronvold</surname> <given-names>NT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Life satisfaction and resilience in medical school—a six-year longitudinal, nationwide and comparative study</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Educ</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>48</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6920-6-48" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1472-6920-6-48</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16984638</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlin</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Runeson</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Burnout and psychiatric morbidity among medical students entering clinical training: a three year prospective questionnaire and interview-based study</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Educ</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6920-7-6" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1472-6920-7-6</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17430583</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallerstein</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Empowerment education: Freire’s ideas adapted to health education</article-title>. <source>Health Educ Q</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1177/109019818801500402" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/109019818801500402</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3230016</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization. World health organization. 2006. Statistics—group on women in medicine and science (GWIMS)—member center 1995.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">The State of Women in Academic Medicine: The Pipeline and Pathways to Leadership, 2013–2014. March 2015. American Association of Medical Colleges. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.aamc.org/members/gwims/statistics/" xlink:type="simple">https://www.aamc.org/members/gwims/statistics/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jefferson</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloor</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Women in medicine: Historical perspectives and recent trends</article-title>. <source>Br Med Bull</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>114</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bmb/ldv007" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bmb/ldv007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25755293</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">DEMOGRAFIA MÉDICA NO BRASIL Dados gerais e descrições de desigualdades. 2012. Demografia Medica No Brasil. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cremesp.org.br/pdfs/demografia_2_dezembro.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cremesp.org.br/pdfs/demografia_2_dezembro.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farooqi</surname> <given-names>YN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghani</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spielberger</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Gender differences in test anxiety and academic performance of medical students</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychology Behavioral Sci</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5923/j.ijpbs.20120202.06" xlink:type="simple">10.5923/j.ijpbs.20120202.06</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyrbye</surname> <given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shanafelt</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Systematic review of depression, anxiety, and other indicators of psychological distress among U.S. And Canadian medical students</article-title>. <source>Acad Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paro</surname> <given-names>HBMS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname> <given-names>NMO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname> <given-names>CHM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rezende</surname> <given-names>CHA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname> <given-names>RMC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Health-related quality of life of medical students</article-title>. <source>Med Educ</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2923.2009.03587.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-2923.2009.03587.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20444053</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0180009.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chazan</surname> <given-names>ACS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Portugal</surname> <given-names>FB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Qualidade de vida de estudantes de medicina da UERJ por meio do Whoqol-bref: Uma abordagem multivariada</article-title>. <source>Ciênc saúde coletiva</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1590/1413-81232015202.05182014" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/1413-81232015202.05182014</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25715148</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>