<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0150736</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-43863</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Labor economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Salaries</subject><subj-group><subject>Minimum wage</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Adults</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Socioeconomic aspects of health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and occupational health</subject><subj-group><subject>Socioeconomic aspects of health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and occupational health</subject><subj-group><subject>Global health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Professions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropometry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropometry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Minimum Wage and Overweight and Obesity in Adult Women: A Multilevel Analysis of Low and Middle Income Countries</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Minimum Wage and Obesity in Women</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Conklin</surname>
<given-names>Annalijn I.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Ponce</surname>
<given-names>Ninez A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Frank</surname>
<given-names>John</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Nandi</surname>
<given-names>Arijit</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Heymann</surname>
<given-names>Jody</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>WORLD Policy Analysis Center, UCLA Fielding School of Public Health, University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Health Policy and Management, UCLA Fielding School of Public Health, University of California Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Scottish Collaboration for Public Health Research &amp; Policy, The University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, Scotland, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff004"><label>4</label> <addr-line>Institute for Health and Social Policy and Department of Epidemiology, Biostatistics, and Occupational Health, McGill University, Montreal, Québec, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Schooling</surname>
<given-names>C. Mary</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Hunter College, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AIC. Performed the experiments: AIC. Analyzed the data: AIC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AN JH. Wrote the paper: AIC NAP JF AN JH. NAP JF AN.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">aconklin@ph.ucla.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>10</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<elocation-id>e0150736</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>7</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>17</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Conklin et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Objectives</title>
<p>To describe the relationship between minimum wage and overweight and obesity across countries at different levels of development.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>A cross-sectional analysis of 27 countries with data on the legislated minimum wage level linked to socio-demographic and anthropometry data of non-pregnant 190,892 adult women (24–49 y) from the Demographic and Health Survey. We used multilevel logistic regression models to condition on country- and individual-level potential confounders, and post-estimation of average marginal effects to calculate the adjusted prevalence difference.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>We found the association between minimum wage and overweight/obesity was independent of individual-level SES and confounders, and showed a reversed pattern by country development stage. The adjusted overweight/obesity prevalence difference in low-income countries was an average increase of about 0.1 percentage points (PD 0.075 [0.065, 0.084]), and an average decrease of 0.01 percentage points in middle-income countries (PD -0.014 [-0.019, -0.009]). The adjusted obesity prevalence difference in low-income countries was an average increase of 0.03 percentage points (PD 0.032 [0.021, 0.042]) and an average decrease of 0.03 percentage points in middle-income countries (PD -0.032 [-0.036, -0.027]).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This is among the first studies to examine the potential impact of improved wages on an important precursor of non-communicable diseases globally. Among countries with a modest level of economic development, higher minimum wage was associated with lower levels of obesity.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by the Canadian Institute for Health Research Postdoctoral Fellowship Award (MFE-135520); the Canadian Institutes of Health Research Operating Grant, “Examining the impact of social policies on health equity” (ROH-115209); and the WORLD Policy Analysis Center of UCLA. No sponsors participated in the study design, data analysis or interpretation of results.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="2"/>
<table-count count="2"/>
<page-count count="14"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>The data are owned by third party, and can be obtained by request from The Measure DHS and MACHEquity websites [URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dhsprogram.com/data/available-datasets.cfm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.dhsprogram.com/data/available-datasets.cfm</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://machequity.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://machequity.com/</ext-link>].</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<boxed-text id="pone.0150736.box001" position="float">
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Research Highlights</title>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Many economic factors are known to influence overweight and obesity, yet evidence on policy-related determinants is scant.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>We examined national minimum wage levels and measured overweight/obesity using multilevel models for 27 developing countries.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>We found a weak but significant lower probability of being overweight or obese associated with higher levels of minimum wage in more developed countries, and a small increase in prevalence in the least developed countries.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Results suggested a potential societal effect of minimum wage on overweight and obesity that should be examined longitudinally to determine its potential as a structural intervention.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</boxed-text>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Overweight and obesity pose one of the biggest public health challenges for high, middle and low income countries. The concern for prevention is several-fold. Obesity creates a large disease burden of multiple chronic conditions, affecting the longevity and quality of life of individuals and imposing substantial cost to healthcare systems and wider society;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref001">1</xref>] and, levels of obesity have doubled in many countries worldwide in the past two decades, including in low and middle-income countries which have fewer resources to prevent and address the burden.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref002">2</xref>]</p>
<p>A key issue is the systematic disparities in obesity across countries and across groups within countries.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref002">2</xref>] While high-income countries show a robust negative gradient by individual-level socioeconomic status (SES) and financial hardships in obesity and weight gain,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref003">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref005">5</xref>] the association between SES and BMI or overweight is positive in most developing countries.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref005">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref007">7</xref>] Some of the literature suggests that the social patterning of BMI in developing countries reverses with greater national wealth.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref009">9</xref>] In addition, ecological studies show that national economic context (e.g. per capita GDP and globalisation) is also associated with BMI in developing countries, and again the patterns may differ by development stage.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref010">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref011">11</xref>] Globally, the economic determinants of obesity appear stronger and more consistent in women, and gender differences are exacerbated in developing countries.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref012">12</xref>]</p>
<p>For governments to succeed in strategies directed at wider socio-economic determinants of obesity, we must understand whether different types of environments, including policies, are associated with differences in weight status, and whether national-level determinants are independent of individual-level drivers. While there is consensus on economic resources constituting a critical determinant of disparities in overweight and obesity, evidence is lacking on the role of economic-related policies.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref013">13</xref>] As one of many ways to ensure a supportive environment, particular interest lies in the role of policies that can be expected to influence a person’s experience of economic (in)security which is associated with obesity.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref014">14</xref>] Minimum wage is a policy lever that is associated with body weight and health outcomes in the US context,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref015">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref016">16</xref>] and could have a profound effect on the lives and health of people living on low wages particularly women who are disproportionately affected by low-wage employment globally.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref017">17</xref>] However, its role may be limited for two reasons: first, large proportions of women work in the informal economy typically without minimum wage protection (e.g. 60–80% in sub-Saharan Africa and 30–60% in Latin America);[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref018">18</xref>] and second, diffusion of cultural ideas and lifestyles has shaped dietary convergence and the desirability of obesogenic fast foods.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref019">19</xref>]</p>
<p>By providing a secure income floor, the economic security theory of obesity postulates that minimum wage could affect women’s BMI through lowering physiological stress, which is one of four biological factors linking economic disadvantage to obesity.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref020">20</xref>] Multiple simultaneous pathways are possible, and minimum wage could also affect obesity through increasing material resources needed to obtain more calories (in low-income countries) and better quality food (in higher-income countries). While higher minimum wage might help create a more economically secure context in all settings, it could have a different instrumental effect depending on country development and norms. In the poorest countries higher minimum wage could increase women’s ability to consume more calories while in middle-income countries it could increase women’s access to more nutrient-dense foods. However, the impact of minimum wage on food purchasing may be moderated by cultural norms regarding healthy weights that vary across the development spectrum,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref012">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref021">21</xref>] and by global marketing of fast food that alters perceptions of food quality and prestige value.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref019">19</xref>] Using a novel database on nationally legislated minimum wage linked to existing anthropometric data from adult women, we assessed whether minimum wage is indeed related to overweight or obesity prevalence separate from individual-level SES, and whether the direction of association after adjustment for SES differs by country development stage.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Data sources and study sample</title>
<p>We linked national minimum wage data to individual anthropometry and socio-demographics. Data on minimum wage levels came from the minimum wage database developed by McGill University’s Maternal and Child Health Equity (MACHEquity) research program, in collaboration with UCLA’s World Policy Analysis Center. It includes year-specific data on legally mandated minimum wage applying to private sector workers or, if sector-/occupation-specific, to either manufacturing sector or unskilled workers. It was constructed primarily from the ILO Global Wage database for countries with DHS and other international household survey data, and supplemented using additional sources on labor and/or wage legislation. These included: US State Department’s Human Rights Reports; NATLEX and ILO TRAVAIL database of legal documents and memoranda; country-specific government websites; and, in a limited number of cases, reports of business and labor organizations. Other country-level statistics came from the World Bank (World Development Indicators), UNICEF (under-five mortality rates), and Heritage Foundation (Economic Freedom Index) databases. Minimum wage values and country statistics were for the index year when DHS surveys were fielded in a given country.</p>
<p>Individual-level anthropometric and control variables came from the Demographic and Health Survey (DHS) of young and adult women across 34 countries who were interviewed during the period 2004–2006. We chose a recent time period that had more global economic stability than after the financial crisis. The DHS uses a multistage probabilistic sampling process to collect nationally-representative health and wellbeing data (using trained interviewers) for women and their children at regular intervals since 1984 in over a hundred countries, as detailed elsewhere.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref022">22</xref>] A total of 462,789 young and adult women (13–49 y) self-reported socio-demographic information and 371,991 were measured objectively for BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>). We excluded 163,321 young females (between 13 and 24 years of age), as we were interested in studying adult women of working age with completed education and physiological development. We also excluded 6% of the remaining adult women who reported being pregnant (n = 17,449), leaving 229,066 non-pregnant adult women with anthropometry data.</p>
<p>Of the 34 countries with DHS survey data, there were 27 countries with information on minimum wage (per month, PPP International $) and measured anthropometry in non-pregnant women aged 24–49 years (n = 190,892). We dichotomized BMI (0 = 18.5–24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; 1 = 25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and above) to identify women who were overweight (pre-obese) or obese since both are strong risk factors of type 2 diabetes and other serious chronic conditions; we also examined obesity only as an outcome (0 = 18.5–29.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; 1 = 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup> and above). Characteristics of the sample are summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0150736.s003">S1 Table</xref> available online.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>A prescribed informed consent statement is read to DHS respondents by the trained interviewer who records whether or not the respondent consented in the questionnaire and then signs to attest that s/he read the consent statement to the respondent. DHS maintains strict standards for protecting privacy and confidentiality of respondents, and procedures were reviewed and approved by the ICF International Institutional Review Board to ensure compliance with the US Department of Health and Human Services regulation for the protection of human subjects (45 CFR 46).[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref023">23</xref>]</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Statistical methods</title>
<p>Descriptive statistics characterized overweight and obesity, minimum wage and key covariates for all countries and for each country income group. We used pairwise correlation coefficients between minimum wage and country covariates and quantified the variance inflation factor (VIF); minimum wage was strongly correlated with logged GDP (r = 0.715), but no multicollinearity problems were detected (VIF&lt;5 for all independent variables). We calculated the variance partition coefficient to measure the proportion of the total variance due to differences between countries (VPC = level 2 residual variance/level 1 residual variance + level 2 residual variance; where level 1 residual variance is 3.29 for a logit model).</p>
<p>Existing literature informed the selection of economic development factors that could influence levels of minimum wage and distributions of weight. Differences in national (or state) income level are associated with many health outcomes including BMI,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref024">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref026">26</xref>] and countries with higher incomes are likely to set more adequate minimum wage levels. At a given income level, countries also vary widely on public expenditures on health and higher spending is associated with better outcomes.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref027">27</xref>] Importantly, less egalitarian (politically polarized) countries invest fewer public resources to create a health infrastructure and so individuals pay large amounts out-of-pocket,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref026">26</xref>] whereas more egalitarian countries provide a greater degree of financial protection for the population against major health costs and so the public share of total health expenditures is greater. Countries’ political behaviors towards social protections could also influence policy-making on minimum wage. In addition, the level of regulatory constraint on commerce may separately influence the degree of economic (in)security provided by minimum wage. Importantly, the form of market governance matters for social inequalities in obesity,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref028">28</xref>] with more market-liberal regulatory structures being associated with greater mean body weight than a more collectivist approach among high-income countries[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref024">24</xref>] but potentially less individual overweight in developing counties.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref010">10</xref>]</p>
<p>We assessed the cross-sectional association of monthly minimum wage levels (main exposure) with the likelihood of being overweight/obese (main outcome) using multivariable logistic regression with two-level random intercept models (STATA ‘melogit’). Multilevel statistical techniques provide a technically robust framework to account for the hierarchical structure of the data (individuals nested within countries), and are pertinent when predictor variables are measured simultaneously at different levels. We first examined the association of minimum wage with overweight/obesity across all 27 countries and stratified by country income group, with mutual adjustment for all covariates and conventional SES indicators. Thus the remaining odds ratios for overweight/obese (or for obesity only) were interpreted as independent associations of minimum wage. In addition, we used regression coefficients for post-estimation calculation of adjusted prevalence difference for a 1-unit change in minimum wage (STATA ‘margins, dydx($exposure) over(lmic)’). For this, we used the pooled data in multilevel models specified with an interaction term between country minimum wage and income group variables in order to have adequate sample size to provide a meaningful analysis of the average marginal effects of the independent association. Final sample sizes varied (range: 58,930–162,446).</p>
<p>Models controlled for interview year and individual-level socio-demographics known to be associated with weight status and/or economic determinants. These included: age (years); marital status (being currently/previously married; single); parity (having no children; 1–2 children; 3–5 children; 6 or more children (reference)); and tobacco consumption (non-user; user (reference); unknown/missing (e.g. Azerbaijan, Bolivia, Chad, Colombia, Morocco)). Adjustment for individual-level SES included three conventional indicators (education, occupational status and urban location (rural as reference)). Education was defined using four DHS levels, i.e. no education (reference), primary, secondary, and higher. Occupational status was constructed from self-reported occupation group and employment status in the previous 12 months, with categories defined similar to previous research:[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref029">29</xref>] not working (reference); household, domestic and service workers; agricultural employees and self-employed workers; skilled and unskilled manual workers; and workers in non-manual occupations (professional and managerial; clerical; sales). Models were also conditioned on country-level factors that are associated with our outcome and likely to be related to differences in minimum wage levels: namely, market size (log of per capita GDP, adjusted for PPP in 2011 International $); public sector health spending (as % of total health expenditure); and market-liberal regulatory structure (Economic Freedom Index).</p>
<p>Sensitivity analyses re-estimated the odds ratios to test separate specifications for alternative coding of covariates (i.e. tobacco (y/n), education (years), public sector expenditures on health (as % of GDP); inclusion of other potential confounders (geographic regions; Human Development Index (low/medium/high)); and exclusion of GDP as covariate, or countries with low overweight/obesity prevalence. We also re-examined associations for obesity only. Analyses were performed using STATA v14.0.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0150736.t001">Table 1</xref> shows the distribution of country and individual characteristics for countries overall and by income group. While the average monthly minimum wage (PPP) across all countries was $192 (SD 104), differences were seen between low-income and middle-income countries ($144 (SD 35) versus $295 (SD 126), respectively). The proportions of women across categories of selected characteristics differed substantially between countries by economic development stage, with few exceptions (e.g. mean age, marital status). On average, just over a third of the women in our sample were overweight/obese; proportions were higher in middle-income (56%) than in low-income (26%) countries.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0150736.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Descriptive characteristics of study sample of adult women in 27 developing countries.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0150736.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Mean (SD) or frequency of country and individual characteristics</th>
<th align="left">All countries (n = 27)</th>
<th align="left">Low income countries (n = 17)</th>
<th align="left">Middle income countries (n = 11)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Country-level</italic></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Monthly minimum wage, International$</td>
<td align="left">192 (104)</td>
<td align="left">144 (35)</td>
<td align="left">295 (126)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">GDP, billions, PPP International $</td>
<td align="left">4120 (2754)</td>
<td align="left">2679 (1101)</td>
<td align="left">7216 (2690)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Log GDP, billions, PPP International $</td>
<td align="left">8.10 (0.70)</td>
<td align="left">7.77 (0.55)</td>
<td align="left">8.81 (0.41)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Under-5 Mortality Rate (U5MR)</td>
<td align="left">70.2 (38.3)</td>
<td align="left">88.0 (31.0)</td>
<td align="left">31.9 (20.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Economic Freedom Index (EFI) score</td>
<td align="left">55.3 (4.2)</td>
<td align="left">53.43 (2.8)</td>
<td align="left">59.2 (3.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Public sector health spending (% of total health expenditure)</td>
<td align="left">39.2 (19.6)</td>
<td align="left">31.9 (14.4)</td>
<td align="left">54.9 (19.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Individual-level</italic></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Women, n</td>
<td align="left">162 446</td>
<td align="left">103 516</td>
<td align="left">58 930</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Age (24–59 y)</td>
<td align="left">35.0 (7.3)</td>
<td align="left">34.8 (7.2)</td>
<td align="left">35.8 (7.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Ever married, n (%)</td>
<td align="left">149 790 (92%)</td>
<td align="left">98 110 (95%)</td>
<td align="left">51 680 (88%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Parity, n (%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">0 children</td>
<td align="left">15 609 (10%)</td>
<td align="left">8831 (9%)</td>
<td align="left">6778 (12%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">1–2 children</td>
<td align="left">55481 (34%)</td>
<td align="left">31 891 (31%)</td>
<td align="left">23 590 (40%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">3–5 children</td>
<td align="left">65 243 (40%)</td>
<td align="left">43 069 (42%)</td>
<td align="left">22 174 (38%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">6+ children</td>
<td align="left">26 113 (16%)</td>
<td align="left">19 725 (19%)</td>
<td align="left">6388 (11%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Tobacco use, n (%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Yes</td>
<td align="left">13 311 (8%)</td>
<td align="left">12 006 (12%)</td>
<td align="left">1305 (2%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">No</td>
<td align="left">115 309 (71%)</td>
<td align="left">89 794 (87%)</td>
<td align="left">25 515 (43%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Unknown/ missing</td>
<td align="left">33 826 (21%)</td>
<td align="left">1716 (2%)</td>
<td align="left">32 110 (54%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Highest education level, n (%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">No education</td>
<td align="left">45 794 (28%)</td>
<td align="left">40 991 (40%)</td>
<td align="left">4803 (8%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Primary</td>
<td align="left">43 888 (27%)</td>
<td align="left">24 875 (24%)</td>
<td align="left">19 013 (32%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Secondary</td>
<td align="left">55 776 (34%)</td>
<td align="left">29 348 (28%)</td>
<td align="left">26 428 (45%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Higher</td>
<td align="left">16 988 (10%)</td>
<td align="left">8302 (8%)</td>
<td align="left">8686 (15%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Occupation group, n (%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Not working</td>
<td align="left">65 285 (40%)</td>
<td align="left">45 066 (44%)</td>
<td align="left">20 219 (34%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Agriculture</td>
<td align="left">34 362 (21%)</td>
<td align="left">29 278 (28%)</td>
<td align="left">5084 (9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Services</td>
<td align="left">16 837 (10%)</td>
<td align="left">4950 (5%)</td>
<td align="left">11 887 (20%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Manual</td>
<td align="left">13 399 (8%)</td>
<td align="left">9360 (9%)</td>
<td align="left">4039 (7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Non-manual</td>
<td align="left">32 563 (20%)</td>
<td align="left">14 862 (14%)</td>
<td align="left">17 701 (30%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Urban location, n (%)</td>
<td align="left">80 727 (50%)</td>
<td align="left">44 617 (43%)</td>
<td align="left">36 110 (61%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">BMI (range: 12.1–59.81 kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td align="left">24.4 (4.6)</td>
<td align="left">23.2 (3.9)</td>
<td align="left">26.5 (5.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Overweight/ Obese, n (%)</td>
<td align="left">59 398 (37%)</td>
<td align="left">26 404 (26%)</td>
<td align="left">32 994 (56%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Obese, n (%)</td>
<td align="left">19,211 (12%)</td>
<td align="left">6,797 (7%)</td>
<td align="left">12,414 (21%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
</table-wrap>
<p>More notably, the proportions of women overweight/obese were unevenly distributed across categories of each SES variable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0150736.g001">Fig 1</xref>). There were large SES differences in women’s overweight prevalence among low-income countries, whereas the social gradient appeared weaker among middle-income countries. SES variation in the outcome specific to each country is also shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0150736.s001">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0150736.s002">S2</xref> Figs.</p>
<fig id="pone.0150736.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Proportion of overweight and obese women in the sample across categories of socioeconomic status (SES).</title>
<p>Panel A. Highest education level. Panel B. Occupation status. Panel C. Geographic location.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Independent associations of minimum wage with overweight/obesity and with obesity</title>
<p>In covariate- and SES-adjusted models, we found a significant (p&lt;0.001) but very weak positive association between national minimum wage and overweight/obesity across 27 developing countries (OR 1.0004 [1.0002, 1.0006]) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0150736.t002">Table 2</xref>). The pattern of independent association, however, differed substantially by country income group. We found a weak positive association (OR 1.0058 [1.0052, 1.0064], p&lt;0.001) in low-income countries, and a weak negative association (OR 0.9996 [0.9993, 0.9998], p = 0.003)) in middle-income countries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0150736.t002">Table 2</xref>). Sensitivity analyses showed the reversed pattern of stratified results persisted.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0150736.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Association of minimum wage with overweight and obesity in adult women in overall and stratified two-level random intercept models.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0150736.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">All countries</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Low-income countries</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Middle-income countries</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">(CI95)</th>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">(CI95)</th>
<th align="left">OR</th>
<th align="left">(CI95)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Monthly minimum wage, International$</td>
<td align="left">1.0004<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.0002, 1.0006</td>
<td align="left">1.0058<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.0052, 1.0064</td>
<td align="left">0.9996<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.9993, 0.9998</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Age (y)</td>
<td align="left">1.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.06, 1.06</td>
<td align="left">1.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.06, 1.06</td>
<td align="left">1.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.06, 1.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Ever married</td>
<td align="left">1.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.38, 1.54</td>
<td align="left">1.64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.49, 1.80</td>
<td align="left">1.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.28, 1.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">0 children</td>
<td align="left">0.95</td>
<td align="left">0.89, 1.01</td>
<td align="left">1.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.03, 1.22</td>
<td align="left">0.91<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">*</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.82, 0.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">1–2 children</td>
<td align="left">1.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.03, 1.12</td>
<td align="left">1.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.12, 1.25</td>
<td align="left">1.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.07, 1.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">3–5 children</td>
<td align="left">1.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.06, 1.14</td>
<td align="left">1.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.05, 1.15</td>
<td align="left">1.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.26, 1.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Tobacco non-user</td>
<td align="left">1.97<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.88, 2.06</td>
<td align="left">1.88<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.78, 1.98</td>
<td align="left">1.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.06, 1.35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Tobacco use unknown/ missing</td>
<td align="left">1.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.36, 1.55</td>
<td align="left">1.75</td>
<td align="left">0.96, 3.18</td>
<td align="left">0.85<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">*</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.74, 0.98</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Primary education</td>
<td align="left">1.83<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.77, 1.89</td>
<td align="left">1.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.40, 1.53</td>
<td align="left">1.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.29, 1.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Secondary education</td>
<td align="left">1.91<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.84, 1.97</td>
<td align="left">1.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.69, 1.84</td>
<td align="left">1.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.19, 1.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Higher education</td>
<td align="left">1.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.48, 1.63</td>
<td align="left">1.89<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.77, 2.01</td>
<td align="left">0.94</td>
<td align="left">0.86, 1.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Agriculture occupation</td>
<td align="left">0.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.44, 0.47</td>
<td align="left">0.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.44, 0.48</td>
<td align="left">0.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.66, 0.76</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Service occupation</td>
<td align="left">0.78<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.75, 0.82</td>
<td align="left">0.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.71, 0.82</td>
<td align="left">1.03</td>
<td align="left">0.97, 1.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Manual occupation</td>
<td align="left">0.85<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.82, 0.89</td>
<td align="left">0.83<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.78, 0.87</td>
<td align="left">1.00</td>
<td align="left">0.93, 1.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Non-manual occupation</td>
<td align="left">1.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">*</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.00, 1.07</td>
<td align="left">1.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.03, 1.13</td>
<td align="left">1.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.12, 1.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Urban</td>
<td align="left">1.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.47, 1.55</td>
<td align="left">2.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.96, 2.10</td>
<td align="left">1.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.23, 1.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Log of per-capita GDP, International$</td>
<td align="left">1.66<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.60, 1.72</td>
<td align="left">0.93<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">*</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.86, 0.99</td>
<td align="left">1.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.22, 1.44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Economic Freedom Score</td>
<td align="left">1.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.02, 1.03</td>
<td align="left">0.94<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.94, 0.95</td>
<td align="left">0.99<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">0.98, 0.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Public spending on health (% of total health expenditures)</td>
<td align="left">1.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">***</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.01, 1.01</td>
<td align="left">1.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">*</xref></td>
<td align="left">1.00, 1.01</td>
<td align="left">0.99</td>
<td align="left">0.99, 1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="right"><inline-formula id="pone.0150736.e001"><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0150736.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><mml:math display="inline" id="M1"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> (Between-country variance)</td>
<td align="left">0.5441</td>
<td align="left">0.1880, 1.5747</td>
<td align="left">0.7757</td>
<td align="left">0.2361, 2.5489</td>
<td align="left">0.0663</td>
<td align="left">0.0038, 1.1582</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>Odds ratios (95% CI) obtained by two-level random intercept model. Sample restricted to adult women (24–49 y). Number of observations were: All, n = 162,446; Low, n = 103,516; Middle, n = 58,930. Reference groups for each set of control variables were: women having 6 or more children, tobacco users, no education, being unemployed, and living in a rural location.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p>*** p&lt;0.001</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn003"><p>** p&lt;0.01</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn004"><p>* p&lt;0.05.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>By contrast, the association of country GDP (logged) with the outcome was much stronger and was negative in low-income countries but positive in middle-income countries (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0150736.t002">Table 2</xref>). And, as expected, there was a monotonic increase in the association between education and the outcome in low-income countries; while in middle-income countries, the opposite was observed. The residual variation in the odds of being overweight/obese that is attributable to unobserved country characteristics was 14% for the overall model (VPC = 0.142); 19% for the low-income stratified model (VPC = 0.19) and 2% for the middle-income stratified model (VPC = 0.019).</p>
<p>Results were different for obesity as the overall association showed a negative direction; was non-significant in low-income countries; but remained negative and stronger in middle-income countries with higher minimum wage associated with significantly less obesity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0150736.s004">S2 Table</xref>). Logged GDP was no longer significant in stratified models but higher education was still associated with higher obesity in low-income countries and with lower obesity in middle-income countries. Notably, we found higher percentages of residual variance in the odds of obesity attributable to unobserved country differences than we did for overweight/obesity.</p>
<p>In post-estimation using the full sample, we found a 1% increase in minimum wage was associated with an average increase of about 0.1 and 0.03 percentage points in the predicted probability of overweight/obesity and obesity, respectively, in low-income countries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0150736.g002">Fig 2</xref>). In middle-income countries, we calculated an average decrease of approximately 0.01 and 0.03 percentage points in the predicted probability of overweight/obesity and obesity for a 1% increase minimum wage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0150736.g002">Fig 2</xref>). Detailed estimates are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0150736.s005">S3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0150736.s006">S4</xref> Tables.</p>
<fig id="pone.0150736.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title/>
<p><bold>Adjusted differences in probability of being overweight/obese (panel A) or being obese (panel B) associated with a 1% increase in monthly minimum wage using pooled data.</bold> Post-estimation calculation of average marginal effects using pooled data in multivariable multilevel models with interaction term between minimum wage and country income group (n = 162 446).</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This cross-sectional study of 27 developing countries used a novel dataset to find very small associations between national minimum wage and individual women’s overweight and obesity, after controlling for known confounders including individual-level SES. In particular, results showed a reversed pattern of association by country development stage, with higher levels of minimum wage appearing protective against overweight and obesity among adult women living in countries with middle income. Findings are suggestive of a potential social-level effect of minimum wage, although the relative contribution was minimal compared to individual-level SES and country income level.</p>
<p>Evidence is generally sparse regarding the role of policy as a social determinant of health,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref013">13</xref>] and employment conditions affecting weight.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref030">30</xref>] There are no studies to our knowledge of minimum wage in relation to overweight and obesity among adult women in a developing context. Our results for middle income countries echo the US studies. Existing research on US adults using survey data over a timeframe including our study period (1984–2006) demonstrates an inverse association between inflation-adjusted minimum wage and self-reported mean BMI and that associations are stronger at the higher end of the distribution.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref016">16</xref>] Meltzer and Chen (2011) further show how declines in real minimum wage of US$0.68 (end of their study period) and US$3.33 (before their study period) explain 4% and 10% of the total increase in average BMI. Another study using the same survey data (1996–2007) shows potential protective effects of higher state-level minimum wage for self-reported health status.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref015">15</xref>] Furthermore, our finding of a reversed pattern of association with overweight and obesity by country development stage parallels other work using DHS data. Another multilevel international study reported protective effects of low individual SES on women’s obesity in low-income countries and insalubrious effects in upper-middle income countries.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref008">8</xref>] And, in a recent econometric study using single-level fixed effects models over a longer period (1991–2009), the relationship between economic globalization and overweight in young and adult women also changed direction from positive in the least economically globalized countries to negative in the most economically globalized.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref010">10</xref>]</p>
<p>Our finding of small magnitudes of association could have resulted from a combination of a large relationship among women in low-wage occupations with minimum wage protection and no relationship (as would be expected) among women unaffected by the minimum wage either because they were in the informal economy (typically without a minimum fixed wage) or because their salaries were already above the legislated level. There are also multiple potential reasons for the mixed pattern in the direction of association by country development stage. It is possible that in least developed countries, minimum wage is relevant only to a small group of women who are employed in the formal economy (or in the informal sector)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref018">18</xref>] and use their secure income to buy energy-dense calories, or who belong to elite social groups that are known to have higher weight status as a result of patterns of low-energy expenditure, lack of food insecurity and cultural values of wealth/prestige favoring large body shape.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref005">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref012">12</xref>] Given we adjusted for individual SES, results for the least developed countries might be explained by other broader factors such as technological change, infrastructure availability, wars, famine and economic/climate shocks could each affect both minimum wage and overweight levels.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref010">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref031">31</xref>]</p>
<p>By contrast, national minimum wage may apply to a wider segment of employed women in the population after a certain stage of development expressed by country per capita GDP. However, several of the middle-income countries examined also have high proportions of women employed in the informal economy.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref032">32</xref>] Nevertheless, the informal economy in relatively more developed countries may have closer or stronger linkages to formal regulatory environment such as minimum wage protection due to different types of production systems,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref018">18</xref>] and to greater awareness among workers of their rights to certain legal and social protection.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref032">32</xref>] Thus, after considering women’s SES, higher levels of national minimum wage may protect women against overweight and obesity through effects on food security which is consistently associated with obesity disparities in women,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref033">33</xref>] and/or on perceived economic security which has stress-related effects on BMI.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref014">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref028">28</xref>] It bears noting that average calorie intake, exercise, smoking and alcohol are important, but do not fully explain the social gradients in obesity in women in developed countries;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref034">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref035">35</xref>] hence stress-related factors are increasingly proposed as plausible mediators.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref036">36</xref>]</p>
<p>Finally, the role of minimum wage in disparities of overweight and obesity may be modified (rather than confounded) by individual SES at any country development level,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref011">11</xref>] and such potential interactions should be further investigated. It is worth noting that we found a strong positive relationship between education and obesity outcomes in low-income countries and a strong negative relationship in middle-income countries, which is consistent with the wider literature.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0150736.ref012">12</xref>] Separately, there was also a differing pattern of association between different occupation categories and obesity outcomes by country development stage, particularly regarding the role of service and manual occupations which were strongly protective in low-income, but not middle-income, countries. The latter might suggest that service and manual occupations might differ in the composition of job types and/or in the nature of work as countries develop. Nevertheless, across development stages, agricultural work was unsurprisingly negatively associated with overweight/obesity while non-manual occupations were positively associated with overweight/obesity.</p>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Study limitations include the cross-sectional nature of the data, which limits causal inference and does not unpack the influence of secular trends in obesity. Absence of reliable data on informal sector workers covering the countries studied, and lack of information on policy enforcement and implementation reach are further limitations. We also cannot investigate gender differences or differences between mandated minimum and prevailing market wage. Moreover, there is potential for residual confounding from individual income not measured in the DHS, and from above-mentioned unobserved country factors. However, we have addressed some important confounding by including three economic development factors that may explain some unmeasured labor market features. Notably, multilevel models also help to address some unobserved natural heterogeneity across countries. Approximately 20% of adult women in the sample were dropped in analyses due to missing anthropometry data which may have induced non-response/ selection bias. And, the small sample of middle-income countries in stratified analysis means that estimates are likely based on extrapolation and SES might be underestimated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Strengths</title>
<p>Several strengths of our study favor the validity of our findings: the nationwide probabilistic samples and large number of observations; comparability of anthropometric outcomes; range of country economic development level and geographical regions; highly standardized data collection procedures; multiple potential confounders; and, appropriate multilevel analyses. Stratified results were robust to alternative model specifications, and the associations between individual-level SES and the outcome also differed by country development stage and revealed a pattern consistent with the literature.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>A clear link exists between national minimum wage and overweight measured in adult women in developing countries. The societal phenomenon observed showed a reversed pattern by country development stage. Future work needs to use longitudinal analyses to show the potential impact of changing minimum wage so as to determine whether this employment policy might serve as a possible structural intervention for the growing burden of excess weight among women across all social groups.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0150736.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Differences by SES in the proportion of overweight and obese women in each low-income country.</title>
<p>Panel A. Highest education level. Panel B. Occupation status. Panel C. Geographic location.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0150736.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.s002" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Fig</label>
<caption>
<title>Differences by SES in the proportion of overweight and obese women in each middle-income country.</title>
<p>Panel A. Highest education level. Panel B. Occupation status. Panel C. Geographic location.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0150736.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.s003" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Adverse anthropometric outcomes, monthly minimum wage and level of development in the study sample of adult women, by country.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0150736.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.s004" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S2 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Association of minimum wage with obesity in adult women in overall and stratified two-level random intercept models.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0150736.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.s005" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S3 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Association of monthly minimum wage with overweight and obesity in adult women using pooled data with interaction terms.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0150736.s006" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0150736.s006" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S4 Table</label>
<caption>
<title>Association of monthly minimum wage with obesity in adult women using pooled data with interaction terms.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors wish to thank José M. Mendoza Rodríguez for preparing and linking the data files for analysis. We also appreciate statistical support and expertise from the UCLA IDRE Statistical Consulting Group and Dr. Antonio Pedro Ramos.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <chapter-title>Global health risks: mortality and burden of disease attributable to selected major risks</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <chapter-title>Closing the gap in a generation: health equity through action on the social determinants of health</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLaren</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic status and obesity</article-title>. <source>Epidemiologic Reviews</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/epirev/mxm001" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/epirev/mxm001</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conklin</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forouhi</surname> <given-names>NG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monsivais</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Persistent financial hardship, 11-year weight gain and health behaviors in the Whitehall II study</article-title>. <source>Obesity</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2606</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/oby.20875" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/oby.20875</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25155547</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobal</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stunkard</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic status and obesity: a review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Psychology Bulletin</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey</surname> <given-names>Smith G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The poor stay thinner: stable socioeconomic gradients in BMI among women in lower- and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Clinical Nutrition</source>. <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Corsi</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanyam</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davey</surname> <given-names>Smith G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Jumping the gun: the problematic discourse on socioeconomic status and cardiovascular health in India</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Epidemiology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>–<lpage>1426</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conde</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Popkin</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Obesity and inequities in health in the developing world</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1181</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15211362</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones-Smith</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon-Larsen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Popkin</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cross-national comparisons of time trends in overweight inequality by socioeconomic status among women using repeated cross-sectional surveys from 37 developing countries, 1989–2007</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Epidemiology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwq428" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/aje/kwq428</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300855</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goryakin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobstein</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suhrcke</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of economic, political and social globalization on overweight and obesity in the 56 low and middle income countries</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>133</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawachi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gortmaker</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>National economic development and disparities in body mass index: a cross-sectional study of data from 38 countries</article-title>. <source>PLOS One</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e99327</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0099327" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0099327</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24919199</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanter</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caballero</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Global gender disparities in obesity: a review</article-title>. <source>Advances in Nutrition: An International Review Journal</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braveman</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Egerter</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <article-title>The social determinants of health: coming of age</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Public Health</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-031210-101218" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-031210-101218</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091195</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reconciling psychology with economics: obesity, behavioral biology, and rational overeating.</article-title> <source>Journal of Bioeconomics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCarrier KP, editor. Exploring the relationship between state-level minimum wage policies and health-related outcomes: An analysis of 2004 BRFSS data. APHA 134th Annual Meeting; 2006; Boston, MA.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meltzer</surname> <given-names>DO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The impact of minimum wage rates on body weight in the United States</chapter-title>. <source>Economic aspects of obesity</source>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>. p. <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heymann</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Forgotten families: Ending the growing crisis confronting children and working parents in the global economy</chapter-title>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Rethinking the informal economy: Linkages with the formal economy and the formal regulatory environment</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year> Contract No.: DESA Working Paper No. 46.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname> <given-names>Muda M</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Globalization of fatness: cultural, social and economic perception of obesity in Southeast Asia</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Magno</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Reflections on the human condition: change, conflict and modernity</source>. <publisher-loc>Bangkok</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Nippon Foundation</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conklin</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Gender, diet quality and obesity: economic and social determinants, and their interactions, in older adults</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Cambridge</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wutich</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falletta-Cowden</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Soto</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Body norms and fat stigma in global perspective</article-title>. <source>Current Anthropology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corsi</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neuman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Demographic and health surveys: a profile</article-title>. <source>International journal of epidemiology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1602</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/ije/dys184" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/ije/dys184</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23148108</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">DHS Program. Protecting the Privacy of DHS Survey Respondents [7 October 2015]. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dhsprogram.com/What-We-Do/Protecting-the-Privacy-of-DHS-Survey-Respondents.cfm" xlink:type="simple">http://dhsprogram.com/What-We-Do/Protecting-the-Privacy-of-DHS-Survey-Respondents.cfm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Egger</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swinburn</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amirul</surname> <given-names>Islam F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Economic growth and obesity: an interesting relationship with world-wide implications</article-title>. <source>Economics &amp; Human Biology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawachi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>Income inequality and health: what have we learned so far?</article-title> <source>Epidemiologic reviews</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diez-Roux</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Link</surname> <given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Northridge</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <article-title>A multilevel analysis of income inequality and cardiovascular disease risk factors</article-title>. <source>Social science &amp; medicine</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>673</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <chapter-title>The World Health Report 2008: Primary health care now more than ever</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Offer</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pechey</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulijaszek</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Obesity under affluence varies by welfare regimes: The effect of fast food, insecurity, and inequality</article-title>. <source>Economics &amp; Human Biology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ehb.2010.07.002" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ehb.2010.07.002</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pampel</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Patterns of tobacco use in the early epidemic stages: Malawi and Zambia, 2000–2002</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2004.056895" xlink:type="simple">10.2105/AJPH.2004.056895</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914826</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friel</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chopra</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Satcher</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Unequal weight: equity oriented policy responses to the gloal obesity pandemic</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>335</volume>:<fpage>1241</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079548</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakdawalla</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Philipson</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>The growth of obesity and technological change</article-title>. <source>Economics &amp; Human Biology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><collab>International Labor Organization</collab>. <chapter-title>Statistical update on employment in the informal economy</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ILO Department of Statistics</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinour</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergen</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname> <given-names>M-C</given-names></name>. <article-title>The food insecurity–obesity paradox: a review of the literature and the role food stamps may play</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Dietetic Association</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1952</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17964316</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickett</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobstein</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Wider income gaps, wider waistbands? An ecological study of obesity and income inequality</article-title>. <source>Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>670</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/jech.2004.028795" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/jech.2004.028795</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16020644</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic status and weight change in adults: a review</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1987</fpage>–<lpage>2010</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0150736.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borodulin</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sippola</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mäkinen</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laatikainen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prättälä</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health behaviours as mediating pathways between socioeconomic position and body mass index</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Behavioral Medicine</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12529-010-9138-1" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s12529-010-9138-1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21184210</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>