<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-39943</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal management</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Vertebrate paleontology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Earth sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Biogeochemistry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Paleontology</subject><subj-group><subject>Vertebrate paleontology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Archaeology</subject><subj-group><subject>Archaeometry</subject><subject>Historical archaeology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pastoralism in Northern Peru during Pre-Hispanic Times: Insights from the Mochica Period (100–800 AD) Based on Stable Isotopic Analysis of Domestic Camelids</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Stable Isotopes and Pre-Hispanic Pastoralism</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>Elise</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goepfert</surname><given-names>Nicolas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutiérrez Léon</surname><given-names>Belkys</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauchat</surname><given-names>Claude</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franco Jordán</surname><given-names>Régulo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>Segundo Vásquez</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle-CNRS, UMR 7209 Archéozoologie, Archéobotanique : sociétés, pratiques et environnements, Département Ecologie et Gestion de la Biodiversité, Paris, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>CNRS-Paris 1, UMR 8096 Archéologie des Amériques, Nanterre, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Universidad Nacional de Trujillo, Trujillo, Peru</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Museo de Cao-Fundación Wiese, Lima, Peru</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caramelli</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Florence, Italy</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">edufour@mnhn.fr</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: ED NG BGL CC RFJ SVS. Performed the experiments: ED NG. Analyzed the data: ED NG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: ED NG BGL CC RFJ SVS. Wrote the paper: ED NG BGL CC RFJ SVS.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<elocation-id>e87559</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Dufour et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Llama (<italic>Lama glama</italic>) and alpaca (<italic>Vicugna pacos</italic>) are the only large domesticated animals indigenous to the Americas. Pastoralism occupies a fundamental economic, social and religious role in Andean life. Today, camelid livestock are confined to the ecozone of the <italic>puna</italic> (above 3,500 masl), while their presence on the Pacific coast during pre-Hispanic times is attested by archaeological skeletal remains. This study aims to document herding practices on the northern Peruvian coast during the Early Intermediate Period (200 BC-600 AD) by gaining insights into diet, location of breeding and mobility of archaeological camelids from the funerary and ritual contexts of two Mochica sites, Uhle Platform in Huacas de Moche and El Brujo. The three first early years and the long-term life histories of the animals were documented by the combined bulk analysis of bone collagen (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub>) and bone structural carbonate (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub>) and the serial analysis of structural carbonate of molar tooth enamel (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub>). Mochica camelids were bred in the low and/or middle valleys, unlike their modern counterparts, who are restricted to highland <italic>puna</italic> C<sub>3</sub> pastures. Archaeological camelids had diverse and complex life histories, usually with substantial maize foddering. An ontogenetic switch in diet and possible residential mobility during the course of life were identified for some specimens. Although the inference of geographic origin from δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values was limited because of the lack of understanding of the influence of environmental and biological factors, tooth enamel analysis has great potential for exploring camelid herding practices and Andean pastoralism. Our study suggested that Mochica herders adapted their practices to the difficult lowland environment and that herding practices were varied and not restricted to breeding at higher altitudes. The role of maize in different aspects of the economic life of the Mochicas is also underlined.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by the Action Thématique du Muséum BIOMINERALIZATION and the Action Thématique du Muséum Biodiversité actuelle et fossile (MNHN) and the Universidad Nacional de Trujillo (UNT). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="20"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Andean pastoralism and the establishment of trade routes between different ecological zones, the so-called concept of Andean verticality, is one of the foundations for the emergence of complex societies in the pre-Hispanic world <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Murra1">[1]</xref>. Alpacas (<italic>Vicugna pacos</italic>) and llamas (<italic>Lama glama</italic>) were domesticated 4,000–6,000 years ago, and experienced an intensification in livestock management from at least the end of the Early Horizon (900–400 BC) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bonavia1">[2]</xref>. From then onwards, camelids have occupied a fundamental economic, social and religious role, both in pre-Hispanic and modern Andean cultures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-FloresOchoa1">[3]</xref>. During the pre-Hispanic period, the llama was the only beast of burden and caravans providing goods to different ecological zones were crucial to the development of extensive trade networks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Murra1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Browman1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-VanBuren1">[6]</xref>. Textiles were manufactured from camelid wool and traded throughout the Andes, their meat was consumed, leather and bones served as raw materials to make tools and various ornaments, and dung was used as fuel. Domestic camelids were sacrificed and deposited into graves to fulfil various symbolic functions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert1">[7]</xref> and their entrails could be used to read omens. Finally, they were a symbol of prestige and a marker of identity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Shimada1">[8]</xref>.</p>
<p>Today, camelid husbandry is essentially restricted to the highlands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Wheeler1">[9]</xref>, in an ecozone called the <italic>puna</italic> that comprises plateaus above 3,500 masl, and more precisely between 3,900 and 4,500 masl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Franklin1">[10]</xref>. <italic>Puna</italic> conditons are characterized by hypoxia, low intra-annual variation in temperature but daily variation as high as 20°C and a higher precipitation rate than that of the lower western slopes of the Andes (between 200 and 1,500 mm per year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson1">[11]</xref>). Water is supplied by rain, snow and hail during the rainy season. The vegetation comprises wetlands such as <italic>bofedales</italic> (peatlands of the central Andes where Juncaceae species dominate and serve as the primary peat-formers) which are naturally conducive to llama and alpaca breeding. The optimum life conditions for llamas and alpacas vary according to the function the animal serves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Topic1">[12]</xref>. Alpaca herds devoted to wool production are raised in rich <italic>bofedales</italic> pasturelands at higher altitudes than llama herds. The presence of domestic camelids in remote and dramatically different habitats, like the Pacific coast – characterized by a higher mean temperature and higher seasonal variations in temperature than the <italic>puna</italic> and almost no precipitation – is attested by skeletal remains, textiles and iconography from at least 200 BC onwards <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bonavia1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Shimada1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert2">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Shimada2">[17]</xref>. It was formerly assumed that lowland camelids were not raised locally but instead were brought by caravans from the Andes shortly before being butchered or sacrificed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Pozorski3">[18]</xref>. This classical view is challenged by new zooarchaeological studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert2">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-VsquezSnchez1">[19]</xref>. The northern coast (0–500 masl) of Peru has witnessed – among others – the development of rich and powerful cultures, such as the Mochica culture (100–800 AD), famous for the construction of monumental ceremonial centers and cultural artefacts such as vessels and metal ornaments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Pillsbury1">[20]</xref>. Camelid skeletal remains were found in different Mochica contexts: domestic, burials, sacrifices, funerary banquets and offering deposits. Because of the arid to hyper arid conditions that prevail today, the Peruvian coast does not seem to provide favorable conditions to camelid herding, compared to the rich productive grasslands and wet <italic>bofedales</italic> of the <italic>puna</italic>. Only a few habitats located in the lower part of the valleys, fog oases (<italic>lomas</italic>) developing in the foothills, or irrigated fields could have provided pastures rich enough to sustain large herds. Maize foddering, diet supplements comprising marine resources (algae) or seasonal transhumance to mid-altitude valleys could have been used to compensate low food availability. Therefore, the breeding of flocks in an environment radically different from their original environment during pre-Hispanic times raises questions about the nature and the location of the dietary resources necessary to maintain animals and the seasonal or year-round nature of their keep. Furthermore, the presence of camelid remains on the north coast is not in itself indicative of local herding. With the exception of juveniles (under two years old) that have not been documented to travel long distances <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Lecoq1">[21]</xref>, the skeletal remains found in the northern coast could have belonged to animals first bred in the <italic>puna</italic> and subsequently brought to the coast. In order to answer these questions and document the management systems developed by coastal breeders it is essential to reconstruct camelid diet and zone of growth.</p>
<p>Measurements of stable isotopes of carbon (δ<sup>13</sup>C), nitrogen (δ<sup>15</sup>N), oxygen (δ<sup>18</sup>O) and strontium (<sup>87</sup>Sr/<sup>86</sup>Sr) in human and animal remains found in archaeological contexts are a primary source of information on the life history of humans and animals. The scope of isotopic analyses is still limited in South America compared to other regions but it is growing rapidly. The western slopes of the Andes present a wide variety of ecological zones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-PulgarVidal1">[22]</xref> from the coast to the highlands, characterized by differences in physical parameters such as temperature and precipitation, as well as availability of different food resource categories. This results in relatively predictable geographical variations in dietary and environmental isotopic signatures across the landmass <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref>, even though the baseline of environmental δ<sup>18</sup>O water data remains to be established on a local scale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Webb1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Buzon1">[25]</xref>. A number of paleodietary studies have been completed using δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N values that enable, for instance, the identification of maize consumption <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Falabella1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Tykot1">[30]</xref>. δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N values, as well as δ<sup>18</sup>O and <sup>87</sup>Sr/<sup>86</sup>Sr values (that rely on climate and geology) can also be used to assess animal mobility between geographical areas that present distinct isotopic values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson2">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>.</p>
<p>Stable isotopic studies of past camelids in the Central Andes have mostly been conducted on bone collagen (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>) and more recently on bone structural carbonate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson3">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert3">[36]</xref> of remains from various archaeological contexts, located at different elevations (lowlands, intermediate lands, highlands). They revealed some diversity in diet, pasturelands and foddering practices among sites and within sites. As bone tissue is constantly renewed during life, it provides a record of diet and habitat averaged out over the lifetime of the animal. Only tissues with accretional growth that do not undergo remodeling after deposition can record the chronology of the animal’s life history. Enamel of high-crowned teeth records events that occurred during the period of tooth formation and reconstructs this record through the isotopic profiles when an appropriate serial sampling protocol is applied.</p>
<p>The serial analysis of tooth enamel has been used successfully in different regions of the world to document herding practices <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Balasse1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Henton1">[38]</xref>. Preliminary data presented in Goepfert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert3">[36]</xref> showed that this technique appears to be very promising in the Central Andean region. Based on these first data, this study aims to document herding practices on the northern Peruvian coast during the Early Intermediate Period (200 BC-600 AD). In order to provide insights into diet, location of breeding of domestic camelids and mobility patterns between the coast and higher elevations, the age of archaeological specimens from two Mochica sites (Uhle Platform in Huacas de Moche and El Brujo, La Libertad region) in the Moche and Chicama Valleys was determined and their stable isotopic composition was analysed and compared to that of modern camelids. The serial analysis of δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values of structural carbonate from molar enamel (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub>) was used to retrospectively record the animals’ early life histories. Enamel δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values were compared to those of bone apatite (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub>) and to δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N values for bone collagen (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub>), to document diachronic changes in diet and growth location.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Geographical and Cultural Context</title>
<p>The Mochica territory ranged from the Piura Valley to the Huarmey Valley on the northern coast of Peru (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Mochica political power was not centralized, but was probably divided into independent centers located around the valleys <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Quilter1">[39]</xref> carved by rivers and streams between the coast and the Andean foothills along a northeast-southwest axis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g001">Figs. 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g002">2</xref>). The Mochica people occupied the lower elevations of the Andes (0–500 masl), which presents contrasting environments. A relative chronology based on stylistic changes in the form and decoration of Mochica ceramic vessels (stirrup spout bottles) was defined by Larco Hoyle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-LarcoHoyle1">[40]</xref>. The sequence includes five successive phases: Moche I and II (100–200 AD), Moche III (200–450 AD), Moche IV (450–650 AD) and Moche V (650–800 AD).</p>
<fig id="pone-0087559-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Topographic map of Peru with valleys and provenance of Mochica and modern domestic camelids.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0087559-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Central Andes ecozones and altitudinal environmental variations.</title>
<p>Cross-section of the western slopes of the Central Andes with the main ecological zones considered in the study with expected trends in variations in environmental conditions and δ<sup>13</sup>C, δ<sup>15</sup>N and δ<sup>18</sup>O measured in domestic camelid tissues.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>At the latitude of the Moche region, the coast is a zone approximately 25 km wide, bordered to the west by a cool and rich ocean and to the east by the foothills of the Andes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The coast is very arid and covered with sand and large dunes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-PeaherreraDelAguila1">[41]</xref>. With less than 20 mm of rain per year, surface waters result mostly from the winter mists called <italic>garúa,</italic> which occur between May and December, and the resurgence of the underground water network <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-CollinDelavaud1">[42]</xref>. <italic>Lomas</italic> develop on the foothills between 200 and 1,000 masl and present specific vegetation which is particularly attractive to wildlife and game. The northern boundary of the <italic>lomas</italic> is located on the foothills of the Cerro Campana, a few kilometers from the modern city of Trujillo. The rivers and the valleys are the most active and dynamic components of the coastal environment and have been classified as oases by Dollfus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Dollfus1">[43]</xref>. With the exception of <italic>lomas</italic>, river mouths and valleys, the arid desert environment of the coast is not conducive to agriculture and permanent domestic animal herding. The sustainability of diversified agriculture was made possible by the development of a complex irrigation system formed of canals, which undoubtedly constituted one of the bases for the expansion of the Mochicas into each valley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Billman1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-CastilloButters1">[45]</xref>.</p>
<p>The site of Huacas de Moche is located on the left bank of the Moche Valley, 4 km from Trujillo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). It comprises two pyramids, the Huaca del Sol and Huaca de la Luna, which are now separated by a vast desert plain which covers an ancient city, the Urban Area, which included domestic sectors and craft workshops. The Uhle Platform, a 75 m long and 25 m wide structure, is located at the bottom of the west side of the Huaca de la Luna. Several excavations were conducted at the Uhle Platform by the Moche International Programme between 1999 and 2008 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Chauchat1">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Chauchat6">[51]</xref>. They led to the discovery of 57 Mochica graves, several human sacrifice areas and large ceremonial deposits. Camelids were found in 42 graves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g003">Fig. 3</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert2">[13]</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0087559-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Tomb 48(Huacas de Moche) with artefacts and domestic camelid offerings.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The site of El Brujo is located 60 km north of Trujillo, close to the village of Magdalena de Cao, in the lower part of the Chicama Valley (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), along the ocean shore <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Franco1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Franco2">[53]</xref>. It comprises two Mochica pyramids, The Huaca Cao Viejo and the Huaca El Brujo. Like Huacas de Moche, El Brujo was one of the major religious centers on the northern coast of Peru. Excavations have been conducted at El Brujo since 1990 by the El Brujo Archaeological Project <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Franco1">[52]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Franco3">[54]</xref>. Tens of Mochica burials have been discovered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Franco1">[52]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Williams1">[57]</xref>, of which eleven contained camelid remains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert2">[13]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Material</title>
<sec id="s2b1">
<title>Ethic statement</title>
<p>All necessary permits were obtained for the described study, which complied with all relevant regulations. Permissions were obtained from the Ministerio de Cultura of Peru to study archaeological remains.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b2">
<title>Archaeological material</title>
<p>Species-specific determination of camelids based on the study of skeletal remains is theoretically possible but proved to be difficult. The phalange is usually the preferred anatomical element <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Kent1">[58]</xref>, but is of limited use here as the presence of this bone in the archaeological site is restricted to adults and it cannot be used to separate hybrid specimens. We therefore used tooth shape <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Wheeler2">[59]</xref> and the size of skeletal remains to discriminate between large (<italic>Lama</italic> sp.) camelids and small camelids (<italic>Vicugna</italic> sp.). Only <italic>Lama</italic> sp. were identified in our two archaeological sites and were probably llamas. However, this does not preclude the presence of alpacas on the coast during pre-Hispanic times. Eight archeological camelid specimens curated at the site Museum of the Huacas de Moche (Moche, La Libertad, Peru) were selected from five graves and from one ceremonial context of the Uhle Platform (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Table 1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Chauchat1">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Chauchat4">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Chauchat6">[51]</xref>. These contexts were dated from the Moche I to Moche IV phases. One piece of bone was selected from the mandible, the skull or a phalanx for six out of the eight individuals for bone collagen extraction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">Table 2</xref>). All the permanent molars present in each hemi-mandible were extracted. Depending on the stage of tooth eruption, one (UH-4, UH-7), two (UH-3, UH-5, UH-9) or the three molars (UH-8, UH-10, UH-11) were present (Table3). δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values for the M2 and M3 of three individuals were previously published in Goepfert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert3">[36]</xref>. Four specimens (<italic>Lama</italic> sp.), curated at the site Museum of El Brujo (Magdalena de Cao, La Libertad, Peru), were selected from four graves at El Brujo (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Table 1</xref>). Three graves were located in the Huaca Cao Viejo, the fourth was situated near the ceremonial place (Ceremonial Wells 2). These contexts were dated from the Moche III and IV phases. A piece of bone from the mandible or the pelvis was collected for each specimen for bone collagen extraction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">Table 2</xref>). One (EBT2-1995, EBT6-1994) or three (EBT2-1998, EBE1-1995) permanent molars were present on each jaw (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0087559-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Origin, context and individual age of modern and archaeological and modern domestic camelids.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0087559-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Origin/Site</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Context</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Areq-1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arequipa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tocra</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vicugna pacos</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9–11 years</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Areq-2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arequipa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tocra</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vicugna pacos</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0–3 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Areq-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arequipa</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tocra</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama glama</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–6 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quiru-1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quirivulca</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vicugna pacos</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 year 3 months-6 years 9 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uhle Platform</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomb 14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche IV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 years 3 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uhle Platform</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomb 22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche IV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year 9 months-2 years</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uhle Platform</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomb 48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years 3 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uhle Platform</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomb 55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 years 3 months-2 years</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uhle Platform</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Element 21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 years</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uhle Platform</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Element 21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years-3 years 6 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uhle Platform</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Element 21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche I</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 years 6 months- 4 years 9 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uhle Platform</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumb 16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche III</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11–13 years</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT2-1995</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">El Brujo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomb 2/Well 2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/d</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year 3 months-2 years</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT6-1994</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">El Brujo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomb 6/Huaca Cao Viejo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moche III–IV</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;3 years</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT2-1998</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">El Brujo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomb 2/Huaca Cao Viejo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/d</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 years-7 years 6 months</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBE1-1995</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Libertad</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">El Brujo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomb 1/Huaca Cao Viejo</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/d</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lama sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 years 6 months</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>n/d : not determinate.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0087559-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰ VPDB) and δ<sup>15</sup>N (‰ AIR) values of bone collagen and δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values (‰ VPDB) of bone structural carbonate of modern and archaeological domestic camelids.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0087559-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen</td>
<td colspan="7" align="left" rowspan="1">Bone collagen</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Carbonate</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰VPDB)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>15</sup>N (‰ AIR)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C:N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wt %</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%C4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰VPDB)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ<sup>18</sup>O (‰VPDB)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% C<sub>4</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰VPDB)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Areq-1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Areq-2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Areq-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quiru-1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT2-1995</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT6-1994</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT2-1998</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBE1-1995</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>δ<sup>13</sup>C values of modern specimens were corrected by +1.5 ‰ for the Suess effect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Marino1">[108]</xref>. Proportion of C<sub>4</sub> (%) in the diet was reconstructed using mean estimated δ<sup>13</sup>C values of pure-C<sub>3</sub> and pure-C<sub>4</sub> feeders.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0087559-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Summary of δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values (‰ VPDB) of enamel structural carbonate of molars of archaeological and modern camelids.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0087559-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Teeth</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td>
<td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰VPDB)</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">% C<sub>4</sub></td>
<td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">δ<sup>18</sup>O (‰VPDB)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">min.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">range</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">min.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">max.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">range</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Areq-1</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.9</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11,0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.1</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.9</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Areq-3</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Pd4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.5</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quiri−1</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.4</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10,0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.4</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.5</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-3</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.4</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.5</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-4</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.2</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-5</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.6</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.9</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-7</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.2</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-8</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.2</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.2</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.3</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-9</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.7</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.9</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-10</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.0</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.1</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.9</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UH-11</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.9</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.1</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.1</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT2-1995</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.1</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">5.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT6-1994</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.0</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">4.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBT2-1998</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.0</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.4</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">3.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.0</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">2.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EBE1-1995</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.8</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.6</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">M3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.7</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">1.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>δ<sup>13</sup>C values of modern specimens were corrected by +1.5 ‰ for the Suess effect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Marino1">[108]</xref>. Proportion of C<sub>4</sub> (%) in the diet is reconstructed using mean estimated δ<sup>13</sup>C values of pure-C<sub>3</sub> and pure-C<sub>4</sub> feeders.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b3">
<title>Modern material</title>
<p>Teeth and bone from modern butchered animals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) were kindly obtained with the permission of herders, Cayetano Mamani (Tocra, Arequipa, Peru) and Santos Mantilla (Quiruvilca, La libertad, Peru). Two alpacas and one llama from the southern region (National reserve of Salinas y Aguada Blanca, Tocra, Arequipa region at 4,200 masl) and one modern alpaca from the northern region (Quiruvilca, La Libertad region at 4,100 masl) were selected. While Quiruvilca is located in the upper Moche Valley, an area which could have provided camelids for the Mochicas, Tocra is situated outside the potential area of interaction between the Mochicas and highland camelid breeders. However, the two <italic>puna</italic> regions present similar environmental characteristics and vegetation formed of <italic>bofedales</italic>. In both locations, modern livestock are raised for meat production and wool and spend their whole life feeding on natural pastures. They thus appear well suited to exploring variations in isotopic values of camelids originating from the <italic>puna</italic> ecological zone. δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values for the M2 and M3 of Areq-1 have been described in Goepfert et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert3">[36]</xref>. Mandibles were defleshed and cleaned by boiling. A piece of mandibular bone was collected from the four individuals for bone collagen and bone apatite analyses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">Table 2</xref>). Depending on the specimen, the three permanent molars (Areq-1, Quiru-1), or the Pd4 premolar (Areq-3) were extracted from the hemi-mandible (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b4">
<title>Individual age estimate and life history record</title>
<p>The age of studied specimens is rarely – if ever – mentioned in the literature, even though it appears essential for the interpretation of each specimen’s life history from the isotopic analysis of its tissues. Age-at-death of modern and archaeological animals was estimated by the observation of tooth wear and eruption stages established by Wheeler <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Wheeler2">[59]</xref>. Age varied between 1 year and 9 months and 13 years and between 3 months and 6 years 9 months, respectively for archaeological and modern camelids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<p>Bone and enamel form at different stages of an individual’s life and present different metabolic activities. Bone is constantly remodeled. Cogenetic bone collagen and structural carbonates remodel together and both provide a long-term isotopic signal. In humans, bone turnover varies between 10 to 30 years, depending on the age of the individual <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-OConnell1">[60]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Hedges1">[61]</xref>. Our sample comprises both young and old specimens. Therefore, the bulk analysis of bone collagen and bone apatite represents on average a few years (for young individuals) and the entire lifespan (for old individuals). Tooth enamel is metabolically inert. It is not remodeled once formed and integrates an individual’s life history over a fixed period of time. Camelids have hypsodont teeth characterized by a high crown with extended incremental growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Hillson1">[62]</xref>. The mineralization process is complex and composed of two different stages: growth and maturation. The duration of mineralization has been determined for domestic sheep (<italic>Ovis aries</italic>) and cattle (<italic>Bos Taurus</italic>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Balasse2">[63]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Zazzo1">[65]</xref>. The schedule of crown growth completion, which is fixed for a given species, was estimated from the time of tooth eruption for domestic camelids. Camelid tooth eruption age is 6 to 9 months for the M1, 17 to 24 months for the M2 and 33 to 44 months for the M3 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Wheeler2">[59]</xref>. The beginning of crown formation is more difficult to assess. In comparison, in domestic sheep, the M1 crown starts to form in utero, the M2 during the second month after birth and the M3 when the lamb is 11 months old <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Zazzo1">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Weinreb1">[66]</xref>. If camelid molar growth follows the same pattern, the analysis of molars M1 to M3 should theoretically allow us to reconstruct a continuous record of the first 3–3.5 years of life of these animals. However, the upper part of each tooth is often worn and therefore the first part of the record of each tooth is missing. In addition, the consumption of milk can influence the isotopic values of tissue in formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Wright1">[67]</xref>. As the first permanent molar grows during the early childhood, breastfeeding can potentially confound its isotopic signal.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Sampling and Analysis of Camelid Tissues</title>
<p>Enamel and bone surfaces were mechanically cleaned to remove soft tissue, adherent soil or other contaminants by abrasion with a tungsten drill bit. Mechanical cleaning also detached the adherent cement on teeth and the outmost layer of bone, which is most susceptible to diagenetic contaminants. Cleaned bone samples were hand ground using an agate mortar and pestle and passed through a series of sieves. The finer fraction (&lt;300 µm) was selected for determining δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> values.</p>
<p>Crown height was measured for each tooth and the highest lobe was selected for sampling. Sequential sampling perpendicularly to the crown growth axis, from the apex to the enamel-dentine junction, was performed using a diamond drill bit. For El Brujo and modern camelid molars, each sample was a 1-mm-wide groove, taken from the buccal side through the whole thickness of the enamel layer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). Uhle Platform camelid molars were fragile and prone to breakage during this direct sampling. The enamel layer on the buccal face was thus first separated from the rest of the crown. Any adhering dentine was removed using a tungsten carbide drill bit and then the sequential sampling of the enamel was conducted as described previously to obtain an intra-tooth enamel sample series. Between 5 and 35 samples (5–11 mg) were obtained per tooth, depending on crown height.</p>
<fig id="pone-0087559-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Sampling of molar enamel.</title>
<p>Permanent M3 molar from specimen EBT2–1998 from El Brujo showing the series of enamel samples (grooves) that have been drilled along the highest lobe of the crown, from the apex to the enamel-root junction.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Bone organic matter was eliminated using a NaOCl (2–3%) treatment. Then, both enamel and bone powder samples were purified with 0.1 M acetic acid (4 h, 0.1 ml mg<sup>−1</sup>) and 1M acetic acid (1 h, 0.1 ml mg<sup>−1</sup>), respectively, due to the higher susceptibility of bone to diagenetic contamination. The acetic acid treatment was used to remove exogenous carbonate and was carried out on both archaeological and modern specimens to ensure consistency when comparing results. All samples were then rinsed at least five times and oven-dried at 50°C. Bioapatite samples weighing 600 µg were reacted with 100% phosphoric acid at 70°C for 4 min in a Kiel IV device, interfaced with a Delta V Advantage isotope ratio mass spectrometer. Analytical precision was ±0.03 ‰ for δ<sup>13</sup>C (1σ) and ±0.05 ‰ for δ<sup>18</sup>O (1σ), based on the repeated analysis of an internal calcite standard (Marble LM), previously calibrated against NBS-19.</p>
<p>Collagen was extracted from the coarser grain size fraction (0.3–0.7 mm), following Longin’s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Longin1">[68]</xref> protocol, modified by Bocherens et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bocherens1">[69]</xref>. About 200 mg of powdered bone was demineralized in a 1 M HCl solution for 20 min at room temperature then filtered through a MF-Millipore 5 µm filter. Potential contamination of fulvic and humic acids was removed by a 0.125 M NaOH (20 hours) treatment. After filtration, collagen was solubilized into a 0.02 M HCl (pH = 2) solution at 100°C for 17 hours, filtered again and freeze-dried.</p>
<p>Bone collagen samples (500 µg) were combusted using an Elemental Analyser Flash 2000, coupled with a Delta V Advantage (Thermo Scientific) isotope ratio mass spectrometer for δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N analysis. Analytical error was estimated to be 0.34 ‰ for δ<sup>13</sup>C and 0.02 ‰ for δ<sup>15</sup>N, based on replicate analysis of the international standard IAEA 600.</p>
<p>The atomic C:N ratio, the carbon and nitrogen content, as well as the yield of collagen, are indicators that can be used to assess potential diagenetic alterations or contaminations of bone collagen. The atomic C:N ratio of unaltered bone collagen ranges from 2.9 to 3.6 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-DeNiro1">[70]</xref>. Fresh bone contains approximately 20–22 wt % collagen, which consists of 34 to 43% of carbon and 11 to 16% of nitrogen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-VanKlinken1">[71]</xref>. The δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values remain constant until bone collagen yields fall to less than 1% of the total bone mass <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Dobberstein1">[72]</xref>. The percentage of carbon and nitrogen in unaltered bone collagen should exceed 13% and 4.8%, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Ambrose1">[73]</xref>. Structural carbonate of bone apatite is sensitive to diagenetic alteration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Koch1">[74]</xref>. Unlike for bone collagen, there is no well-established indicator to assess the preservation of structural carbonate in bone and enamel apatite <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Shin1">[75]</xref>. In order to check the preservation of δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O for bone values, they can be compared with the bone collagen yields to assess the influence of collagen loss on structural carbonate. δ<sup>13</sup>C values of bone structural carbonates can also be compared to those of bone collagen. In herbivores, the spacing (Δδ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone-col</sub>) between the two tissues is 7.6±0.5 ‰ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Clementz1">[76]</xref>. Enamel is considered to be highly resistant to diagenetic alterations and is generally thought to preserve its original δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Zazzo2">[77]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Wang1">[78]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Diet and Mobility through the Analysis of δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N Values</title>
<p>Measurements of δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N values are used for investigating past diet because 1) there is a direct relationship between the values of an animal’s tissues and that of its food <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-DeNiro2">[79]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Jim1">[82]</xref> and 2) certain food categories present distinctive isotopic values. The δ<sup>13</sup>C values of bone collagen (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub>) are generally 5‰ higher compared to those of consumed plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-LeeThorp1">[81]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Fernandez1">[83]</xref>. However, this fractionation value can vary as carbon collagen is mainly derived from dietary proteins (75% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Fernandez1">[83]</xref>). In contrast, δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> or δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values represent an average carbon input into the whole diet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Jim1">[82]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Ambrose2">[84]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Tieszen1">[85]</xref>. Therefore, the combined analysis of collagen and structural carbonate provides complementary dietary data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Warinner1">[86]</xref>. Different fractionation values between structural carbonate and diet have been determined in the literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Ambrose2">[84]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Passey2">[87]</xref>. We used a value of ∼+14 ‰, estimated for ruminant methanogenic herbivores <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Balasse2">[63]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Zazzo1">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Passey2">[87]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Cerling1">[88]</xref>. The same fractionation value is often used for structural carbonate from both bone and enamel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Warinner1">[86]</xref>. However, analysis of paired enamel and bone samples for pigs raised on controlled diets showed that enamel apatite was consistently enriched in <sup>13</sup>C (2–3 ‰) over bone apatite <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Warinner1">[86]</xref>. Because the two tissues formed concomitantly, without seasonal or ontogenetic variations in diet, the difference in tissue-diet spacing appears inherent to the two tissues. This difference was taken into account for camelid palaeodietary reconstructions.</p>
<p>Differences in the fixation of carbon during photosynthesis result in very different δ<sup>13</sup>C values between plants using the C<sub>3</sub> (Calvin) and C<sub>4</sub> (Hatch-Slack) photosynthetic pathways <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Smith1">[89]</xref> at the base of terrestrial food webs. CAM plants that use a third photosynthetic pathway (Crassulacean Acid Metabolism) have intermediate δ<sup>13</sup>C values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Ranson1">[90]</xref>. Marine plants mostly use the C<sub>3</sub> pathways but rely on dissolved inorganic instead of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and also have intermediate δ<sup>13</sup>C values. Many factors can affect the δ<sup>13</sup>C value of terrestrial plants, such as the canopy effect, water availability and soil salinity (reviewed by Szpak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref> for northern Peru). In the Andes, both C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants are present but C<sub>3</sub> plants are predominant. A few studies have documented the isotope composition of a variety of terrestrial and marine plants in the Central Andes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Tieszen2">[91]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Skrzypek1">[92]</xref>. Szpak et al.’s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Lecoq1">[21]</xref> comprehensive data provide the most relevant isotopic baseline for the present study, as it was conducted along an altitudinal transect of the Moche Valley. Mean δ<sup>13</sup>C values are –27.6±1.9 ‰ and –13.5±1.0‰ for wild C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants, respectively. Maize is one of the key products in the diet of farming people and is the only major C<sub>4</sub> cultivar in the Central Andes. Consumable maize parts exhibited a mean δ<sup>13</sup>C value of –11.8‰ ±0.4 ‰, while leaf mean value was –12.9±0.4 ‰ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref>.</p>
<p>Among terrestrial plants only plants that fix atmospheric nitrogen, such as legumes, present clearly distinctive δ<sup>15</sup>N values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Schoeninger1">[93]</xref>. Variations in terrestrial plants can be linked to the application of fertilizers for agriculture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak2">[94]</xref>, as well as consequences of local environmental factors, such as aridity and salinity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Ambrose3">[95]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Ambrose4">[96]</xref>. <italic>Lomas</italic> vegetation in highly arid and saline soil conditions presents a wide range of δ<sup>15</sup>N values and a tendency towards relatively high values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Evans1">[97]</xref>. It is usually generally assumed that marine plants have significantly higher δ<sup>15</sup>N values than terrestrial plants but no difference was found between macroalgae and coastal terrestrial plants for northern Peru <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref>. δ<sup>15</sup>N analysis has proven fruitful for investigating the food chain level and degree of carnivory in past human diets because of the step-wise enrichment between the consumer’s tissues and its diet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-DeNiro3">[80]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Schoeninger1">[93]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bocherens2">[98]</xref> and the importance of marine protein because marine food chains are usually longer than terrestrial ones, resulting in higher values for secondary consumers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Minagawa1">[99]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Schoeninger2">[100]</xref>. δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values can be affected by many factors, such as pregnancy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Fuller1">[101]</xref>, breastfeeding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Fuller2">[102]</xref>, growth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Trueman1">[103]</xref>, disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Katzenberg1">[104]</xref> or starvation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Mekota1">[105]</xref>.</p>
<p>The existence of geographic variations in isotopic values potentially enables us to distinguish whether camelids found in coastal sites were raised locally or in the highlands. Natural variations in δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N among camelids bred at different altitudes are expected, with higher δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N values for lowland than highland camelids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). A positive relationship between the δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> values and elevation was observed for Argentinian llamas fed on natural pastures at different altitudes (3500–4000 masl) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Yacobaccio1">[106]</xref> but the reason for this relation – difference in vegetation assemblages or difference in δ<sup>13</sup>C linked to altitude – is not clear. In contrast with this negative relationship between vegetation δ<sup>13</sup>C values and elevation, a positive correlation was found in northern Peru <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref> and northern Chile <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Tieszen2">[91]</xref>. However, the frequency of C<sub>4</sub> plants increases with the decrease of altitude and the <italic>puna</italic> is nearly devoid of C<sub>4</sub> plants. Besides, the upper limit for maize cultivation ends at about 3,500 masl and <italic>puna</italic> crops are limited to C<sub>3</sub> plant species. The altitudinal distribution of C<sub>4</sub> plants is linked to temperature, sunlight and precipitation. Thus, the highlands can be characterized as an exclusively C<sub>3</sub> plant habitat type and camelids are expected to present a pure C<sub>3</sub> plant diet. Camelids grazing at low elevations have increased access to wild C<sub>4</sub> plants or could have been fed C<sub>4</sub> crops. C<sub>4</sub> plant and mixed C<sub>3</sub>/C<sub>4</sub> plant diets thus indicate that camelids were raised in the lowlands or intermediate lands. Nevertheless, because the many C<sub>3</sub> plants that grow on the coast could have potentially provided fodder – various non-maize crops, pods or leaves –, a camelid with a pure C<sub>3</sub> diet did not necessarily originate from the highlands. Finally, potential access to marine resources in the lowlands could also influence camelid δ<sup>13</sup>C values.</p>
<p>Mean δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> values of –19.2±0.2 ‰ were measured for domestic camelids in southern Peru <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Schoeninger1">[93]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Schoeninger3">[107]</xref>, while mean δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> values of –12.0±0.4 ‰ were measured at La Raya (Peru) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Schoeninger1">[93]</xref>. These values – as all following modern animal and plant δ<sup>13</sup>C values –were corrected by 1.5 ‰ to adjust for the Suess effect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Marino1">[108]</xref>. There are no available data for modern camelids feeding on natural forage at coastal or very low elevations (&lt;1000 masl), due to the scarcity of wild or domestic camelids in these habitats today. The δ<sup>13</sup>C values of pure C<sub>3</sub> and pure C<sub>4</sub>-feeders can be predicted from the δ<sup>13</sup>C values of pre-industrial C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants and used to determine the proportions of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> in the diet of archaeological specimens. The mean δ<sup>13</sup>C for pre-industrial C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants is estimated to be ∼–26 ‰ by correcting the average value of modern plants for fossil fuel effect (∼1.5 ‰). Szpak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref> suggested an average maize δ<sup>13</sup>C value of –10.3 ‰ to be appropriate for human palaeodietary models in the Central Andes. However, kernels are consumed by humans whereas the leaf was more likely to be consumed by camelids. A mean leaf value of –11.4 ‰, which is similar to the average values of wild C<sub>4</sub> plants, thus appears more appropriate for camelid dietary studies. Using the +14 ‰ bioapatite-diet spacing and a collagen-diet spacing of 5 ‰, a C<sub>3</sub> plant-based diet therefore results in an average δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> of ∼–12 ‰, δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> of ∼–14 ‰ and a δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> of ∼–21‰. The mean δ<sup>13</sup>C of pre-industrial C<sub>4</sub> plants is estimated to be ∼–11.5 ‰ and a pure C<sub>4</sub>-diet should result in an average δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> of∼ +2.5 ‰, δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bonel</sub> of 0 ‰ and a δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> of –6.5 ‰. The estimated δ<sup>13</sup>C values of pure C<sub>3</sub> and pure C<sub>4</sub>-feeders were used as end-members in a simple mixing model for calculating the proportion of C<sub>4</sub> in the diet of archaeological camelids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Tables 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">2</xref>). However, absolute values for reconstructed C<sub>4</sub> proportion values of should be considered with caution because the range of variation in δ<sup>13</sup>C values in natural C<sub>3</sub> plants is wide (∼18 ‰).</p>
<p>Higher δ<sup>15</sup>N values are expected for domestic camelids feeding extensively on coastal or low-altitude forage, due to the consumption of terrestrial plants with relatively high δ<sup>15</sup>N values and the potential intake of marine resources <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Schoeninger2">[100]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-DeNiro4">[109]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). Szpak et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref> showed that the foliar δ<sup>15</sup>N values were negatively correlated with altitude and mean annual precipitation along an altitudinal transect of the Moche Valley. The magnitude of difference between animals feeding on wild plants at lower (and drier) altitudes and animals feeding at higher (and wetter) altitudes has been estimated to be 4–6 ‰ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref>. However, the consumption of cultivated plants dependent on irrigation at lower altitudes could partly confound this difference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref>. As mentioned previously, there are no modern data for camelids feeding on natural forage at coastal or very low elevations. Camelids from the coastal site of La Paloma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-DeNiro4">[109]</xref> are thought to be wild guanacos and therefore are likely to have consumed natural forage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>. They present slightly to considerably elevated δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values compared to modern <italic>puna</italic> camelids, suggesting that plants characterized by high δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values can be naturally selected by wild camelids.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Origin and Mobility through the Analysis of Structural Carbonate δ<sup>18</sup>O Values</title>
<p>The δ<sup>18</sup>O values of structural carbonate in bone and tooth enamel reflect the δ<sup>18</sup>O value of body water at body temperature. Body water oxygen comes mostly from drinking water and from food, and to a lesser extent from the atmosphere via inhalation, with a predictable fractionation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Longinelli1">[110]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Luz2">[112]</xref>. Different equations that relate the δ<sup>18</sup>O values of ingested water (δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>d w</sub>) to the δ<sup>18</sup>O values of structural carbonate and phosphate phases of enamel have been developed in the literature. In this study, we used two equations (Eq. 1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Amiot1">[113]</xref> and (Eq. 2) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Lcuyer1">[114]</xref> developed for all mammals:<disp-formula id="pone.0087559.e001"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.e001" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pone.0087559.e002"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.e002" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula></p>
<p>Basic Andean environmental trends do not seem to have changed over the past 2,000 years (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson1">[11]</xref>). δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values measured in pre-Hispanic remains can be compared to those of modern δ<sup>18</sup>O values for environmental water (δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub>) for assessing an animal’s movement to different geographical areas and estimating the place of residence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-White2">[115]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-White3">[116]</xref>. Because variations in δ<sup>18</sup>O values of meteoric water (δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub>) are theoretically transferred and retained in the body of living organisms, studies of modern precipitation provide some of the necessary baseline data for residential mobility studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert3">[36]</xref>. δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> values are governed by the amount of rainfall, altitude, latitude, distance from the coast and temperature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Epstein1">[117]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bowen1">[119]</xref>, through the preferential loss of <sup>16</sup>O during evaporation and the progressive loss of <sup>18</sup>O during precipitation as air masses move inland and upwards <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Dansgaard1">[118]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Gat1">[120]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-White4">[121]</xref>. The wide amplitude of temperature, altitude, rate of precipitation and hydrological systems between the different ecological zones of the Andes leads to high natural variations in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> values, which tend to vary predictably across a landmass such as the Andean region in relation to local topography <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson1">[11]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The availability of measured δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> is limited in the Central Andean region. Preliminary data obtained on an altitudinal transect along the Moche Valley indicate a difference as high as 14 ‰ between the coast and the highlands (4,100 masl) (<italic>Elise Dufour, unpublished data</italic>). δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> values for a specific geographical location can be estimated using the Online Isotopes in Precipitation Calculator (OPIC Version 2.2: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.waterisotopes.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.waterisotopes.org/</ext-link>). This calculator takes into account the geographic location (latitude, longitude, distance to the sea and altitude) to model the annual and monthly variations in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> for the entire globe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bowen1">[119]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bowen2">[122]</xref>. These average values do not take into account the inter-annual variations, the accuracy of which in a given geographical area is linked to the availability of actually measured δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> values, which are limited in the case of the Andes. OPIC predicted mean annual δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> values are –11.8 ‰ (annual range: –17.3 to –7.0 ‰ SMOW) and –12.8 ‰ (annual range: –17.4 to –8.3 ‰ SMOW) for the <italic>puna</italic> of Tocra and Quiruvilca, respectively, and –4.8 ‰ (annual range: –8.6 to –2.7 ‰ SMOW) for the coastal region of the modern city of Trujillo (−7°99′S).</p>
<p>However, domestic animals (and humans) do not ingest meteoric water but surface waters, or groundwater from wells. Environmental water comprises surface waters (rivers, lakes, reservoirs, irrigation channels) and groundwater. The δ<sup>18</sup>O values of environmental water (δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub>) are not solely tied to rainfall values, which complicates their use <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson1">[11]</xref>. Different processes may result in magnitudes of variation in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values within regions that may in fact exceed differences between regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson1">[11]</xref>. Surface water values are influenced by evaporation, movements between ecozones, mixing with groundwater, El Niño Southern Oscillation events and local topographic relief <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Webb1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Sharp1">[123]</xref>. Overall, δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values in the Central Andes have been reported to range from –6 to –3 ‰ on the coast, from –9 to –5 ‰ in the <italic>yunga</italic> (intermediate lands) and from –18 to –11 ‰ in the <italic>puna</italic> (data from IAEA/WMO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-IAEAWMO1">[124]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson1">[11]</xref>). In addition, consumption patterns, such as the intake of water collected in cisterns and water exposed to evaporative processes, may also influence δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values. Finally, weaning has been shown to cause a trophic enrichment of <sup>18</sup>O in human tissues formed during infancy, due to the equilibration with maternal body water during breastfeeding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Roberts1">[125]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Wright2">[126]</xref>. Breastfeeding usually lasts for six months in camelids and can influence teeth (such as the first permanent molar) and tissues that form during the first months of life. However, this influence might not be very significant for adult individuals because in most cases the upper part of the M1 is missing due to tooth wear.</p>
<p>Because of topographic variations in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> values, higher aridity and evaporation of surface water, camelids raised on the coast or at low altitudes should present higher δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values than camelids raised in the highlands. Based on Eq. 1 and Eq. 2 and OPIC intra-annual variation in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>m w</sub> and IAEA/WMO δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values, δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> of animals living in the lowlands, <italic>yunga</italic> and <italic>puna</italic> can be predicted to vary from –5.8 to +0.5 ‰, –6.2 to –2.3 ‰ and –15 to –5.5 ‰, respectively. The enrichment of structural carbonate in enamel compared to that of bone structural carbonate has been estimated to be 1.7 ‰ in oxygen in pigs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Warinner1">[86]</xref>. A correction of –1.5 ‰ was then applied to previous estimated values of δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> to estimate δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values for animals living along the coast and in the <italic>yunga</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g005">Figs. 5</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g006">6</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0087559-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Isotopic composition of bone collagen.</title>
<p>Plot of bone collagen δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N values of archaeological (El Brujo) and modern highland domestic camelids from Tocra and Quiruvilca, compared to the range of variations (represented by dashed lines) of modern specimens, compiled by Thornton et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>. The proportion of C<sub>4</sub> in the diet was reconstructed using mean estimated pre-industrial δ<sup>13</sup>C values of pure-C<sub>3</sub> and pure-C<sub>4</sub> feeders.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0087559-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Isotopic composition of bone structural carbonate.</title>
<p>Plot of δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values (‰ VPDB) of bone structural carbonate of archaeological and modern highland domestic camelids. The proportion of C<sub>4</sub> in the diet was reconstructed using estimated mean pre-industrial δ<sup>13</sup>C values of pure-C<sub>3</sub> and pure-C<sub>4</sub> feeders. Estimated ranges of δ<sup>18</sup>O values for animals raised in the three ecozones are represented by rectangles.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>All δ<sup>13</sup>C values of modern specimens presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">2</xref> have been corrected by +1.5 ‰ to account for the atmospheric enrichment in <sup>12</sup>C, caused by the burning of fossil fuel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Marino1">[108]</xref>, and for comparison with δ<sup>13</sup>C values of archaeological specimens.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Bone Collagen</title>
<p>Only three on the ten archaeological specimens, all from El Brujo, provided collagen (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). The bone collagen yields varied from 1.9 to 21.7% for both modern and archaeological specimens. C:N ratio varied from 3.1 to 3.3 for all specimens while the carbon and nitrogen concentrations in bone collagen ranged from 41.2 to 44.1% and from 14.9 to 16.4%, respectively. These criteria were used to check the quality of bone collagen preservation for the El Brujo specimens and showed that δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values can be used for dietary reconstruction. δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values for modern specimens varied from –20.8 to –20.2 ‰ and from 3.1 to 5.1‰, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). For archaeological specimens, δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values were higher than those of modern specimens and varied from –14.8 and –13.2 ‰ and from 7.4 to 10.0 ‰, respectively.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Bone Structural Carbonate</title>
<p>δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values of modern specimens varied from –14.7 and –12.3 ‰ and from –10.0 to –4.2‰, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Both δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values for archaeological specimens were higher than those of modern specimens. δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> values varied from –9.3 to –7.4 ‰ and from –7.2 to –5.6 ‰ for Uhle Platform camelids and for El Brujo, respectively. δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values varied from –3.4 to 1.3 ‰ and from –2.1 to 1.5 ‰ for Uhle Platform and El Brujo, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Δδ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone-col</sub> values varied from 7.6 to 7.9 ‰ and were typical of herbivores (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">Table 2</xref>). There was no relationship between variation in δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values and extraction yield indicative of marked diagenetic alteration of bone.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Enamel Structural Carbonate</title>
<p>For modern camelids, δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values ranged from –13.6 ‰ (Areq-3) to –8.9 ‰ (Areq-1), with mean tooth values ranging from –12.1±0.8 to –9.6±0.2 ‰ (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g007">Figs. 7</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g008">8</xref>). Intra-tooth variation ranged from 0.6 (M2 of Quiru-1) to 2.3‰ (M1 of Areq-1), while intra-individual variations (for specimens with three sampled teeth) were 2.0 ‰ for Quiru-1 and 2.3 ‰ for Areq-1. Archaeological specimens usually present higher δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values than modern specimens (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g007">Figs. 7</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g009">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g010">10</xref>). For Uhle Platform, δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values varied from –10.5 to –1.5 ‰, with mean tooth values ranging from –10.0±0.4 to –2.4±0.5 ‰. Intra-tooth variation ranged from 0.3 (M1 of UH-8) to 2.8 (M3 of UH-11). Maximum intra-individual variation is 3.3 ‰ for the three molars of UH-8. At El Brujo, δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>en</sub> values varied from –9.9 to –0.1 ‰ with mean tooth values varying from –8.1±0.2 to –1.4±0.4 ‰ (EBE1-1995). Intra-tooth variation ranged from 0.6 to 5.4 ‰ (EBT2-1995) while intra-individual variation was 4.7 ‰ for EBT2-1998 and 6.9 ‰ for EBE1-1995.</p>
<fig id="pone-0087559-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Mean isotopic composition of enamel structural carbonate.</title>
<p>Plot of mean δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values (‰ VPDB) of enamel structural carbonate for all teeth (molars) of archaeological and modern highland domestic camelids. The proportion of C<sub>4</sub> in the diet was reconstructed using estimated mean pre-industrial δ<sup>13</sup>C values of pure-C<sub>3</sub> and pure-C<sub>4</sub> feeders. Estimated ranges of δ<sup>18</sup>O values for animals raised in the three ecozones are represented by rectangles.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0087559-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Intra-tooth isotopic composition of enamel structural carbonate of modern camelids.</title>
<p>Intra-tooth variations in δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values (‰ VPDB) measured along the molar crowns of modern highland domestic camelids and estimation of the contribution of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants during crown growth. For each specimen, the left graph is for the M1 molar (except for Areq-3), the middle graph for the M2 molar and the right graph for the M3 molar. On each graph, the left axis refers to δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values and the right to δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0087559-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption>
<title>Intra-tooth isotopic composition of enamel structural carbonate of Uhle Platform camelids.</title>
<p>Intra-tooth variations in δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values (‰ VPDB) measured along the molar crowns of archaeological and modern highland domestic camelids and estimation of the contribution of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants during crown growth. For each specimen, the left graph is for the M1 molar, the middle graph for the M2 molar and the right graph for the M3 molar. On each graph, the left axis refers to δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values and the right to δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g009" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<fig id="pone-0087559-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption>
<title>Intra-tooth isotopic composition of enamel structural carbonate of El Brujo camelids.</title>
<p>Intra-tooth variations in δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>18</sup>O values (‰ VPDB) measured along the molar crowns of archaeological and modern highland domestic camelids and estimation of the contribution of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants during crown growth. For each specimen, the left graph is for the M1 molar, the middle graph for the M2 molar and the right graph for the M3 molar. On each graph, the left axis refers to δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values and the right to δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g010" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Modern camelid δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values ranged from –10.1 (Areq-1) to –1.3 ‰ (Quiru-1), with mean tooth values ranging from –8.8±0.2 to –2.0±0.6 ‰ (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g007">Fig. 7</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g008">8</xref>). Intra-tooth variation ranged from 1.4 to 4.7 ‰. Archaeological specimens usually presented higher δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values than the modern ones but values overlapped (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g007">Figs. 7</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g008"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g009">9</xref>–10). Uhle Platform values varied from –3.6 ‰ (UH-3) to 1.8‰ (UH-8). Intra-tooth maximum variation ranged from 0.2 to 2.6 ‰. At El Brujo, δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values ranged from –2.9 ‰ (EBT2-1995) to 3.1 ‰ (EBT6-1994). Intra-tooth variation ranged from 0.3 to 2.8 ‰.</p>
<p>The M3 from modern specimens presented cyclic variations in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g008">Fig. 8</xref>) whereas no cyclic variation was observed for the M3 of archaeological specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g009">Figs. 9</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g010">10</xref>). Only the youngest individuals (M1 of UH-4, UH-7, EBT2-1995, EBT6-1994) exhibited cyclicity in δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g009">Figs. 9</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g010">10</xref>).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In the present study, the life history of Mochica archaeological camelids was reconstructed through the analysis of the stable isotope composition of bone and enamel and comparisons with modern highland (<italic>puna</italic>) specimens. Archaeological camelids are discriminated from modern specimens by δ<sup>13</sup>C values measured in both organic and inorganic bone fractions. δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> values of modern specimens from the <italic>puna</italic> of Tocra (Areq-1, Areq-2, Areq-3) and Quiruvilca (Quiru-1) were consistent with predicted and previously measured values from the literature and all indicate the sole consumption of C<sub>3</sub> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g005">Figs. 5</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g006">6</xref>). Considering that archaeological camelid diets consisted exclusively of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> plants, the reconstructed proportion of C<sub>4</sub> plants is consistent among specimens, varying from 43 to 54% and from 34 to 60%, based on bone collagen and bone structural carbonate analysis respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g005">Figs. 5</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g006">6</xref>). δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values for archaeological specimens fall within the predicted range for animals raised in the lowlands and are distinct from those from modern specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). However, while the three specimens from Tocra fall within the predicted range of variation for animals raised in the <italic>puna</italic>, δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values of the Quiruvilca alpaca (Quiru-1) were higher.</p>
<p>δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> or δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> and δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values point to a mixed C<sub>3</sub>/C<sub>4</sub> diet and relatively high δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values indicate an arid habitat, suggesting long-term herding of Mochica camelids outside the <italic>puna</italic> C<sub>3</sub> pastures. This lowland presence of Mochica domestic camelids is in contradiction with the modern distribution of camelids and the classical view that considers it impossible to maintain herds outside the <italic>puna</italic> grasslands. However, it does not necessarily challenge the model of verticality and exchange between the ecological zones of Andean pastoralism. Adult camelids analysed in the present paper could have spent their youth in the highlands and then been brought to the coast as part of a caravan. Their long-term, mixed C<sub>3</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> diet signal, associated with an aridity signal, would thus have resulted from a diachronic switch in diet associated with the change in geographic location. Because of bone remodeling, the isotopic signal resulting from this diachronic switch cannot be distinguished from that of an entire life spent on the coast feeding on a mixed C<sub>3</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> diet.</p>
<p>The analysis of tooth enamel reveals more diverse and complex life histories for Mochica camelids than bone analysis. Whereas all the modern specimens had a pure C<sub>3</sub> diet during their youth, most of the archaeological camelids consumed C<sub>4</sub> plants. The mean C<sub>4</sub> contribution to the juveniles’ diet was much more variable than the long-term C<sub>4</sub> contribution recorded in bone, ranging from 14 to 73% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Although the use of the mixing model leads to the reconstruction of a small proportion of C<sub>4</sub> for the M1 from the two youngest camelids from the Uhle Platform (UH-4 and UH-7) and from an adult (UH-8), their δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> values were very similar to those of modern <italic>puna</italic> camelids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Keeping in mind the high variability in δ<sup>13</sup>C values for C<sub>3</sub> plants, these three animals may have had a pure C<sub>3</sub> diet throughout their first year of life. Considering the other specimens, diet change during youth was usually moderate (10–25%), except for one adult from El Brujo (EBE1-1995), for which the C<sub>4</sub> contribution increased by 50% between the second and third years of life (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g011">Fig. 11</xref>). The δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values for modern animals from Tocra fitted into the estimated range for <italic>puna</italic> camelids, while the alpaca (Quiru-1) from Quiruvilca exhibited higher δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values than predicted values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). In the absence of a comprehensive survey of δ<sup>18</sup>O values of surface water ingested by camelids, the reason for this discrepancy remains unknown. δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values of archaeological specimens partially overlap those of modern camelids. However, they all fitted into the estimated range of variation for the lowlands or intermediate lands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g007">Fig. 7</xref>), suggesting a youth spent in environments characterized by high δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values or surface water affected by a high evaporation rate. Most individuals exhibited moderate variations in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values during youth, suggesting no major change in habitat, except for one adult from the Uhle Platform (UH-11) that might have moved to a habitat characterized by lower δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values or less arid conditions, probably at a higher altitude.</p>
<fig id="pone-0087559-g011" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g011</object-id><label>Figure 11</label><caption>
<title>Reconstruction of diachronic changes in the contribution of C<sub>4</sub> plants to camelid diet.</title>
<p>Dietary contribution of C<sub>4</sub> plants over the first years of life of specimen EBE1-1995 and in the long term is estimated by the combined analysis of enamel (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub>) from the three molars and the bulk analysis of collagen (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub>) and structural carbonate (δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub>) from bone.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0087559.g011" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The comparison of the enamel isotopic signal with that of bone indicated that most adults were kept outside the <italic>puna</italic> all their life, as shown by the incorporation of C<sub>4</sub> plants. However, the comparison between these two tissues also identified an ontogenetic switch in diet and possible residential mobility throughout life for three animals from the Uhle Platform (UH-4, UH-7 and UH-8). This ontogenetic switch indicates a pure (or almost pure) C<sub>3</sub> diet during the first year of life, followed by a mixed C<sub>3</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> plant diet afterwards. A pure C<sub>3</sub> diet alone is not indicative of the animal’s geographic origin because C<sub>3</sub> plants dominate in all habitats. Many C<sub>3</sub> species that thrive on the coast could have potentially provided fodder – various non-maize crops, shrub leaves or pods − for camelids. <italic>Prosopis</italic> sp. remains have been reported from camelid coprolites dated of the Chimú Period <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bonavia2">[127]</xref>. Due to relatively low M1 δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values for the two youngest camelids (UH-4 and UH-7; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g007">Figs. 7</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g009">9</xref>) – and the wide variation in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values for modern <italic>puna</italic> camelids – it is not possible to identify their whereabouts during their first year of growth. Theoretically, they could have been born in the <italic>puna</italic> but could have fed in the lowlands during at least several months of the year, and again before death (because of the mixed C<sub>3</sub>/C<sub>4</sub> diet recorded by bone collagen). Regarding the adult specimen (UH-8), the arid signal exhibited in the M1 δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values (the highest values recorded for all Uhle Platform individuals) suggests that this animal was bred in the lowlands where it switched diet during the second year of life (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0087559-t003">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g009">Fig. 9</xref>).</p>
<p>Despite the importance of domestic camelids in the Mochica culture, management strategies and pastoralism remain poorly documented. In the present study, adults and juveniles of more than 1 year were analysed. Combined isotopic measurements of bone and tooth enamel clearly showed that all the adults and most juveniles spent their all life outside the <italic>puna</italic>, in the lowlands (and/or intermediate lands for UH-11). Furthermore, all juveniles were present locally at least several months before slaughtering. The probable pure C<sub>3</sub> diet during early life for two young individuals from Uhle Platform (UH-4 and UH-7) raises questions concerning their geographic origin. These individuals could have either been raised locally or in the highlands. If so, they would have subsequently reached the coast during trips for product exchanges (fish, cotton, <italic>aji</italic>, corn, gold, silver, etc.) between ecological zones. Although young individuals are not considered robust enough to carry large burdens during such trips <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert2">[13]</xref>, they might have accompanied their mothers. This latter hypothesis cannot be totally excluded, even though ethnographic data indicate that young llamas do not integrate caravans before adulthood, when they are around two years old <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Lecoq1">[21]</xref>. We can thus assume that UH-4 and UH-7were born in the lowlands like the other juveniles and the adults.</p>
<p>At both El Brujo and Uhle Platform, animals used for funerary and ritual purposes were kept in the lower part of the valleys. Local herds were maintained both for slaughtering purposes and reproduction, as indicated by demographic data based on the study of archaeozoological remains and domestic camelid ethology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert2">[13]</xref>. Local breeding not only implies the presence of young age classes outside the <italic>puna</italic> during the Mochica period but also that of gregarious adult females. The latter do not travel during the gestation period, which lasts from eleven to twelve months <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Wheeler1">[9]</xref>. Moreover, this suggests that camelid breeding was an important activity. Young camelids were sacrificed before reaching their maximum meat yield by weight and consequently herds had to be large enough to absorb the loss of young immature animals. Herds might have been large or alternatively small but numerous, at the scale of a site or a valley. While large herding has also been suggested by the increased number of camelid remains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Pozorski2">[16]</xref>, there is currently no available estimate of herd size during Mochica times.</p>
<p>Camelid management outside the modern geographical range has been documented for middle valley areas in Andean regions where richer pasturelands are available and foddering might have been practiced during pre-Hispanic times <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson3">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Finucane2">[128]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Izeta1">[129]</xref>. As for the Peruvian coast where arid conditions prevail, questions subsist concerning the availability and precise location of food resources to maintain herds. <italic>Lomas</italic> are present close to Cerro Campana, between the Moche and Chicama valleys, and can be considered as a potential herding location, at least during the austral winter, as suggested for other sites in Peru <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>. In intermediate lands, C<sub>4</sub> plants are relatively rare and high δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> (or δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub>) values, such as those recorded at the Middle Horizon Wari-affiliated site of Conchopata <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Finucane2">[128]</xref>, can be confidently interpreted as the result of the consumption of maize. On the coast, wild C<sub>4</sub> species, such as the saltgrass <italic>grama salada</italic> (<italic>Distichlis spicata</italic>), can locally form relatively large patches and pastures where herders could have taken their animals. C<sub>3</sub> plants nevertheless dominate the Peruvian flora and it could be difficult for herders to find wild C<sub>4</sub> pastures capable of contributing as much as 50–70% of the diet of some camelids. Maize but also marine algae can supplement the diet of wild or domestic herds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Balasse3">[130]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Yesner1">[131]</xref>, at least seasonally when the terrestrial pastures are restricted. Records of this practice during ancient times are hard to come by as seaweed is rarely preserved in archaeological sites. High δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values measured at the coastal sites of central and south Peru of La Paloma and Chilca were interpreted as lowland breeding, on the arid coast itself <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-DeNiro4">[109]</xref>. These high values were attributed to the consumption of non-terrestrial resources, such as marine plants or aquatic vegetation growing along lagoons, riverbanks or the shores of saltwater lakes because of assumed distinctive (higher) δ<sup>15</sup>N values for marine plants compared to terrestrial plants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-DeNiro4">[109]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Verano1">[132]</xref>. In fact, no distinction between the two types of plants was found along the northern coast of Peru <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref> that could also explain the high δ<sup>15</sup>N<sub>col</sub> values of archaeological camelids. Marine algae have a mean δ<sup>13</sup>C value of –15.0 ‰ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Szpak1">[23]</xref>. Their contribution to the diet of Mochica camelids should have been as high as 75% to explain the highest measured δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>col</sub> and δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>bone</sub> values. Although this high proportion of marine algae seems unlikely, they may still have contributed to the camelid diet, along with C<sub>4</sub> plants. This hypothesis cannot be ruled out by the isotopic tracers used in the present study.</p>
<p>The geographical origin of camelids appears difficult to assess from δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>bone</sub> values, but they might nevertheless provide insights into herding practices. A negative trend in the relationship between δ<sup>13</sup>C<sub>enamel</sub> and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values is observed when all archaeological teeth are considered, suggesting that there is no connection between aridity and dietary signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). A positive relation was expected because the lower the elevation, the higher the aridity, the δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values and the frequency of wild C<sub>4</sub> in the vegetation assemblage. The disconnection between aridity and dietary signals could result from the consumption of water and maize (and other cultivated crops) grown at various altitudes from the arid coast to intermediate lands. Cultivation on the coast is rendered possible by the presence of irrigation networks supplied by rivers from the Andes, which have different δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values from those predicted at local altitudes, as well as different precipitation rates and temperatures. The control of drinking by the herders is not only suggested by the absolute δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values, but also by the difference in the shape of isotopic intra-tooth profiles between archaeological and modern specimens. The two modern adult alpacas (Areq-1 and Quiru-1) were raised on natural <italic>puna</italic> pastures all year around, without fodder, and widescale geographic movement over throughout life. The intra-tooth cyclic variation in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> recorded in their M3 is linked to seasonal variation in temperature and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Goepfert3">[36]</xref>. In contrast – except for the M1 from the youngest specimens (UH-4, UH-7, EBT6-1994, EBT2-1995) – most archaeological Mochica camelids do not display cyclicity in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> intra- tooth cyclic variations, independently of the proportion of C<sub>4</sub> plants in their diet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g009">Fig. 9</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g010">10</xref>). The flat profiles for the δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values of Mochica camelids not only suggest that no important change in geographic location occurred (except UH-11), but also that drinking water was not affected by seasonal variations, such as natural surface water and precipitation, but came from controlled sources such as wells or canals.</p>
<p>Combined isotopic measurements of bone and tooth enamel indicate that most Mochica camelids relied upon substantial maize foddering on coastal irrigated (and/or fertilized) fields or at different elevations in the valleys. Maize played a key role in the political economy and has constituted a primary component of the diet of diverse Andean polities and cultures from at least the late Archaic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bonavia2">[127]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Haas1">[133]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Johannessen1">[134]</xref>. In the Moche Valley, the intensification of maize production appeared during the Gallinazo phase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Lambert1">[135]</xref> and maize was a crucial crop during the development of the Mochica state <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Bonavia2">[127]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Gumerman1">[136]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Gumerman3">[138]</xref>. Herders could have let the animals graze on the stalks in maize fields, forage in cultivated plots or fields, or brought stalks to the herds in corrals and pens. Further archaeological research is needed to determine if maize culture and herds were spatially segregated or in close relation with each other. No corrals or pens used for keeping the herds have been found in the proximity of Huacas de Moche and El Brujo. Thus, if the camelids lived on the coast, their settlement was not in the direct vicinity of the sites. Our study showed that the animals were bred in the low and/or middle valleys and that none of the domestic camelids originated from the <italic>puna</italic>. As the Mochica polities exerted their political and social power at the scale of the valleys, the provisioning of domestic camelids might also have been organized at this level. All animals were bred in the lowlands but had different life histories, with the exception of the three specimens (UH-8, UH-9 and UH-10) recovered from the same ceremonial context (Element 21) at the Uhle Platform. They shared similar trends in life histories despite differences in age and may represent a single ritual event (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0087559-g009">Fig. 9</xref>). Part of the inter-individual variability could be linked to the fact that remains were recovered from different chronological phases of occupation. It also suggests that camelids came from various herds presenting difference in herding management strategies. The presence of camelids from different geographic origins (classified as local and non-local) at the same site has previously been related to the different functions of camelids: sacrifice <italic>versus</italic> meat or wool production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson3">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Finucane2">[128]</xref>. The site of Tiwanaku is situated in a zone of rich <italic>puna</italic> pastures and the provisioning of non-local – but still originating from the highlands – camelids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Knudson3">[35]</xref> illustrates the complexity of ritual contexts. The present work concerns camelids from funerary and ritual contexts. The lack of analysis of remains from domestic contexts does not enable us to discuss the specialization of Mochica herds for meat procurement or animal sacrifice, as was described for Inka times.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The present study underlines the adaptive capacities of the Mochica people to their environment. Irrigation allowed for the development of extensive agriculture in a very arid environment. Herders also adapted their practices to this difficult environment. This study also emphasizes the role of maize in different aspects of Mochica economic life. Further work will be conducted on Mochica camelids from different valleys to confirm these first results and to compare herding practices on a regional scale. Strong relationships might have been established between two major religious centers, such as the Huacas de Moche and El Brujo, and their hinterlands. A better understanding of these relationships is required in order to describe how herd management was spatially organized. Camelids from domestic contexts should also be analysed to compare them with camelids from ritual contexts, to determine whether or not they have the same origin and to gain insights into meat exchange in the different Andean ecozones. Our study also indicates that diversity in herding practices existed in the lowlands, as already described for higher altitudes, even though only animals with similar functions (funerary and ritual) were analysed. Species-specific identification of llamas and alpacas was not possible from the osteological study of archaeological remains. This would, however, provide a better understanding of the relation between camelid functions and herding practices.</p>
<p>An increasing number of studies have used stable isotopic analyses to document camelid diet and herding practices in Peru, Chile and Argentina, during the pre-Hispanic period <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Thornton1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Finucane2">[128]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Izeta1">[129]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Burger1">[139]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-MengoniGoalones1">[141]</xref>. Together with the data presented in this study, these analyses have identified variations in the geographic locations of camelid breeding and pastureland and/or foddering practices outside the modern geographic range. Our work underscores regional and temporal variations in Andean pastoralism and disparity with the classical model of vertical exchange. Most previously published studies were performed on bone tissue and make no reference to the age of the sampled individuals. Because of the remodeling of bone tissue, age is essential for reconstructing the individual life history of each specimen and for identifying the place of birth. The serial analysis of tooth enamel brings new information on camelid pastoralism and complements bone collagen analysis. The combined analysis of different tissues, which form at different times, enables us to detect potential diachronic change in diet and geographical location throughout an animal’s life. Besides, tooth enamel is better preserved over time than bone collagen. The poor quality of preservation of bone collagen in the Moche Valley was also observed for human remains at Cerro Oreja <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0087559-Lambert1">[135]</xref>. Moreover, enamel analysis offers the opportunity to independently assess the geographic habitat of organisms through climate records. δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values provide some information but inferences are limited so far because the environmental and biological factors that might influence δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values need to be better understood. The influence of the circulation of surface water that might mask the difference in δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>e w</sub> values between ecological zones, breastfeeding and milk consumption are some of the factors that have to be documented. The duration of tooth mineralization in domestic camelids would also need to be determined. Finally, a more precise reconstruction of the geographic location of pastureland and mobility is expected from the combination of the measurement of δ<sup>13</sup>C, δ<sup>15</sup>N and δ<sup>18</sup>O<sub>enamel</sub> values with <sup>87</sup>Sr/<sup>86</sup>Sr values.</p>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Marion Médevielle, Olivier Tombret and Antoine Zazzo for their help during sample preparation and Joël Ughetto for mass spectrometry analysis at the Service de Spectrometry of the Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle (Paris, France). We thank Cesar Galvez, the co-director of El Brujo Archaeological Project, for his help and access to El Brujo archaeological material. We also thank Carlos Gutiérrez Vereau for his assistance during modern sample collection in the Moche Valley, camelid breeders in Quiruvilca and Tocra, and Louise Byrne for English improvement. Paul Szpak and an anonymous reviewer provided insightful and constructive comments on a previous version of the manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Murra1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Murra J (1975) El control vertical de un máximo de pisos ecológicos en la economía de las sociedades andinas. In: Murra J, editor. Formaciones económicas del mundo andino. Lima: Instituto de Estudios Peruanos. 59–115.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Bonavia1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bonavia D (1996) Los Camélidos sudamericanos. Una introducción a su estudio. Lima: Ifea-Upch-Conservación International. 845 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-FloresOchoa1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Flores Ochoa JA, MacQuarrie K, Portus J (1994). Oro de los Andes. Las Llamas, Alpacas, Vicuñas y Guanacos de Sudamérica. Barcelone: Jordi Blassi, 2 volumes.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Browman1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Browman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Pastoral nomadism in the Andes</article-title>. <source>Current Anthropology</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Nuez1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nuñez L, Dillehay TS (1978) Movilidad giratoria, armonía social y desarrollo en los Andes Meridionales: Patrones de tráfico e interacciones económicas. Antofagasta, Universidad Católica Del Norte. 170p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-VanBuren1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Buren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Rethinking the Vertical Archipelago</article-title>. <source>American Anthropologist</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Goepfert1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goepfert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>New zooarchaeological and funerary perspectives on Mochica Culture (100–800 A.D.), Peru</article-title>. <source>Journal of Field Archaeology</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Shimada1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Prehistoric llama breeding and herding on the North Coast</article-title>. <source>American Antiquity</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Wheeler1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wheeler JC (1991) Origen, evolución y status social. In: Fernandez-Baca S, editor. Avances y perspectivas del conocimiento de los camélidos Sudamericanos. Santiago du Chili: Fao. 11–48.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Franklin1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Franklin WL (1982) Biology, ecology, and relationship to man of the South American camelids. In: Mares MA, Genoways HH, editors. Mammalian biology in South America. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh. 457–489.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Knudson1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knudson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Oxygen isotope analysis in a land of environmental extremes: the complexities of isotopic work in the Andes</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Topic1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Topic</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGreevy</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Topic</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>A comment on the breeding and herding of llamas and alpacas on the north Coast of Peru</article-title>. <source>American Antiquity</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>832</fpage>–<lpage>835</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Goepfert2"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Goepfert N (2011) Frayer la route d’un monde inversé. Sacrifice et offrandes animales dans la culture Mochica (100–800 apr. J.-C.), côte nord du Pérou. Oxford: British Archaeological Reports International Series 2278 (BAR). 428 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Lozada1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lozada MC, Buikstra JE, Rakita G, Wheeler JC (2009) Camelid Herders: The forgotten specialists in the coastal Señorío of Chiribaya, southern Perú. In Marcus J, Williams PR, editors. Andean Civilization: A Tribute to Michael E. Moseley. Los Angeles: Cotsen Institute of Archaeology-Ucla. 351–377.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Pozorski1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pozorski SG (1976) Prehistoric subsistence patterns and site economics in the Moche valley, Peru. PhD in Anthropology. Austin, University of Texas. 475 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Pozorski2"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pozorski</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Late Prehistoric llama remains from the Moche Valley, Peru</article-title>. <source>Annals of Carnegie Museum</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Shimada2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Explotación y manejo de los recursos naturales en Pampa Grande, sitio Moche V. Significado del análisis orgánico</article-title>. <source>Revista del Museo Nacional</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Pozorski3"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pozorski</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pozorski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>An early subsistence exchange system in the Moche Valley, Peru</article-title>. <source>Journal of Field Archaeology</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>432</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-VsquezSnchez1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Vásquez Sánchez VF, Rosales Tham TE, Coronado Tello L (2001) Evidencias arqueológicas de crianza de camélidos en los siglos V y VI en la Costa Norte de Perú. In: Mengoni Goñalons GL, Olivera DE, Yacobaccio HD, editors. El Uso de los camélidos a través el tiempo. Buenos Aires: Ediciones del Tridente-GZC-Icaz. 241–260.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Pillsbury1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pillsbury J (2001) Moche Art and Archaeology. Washington DC: National Gallery of Art. 344p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Lecoq1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lecoq</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Caravanes de lamas, sel et échanges dans une communauté de Potosí, en Bolivie</article-title>. <source>Bulletin de l’Institut Français d’Études Andines</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-PulgarVidal1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pulgar Vidal J (1981) Geografía del Perú: las ocho regiones naturales del Perú. Lima: Universo. 313p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Szpak1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szpak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longstaffe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Millaire</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasquez Sanchez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>carbon and nitrogen isotopic survey of northern Peruvian plants: Baselines for Paleodietary andPaleoecological Studies</article-title>. <source>Plosone</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Webb1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longstaffe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Exploring geographic origins at Cahuachi using stable isotopic analysis of archaeological human tissues and modern environmental waters</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>698</fpage>–<lpage>715</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Buzon1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buzon</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conlee</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Refining oxygen isotope analysis in the Nasca region of Peru: an investigation of water sources and archaeological samples</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>446</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Falabella1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falabella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Planella</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tykot</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>El maíz (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) en el mundo Prehispánico de Chile Central</article-title>. <source>Latin American Antiquity</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Finucane1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Maize and Sociopolitical Complexity in the Ayacucho Valley, Peru</article-title>. <source>Current Anthropology</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Hastorf1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastorf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The effect of the Inka state on Sausa agricultural production and crop consumption</article-title>. <source>American Antiquity</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Kellner1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellner</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoeninger</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A simple carbon isotope model for reconstructing prehistoric human diet</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physical Anthropology 133</source> <volume>(4)</volume>: <fpage>1112</fpage>–<lpage>1127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Tykot1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tykot</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staller</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The importance of early maize agriculture in Coastal Ecuador: New data from La Emerenciana</article-title>. <source>Current Anthropology</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>666</fpage>–<lpage>677</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Knudson2"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knudson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forgey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The geographic origins of Nasca trophy heads in the Kroeber collection using strontium, oxygen, and carbon isotope data</article-title>. <source>Journal of Anthropological Archaeology</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-White1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longstaffe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grupe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Landscape bioarchaeology at Pacatnamu, Peru: inferring mobility from δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N values of hair</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1527</fpage>–<lpage>1537</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Turner1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamenov</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kingston</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armelagos</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Insights into immigration and social class at Machu Picchu, Peru based on oxygen, strontium, and lead isotopic analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Thornton1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeFrance</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krigbaum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Isotopic evidence for Middle Horizon to 16th Century camelid herding in the Osmore Valley, Peru</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Knudson3"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knudson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardella</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yaeger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Provisioning Inka feasts at Tiwanaku, Bolivia: the geographic origins of camelids in the Pumapunku complex</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>491</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Goepfert3"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goepfert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chauchat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Origen geográfico de camélidos en el periodo mochica (100–800 AD) y análisis isotópico secuencial del esmalte dentario: enfoque metodológico y aportes preliminares</article-title>. <source>Bulletin de l’Institut Français d’Etudes Andines</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Balasse1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balasse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrose</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The seasonal mobility model for prehistoric herders in the south-western Cape of South Africa assessed by isotopic analysis of sheep tooth enamel</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>917</fpage>–<lpage>932</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Henton1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meier-Augenstein</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The use of oxygen isotopes in sheep molars to investigate past herding practices at the Neolithic settlement of Catalhöyük, central Anatolia</article-title>. <source>Archaeometry</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Quilter1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Quilter J, Castillo Butters LJ (2010) New perspectives on Moche political organization. Washington D.C.: Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collections. 388p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-LarcoHoyle1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Larco Hoyle R (1948) Cronología arqueológica del norte de Perú. Buenos Aires: Sociedad Geográfica Americana. 87 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-PeaherreraDelAguila1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Peñaherrera Del Aguila C (1986) Gran geografía del Perú. Naturaleza y Hombre. Volumen I Geografía fisica del Perú. Lima: Manfer-Juan Mejia Baca. 220p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-CollinDelavaud1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Collin Delavaud C (1968) Les régions côtières du Pérou septentrional. Lima: IFEA. 409p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Dollfus1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dollfus</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Les Andes intertropicales : une mosaïque changeante</article-title>. <source>Annales ESC (Économies, Sociétés, Civilisations)</source> <volume>5–6</volume>: <fpage>895</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Billman1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Irrigation and the origins of the southern Moche State on the north coast of Peru</article-title>. <source>Latin American Antiquity</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-CastilloButters1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Castillo Butters LJ (2010) Moche politics in the Jequetepeque valley. A case for Political Opportunism. In Quilter J, Castillo Butters LJ, editors. New perspectives on Moche political organization. Washington D.C.: Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection. 83–109.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Chauchat1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chauchat C, Gutiérrez León B (2006) Excavaciones en el Conjunto Arquitectónico 18 (Plataforma Uhle) durante las temporadas 1999 y 2000. In: Uceda S, Mujica E, Morales R, editors. Investigaciones en Huaca de la Luna 2000. Trujillo: Facultad de Ciencias Sociales-Universidad Nacional de la Libertad. 103–147.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Chauchat2"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chauchat C, Gutiérrez León B (2008) Excavaciones en la Plataforma Uhle, temporada 2001. In: Uceda S, Mujica E, Morales R, editors. Investigaciones en Huaca de la Luna 2001.Trujillo: Facultad de Ciencias Sociales-Universidad Nacional. 63–91.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Chauchat3"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chauchat C, Gutiérrez León B (2008) Excavaciones en la Plataforma Uhle, temporada 2002. In: Uceda S, Mujica E, Morales R, editors. Investigaciones en Huaca de la Luna 2002. Trujillo:Facultad de Ciencias Sociales-Universidad Nacional de la Libertad. 53–92.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Chauchat4"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chauchat C, Gutiérrez León B (2012) Excavaciones en la Plataforma Uhle durante el 2003: nuevas evidencias de entierros rituales Moche. In: Uceda S, Mujica E, Morales R, editors. Investigaciones en Huaca de la Luna 2003. Trujillo:Facultad de Ciencias Sociales-Universidad Nacional de la Libertad. 69–100.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Chauchat5"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauchat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deverly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goepfert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Recherches sur l’élite de la société mochica. La Plate-forme Uhle à Moche, sur la côte nord du Pérou</article-title>. <source>Les Nouvelles de l’Archéologie</source> <volume>111–112</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Chauchat6"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauchat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deverly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goepfert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huchet</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>La Plataforma Uhle en Moche: una síntesis de los descubrimientos</article-title>. <source>Revista del Museo de Arqueología, Antropología e Historia de Trujillo</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Franco1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Franco R, Gálvez C, Vásquez S (1994) Arquitectura y decoración mochica en Huaca Cao Viejo, Complejo El Brujo: resultados preliminares. In: Uceda S, Mujica E, editors. Moche: propuestas y perspectivas. Actas del Primer Coloquio sobre la Cultura Moche (Trujillo, 12 al 16 de abril 1993). Lima: U.N.T.-IFEA y Asociación Peruana para el Fomento de las Ciencias Sociales. 147–180.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Franco2"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Franco R, Gálvez C, Vásquez S (2005) El Brujo. Pasado Milenario. Trujillo: Ediciones Sian. 48 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Franco3"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gálvez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vásquez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Modelos, función y cronología de la Huaca Cao Viejo, complejo El Brujo</article-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Uceda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mujica</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, editors. Moche. Hacia el final del milenio, Actas del Segundo Coloquio sobre la Cultura Moche (Trujillo, 1 al 7 de agosto de 1999). Trujillo: Pontificia Universidad Católica del Perú-Universidad Nacional de la Libertad. Vol. <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Franco4"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Franco R, Gálvez C, Vásquez S (1999) Tumbas de cámara Moche en la Plataforma Superior de la Huaca Cao Viejo, Complejo El Brujo. Lima: Fundación Augusto N. Wiese. 54p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Franco5"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Franco R, Gálvez C, Vásquez S (2001) Desentierro y Reenterramiento de una Tumba de Elite Mochica en el Complejo El Brujo. Lima: Fundación Augusto N. Wiese. 69p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Williams1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>El misterio de la momia tatuada</article-title>. <source>National Geographic</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Kent1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kent JD (1982) The domestication and exploitation of the South American camelids: methods of analysis and their application to circum-lacustrine archaeological sites in Bolivia and Peru. PhD in Anthropology. Washington DC: Wasghinton University. 2 volumes.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Wheeler2"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Aging llamas and alpacas by their teeth</article-title>. <source>Llama World</source> <volume>I</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-OConnell1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Connell</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Healey</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>AHR</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Isotopic comparison of hair, nail and bone: Modern analyses</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1247</fpage>–<lpage>1255</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Hedges1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>REM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CDL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’connell</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Collagen turnover in the adult femoral mid-shaft: Modeled from anthropogenic radiocarbon tracer measurements</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physical Anthropology</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>808</fpage>–<lpage>816</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Hillson1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hillson (1986) Teeth. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 377 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Balasse2"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balasse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Reconstructing dietary and environmental history from enamel isotopic analysis: Time resolution of intra-tooth sequential sampling</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Passey1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Passey</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerling</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Tooth enamel mineralization in ungulates: Implications for recovering a primary isotopic time-series</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>3225</fpage>–<lpage>3234</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Zazzo1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zazzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passey</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moloney</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monahan</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The isotope record of short- and long-term dietary changes in sheep tooth enamel: Implications for quantitative reconstruction of paleodiets</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>3571</fpage>–<lpage>3586</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Weinreb1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinreb</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharav</surname><given-names>DMD</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>Tooth development in sheep</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Veterinary Research</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>891</fpage>–<lpage>908</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Wright1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarcz</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Stable carbon and oxygen isotopes in human tooth enamel: Identifying breastfeeding and weaning in prehistory</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physical Anthropology</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Longin1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>New method of collagen extraction for radiocarbon dating</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>230</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Bocherens1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocherens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fizet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mariotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lange-Badre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vandermeersch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Isotopic biogeochemistry (<sup>13</sup>C, <sup>15</sup>N) of fossil vertebrate collagen: application to the study of a past food web including Neandertal man</article-title>. <source>Journal of Human Evolution</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>492</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-DeNiro1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeNiro</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Postmortem preservation and alteration of in vivo bone collagen ratios in relation to palaeodietary reconstruction</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>317</volume>: <fpage>806</fpage>–<lpage>809</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-VanKlinken1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Klinken</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Bone collagen quality indicators for palaeodietary and radiocarbon measurements</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>695</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Dobberstein1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobberstein</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penkman</surname><given-names>KEH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Archaeological collagen: Why worry about collagen diagenesis</article-title>? <source>Archaeological and Anthropological Science</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Ambrose1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrose</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Preparation and characterization of bone and tooth collagen for isotopic analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>451</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Koch1"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuross</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fogel</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The effects of sample treatment and diagenesis on the isotopic integrity of carbonate in biogenic hydroxylapatite</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>429</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Shin1"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>REM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Diagenesis in bone and enamel apatite carbonate; the potential of density separation to assess the original composition</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1123</fpage>–<lpage>1130</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Clementz1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clementz</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fox-Dobbs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wheatley</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doak</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Revisiting old bones: coupled carbon isotope analysis of bioapatite and collagen as an ecological and palaeoecological tool</article-title>. <source>Geological Journal</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>–<lpage>620</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Zazzo2"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zazzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lécuyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mariotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Experimentally-controlled carbon and oxygen isotope exchange between bioapatites and water under inorganic and microbially-mediated conditions</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Wang1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerling</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>A model of fossil tooth and bonediagenesis: Implications for paleodiet reconstruction from stable isotopes</article-title>. <source>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology Palaeoecology</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-DeNiro2"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeNiro</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Influence of diet on the distribution of carbon isotopes in animals</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>506</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-DeNiro3"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeNiro</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Influence of diet on the distribution of nitrogen isotopes in animals</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-LeeThorp1"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee-Thorp</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sealy</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Der Merwe</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Stable carbon isotope ratio differences between bone collagen and bone apatite, and their relationship to diet</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Jim1"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrose</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evershed</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Stable carbon isotopic evidence for differences in the dietary origin of bone cholesterol, collagen and apatite: implications for their use in palaeodietary reconstruction</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Fernandez1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grootes</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Macronutrient-based model for dietary carbon routing in bone collagen and bioapatite</article-title>. <source>Archaeological and Anthropological Sciences</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Ambrose2"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ambrose SH, Norr L (1993) Experimental evidence for the relationship of the carbon isotope ratios of whole diet and dietary protein to those of bone collagen and carbonate. In: Lambert JB, Grupe G, editors. Prehistoric human bone Archaeology at the molecular level. Berlin: Springer. 1–37.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Tieszen1"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tieszen LL, Fagre T (1993) Effect of diet quality and composition on the isotopic composition of respiratory CO<sub>2</sub>, bone collagen, bioapatite, and soft tissues. In: Lambert JB, Grupe G, editors. Prehistoric human bone: archaeology at the molecular level. Berlin: Springer. 121–155.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Warinner1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warinner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tuross</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Alkaline cooking and stable isotope tissue-diet spacing in swine: Archaeological implications</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1690</fpage>–<lpage>1697</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Passey2"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Passey</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayliffe</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cerling</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sponheimer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Carbon isotope fractionation between diet, breath CO<sub>2</sub>, and bioapatite in different mammals</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaelogical Science 32</source> <volume>(10)</volume>: <fpage>1459</fpage>–<lpage>1470</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Cerling1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerling</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Carbon isotope fractionation between diet and bioapatite in ungulate mammals and implications for ecological and paleoecological studies</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Smith1"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Two categories of <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>12</sup>C ratios for higher plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>380</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Ranson1"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1960</year>) <article-title>Crassulacean acid metabolism</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Tieszen2"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tieszen LL, Chapman M (1992) Carbon and nitrogen isotopic status of the major marine and terrestrial resources in the Atacama Desert of northern Chile. In: Aufderheide A, editor. Proceedings of the First World Congress on Mummy Studies. Santa Cruz de Tenerife: Museo Arquelógico y Etnográfico de Tenerife. 409–425.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Skrzypek1"><label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skrzypek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chuman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Šefrna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title><italic>Distichia peat</italic> - A new stable isotope paleoclimate proxy for the Andes</article-title>. <source>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</source> <volume>307</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Schoeninger1"><label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoeninger</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeNiro</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Nitrogen and carbon isotopic composition of bone collagen from marine and terrestrial animals</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>639</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Szpak2"><label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szpak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Millaire</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longstaffe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Influence of seabird guano and camelid dung fertilization on the nitrogen isotopic composition of field-grown maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>3721</fpage>–<lpage>3740</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Ambrose3"><label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrose</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeNiro</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Bone nitrogen isotope composition and climate</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>325</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Ambrose4"><label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrose</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Effects of diet, climate and physiology on nitrogen isotope abundances in terrestrial foodwebs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Evans1"><label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehleringer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Plant δ<sup>15</sup>N values along a fog gradient in the Atacama desert, Chile</article-title>. <source>Journal of Arid Environments</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Bocherens2"><label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocherens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drucker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Trophic level isotopic enrichment of carbon and nitrogen in bone collagen: case studies from recent and ancient terrestrial ecosystems</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Minagawa1"><label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Minagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Stepwise enrichment of <sup>15</sup>N along food chains: further evidence and the relation between <sup>15</sup>N and animal age</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1135</fpage>–<lpage>1140</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Schoeninger2"><label>100</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoeninger</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeNiro</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tauber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Stable nitrogen isotope ratios of bone collagen reflect marine and terrestrial components of prehistoric human diet</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>220</volume>: <fpage>1381</fpage>–<lpage>1383</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Fuller1"><label>101</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sage</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Connell</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Nitrogen balance and δ<sup>15</sup>N: why you’re not what you eat during pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Rapid Communication in Mass Spectrometry</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>2889</fpage>–<lpage>2896</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Fuller2"><label>102</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molleson</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>REM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Isotopic evidence for breastfeeding and possible adult dietary differences from late/sub-Roman Britain</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physical</source> <volume>Anthropology129</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Trueman1"><label>103</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trueman</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGill</surname><given-names>RAR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guyard</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The effect of growth rate on tissue-diet isotopic spacing in rapidly growing animals. An experimental study with Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Rapid Communication in Mass Spectrometry</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>3239</fpage>–<lpage>3247</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Katzenberg1"><label>104</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katzenberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Stable isotope variation in pathological bone</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Mekota1"><label>105</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mekota</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grupe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ufer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cuntz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Serial analysis of stable nitrogen and carbon isotopes in hair: monitoring starvation and recovery phases of patients suffering from anorexia nervosa</article-title>. <source>Rapid Communication in Mass Spectrometry</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1604</fpage>–<lpage>1610</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Yacobaccio1"><label>106</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yacobaccio</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samec</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Towards an isotopic ecology of herbivory in the Puna ecosystem: new results and patterns on <italic>Lama glama</italic></article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Schoeninger3"><label>107</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoeninger</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeNiro</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Carbon isotope ratios of apatite from fossil bone cannot be used to reconstruct diets of animals</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>297</volume>: <fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Marino1"><label>108</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McElroy</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Glacial-to-interglacial variations in the carbon isotopic composition of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>349</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>131</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-DeNiro4"><label>109</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">DeNiro MJ (1988) Marine food source for prehistoric coastal Peruvian camelids: isotopic evidences and implications. In: Wing ES, Wheeler JC, editors. Economic prehistory of the Central Andes. Oxford: British Archaeological Reports International Series 427 (BAR). 119–130.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Longinelli1"><label>110</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longinelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Oxygen isotopes in mammal bone phosphate: a new tool for paleohydrological and paleoclimatological research</article-title>? <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Luz1"><label>111</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolodny</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Fractionation of oxygen isotopes between mammalian bone-phosphate and environmental drinking water</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1689</fpage>–<lpage>1693</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Luz2"><label>112</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolodny</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Oxygen isotope variations in phosphate of biogenic apatites. IV. Mammal teeth and bones</article-title>. <source>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Amiot1"><label>113</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amiot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecuyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buffetaut</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fluteau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Latitudinal temperature gradient during the Cretaceous Upper Campanian-Middle Maastrichtian: δ<sup>18</sup>O record of continental vertebrates</article-title>. <source>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</source> <volume>226</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Lcuyer1"><label>114</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lécuyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martineau</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fourel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Oxygen isotope fractionation between apatite -bound carbonate and water determined from controlled experiments with synthetic apatites precipitated at 10°C to 37°C</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>2072</fpage>–<lpage>2081</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-White2"><label>115</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longstaffe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Testing the nature of Teotihuacan imperialism at Kaminaljuyu Using Phosphate Oxygen-Isotope Ratios</article-title>. <source>Journal of Anthropological Research</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-White3"><label>116</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longstaffe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart-Williams</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Geographic identities of the sacrificial victims from the Feathered Serpent Pyramid, Teotihuacan: Implications for the nature of state power</article-title>. <source>Latin American Antiquity</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Epstein1"><label>117</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>Variation of <sup>18</sup>O content of waters from natural sources Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</article-title>. <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Dansgaard1"><label>118</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dansgaard</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>Stable isotopes in precipitation</article-title>. <source>Tellus</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>436</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Bowen1"><label>119</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Spatial distribution of δ<sup>18</sup>O in meteoric precipitation</article-title>. <source>Geology</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Gat1"><label>120</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gat</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Oxygen and hydrogen isotopes in the hydrologic cycle</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Science</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-White4"><label>121</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart-Williams</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarcz</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Oxygen Isotopes and the Identification of Geographical Origins: The Valley of Oaxaca versus the Valley of Mexico</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>643</fpage>–<lpage>655</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Bowen2"><label>122</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Revenaugh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Interpolating the isotopic composition of modern meteoric precipitation</article-title>. <source>Water Resources Research</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1299</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Sharp1"><label>123</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sharp ZD (2007) Principles of stable isotope geochemistry. New Jersey: Pearson Prentice Hall: Upper Saddle River. 344p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-IAEAWMO1"><label>124</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">IAEA/WMO (2006) Global network of isotopes in precipitation. The GNIP database. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http:/isohis.iaea.org" xlink:type="simple">http:/isohis.iaea.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Roberts1"><label>125</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coward</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Effect of weaning on accuracy of doubly labeled water method in infants</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physiology-Regulatory, Integrative and Comparative Physiology</source> <volume>254</volume>: <fpage>622</fpage>–<lpage>627</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Wright2"><label>126</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarcz</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Correspondence between stable carbon, oxygen and nitrogen isotopes in human tooth enamel and dentine: infant diets at Kaminaljuyú</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1159</fpage>–<lpage>1170</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Bonavia2"><label>127</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bonavia D (2008) El Maíz. Su origen, su domesticación y el rol cumplido en el desarrollo de la cultura. Lima: Universidad San Martin de Porres. 408p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Finucane2"><label>128</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maita Agurto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isbell</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Human and animal diet at Conchopata, Peru: stable isotope evidence for maize agriculture and animal management practices during the Middle Horizon</article-title>. <source>Journal of Archaeological Science</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1766</fpage>–<lpage>1776</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Izeta1"><label>129</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Izeta</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laguens</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marconetto</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scattolin</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Camelid handling in the meridional Andes during the first millennium AD: a preliminary approach using stable isotopes</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Osteoarchaeology</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Balasse3"><label>130</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balasse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tresset</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobney</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrose</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The use of isotope ratios to test for seaweed eating in sheep</article-title>. <source>Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>266</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Yesner1"><label>131</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yesner</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>MJF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guichon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borrero</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Stable isotope analysis of human bone and ethnohistoric subsistence patterns in Tierra del Fuego</article-title>. <source>Journal of Anthropological Archaeology</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Verano1"><label>132</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Verano JW, DeNiro MJ (1993) Locals or foreigners? Morphological, biometric and isotopic approaches to the question of group affinity in human skeletal remains recovered from unusual archaeological context. In: Sandford MK, editor. Investigations of Ancient Human Tissue: Chemical Analysis in Anthropology. Langhorne: Gordon and Breach. 361–386.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Haas1"><label>133</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Creamer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huamán Mesíac</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reinharde</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Evidence for maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) in the Late Archaic (3000–1800 B.C.) in the Norte Chico region of Peru</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>4945</fpage>–<lpage>4949</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Johannessen1"><label>134</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Johannessen S, Hastorf CA (1994) Corn and culture in the Prehistoric New World. Boulder: Westview press. 623p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Lambert1"><label>135</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Billman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katzenberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carcelén</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Bone Chemistry at Cerro Oreja: A stable isotope perspective on the development of a regional economy in the Moche Valley, Peru during the Early Intermediate Period</article-title>. <source>Latin American Antiquity 2012</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>144</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Gumerman1"><label>136</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gumerman G (1991) Subsistence and complex societies: diet between diverse socio-economic Groups at Pacatnamú, Peru. PhD in Anthropology. Los Angeles: University of California. 356 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Gumerman2"><label>137</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gumerman G (1994) Corn for the dead: the significance of <italic>Zea mays</italic> in Moche burial offerings. In: Johannessen S, Hastorf CA, editors. Corn and Culture in the Prehistoric New World. Boulder: Westview press. 399–410.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Gumerman3"><label>138</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gumerman G (1997). Botanical offerings in Moche burials at Pacatnamu. In: Donnan CB, Cock G, editors. The Pacatnamu Papers. Volume 2. Los Angeles: Fowler Museum of Cultural History-University of California. 243–249.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-Burger1"><label>139</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Merwe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Maize and the origin of Chavin civilization: an isotopic perspective</article-title>. <source>American Anthropologist</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-McCorkle1"><label>140</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCorkle CM (1987) Punas, pastures and fields: grazing strategies and the agropastoral dialectic in an indigenous Andean community. In Browman DL, editor. Arid land use strategies and risk management in the Andes: A Regional Anthropological Perspective. Boulder: Westview Press. 57–80.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0087559-MengoniGoalones1"><label>141</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mengoni Goñalones</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Camelid management during Inca times in N.W. Argentina: models and archaeozoological indicators</article-title>. <source>Anthropozoologica</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>