<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-47446</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090414</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome sequencing</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Human genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Y-linked</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Effective population size</subject><subject>Gene flow</subject><subject>Genetic drift</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject><subject>Haplotypes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological anthropology</subject><subject>Physical anthropology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Y Chromosome Haplogroup Distribution in Indo-European Speaking Tribes of Gujarat, Western India</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Y Haplogroups in Tribes of Western India</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>Priyanka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>Aastha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>Siuli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Italia</surname><given-names>Yazdi M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saraswathy</surname><given-names>Kallur N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrasekar</surname><given-names>Adimoolam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kshatriya</surname><given-names>Gautam K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Anthropology, School of Applied Sciences, Dr. Harisingh Gour University, Sagar, Madhya Pradesh, India</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>South Asia Network for Chronic Disease, Public Health Foundation of India, Delhi, India</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Anthropology, University of Delhi, Delhi, India</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Valsad Raktdan Kendra, R.N.C. Free Eye Hospital Complex, Valsad, Gujarat, India</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Anthropological Survey of India, Southern Regional Center, Mysore, Karnataka, India</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petraglia</surname><given-names>Michael D.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Oxford, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">g26_51@yahoo.co.in</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: GKK KNS YMI PK. Performed the experiments: PK SM AA. Analyzed the data: PK AA AC GKK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AC GKK YMI KNS. Wrote the paper: PK AC AA GKK.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<elocation-id>e90414</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Khurana et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The present study was carried out in the Indo-European speaking tribal population groups of Southern Gujarat, India to investigate and reconstruct their paternal population structure and population histories. The role of language, ethnicity and geography in determining the observed pattern of Y haplogroup clustering in the study populations was also examined. A set of 48 bi-allelic markers on the non-recombining region of Y chromosome (NRY) were analysed in 284 males; representing nine Indo-European speaking tribal populations. The genetic structure of the populations revealed that none of these groups was overtly admixed or completely isolated. However, elevated haplogroup diversity and F<sub>ST</sub> value point towards greater diversity and differentiation which suggests the possibility of early demographic expansion of the study groups. The phylogenetic analysis revealed 13 paternal lineages, of which six haplogroups: C5, H1a*, H2, J2, R1a1* and R2 accounted for a major portion of the Y chromosome diversity. The higher frequency of the six haplogroups and the pattern of clustering in the populations indicated overlapping of haplogroups with West and Central Asian populations. Other analyses undertaken on the population affiliations revealed that the Indo-European speaking populations along with the Dravidian speaking groups of southern India have an influence on the tribal groups of Gujarat. The vital role of geography in determining the distribution of Y lineages was also noticed. This implies that although language plays a vital role in determining the distribution of Y lineages, the present day linguistic affiliation of any population in India for reconstructing the demographic history of the country should be considered with caution.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The work was funded by Department of Biotechnology (DBT) grant (vide letter BT/PR9840/MED/12/366/2007). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>India is the second most populous country in the world with a population of 1.21 billion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Census1">[1]</xref>. About 4,635 different population groups are spread across the country <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Singh1">[2]</xref>. Exorbitant as it may sound, existence of at least 50–60 thousand essentially endogamous groups has been reported in the country <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Gadgil1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Joshi1">[4]</xref>. The present day Indian population is divided into tribal and non-tribal groups. Tribal populations constitute 8.2% of the total population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Census2">[5]</xref> and are considered to be the indigenous populations of India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Fuchs1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Ray1">[8]</xref>. The tribal groups of India belong to four broad linguistic families: Austro-Asiatic, Dravidian, Indo-European and Tibeto-Burman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Majumder1">[9]</xref>. The Indo-European and Dravidian speaking populations are considered to be the major contributors to the development of Indian culture and society <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Meenakshi1">[10]</xref>. Both Austro-Asiatic and Dravidian speaking tribes belong to the primary pre-historic populations of India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Thapar1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Malhotra1">[11]</xref>. Tibeto-Burman speakers also include many tribal populations but their geographical distribution is largely restricted to the North-Eastern region of India. India thus exhibits an enormous genetic, cultural and linguistic diversity which can partly be attributed to its position at the tri-junction: with Africa in the west, Eurasia in the north and the Orient in the east. The country's unique location gives rise to a great variety of environmental conditions and associated biodiversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Gadgil2">[12]</xref> which in turn has attracted people from all over the globe.</p>
<p>Archaeological and paleontological evidence dating back to the middle and late Pleistocene era points towards early human occupation of the Indian subcontinent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sonakia1">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Cameron1">[16]</xref>. Similar evidence of antiquity of Indian populations has been established by genetic marker studies. The high levels of gene diversity and coefficients of gene differentiation obtained using autosomal markers for Indian populations are a testimony of both, the antiquity and the complex population structure, of this massive human conglomeration existing in the southern part of Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Majumder2">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Reich1">[19]</xref>. Recent genetic studies based on mtDNA showing the high frequency of mitochondrial lineages with greater age, high diversity and wide distribution amply demonstrate the prehistoric existence of mankind on the Indian subcontinent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Chandrasekar1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Thangaraj1">[21]</xref>. Similar analyses of Y chromosome variation based on both bi-allelic and microsatellite markers have documented the existence of substantially deep rooted lineages among Indian populations buttressing the claim of early habitation of humans on the Indian subcontinent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Underhill1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kumar1">[25]</xref>.</p>
<p>The unique and complex structure of the Indian population is attributed to the multiple waves of migration and the resultant gene-flow which occurred in the past <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Gadgil2">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Ratnagar1">[26]</xref>. Some scholars have provided evidence to explain the origin and migration of the major linguistic families extant in India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kumar1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Chaubey1">[27]</xref>. It is worth mentioning that speakers of Austro-Asiatic language in India are exclusively tribal, which may be indicative of their being one of the oldest inhabitants of India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Gadgil3">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Pattanayak1">[29]</xref>. The arrival of the Indo-European speakers via the Northern corridor of India around 3,500–4,000 years ago is believed to be responsible for one of the major influxes of people in the Indian subcontinent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-CavalliSforza1">[30]</xref>, followed later by the infiltration of colonizers from different parts of the world. Thus, several studies have affirmed the influence of Eurasian and Asian populations on the Indian gene pool <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sahoo1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Bamshad1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kivisild1">[34]</xref>.</p>
<p>Within this complex scenario, many interaction models such as gene-language, gene-geography and gene-ethnicity have been contested. Previous studies have shown inverse correlation between genetic affinities and geographical distance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Malhotra1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Cordaux1">[35]</xref>. Significant genetic differentiation between caste and tribal populations has been reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Bamshad1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Basu1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Cordaux2">[36]</xref>, as against a model which suggests that there is considerable sharing of Pleistocene heritage among them with a limited gene flow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kivisild1">[34]</xref>. Similarly, congruence between language and genes has been proposed by various scholars <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Majumder1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-CavalliSforza2">[37]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Roychoudhury1">[38]</xref> along with a competing view supporting that genetic affinities may not necessarily be dependent on linguistic similarities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Chaubey2">[39]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sharma1">[41]</xref>. Although each study has contributed significantly to understanding the role of language, culture and geography in relation to the genetic affiliation and demographic history of Indian populations; a major limitation in them has been the poor representation of Indo-European speaking tribal populations. This is a critically important limitation since the Indo-European speaking tribes provide ample opportunity for examining the influence of linguistic assimilation on the genomic diversity of India.</p>
<p>Keeping the above in view, we present an analysis based on the study of 48 bi-allelic markers in nine Indo-European speaking tribal groups of Southern Gujarat which lies in the western part of India. The main objectives of the study were (a) to study the distribution of Y haplogroups; (b) to study the relative influence of language, geography or ethnicity on the genetic structure of populations using the pattern of Y haplogroup clustering and finally (c) to relate the observed pattern of Y haplogroup clustering with the Y chromosome lineages which arrived in India largely from the Northern corridor at different points of time. To achieve the study objectives the results were first compared with published studies on the Indian populations and then with available data on the Eurasian populations. The Indian populations were selected keeping in view the availability of data, their linguistic and socio-culture status and geographical position. Similarly, the Eurasian populations for which published sources were available were considered for analysis since the historical migrations from these regions are known.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Collection and processing of blood samples</title>
<p>This study was approved by the Departmental Ethical Committee of the Department of Anthropology, University of Delhi. Informed written consent was obtained from all the participants. A 5 ml blood sample was drawn by a trained medical practitioner from randomly chosen 284 healthy, unrelated males from nine tribal population groups of Valsad and Surat districts of Gujarat. A description of relevant population characteristicsof study groups along with populations from other studies is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0090414-t001">Table 1</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0090414-g001">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the sampling location of study populations from Gujarat. The detailed description of the study populations has been given previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kshatriya2">[42]</xref>. Blood samples collected in EDTA coated vacutainers were subjected to DNA extraction following salting-out method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Miller1">[43]</xref>. A total of 48 bi-allelic markers were analysed to identify the Y chromosome haplogroups. The markers were typed using primer pairs described in Karafet et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Karafet1">[44]</xref>. The PCR cycling conditions with an initial denaturation of 5 minutes at 95°C; followed by 35 cycles of 1 minute at 94°C; 45 seconds at the primer-specific annealing temperature (52–60)°C and extension at 72°C for 2 minutes and 30 seconds; followed by final extension of 7 minutes at 72°C were followed. The amplicons generated were subjected to sequence reactions using BigDye™ (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, USA) Terminator Cycle sequencing kit in ABI Prism 3730 DNA analyser following manufacturer's protocol and further analysed in SeqScape software, version 2.5.</p>
<fig id="pone-0090414-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Sampling areas; Map of India highlighting Gujarat (top); Regions of study pointed out in the map of Gujarat (bottom).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0090414-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Geographical, Social and Linguistic description of study groups and populations included in the study for Y haplogroup comparison.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0090414-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linguistic affiliation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socio-Culture affiliation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>South Asia</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>India</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>West</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dhodia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dubla</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Konkana</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vasava</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gamit</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valvi Chaudhari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nana Chaudhari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mota Chaudhari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pavagadhi Chaudhari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Madia Gond</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Katkari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MahadeoKoli</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pawara</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thakur</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Desasth Brahmin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maratha</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dhangar</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chitpavan Brahmin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gujrat Patel</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>South</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chenchu</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yerukula</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuruva</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irular</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naikpod Gonnd</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andhra Brahmin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kamma Chaudhary</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kappu naidu</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Komati</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raju</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reddy</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhovi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gowda</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iyengar</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lingayat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chakkliar</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gounder</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kallar</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pallar</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vanniyar</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>East</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mahali</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhumij</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birhor</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ho</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kharia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Munda</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Santhal</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juang</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saora</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paroja</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhuiyan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bathudi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kora</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bihar brahmin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">kayasth</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">bhumihar</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baniya</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rajput</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yadav</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gope</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oriya Brahmin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bauri</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mahishiya</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Namasudra</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Central</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Halba</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">jaunsri</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhoksha</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kanyakubj Brahmin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khatri</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kurmi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UP Thakur</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UP Kurmi</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>North-East</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hamar</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuki</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lai</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lusei</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mara</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>North</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Himachal Pradesh RAJPUT</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afganistan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pakistan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">718</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>West Asia</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iraq</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jordan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">523</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lebanon</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syria</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Central Asia</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kazakhstan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alltai</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uzbekistan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kyrgyzthan</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uyghursta</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Europe</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">442</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherlands</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Czech and Slovakia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alabina</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macedonia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hungary</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Georgia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>Linguistic affiliation: Indo-European (IE), Dravidian (DR), Tibeto-Burman (TB) and Austro-Asiatic (AA);</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>b</label><p>Socio-cultural affiliation: Tribe (T), Caste (C).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Statistical and phylogenetic analysis</title>
<p>The revised Y-Chromosome phylogenetic tree <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Karafet1">[44]</xref> was referred to for the assignment of haplogroups based on informative binary markers. Haplogroup frequencies were estimated by a simple gene count method. In order to determine the genetic structure of study populations, a model propounded by Harpending and Ward <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Harpending1">[45]</xref> was applied. The model examines the relative role of genetic drift and gene flow in causing population differentiation. In the model, the expected frequency of gene diversity for each population is first graphically represented with respect to the distance from the gene frequency centroid, <italic>r<sub>ii</sub></italic>, which is given by the formula:<disp-formula id="pone.0090414.e001"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>Where, <italic>p<sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>P</italic> are the frequency of the haplogroups in a population <italic>i</italic> and in the pooled populations respectively. In the second stage of the model, Harpending and Ward propose an island model of population structure in which there is a linear relationship between gene diversity and the distance from the centroid which is calculated by the formula:<disp-formula id="pone.0090414.e002"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>Where, <italic>h<sub>i</sub></italic> and <italic>H</italic> correspond to the gene diversity value in the population <italic>i</italic> and in all the populations as a whole respectively. As per the model, outlier populations that have undergone systematic migrations will show greater gene diversity than predicted by the regression line, while outlier groups that are isolated will exhibit lower than predicted gene diversity.</p>
<p>In order to determine whether the Y chromosome haplogroup distribution among Indian populations is structured on the basis of ethnicity, geography or linguistic affiliation, an analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) based on haplogroup frequencies was computed for the various tentative categories using ARLEQUIN software, version 3.1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Excoffier1">[46]</xref>. Using the same software Slatkin's lineraised pairwise F<sub>ST</sub> values were calculated on haplogroup frequencies and analysed through non metric multidimensional scaling (MDS) in SPSS version 16.0 using ALSCAL programme. The MDS plot was constructed in order to graphically represent the nature of clustering between the study populations and other world populations.</p>
<p>For carrying out AMOVA on different populations secondary source haplogroup frequency data (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0090414.s001">Table S1</xref>) was compiled from different studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sahoo1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kumar1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Thangaraj2">[47]</xref>. For the construction of the MDS plot data (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0090414.s002">Table S2</xref>) was compiled from various studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Semino1">[48]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Haber1">[53]</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Haplogroups distribution</title>
<p>The frequency distribution of Y chromosome haplogroups among the study populations along with the phylogenetic relationship between them is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0090414-g002">Figure 2</xref>. The side branches on the tree represent Y SNP for which the ancestral state was observed, while the direct branch represents Y markers for which the mutant allelic state was observed; leading to haplogroup designation in the particular sample. Analysis of 48 bi-allelic markers of the Y chromosome showed 13 paternal lineages that were distributed throughout haplogroups H, R, J, C, F, L, K and Q. Haplogroup H represented the most frequently occurring haplogroup (40.14%) followed by groups R (28.17%), J (10.21%) and C (8.45%) respectively. Sparse distribution was observed for the lineages F*, L1, Q3 and K* across all the populations.</p>
<fig id="pone-0090414-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Distribution of Y-binary halpogroups and haplogroup diversity (<italic>h</italic>) among the study populations of Gujarat.</title>
<p>The markers used in the study are shown on each branch.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><sec id="s3a1">
<title>Haplogroup H</title>
<p>M69 mutation, which is a characteristic of haplogroup H was found on 114 of the total 284 Y chromosomes. Haplogroup H was further segregated into three lineages, H1 by the presence of M52-C allele, H2 by the presence of Apt-A allele and H* by absence of the two alleles. These haplogroups were further subdivided into a number of sub-clades. Lineage H1a* of H1 group was observed 71 times and represented the most frequently occurring lineage across all the populations. Its frequency varied from a minimum of 3.45% among Pavagadhi Chaudhari to a maximum of 62.5% in Vasava. Lineage H2 represented the second most frequently occurring lineage among the H haplogroup and third most common haplogroup among all the haplogroups. Its frequency varied from 3.45% among Pavagadhi Chaudhari to 40.74% among Mota Chaudhari. However, H2-Apt was found to be absent among Vasava and Gamit populations. While lineage H* was observed in only three individuals, one each from Konkana, Gamit and Mota Chaudhari.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3a2">
<title>Haplogroup R</title>
<p>R1a1*a sub-clade of R haplogroup was found to be the next most frequently occurring lineage after H1a*. Its frequency was found ranging from 5.56% in Gamit to 62.07% in Pavagadhi Chaudhari. Its sister sub-clade R2-M124 was observed 27 times with a frequency varying from 5.56% among Gamit to 20.83% among the Konkana tribe. Barring Valvi Chaudhari, R2 was absent from all other Chaudhari groups.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3a3">
<title>Haplogroup J</title>
<p>J2 with its two sub-clades J2b2* and J2a constituted a major portion of Haplogroup J in the current study. Except Konkana and Mota Chaudhari, either of the two J2 sub-clades was present in all other groups. J2b2* sub-clade was observed in 21 Y chromosomes. Its frequency was found to be 11% in Gamit, 19% in Valvi Chaudhari and 21% in Pavagadhi Chaudhari. The remaining four populations of Dhodia, Dubla, Vasava and Nana Chaudhari exhibited similar frequency values varying in a narrow range between 4% and 4.48%. Sub-clade J2a was observed only 8 times in the nine groups. It was present in four of the groups with a minimum frequency of 3.17% in Dhodia to a maximum frequency of 7.14% in Dubla.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3a4">
<title>Haplogroup C</title>
<p>Out of the seven sub-clades of C haplogroup, only one sub-clade C5 with its two main derivatives C5a and C5* was observed 21 times in all the populations except Pavagadhi Chaudhari. C5a lineage was observed to be 62 times more frequent then its sister branch C5*. Its frequency varied from 3.17% in Dhodia to 12.5% in Valvi Chaudhari, while that of C5* was found to vary from 3.7% in Mota Chaudhari to 9.38% in Valvi Chaudhari.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3a5">
<title>Haplogroup F*, K*, L1 and Q3</title>
<p>Parahaplogroup F* along with the other parahaplogroup K* and two haplogroups L and Q accounted for 13.03% of the total haplogroups. After initial screening of M89-T allele, 11 samples failed to resolve further and were therefore grouped under F*. Similarly, 8 individuals did not exhibit any mutation except G allele for M9 and were therefore grouped under K*. Other two sub-clades L1-M27 and Q3-M346 were present, but in low frequencies only.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Y chromosome diversity</title>
<p>Haplogroup diversity values for each of the nine populations along with haplogroup distribution are given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0090414-g002">Figure 2</xref>. Haplogroup diversity (<italic>h</italic>) which is equivalent to gene diversity for haploid genomes ranged from 0.586 in Pavagadhi Chaudhari to 0.899 in Valvi Chaudhari.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Population Structure and Gene Flow</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0090414-g003">Figure 3</xref> represents a plot of haplogroup diversity regressed against distance from gene frequency centroid (<italic>r<sub>ii</sub></italic>). The values of gene diversity (<italic>h<sub>i</sub></italic>) and genetic distances from centroid (<italic>r<sub>ii</sub></italic>) used in the nine study population groups along with their standard errors are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0090414-t002">Table 2</xref>. Majority of the populations exhibited higher than predicted gene diversity combined with a low to moderate deviation from the theoretical line of regression and the distance from the gene frequency centroid. Three populations Gamit, Vasava and Pavagadhi Chaudhari displayed lower than predicted gene diversity. Pavagadhi Chaudhari showed the farthest distance from the gene frequency centroid. The results indicated that the tribal groups of Gujarat are neither explicitly isolated nor absolutely admixed.</p>
<fig id="pone-0090414-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Regression of gene diversity (<italic>h<sub>i</sub></italic>) on distance from centroid (<italic>r<sub>ii</sub></italic>).</title>
<p>The solid line represents the theoretical regression line.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0090414-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Gene diversity (<italic>h<sub>i</sub></italic>) and genetic distances from the centroid (<italic>r<sub>ii</sub></italic>) among the study populations of Gujarat.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0090414-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r<sub>ii</sub> ± S.E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h<sub>i</sub>± S.E</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dhodia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024±0.008</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.869±0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dubla</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024±0.006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.866±0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Konkana</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055±0.011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855±0.009</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vasava</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086±0.057</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.605±0.022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gamit</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092±0.038</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.699±0.028</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valvi Chaudhari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062±0.019</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.899±0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nana Chaudhari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067±0.029</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.823±0.010</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mota Chaudhari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089±0.043</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792±0.012</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pavagadhi Chaudhari</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157±0.093</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.586±0.017</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>AMOVA</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0090414-t003">Table 3</xref> presents the results of the AMOVA based on different categories of populations subdivided by language, geography and ethnicity. Analysis of molecular variance based on haplogroup frequencies among the study groups showed that 91.6% of variability is due to within population differences and 8.4% (p&lt;0.001) is due to differences between the populations. In the hierarchical approach taken, at the next level populations were subdivided according to their affiliation into: Indo-European, Dravidian, Tibeto-Burman and Austro-Asiatic language families. A substantially high percentage of difference between populations (13.21%) was observed indicating strong distinctiveness of populations belonging to the different linguistic families. This was followed by the subdivision of populations by the geographical regions they inhabit. The geographical clustering of populations displayed comparatively lower (6.25%) amount of differentiation between the populations. Similarly, in a comparison between Indian castes and tribes a comparatively lower fraction of variance (5.13%) points towards relatively lesser differences between them. Following this, further categories of Indo-European speaking tribal populations of Gujarat were made for comparing with other Indian populations, keeping in mind the effect of language, geography and ethnicity; in that order of importance. The results showed that the lowest group variance among all categories was between Indo-European speaking groups of Gujarat and other Indo-European populations; it was almost 5 times lesser than the variance observed between the studied populations and the Dravidian speaking groups of India. Interestingly, further subdivision of Indo-European populations into tribes and castes revealed a lesser fraction of variability among study populations and Indo-European caste populations (3.45%) as compared to Indo-European speaking tribes (6.57%). Moreover, as compared to Dravidian speaking caste populations, the population in Gujarat showed less differentiation with Dravidian speaking tribes as reflected by low group variance values (5.3%). Subdivision of Indo-European populations simultaneously by caste, tribe and geographical zones (West, Central and East) indicated effective role of geographic distance in determining genetic distance. All the values compared were found to be highly significant.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0090414-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>AMOVA based on Y Chromosome haplogroup frequencies.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0090414-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Categories</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Among groups variance (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Among populations within groups variance (%)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within populations variance (%)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 language groups<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geography<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Castes and tribes of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with IE populations of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with DR populations of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with AA Populations of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.94</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with IE castes of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with IE tribes of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with DR tribes of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with DR caste of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with IE tribes from three geographical regions C,W &amp; E of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.24</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IE speaking tribes of Gujarat with IE castes from three geographical regions C,W &amp; E of India</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.59</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.63</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label>a</label><p>Language groups = Indo-European (IE), Dravidian (DR), Tibeto-Burman (TB) and Austro-Asiatic (AA),</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>b</label><p>Geography = Central (C), West (W), East (E), South(S) and North East (NE). All the values are significant, p&lt;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3e">
<title>Genetic proximities</title>
<p>We compared the study populations with 24 additional world populations already published in separate studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0090414-g004">Figure 4</xref>). A stress value of 0.18 for the MDS plot indicated a good fit between the two dimensional graph and the original distance matrix. The comparison revealed four major clusters of South Asian, Central Asian, West Asian and European populations. All the populations under study with the exception of Pavagadhi Chaudhari were found to be clustered together. The occurrence of South Asian populations (the current study groups, Afghanistan, Pakistan and Iran) with Central Asian populations (Kazakhstan, Altai Region, Uzbekistan, Kyrgyzstan, Uyghurstan) on Axis I, conversely with West Asian populations (Iraq, Jordan, Turkey, Lebanon, Syria) with respect to Axis II probably indicate similarities of haplogroups between them.</p>
<fig id="pone-0090414-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>MDS Plot showing genetic relationships particularly between the South Asian populations with the world populations.</title>
<p>The South Asian populations including the study populations of India are shown in as solid circles (•), the European populations as open circles (o), Central Asian populations as triangle (Δ) and West Asian population as cross (x). The abbreviation used are Afganistan (Afg), Pakistan (Pak), Iran (Ira), Iraq (Irk), Jordan (Jor), Turkey (Tur), Lebanon (Leb), Syria (Syr), Kazakhstan (Kaz), Altai (Alt), Uzbekistan (Uzb), Kyrgyztan (Kyr), Uyghurstan (Uyg), Greece (Gre), France (Fra), Netherlands (Net), Germany (Ger), Czech and Slovakia (CzandSlo), Alabina (Ala), Macedonia (Mac), Poland (Pol), Hungary (Hun), Ukraine (Ukr), Georgia (Geo), Dhodia (Dh), Dubla (Du), Konkana (Kon), Vasava (Vas), Gamit (Gam), Valvi Chaudhari (VC), Nana Chaudhari (NC), Mota Chaudhari (MC), Pavagadhi Chaudhari (PC).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The North-Western corridor of India has witnessed many waves of migrants from different parts of the world, with a majority being male migrants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Bamshad1">[31]</xref>. Gujarat is located on the western most point of the Indian sub-continent and has acted as a significant corridor to draw outsiders -conquerors, refugees and travellers who have contributed significantly to the present day gene pool of Indian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kivisild1">[34]</xref>. Valsad and Surat districts are part of the tribal belt of Gujarat and are composed of tribal populations which are linguistically classified as Indo-European. To date several studies have provided significant insights into the paternal genetic history of India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sahoo1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kivisild1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Cordaux2">[36]</xref>; however none till now had taken into consideration the Indo-European speaking tribal populations inhabiting Gujarat in spite of their interesting geographical location and cultural attributes. It is also worth mentioning that the Indo-European speaking tribes of India not only exhibit the complexity of historical interaction between the indigenous Indian and migratory groups but also reflect lack of one-to-one correlation between language, mode of subsistence and social system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sahoo1">[23]</xref>. Thus, the Indo-European speaking tribes represent an appropriate model to study the possible genetic foot prints of the multiple waves of migrations. In addition to tracing the origin and impact of ancient migrations, evaluation of the impact of geography and social structure in shaping the genetic structure of the present day Indo-European speaking tribal populations of Gujarat was considered equally important. Thus, in the subsequent text we examine the paternal genetic variation of the nine Indo-European speaking tribes from Gujarat using high resolution Y chromosomal unique event polymorphisms (UEPs).</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Genetic structure of study populations</title>
<p>Our analysis based on Y chromosomal UEPs apportioned the study samples into 13 haplogroups representing 10 major Y lineages (C5, H1a*, H2, R1a1*, R2, J2, L1, F*, K* and Q3) in India. Haplogroup diversity (0.772) was found to be comparable with Dravidian speaking populations (0.723), but higher than Indo-European speaking populations (0.684) in the country <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Trivedi1">[54]</xref>. Given the number of views in support of Austro-Asiatic and Dravidian speaking tribes belonging to the primary pre-historic population of India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Thapar1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Malhotra1">[11]</xref>; the high gene diversity values observed in the study populations, which are in turn comparable to Dravidian speaking populations, are suggestive of greater antiquity, large effective size or role of gene flow in these groups. The analysis of molecular variance revealed that the extent of genetic differentiation was high among study populations which could be attributed to either the lower effective population size of these groups or the Y chromosome making them vulnerable to the effect of genetic drift which further accelerates the process of differentiation between the populations. But, accentuated differentiation due to genetic drift is expected to be accompanied with lower diversity. However, in the present study, elevated levels of gene diversity, rule out a major role of genetic drift in shaping the observed pattern of genetic differentiation. Nevertheless, the explanation for the observation of high gene diversity coupled with high-level of genetic differentiation could lie in an overwhelming genetic admixture from different sources or in an early inflow of genes from a common source followed by rapid population expansion and subsequent fission into isolated, endogamous populations. Results from Harpending and Ward analysis do not appear to favour the former explanation. Thus, the most plausible explanation for the current diversity scenario in the Indian population seems to be the suggestion made by Majumder et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Majumder2">[17]</xref>, in which an early demographic expansion of modern humans within India during Palaeolithic period and later fission of the populations is conjectured.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>In-situ versus Ex-situ Origin of Y lineages</title>
<p>The indigenous versus exogenous origin of Indian paternal lineages has been widely contested. Among the study populations, six sub-haplogroups namely, C5, H1a*, H2, J2, R1a1* and R2 constituted the major paternal lineages that together accounted for 85.92% of the Y chromosomes. While the indigenous origin of sub-clades C5, H1a*, H2 and R2 are accepted, the status of sub-clades J2 and R1a1* are contested as they are believed to have been introduced in India with the demic diffusion of Proto-Dravidian Neolithic agriculturists from West Asia and the influx of Indo-European pastorals from Central Asia. It is worth mentioning here that the high frequency and associated diversity of a haplogroup is correlated with the possible place of origin of a particular haplogroup <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Barbujani1">[55]</xref>. In the present investigation haplogroup H, especially H1a, represented the most frequently observed Y chromosomal lineage followed by H2 sub-haplogroup. Its higher frequency among the Indian tribes particularly among the Dravidian speaking tribes of South India and its limited presence elsewhere on the Indian subcontinent had led some scholars to denote it as a tribe-specific haplogroup <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Cordaux2">[36]</xref>. However, several subsequent studies have confirmed the presence and equal prevalence of haplogroup H and its associated H1a and H2 branches across linguistically and ethnically diverse populations and in different regions of India, except the North-Eastern region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sahoo1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Trivedi1">[54]</xref>; thus ruling it out as a tribal-specific marker and supporting the uniform distribution of haplogroup H among Indian populations. An Indian homeland for haplogroup H can also not be refuted keeping in view its higher microsatellite diversity among Indian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>. Haplogroup H has also been reported from Central Asian, West Asian and Gypsy populations in Europe. However, its low frequency and prevalent diversity pattern in Central Asia and West Asia could be due to recent back migration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Wells1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Regueiro1">[52]</xref>. On the other hand, the established Indian ancestry of gypsy populations is surely the reason for elevated levels of H haplogroup among them <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Rai1">[56]</xref>. All the observations, therefore clearly point towards in-situ origin of haplogroup H among Indian populations.</p>
<p>Haplogroup C is widely distributed in Eastern and Central Asia, Oceania and Australia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Karafet1">[44]</xref>. As expected, all the Y chromosomes under C haplogroup belonged to the C5 sub-clade. It was observed in a frequency of 8.45% which is the highest ever reported frequency for C5 in India and whose spread is circumscribed along the coastal belt of India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Trivedi1">[54]</xref>. High STR diversity in India and South-East Asia in the backdrop of haplogroup C has also been observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kivisild1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Zhong1">[57]</xref>. Interestingly none of the C haplogroup derivatives frequent in South-East Asia have been reported from India. Therefore, the possibility of introduction of C5 haplogroup from South-East Asia as a result of back migration to India appears doubtful and its indigenous origin appears to be more probable <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sonakia1">[13]</xref>.</p>
<p>Haplogroup J is predominantly found among the populations of West Asia, North Africa, Europe, Central Asia, Pakistan, and India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Karafet1">[44]</xref> and widely linked with the spread of agriculture from the Fertile Crescent that extends from Israel to Western Iraq. In the Indian subcontinent two sub-clades of J - J2a and J2b have been reported. Consistent with the previous studies, a higher proportion of J2 in West India as compared to North and South regions of India has been recorded in the present study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Trivedi1">[54]</xref>. Two models pertaining to the homeland for Indian J2 sub-clades have been contested, West Asia and Central Asia. Cordaux et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Cordaux1">[35]</xref> had proposed the Central Asian homeland for Indian J2 sub-clade mainly because of higher frequency of J2 in Central Asia. It is worth mentioning here that J1 sub-clade which appears in appreciable frequency in Central Asia is largely absent from the Indian as well as most of the West Asian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Karafet1">[44]</xref>. Haplogroup R is represented by two sub-clades R1a1* and R2 among the study populations. After haplogroup H1a, haplogroup R1a1* represented the most frequently occurring haplogroup. Haplogroup R is widely distributed in Central Asia, Eastern Europe, West Asia and the Indian subcontinent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Karafet3">[58]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Underhill2">[59]</xref>. The higher frequency of haplogroup R1a, up to 63% in Central Asia and its relatively lower occurrence in other regions has been linked with Central Asian origin of R1a clade <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Cordaux2">[36]</xref>. However, later studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Trivedi1">[54]</xref> showing higher prevalence of R1a sub-clade along with high microsatellite diversity among the tribal populations of India lend support to probable South Asian origin of R1a sub-clade as suggested by Kivisild et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kivisild1">[34]</xref>. This is further substantiated by almost the complete absence of other derivatives of haplogroup R1 among the Indian populations, which is expected in case of the inflow from Central Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sahoo1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sharma1">[41]</xref>.</p>
<p>In the present investigation sub-clade R2 occurred with a frequency of 9.51%, which is similar to its frequency reported from other Indian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Sengupta1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Kivisild1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Cordaux2">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Trivedi1">[54]</xref>. The frequency of R2 decreases as one goes further west from India and its frequency is almost negligible in Europe. Moreover, its frequent occurrence among Dravidian speaking groups as compared to Indo-European or Austro-Asiatic speaking groups of India can be attributed to its indigenous Indian origin.</p>
<p>The MDS plot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0090414-g004">Figure 4</xref>) also reflects the closeness of South Asian populations with West Asian and Central Asian populations possibly due to overlapping of haplogroups. In comparison to the world populations the overall mean haplogroup diversity among the study populations was relatively higher than in the European or East Asian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Wells1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Semino1">[48]</xref> whereas it was found to be lower than that of Central Asian and West Asian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Karafet2">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Flores1">[51]</xref>. As mentioned earlier the high frequency and diversity of a haplogroup is indicator of the possible place of origin of a particular haplogroup <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0090414-Barbujani1">[55]</xref>. Consequently, the observed haplogroups in the present investigation could be apportioned into three Y lineages based on their possible origin. These lineages include Central Asian, West Asian and indigenous Indian Y lineages.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>Determinants of population Clustering</title>
<p>Lack of any major exogenous contribution of Y lineages and existence of high haplogroup diversity indicate the possible male assimilation from other neighbouring populations of India among the study groups. Analysis of molecular variance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0090414-t003">Table 3</xref>) performed on the basis of haplogroup frequencies revealed some interesting patterns. The quantification of variance into different categories of population showed the highest variance between the four linguistic groups of India followed by the variance between geographical regions and finally the caste versus tribe categories. The least percentage of variance was observed between the study populations and other Indo-European speaking caste populations. However, the geographical partitioning of the Indo-European speaking tribal and caste populations into three major zones: West, Central and East showed the important effect of geography in shaping the Y diversity pattern since on this basis the zonal percentage of variance was observed to elevate between the study populations and other Indo-European groups of India. Thus, pattern of Y chromosome clustering of Indian populations reflects the major role of geography over language and ethnicity as far as Y chromosomal lineages are concerned. After Indo-European speaking caste populations, the lowest variance of Gujarat populations was observed with Dravidian speaking tribal populations. These similarities suggest either shared paternal ancestries of linguistically dissimilar groups or the influence over the indigenous tribal groups of India of the Indo-European speakers, who arrived later.</p>
<p>The present investigation indicates that tribes of Gujarat show both high genetic diversity and genetic differentiation. It is therefore conceivable that these groups, with a fairly large population size, have passed through a long evolutionary history experiencing an early demographic expansion and later fission of the populations. Further affinities of study groups with Indo-European speaking non tribes followed by Dravidian speaking tribal groups suggest the possibility that these native tribal population groups of Western India might have adopted the Indo-European language during the process of cultural assimilation and absorption while still retaining their genetic links with the Dravidian speaking tribal populations. Thus, it is recommended that the present day linguistic affiliation of any Indian population should be considered with caution while reconstructing the demographic history of the country. In conclusion, a study based on the recently discovered bi-allelic loci and microsatellite loci in the populations can shed light on the possible explanation of the overlapping of haplogroup distribution between tribes of Gujarat with other Asian populations and further deepen the understanding of the population history of India.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0090414.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Y chromosome haplogroup frequencies data among study populations and other populations of India considered for AMOVA.</bold></p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0090414.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0090414.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Y chromosome haplogroup frequencies data among study populations and other populations of World considered for MDS analyses.</bold></p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank all the individuals who volunteered for this study on genetic variation and provided their blood samples. We would like to extend our gratitude towards the <italic>Valsad Raktdan Kendra</italic> (Centre for Blood Donation, Valsad), Valsad, Gujarat for helping us collect the blood samples. We would also like to thank the Anthropological Survey of India for their collaboration and for giving the permission to undertake our laboratory work in their Southern Regional Centre. We also wish to thank the Department of Anthropology, University of Delhi, Delhi for granting us the ethical clearance to carry out our work.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Census1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Census of India (2011) Registrar General and Census commissioner, Government of India.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Singh1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>People of India: The profile of national project (1985–92)</article-title>. <source>Curr Sci</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Gadgil1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadgil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Adaptive significance of the Indian caste system: an ecological perspective</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Joshi1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gadgil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Exploring cultural diversity of the people of India</article-title>. <source>Curr Sci</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Census2"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Census of India (2001) Registrar General and Census commissioner, Government of India.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Fuchs1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Fuchs S (1964) Anthropometry of the Gujarat tribes. In: Shah PG, editor. Tribal life in Gujarat. Bombay: Gujarat Research Society. pp. 263–275.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Thapar1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Thapar R (1966) A history of India. Volume 1. Middlesex, UK: Penguin.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Ray1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Ray N (1973) Nationalism in India. Aligarh, India: Aligarh Muslim University.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Majumder1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>People of India: biological diversity and affinities</article-title>. <source>Evol Anthrop</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Meenakshi1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Meenakshi K (1995) Linguistics and the study of early Indian history. In: Thapar R, editor. Recent perspectives of early Indian history. Mumbai, India: Popular Prakashan. pp 53–79.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Malhotra1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Malhotra KC, Vasulu TS (1993) Structure of human populationsin India. In: Majumdar PP, editor. Human population genetics: a centennial tribute to J.B.S. Haldane. New York: Plenum Press. pp. 207–233.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Gadgil2"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Gadgil M, Joshi NV, Prasad UVS, Manoharan S, Patil S (1997) Peopling of India. In: Balasubramanian D, Rao NN, editors. The Indian human heritage. Hyderabad: University Press. pp. 100–129.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Sonakia1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonakia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Skull cap of an early man from the Narmada valley alluvium (Pleistocene) of central India</article-title>. <source>Am Anthropol</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>612</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Kennedy1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>KAR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deraniyagala</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Fossil remains of 28,000-year-old hominids from Sri Lanka</article-title>. <source>Curr Anthropol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>394</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Misra1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Stone age in India: an ecological perspective</article-title>. <source>Man Environ</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Cameron1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patnaik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sahni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The phylogenetic significance of the Middle Pleistocene Narmada cranium from Central India</article-title>. <source>Int J of Osteo</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Majumder2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Human-specific insertion/deletion polymorphisms in Indian populations and their possible evolutionary implications</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Indian1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">Indian Genome Variation Consortium</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genetic landscape of the people of India: a canvas for disease gene exploration</article-title>. <source>J Genet</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Reich1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thangaraj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Reconstructing Indian population history</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>461</volume>: <fpage>489</fpage>–<lpage>494</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Chandrasekar1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrasekar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sreenath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urade</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Updating phylogeny of Mitochondrial DNA macrohaplogroup M in India: dispersal of modern human in South Asian corridor</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e7447</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Thangaraj1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thangaraj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genetic Affinities of the Andaman Islanders, a Vanishing Human Population</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Underhill1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passarino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Y chromosome sequence variation and the history of human populations</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>358</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Sahoo1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Himabindu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sitalaximi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A prehistory of Indian Y chromosomes: evaluating demic diffusion scenarios</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Sengupta1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhivotovsky</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehdi</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Polarity and temporality of high-resolution Y-chromosome distributions in India identify both indigenous and exogenous expansions and reveal minor genetic influence of central Asian pastoralists</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Kumar1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langstieh</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Y-chromosome evidence suggests a common paternal heritage of Austro-Asiatic populations</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Ratnagar1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Ratnagar S (1995) Archaeological perspectives of early Indian societies. In: Thapar R editor. Recent perspectives of early Indian history Bombay, India: Popular Prakashan. pp. 1–52.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Chaubey1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaubey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Population genetic structure in Indian Austroasiatic speakers the role of landscape barriers and sex-specific admixture</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1024</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Gadgil3"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Gadgil M., Joshi NV, Manoharan S, Patil S, Prasad UVS (1998) In: Balasubramanian, D, Rao NA, editors. The Indian Human Heritage. Hyderabad: Hyderabad University press. pp. 100–129.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Pattanayak1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Pattanayak DP (1998) In: The Indian Human Heritage. Balasubramanian D, Rao NA, editors. Universities Press, Hyderabad. pp. 95–99.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-CavalliSforza1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Cavalli-Sforza LL, Menozzi P, Piazza A (1994) The history and geography of human genes. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Bamshad1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bamshad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kivisild</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricker</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Genetic evidence on the origins of Indian caste populations</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>1004</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Wells1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuldasheva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruzibakiev</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evseeva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The Eurasian heartland: a continental perspective on Y-chromosome diversity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>10244</fpage>–<lpage>10249</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Basu1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Ethnic India: a genomic view, with special reference to peopling and structure</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>2277</fpage>–<lpage>2290</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Kivisild1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kivisild</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rootsi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mastana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaldma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The genetic heritage of earliest settlers persist in both the Indian tribal and caste populations</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Cordaux1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordaux</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aunger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sirajuddin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA analysis reveals diverse histories of tribal populations from India</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Cordaux2"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordaux</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aunger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nasidze</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sirajuddin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Independent origins of Indian caste and tribal paternal lineages</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-CavalliSforza2"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalli-Sforza</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mountain</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Coevolution of genes and languages revisited</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>5620</fpage>–<lpage>5624</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Roychoudhury1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roychoudhury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vishwanathan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Genomic structure and population histories of linguistically distinct tribal groups of India</article-title>. <source>Hum Genet</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Chaubey2"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaubey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metspalu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karmin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thangaraj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rootsi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Language shift by indigenous population: A model genetic study in South Asia</article-title>. <source>Int J Hum Genet</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Kshatriya1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kshatriya</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Italia</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Genomic congruence of Indo-European speaking tribes of Western India with Dravidian-speaking populations of southern India: A study of 20 autosomal DNA markers</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Biol</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>591</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Sharma1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genetic affinities of the Central Indian tribal populations</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e32546</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Kshatriya2"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kshatriya</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Italia</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genomic and linguistic affinities: a study of allelic and haplotype diversity at DRD2 locus among the tribes of Gujarat, Western India</article-title>. <source>Genet Test Mol Biomarkers</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Miller1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dykes</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polesky</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>A simple salting out procedure for extracting DNA from human nucleated cells</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1215</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Karafet1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karafet</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meilerman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zegura</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>New binary polymorphisms reshape and increase resolution of the human Y chromosomal haplogroup tree</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>830</fpage>–<lpage>838</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Harpending1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Harpending HC, Ward R (1982) Chemical systematics and human evolution. In: Nitecki M, editor. Biochemical aspects of evolutionary biology. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. pp. 213–256.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Excoffier1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laval</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Arlequin: An integrated software for population genetics data analysis</article-title>. <source>Evol Bioinform Online</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Thangaraj2"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thangaraj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naidu</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crivellaro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The influence of natural barriers in shaping the genetic structure of Maharashtra populations</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e15283</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Semino1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semino</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passarino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oefner</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arbuzova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The genetic legacy of Paleolithic Homo sapiens sapiens in extant Europeans: a Y chromosome perspective</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>290</volume>: <fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Karafet2"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karafet</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osipova</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gubina</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posukh</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>High levels of Y-chromosome differentiation among native Siberian populations and the genetic signature of a boreal hunter-gatherer way of life</article-title>. <source>Hum Biol</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>761</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Qamar1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qamar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayub</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohyuddin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Helgason</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazhar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Y-chromosomal DNA variation in Pakistan</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1107</fpage>–<lpage>1124</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Flores1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maca-Meyer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karadsheh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Isolates in a corridor of migrations: a high-resolution analysis of Y-chromosome variation in Jordan</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Regueiro1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Regueiro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cadenas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gayden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Iran: tricontinental nexus for Y-chromosome driven migration</article-title>. <source>Hum Hered</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>132</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Haber1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashrafian Bonab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Youhanna</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soria-Hernaz</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Afghanistan's ethnic groups share a Y-chromosomal heritage structured by historical events</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e34288</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Trivedi1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bindu</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genetic imprints of pleistocene prigin of Indian Ppopulations: A comprehensive phylogeographic sketch of Indian populations</article-title>. <source>Int J Hum Genet</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Barbujani1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbujani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Geographic patterns: how to identify them and why</article-title>. <source>Hum Biol</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Rai1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaubey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The phylogeography of Y-chromosome haplogroup h1a1a-82 reveals the likely Indian origin of the European Romani populations</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e48477</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Zhong1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Global distribution of Y-chromosome haplogroup C reveals the prehistoric migration routes of African exodus and early settlement in East Asia</article-title>. <source>Hum Genet</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Karafet3"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karafet</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zegura</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posukh</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osipova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Ancestral Asian source(s) of new world Y-chromosome founder haplotypes</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>817</fpage>–<lpage>831</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0090414-Underhill2"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passarino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirazón Lahr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The phylogeography of the Y chromosome binary haplotypes and the origins of modern human populations</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Genet</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>