<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-54091</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095361</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavioral ecology</subject><subject>Evolutionary ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physical anthropology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal behavior</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Ecology and environmental sciences</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychological anthropology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Chimpanzees Preferentially Select Sleeping Platform Construction Tree Species with Biomechanical Properties that Yield Stable, Firm, but Compliant Nests</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Chimpanzees Know Sleep Tree Species Biomechanics</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>David R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>Kevin D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Anthropology, University of Nevada, Las Vegas, Las Vegas, Nevada, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Anthropology, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brosnan</surname><given-names>Sarah Frances</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Georgia State University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">drsamson@gmail.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DRS. Performed the experiments: DRS. Analyzed the data: DRS KDH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DRS KDH. Wrote the paper: DRS KDH.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<elocation-id>e95361</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Samson, Hunt</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The daily construction of a sleeping platform or “nest” is a universal behavior among large-bodied hominoids. Among chimpanzees, most populations consistently select particular tree species for nesting, yet the principles that guide species preferences are poorly understood. At Semliki, <italic>Cynometra alexandri</italic> constitutes only 9.6% of all trees in the gallery forest in which the study populations ranges, but it was selected for 73.6% of the 1,844 chimpanzee night beds we sampled. To determine whether physical properties influence nesting site selection, we measured the physical characteristics of seven common tree species at the Toro-Semliki Wildlife Reserve, Uganda. We determined stiffness and bending strength for a sample of 326 branches from the seven most commonly used tree species. We selected test-branches with diameters typically used for nest construction. We measured internode distance, calculated mean leaf surface area (cm<sup>2</sup>) and assigned a tree architecture category to each of the seven species. <italic>C. alexandri</italic> fell at the extreme of the sample for all four variables and shared a tree architecture with only one other of the most commonly selected species. <italic>C. alexandri</italic> was the stiffest and had the greatest bending strength; it had the smallest internode distance and the smallest leaf surface area. <italic>C. alexandri</italic> and the second most commonly selected species, <italic>Cola gigantea,</italic> share a ‘Model of Koriba’ tree architecture. We conclude that chimpanzees are aware of the structural properties of <italic>C. alexandri</italic> branches and choose it because its properties afford chimpanzees sleeping platforms that are firm, stable and resilient.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>National Science Foundation (SGER BNS 97-11124 and BCS 98-15991) and Indiana University (Faculty Research Support Program and the College of Arts and Sciences. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Juvenile and adult apes devote considerable time and energy to the construction of a new sleeping platform or “nest” at the end of their daily active period <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Goodall1">[1]</xref>. Current data suggests that infants and young juveniles (i.e. nursing young) acquire skills over years both through observation of their mother and practice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Goodall1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Videan1">[3]</xref> and begin making their own nests after weaning. The universality of sleeping platform construction among the great apes suggests the behavior is genetically predisposed, though observation and learning are known to be critical <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Videan1">[3]</xref>. Nest-builders must select an appropriate site, climb to the site and manipulate a large volume of foliage while maintaining balance. They bend and break stiff, strong stems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Goodall1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Goodall2">[2]</xref> as they incorporate foliage into the nest structure, pulling nest material inwards and interweaving it into a thick, springy ‘mattress,’ often bending branches in two. Ape nest mattresses are functionally concave in that either the edges are elevated over the mattress surface or the edges are less compliant than the center <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart1">[4]</xref>, causing the nest to assume a concave surface under pressure.</p>
<p>The function of sleeping platforms seems straightforward: a compliant yet constraining structure reduces stress on tissues and the functional concavity of the nests obviates the need to adjust posture during sleep to prevent falls. This <italic>sleep quality hypothesis</italic> holds that apes construct sleeping platforms to allow uninterrupted sleep and to promote longer individual sleep stages, resulting in a higher sleep quality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Videan1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Videan2">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson1">[9]</xref>. Additionally, captive orangutans exhibit higher quality sleep with less gross-motor movements and greater overall sleep times when using complex sleeping platforms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson2">[10]</xref>. The evidence for the sleep quality hypothesis seems compelling, yet observations of patterns of nest site selection, nest heights and the physical characteristics of the most-preferred tree species are taken by some researchers as supporting a different function for nesting (although these hypotheses need not be mutually exclusive), including <italic>predation avoidance</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart3">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Pruetz1">[12]</xref>, <italic>postural stability</italic> (preventing falls assumed to be more likely because apes have great body mass relative to local supporting branch diameter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Baldwin1">[13]</xref>), <italic>thermoregulation</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-McGrew1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart2">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Koops1">[14]</xref>, and <italic>pathogen avoidance</italic>–either because the nest serves as a physical barrier to insect vectors such as mosquitoes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-McGrew1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart2">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Nunn1">[15]</xref> or because some chemical property of the species selected for nesting discourages mosquitoes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart2">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson3">[16]</xref>. In accord with <italic>predation avoidance,</italic> chimpanzees appear to select sites both as far from the main stem or trunk as possible and with an escape route to neighboring trees due to canopy connectivity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart3">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Anderson1">[17]</xref>. In accord with the <italic>sleep quality hypothesis</italic>, tree species with smaller leaves and/or denser leaf distribution are argued to be selected to reduce stress on pressure points thus affording ‘comfort’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart1">[4]</xref> and potentially effect thermoregulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Fruth2">[18]</xref>. Tree morphology may influence site selection because particular branching patterns such as the inverted tripod form is most easily manipulated into a bowl-shaped nest; chimpanzee preference at Bwindi for <italic>Drypetes gerrardii</italic> is hypothesized to be related to its “lollipop” crown shape and tripod morphology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stanford1">[19]</xref>. Furthermore, tree morphologies may be reinforced through time by way of long term re-use of trees, which shapes local branch ‘morphologies’ of potential sleep sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart4">[20]</xref>.</p>
<p>To the extent that tree species vary in morphology, physical characteristics such as stiffness and habitat preference, functional imperatives are expected to be expressed in the selection of particular tree species as sleeping sites. If the sleep quality hypothesis is correct, chimpanzees should prefer species that have smaller leaves, denser canopies and tripod-shaped branchings, compared to other available species. It follows from the thermoregulation hypothesis that species with dense, leafier canopies would be preferred. The predator-avoidance hypothesis entails a preference for tree species that are tall, are characterized by broad canopies and are distributed near waterways or gorges because slopes increase the functional height of nests. The antivector hypothesis suggests that species with certain volatile compounds in bark, sap or leaves will be preferentially selected.</p>
<p>Branch diameters of supporting structures have been shown to be an essential variable for understanding sleep site selection and canopy movement in orangutans, as local diameter is negatively related to compliance and positively related to length of the trunk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-vanCasteren1">[21]</xref>. Furthermore, is has been suggested that orangutans choose nest sites that afford stem diameters that yield optimal nest characteristics and that they manipulate nest materials in specific ways that demonstrate technical knowledge concerning structural properties of stems. Orangutan sleeping platforms have a high proportion of “greenstick fractures,” which are purported to impart a stronger and more resilient quality to supporting branches, suggesting that orangutans purposely break branches in this fashion during nest construction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-vanCasteren2">[22]</xref>. Semliki chimpanzee tree-species preference may indicate that chimpanzees display technical knowledge of the physical properties of raw materials similar to that of orangutans and that it leads them to choose particular species for nesting. Eastern chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic>) at three relatively dry sites (Ishaha <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Sept1">[23]</xref>, Budongo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Brownlow1">[24]</xref> and Toro-Semliki <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Hunt1">[25]</xref>) in western Uganda strongly prefer the species <italic>Cynometra alexandri</italic> (C.H.Wright) as raw material for sleeping platform construction. <italic>C. alexandri</italic> is common in dry or riverine forests throughout Central and East Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Plumptre1">[26]</xref> where the wood is often known locally as ‘ironwood’ or ‘muhindi’ in recognition of its dense, durable and resilient qualities; it is useful as a construction material <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Chudnoff1">[27]</xref>. Here we compare the structural qualities of seven common species of trees at Semliki to determine whether chimpanzees purposely select tree species that possess mechanical properties that determine superior nesting qualities.</p>
<p>A body mass of 30 kg or more means that chimpanzees require strong materials to contain their center of mass during sleep phases with a period of physical paralysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson1">[9]</xref>. Furthermore, it is expected that materials with great stiffness would be preferred for construction of a springy mattress that can bear weight without over-compressing thus allowing contact with inflexible and uncomfortable large-diameter supports. If the physical properties of trees influence nesting site selection, we predict that the trees most commonly selected by chimpanzees will have significantly greater strength (capacity to bear stress before catastrophic failure), a higher elastic modulus or stiffness, significantly smaller internode distances (correlated with stiffness), tree architecture characterized by a high proportion of inverted tripod branchings and/or small leaf surface areas.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Ethics Statement</title>
<p>Authorization to conduct research inside Uganda was granted by the Government of Uganda. Permission to carry out research at the Toro-Semliki Wildlife Reserve was granted and approved through permits from the Uganda Wildlife Authority (UWA) and the National Research Council.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Study Area</title>
<p>The Toro-Semliki Wildlife Reserve (TSWR) occupies 548 km<sup>2</sup> in the Great Rift Valley from the Semliki River in the west to the top of the escarpment in the east, and from the foothills of the Ruwenzori Mountains in the south to the shore of Lake Albert in the north, northwest of Fort Portal, Uganda (0°50′ to 1°05′N, 30°20′ to 30°35′ E). The Wasa River runs from south to north through the center of the reserve, emptying into Lake Albert in the north. The reserve is crosscut by small, shallow, often seasonal water-courses that support narrow gallery forests ranging in width from 50–250 m <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Hunt1">[25]</xref>. The chimpanzee study community occupies the Mugiri River valley and eastwards up the escarpment slope to include valleys and seasonal tributaries to the Mugiri and the open woodland, bushland and grassland between the water-course; the community home range is the largest known of any site <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson4">[28]</xref> and has been calculated to be 96 km<sup>2</sup> (minimum convex polygon). The biome is predominantly dry <italic>Combretum</italic> and <italic>Borassus</italic> palm grassland with only 7.25% forest cover <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Hunt1">[25]</xref>. The habitat is hot and dry, with a daily maximum averaging 34°C and an average rainfall of 1389 mm (1996–2012), though earlier rainfall records vary between 700 and 1300 mm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Plumptre1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Pratt1">[29]</xref>. The Mugiri community may have 150 members; 29 males have been identified, but few females are known as individuals; however, typical chimpanzee demography yields 60 females and 60 immatures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stumpf1">[30]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Sleeping Platform Tree Species</title>
<p>Phenology data on tree species distribution throughout the habitat was used from previous work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Hunt1">[25]</xref>. Chimpanzee sleeping platforms were noted during the course of regular behavioral observation. Typical variables were recorded for each nest, including the species in which the nest was found. N = 1844 nests were included in the sample.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Tree Architecture Classification</title>
<p>We followed van Wyk and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-vanWyk1">[31]</xref> in assigning tree species used for nesting to one of 23 architectural model categories. Tree architecture is classified according to the developmental sequence of axes, or shoots <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-vanWyk1">[31]</xref>. Six tree architecture models were used for nest construction at Semliki (with associated prevalence throughout the home range): <italic>Model of Attim</italic> (9.9%), <italic>Model of Fagerlind</italic> (5.3%), <italic>Model of Koriba</italic> (58.2%), <italic>Model of Leeuwenberg</italic> (10.4%), <italic>Model of Tomlinson</italic> (4.4%), <italic>and Model of Troll</italic> (0.4%). We used <italic>X<sup>2</sup></italic> analysis to assess chimpanzee preference for architectural models, relative to prevalence within the home range.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Material Properties Measurement</title>
<p>Our methods closely followed Stewart and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart1">[4]</xref> by determining the biomechanical propeties of stems (a primary plant axis that develops buds and shoots instead of roots). Three-hundred and twenty six stems were used from the same multiple species generated in a sample of 65 nests from May–June 2008 and August 2010–January 2011; samples closely conformed to the length and diameter of “frame support branches” in nests (FSB diameter [N = 60, 4.13 cm ±1.11], see 9); FSB’s are branches that have been bent double and interwoven in the initial stages of nest construction and are used as primary weight bearing supports. The force in kg required to bend stems to 45°, 90° and to the point of structural failure were measured with a spring balance. We used the point of attachment of the spring balance and the distance from the anchor point to the break point to calculate torque, equal to the force applied multiplied by the distance between an object’s axis of rotation and the point where the force is applied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart1">[4]</xref>. A relative break force (RBF) value was calculated using a standardized measure of the force necessary to break any branch at a distance of 1 m. The RBF values were used to assess bending strength across tree species (One-way ANOVAs). <italic>Beilschmiedia ugandensis</italic> was an ideal control given its rare selection as a sleeping site and ubiquity throughout the home range and was featured in a LSD post hoc analysis of the RBF values compared among preferred species.</p>
<p>We measured internode lengths (N = 2574) along the stems of selected tree species often selected for sleeping sites to compare internode distances among genera (One-way ANOVA), using <italic>Beilschmiedia ugandensis</italic> as a control. We calculated the surface area of leaves (N<italic> = </italic>428) from selected tree species by tracing leaf outlines over 1 cm<sup>2</sup> paper (then summing the number of squares within the outline) and compared species using a one-way ANOVA, again with <italic>B. ugandensis</italic> used as a control.</p>
<p>All statistical tests were 2-tailed, set at an alpha = 0.05 significance level.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Of 1,844 nests sampled, <italic>Cynometra alexandri</italic> was selected for 73.6% of the nests, even though it represents only 9.6% of all trees on our 20 habitat-sampling transects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0095361-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Hunt1">[25]</xref>); this value is the second strongest preference for sleeping tree species recorded to date among all chimpanzee sites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095361-t001">Table 1</xref>). The second most commonly selected tree species at Semliki was <italic>Cola gigantea,</italic> constituting 9.2% of all recorded nests, but representing only 0.9% tree species in the habitat. The most common species sampled on our transects was <italic>Beilschmiedia ugandensis,</italic> representing 42.3% of all tree species. This most-common species was selected for nesting only 16 times, making up only 0.8% of all nests. Other species selected for nesting were <italic>Albizia grandibracteata, Combretum molle, Ficus mucuso, Phoenix reclinata</italic> and <italic>Pseudospondias microcarpa.</italic></p>
<fig id="pone-0095361-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Top seven tree species selected by chimpanzees for sleeping platform construction at TSWR relative to species availability, included the control species <italic>Beilschmiedia ugandensis</italic> selected as a sleeping site &lt;1% (adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Hunt1">[25]</xref>).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0095361-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Previously recorded chimpanzee sleeping tree species preference by field site.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0095361-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tree species</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>West Africa</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cantanhez, Guinea- Bissau</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Elaeis guineensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Sousa1">[34]</xref>(11) et al. 2008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German-Fort, Gashaka- Gumti, Nigeria</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Khaya seneganensis</italic> (dry season), <italic>Craibia atlantica</italic> (wet season)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Ogunjemite1">[35]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yealé, Nimba, Ivory Coast</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Chidlowia sanguinea</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Humle1">[36]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assirik, Senegal</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Spondias mombin, Adansonia digitata</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Baldwin1">[13]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Central Africa</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goualougo Triangle, Nouabalé-Ndoki,CongoSanz et al. 2007Ham 199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Greenwayodendron suaveolens</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Sanz1">[37]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ishasha, DRC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra alexandri</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Sept1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Sept2">[38]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tishibati, Kahuzi-Biega, DRC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Syzygium parvifolium</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Basabose1">[39]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rio Muni, Equatorial Guinea</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Spondias mombin, Adansonia digiata</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Baldwin1">[13]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pongara, Gabon</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Coula edulis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Petre1">[40]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seringbara Nimba, Guinea</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Amanoa bracteosa</italic> (two study periods), <italic>Childlowia sanguinea</italic>(one study period)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.910.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Koops1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Humle1">[36]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wawba, DRC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Leonardoxa romii</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Mulavwa1">[41]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yalosidi, DRC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Leonardoxa romii</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Kano1">[42]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>East Africa</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gombe, TanzaniaGoodall 1962Hernandez-Aguilar 201</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachstegia bussei, Elaes grineensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Goodall1">[1]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Issa, Tanzania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachystegia sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-HernandezAguilar1">[43]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kasakati, Tanzania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra sp.</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Izawa1">[44]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lwazi, Tanzania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trichilia dregeana, Pseudospondia microcarpa, Dichapetalum stuhlmannii</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Ogawa1">[45]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ntakata/Kakungu, Tanzania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachystegia bussei</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Ogawa2">[46]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ugalla, Tanzania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Monopetalanthus richardsiae</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Ogawa3">[47]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kwitanga, Tanzania</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brachstegia bussei</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Ndimuligo1">[48]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Budongo, Uganda</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra alexandri</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Brownlow1">[24]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bwindi, Uganda</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Drypetes gerrardii</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stanford1">[19]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kalinzu, Uganda</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Uvariopsis congensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Ndimuligo1">[48]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kibale Ngogo, Uganda</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Uvariopsis congensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Ghiglieri1">[49]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semliki, Uganda</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra alexandri</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Hunt1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson4">[28]</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Field sites recording up to three preferred species, without statistical supporting data, were included; citations where greater than three species were recorded as “preferred” were not included. Percentages were included when presented.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>In a one-way ANOVA test <italic>C. alexandri</italic> was the stiffest and most stress resistant of the eight species we tested, with the highest relative break force (RBF) greater than the other seven species in three of four diameter categories (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095361-t002">Table 2</xref> for RBF distributions and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095361-t003">Table 3</xref> for post hoc analysis), category 1, &lt;3 cm (F [6, 199]) = 11.49, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001), category 2, 3–4.9 cm (F [6, 155] = 6.41, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001), category 3, 5–6.9 cm (F [6, 50] = 10.80, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). Size category 4, 7–9 cm, (F <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stewart1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson3">[16]</xref> = 0.84, <italic>P</italic> = 0.524) did not differ significantly from other species; however, our sample contained very few branches in this diameter category (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095361-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0095361-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Relative break force values (scores 1–4) of the preferred species used to construct SPs (including the control <italic>Beilschmiedia ugandensis</italic>); total N = 441 tested breaks and generated RBF values.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0095361-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diameter Score</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Top seven genera RBF values</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean and SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N total per species</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (&lt;3 cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213.7±116.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34–721</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cola</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.7±62.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71–248</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudospondias</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.9±67.54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22–312</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Combretum</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.5±55.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37–192</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albizia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.1±70.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26–331</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Beilschmeidia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0±62.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33–220</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phoenix</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.7±36.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52–124</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3–5 cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">531.8±284.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120–1650</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudospondias</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">408.5±33.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103–1063</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Beilschmeidia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367.3±152.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220–670</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Combretum</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">353.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phoenix</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270.8±224.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55–568</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cola</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253.4±147.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82–607</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albizia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240.9±129.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56–445</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5–7 cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1493.9±473.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">856–2200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudospondias</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1019.9±420.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469–1550</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Beilschmeidia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">838.5±166.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">700–1068</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Combretum</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">596.0±567.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196–1246</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phoenix</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">589.8±64.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">499–653</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cola</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">520.5±217.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259–1104</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albizia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">504.0±293.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215–1052</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7–9 cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1630.3±460.88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1301–2306</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Beilschmeidia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1364.5±459.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">791–2200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cola</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1340.0±721.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">830–1850</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Combretum</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1118.0±538.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">530–1800</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albizia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">766.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0095361-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Least Significant Difference (LSD) post hoc analysis comparing the control species <italic>Beilschmeidia ugandensis</italic> to preferred sleeping tree species (score 4 was omitted due to multiple groups having fewer than two cases).</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0095361-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diameter Score</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean difference</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard error</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (&lt;3 cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B. ugandensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−113.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P&lt;</italic>0.01*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cola</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudospondias</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Combretum</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albizia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phoenix</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3–5 cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B. ugandensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−164.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.05*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albizia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−126.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudospondias</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−41.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Combretum</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phoenix</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.47</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cola</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5–7 cm)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B. ugandensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynometra</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−655.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P&lt;</italic>0.01*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudospondias</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−181.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phoenix</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cola</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318.0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Albizia</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">334.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P = </italic>0.09</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>For each diameter score, <italic>Cynometra</italic> is uniquely positioned as significant with the greatest RBF value relative to the control.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>In a one-way ANOVA, <italic>C. alexandri</italic> had significantly smaller internode distances compared to seven comparison species (N = 150, 1.47±1.3 cm, range: 0–9; F [6, 1219] = 13.20, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). In a one-way ANOVA <italic>C. alexandri</italic> had significantly smaller leaf surface areas than other species (N = 83, 3.77±2.9 cm, range: 0.25–18; F [4, 240] = 140.31, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). The second most commonly selected tree species, <italic>C. gigantea,</italic> had the largest leaf surface area (N<italic> = </italic>33, 208.14±112.4 cm, range: 17.5–426.25).</p>
<p>Of the seven architectural models characterizing trees in the TSWR, four were commonly used by chimpanzees: <italic>Model of Troll</italic> (characteristic of <italic>Albizia;</italic> N = 120); <italic>Model of Leewenberg</italic> (both <italic>Combretum</italic> [N = 24] and <italic>Ficus</italic> [N<italic> = </italic>30]); <italic>Model of Tomlinson</italic> (<italic>Phoenix</italic> [N<italic> = </italic>70]); <italic>Model of Koriba</italic> (<italic>Cynometra</italic> [N<italic> = </italic>1430], <italic>Cola</italic> [N = 189], and <italic>Pseudospondias</italic> [N<italic> = </italic>19]). <italic>Koriba</italic> was the most preferred tree architecture, selected for 90.0% of all trees, significantly greater than expected by chance (<italic>X<sup>2</sup></italic> = 1013.9, df = 6, P&lt;0.001; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095361-t004">Table 4</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0095361-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Tree architecture models preferentially chosen as sleep sites by TSWR chimpanzees.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0095361-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Architectural model</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed as sleep site</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expected # to be observed as sleep site</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expected % based off of species distribution</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Koriba</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1660</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1073</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Troll</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leeuwenberg</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fagerlind</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attim</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomlinson</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.81</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our results strongly suggest that just as do orangutans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-vanCasteren2">[22]</xref>, chimpanzees are selective of tree species when considering where to sleep. These data further suggest that chimpanzees select species of trees that possess physical properties that result in nests that are sturdy and resilient, optimizing comfort and reducing the risk of falls. The preferred species at Semliki, <italic>C. alexandri</italic> has the greatest relative break force and the smallest internode distance of the species tested; both promote stiffness. Because sleeping platforms utilize the <italic>basketweave</italic> (a variation of the <italic>plain weave</italic> [the most fundamental type of weave with a simple crisscross pattern] in which two are more stems can be bundled and then woven as one) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Kadolph1">[32]</xref>, smaller internode distances may also introduce a greater number of interlocking points, yielding greater structurally integrity and resilience. Future research directions should investigate the mechanisms by which chimpanzees consider the physical properties of stems during platform construction and whether weaving patterns produce biomechanically sturdier sleeping platforms.</p>
<p><italic>C. alexandri</italic> had the smallest leaves with the greatest density (i.e., internode distance) of all nesting tree-species, which has been suggested as affording the greatest comfort <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Fruth2">[18]</xref> by reducing exposure to branches protruding from the nest structure and increasing friction among interlocking of stems, creating a tighter, more securely woven structure. By providing thicker foliage, it may also increase insulation and thus offer thermoregulatory advantages. Finally, <italic>C. alexandri</italic> may also have insect-repellent properties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Samson3">[16]</xref>.</p>
<p>Among the preferred tree species at Semliki (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0095361-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) was <italic>Phoenix reclinata,</italic> a palm with physical characteristics dramatically different from the most-preferred species. <italic>P. reclinata</italic> has pinnate, or feather-shaped leaves 3–5 cm in breadth and 40 cm in length. The leaves are stiff and the base of the leaf stem has thorns that incorporate paralytic secondary compounds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Palgrave1">[33]</xref>. Use of palms for nest manufacture is common and highly preferred at some sites (refs. in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0095361-t001">Table 1</xref>); palms are the preferred species in southern Guinea-Bissau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Sousa1">[34]</xref>. We consider the selection of this species to be at odds with most hypotheses for nest construction: it rarely interdigitates with other canopies; it has no lateral branches; it is a short tree (relative to other nesting species); leaves are large; and interweaving is difficult. Sousa and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Sousa1">[34]</xref> hypothesized that oil palm are selected for their antipredator qualities including increased line of sight (given the spatial location of oil palm was significantly situated at forest edge), increased communication possibilities with conspecifics and improved access to resources. We additionally hypothesize that the paralytic secondary compounds associated with thorny leaf stems and protruding, jagged trunk morphology attribute the antipredition characteristics associated with this species. Furthermore, it may be that oil palm is preferred because if affords maximal stiffness in substrate, given it is characterized by having no lateral branches and the weight bearing structure is the trunk itself.</p>
<p>Our results are compatible with the hypothesis that chimpanzees select trees that are configured similar to the lollipop morphology of <italic>Drypetes gerrardii</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-Stanford1">[19]</xref>. The model of Koriba <italic>C. alexandri</italic> tree architecture affords chimpanzees inverted-tripod nest frames, which are hypothetically the easiest to transform into the functionally concave form to maximize comfort and safety <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-vanCasteren2">[22]</xref>. Other species selected less preferentially than <italic>C. alexandri</italic> likewise support this hypothesis: three of the four (96.2% of all selected species) tree architectures used by chimpanzees at Semliki possess inverted tripod branching patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0095361-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The tree architecture <italic>Tomlinson</italic> is a unique case, as it is an oil-palm tree with a markedly different shoot development.</p>
<fig id="pone-0095361-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title><italic>Model of Koriba</italic> (above left corner) is the specialized tree architecture preferred by Semliki chimpanzee for use as a sleeping site.</title>
<p>Notice the shoot development which produces a node dense, leafy and sturdy substrate with multiple frame supporting branches (FSBs) with which to construct a sleeping platform. In contrast, the shoot development which produces lateral drooping (inferred low levels of stiffness) and long internode distances illustrated by <italic>Model of Champagnat</italic> (below right corner), provides a poor sleeping substrate and is never selected by Semliki chimpanzees. Models Koriba, Troll and Leeuwenberg comprise 96.2% of all selected species and share the “lollipop” end static tree shape (adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0095361-vanWyk1">[31]</xref>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0095361.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Our results suggest that the ideal sleeping platform tree species might well possess multiple advantages, perhaps possessing antipredator, antivector, thermoregulatory and comfort- maximizing qualities all at once. <italic>C. alexandri</italic> has all of these properties, suggesting that chimpanzees are keen observers of physical properties of trees, including stiffness, strength and leaf surface area, and that they select species that provide the widest range of advantages, including predator avoidance, postural stability, thermoregulation and pathogen avoidance.</p>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are grateful to the Government of Uganda, the Uganda Wildlife Authority and the National Research Council. We are grateful to the staff at the Semliki Chimpanzee Project, particularly Moses Comeboy. H. Green commented helpfully on the manuscript. S. Dickinson and the Indiana Statistical Consulting Center (ISCC) advised us on statistical methods.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Goodall1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>Nest building behavior in the free ranging chimpanzee. Ann</article-title>. <source>New York Acad Sci</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>467</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Goodall2"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>The behaviour of free-living chimpanzees in the Gombe Stream Reserve</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav Monogr</source> <volume>1(3)</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Videan1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Videan</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Bed-building in captive chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>): The Importance of early rearing</article-title>. <source>Am J Primatol</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>751</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Stewart1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pruetz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansell</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Do chimpanzees build comfortable nests?</article-title> <source>Am J Primatol</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>930</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Videan2"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Videan EN (2005) Sleep and sleep-related behaviors in chimpanzee (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>). PhD (Miami University, Oxford, OH) p.93.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Fruth1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fruth B, Hohmann G (1996). Nest building behavior in the great apes: The great leap forward? <italic>Great Ape Societies</italic>, eds McGrew WC, Marchant LF, Nishida T (Cambridge Univ Press: Cambridge), 225–240.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-McGrew1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McGrew WC (2004) <italic>The Cultured Chimpanzee: Reflections on Cultural Primatology</italic>. (Cambridge Univ Press: New York) p 248.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Stewart2"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Brief Communication: Why Sleep in a Nest? Empirical Testing of the Function of Simple Shelters Made by Wild Chimpanzees</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>318</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Samson1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The chimpanzee nest quantified: morphology and ecology of arboreal sleeping platforms within the dry habitat site of Toro-Semliki Wildlife Reserve, Uganda, Primates</article-title>. <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Samson2"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shumaker</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Documenting orang-utan sleep architecture: sleeping platform complexity increases sleep quality in captive <italic>Pongo</italic></article-title>. <source>Behaviour</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>845</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Stewart3"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pruetz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Do chimpanzee nests serve an anti-predatory function?</article-title> <source>Amer J Primatol</source> <volume>75(6)</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Pruetz1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pruetz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>MSM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Arboreal nesting as anti-predator adaptation by savanna chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes verus</italic>) in southeastern Senegal</article-title>. <source>Am J Primatol</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Baldwin1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabater Pi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tutin</surname><given-names>CEG</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Comparisons of nests made by different populations of chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Primates</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>474</fpage>–<lpage>486</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Koops1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koops</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Nest-building by chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes verus</italic>) at Seringbara, Nimba Mountains: antipredation, thermoregulation, and antivector hypotheses</article-title>. <source>Int J Primatol</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Nunn1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunn</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heymann</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Malaria Infection and Host Behavior: A Comparative Study of Neotropical Primates</article-title>. <source>Beh Ecol Sociobiol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Samson3"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muehlenbein</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Do chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic>) exhibit sleep related behaviors that minimize exposure to parasitic arthropods? A preliminary report on the possible anti-vector function of chimpanzee sleeping platforms</article-title>. <source>Primates</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Anderson1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Ethology and ecology of sleep in monkeys and apes</article-title>. <source>Adv Study Behav</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Fruth2"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fruth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Ecological and behavioural-aspects of nest-building in wild bonobos <italic>(Pan paniscus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Ethology</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Stanford1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanford</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Sleeping tree choice by Bwindi chimpanzees</article-title>. <source>Am J Primatol</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>642</fpage>–<lpage>649</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Stewart4"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piel</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Living archaeology: artefacts of specific nest site fidelity in wild chimpanzees</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-vanCasteren1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Casteren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>SKS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crompton</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myatt</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ennos</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Nest-building orangutans demonstrate engineering know-how to produce safe, comfortable beds</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>6873</fpage>–<lpage>6877</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-vanCasteren2"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Casteren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>SKS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cromton</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ennos</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Factors affecting the compliance and sway properties of tree branches used by the Sumatran orangutan (<italic>Pongo abelii</italic>)</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e67877</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Sept1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sept</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Was there no place like home? A new perspective on early hominid archaeological sites from the mapping of chimpanzee nests</article-title>. <source>Curr Anthropol</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Brownlow1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brownlow</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plumptre</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sources of variation in the nesting behavior of chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic>) in the Budongo Forest, Uganda</article-title>. <source>Am J Primatol</source> <volume>551</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Hunt1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hunt KD, McGrew WC (2002) Chimpanzees in dry habitats at Mount Assirik, Senegal and at the Semliki-Toro Wildlife Reserve, Uganda, <italic>Behavioural Diversity in Chimpanzees and Bonobos,</italic> eds Boesch C, Hohmann G, and Marchant LF (Cambridge Univ Press: Cambridge) 35–51.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Plumptre1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Plumptre AJ (2010) Long term changes in Africa’s Rift Valley: impacts on biodiversity and ecosystem (Nova Science Publishers).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Chudnoff1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chudnoff M (1984) Tropical Timbers of the World. <italic>USDA Forest Service</italic>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Samson4"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A Thermodynamic Comparison of Arboreal and Terrestrial Sleeping Sites for Dry-Habitat Chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii) at the Toro-Semliki Wildlife Reserve, Uganda</article-title>. <source>Am J Primatol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>818</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Pratt1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pratt DJ, Gwynne MD, Blackie JR (1977) Rangeland management and ecology in east Africa (Hodder and Stoughton, London) 310.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Stumpf1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Stumpf R (2007) Chimpanzees and bonobos: diversity within and between species, <italic>Primates in Perspective</italic>, (eds) Campbell CJ, Fuentes A, MacKinnon KC, Panger M, Bearder SK (Oxford University Press: New York) 321–344.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-vanWyk1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">van Wyk B, van Wyk BE, van Wyk P (2002) <italic>Photographic Guide to Trees of Southern Africa.</italic> Wissenschaftliche Verlagsges: Broschiert.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Kadolph1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kadolph SJ (2007) Textiles, 10<sup>th</sup> ed. Saddle River, New Jersey, Pearson/Prentice-Hall.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Palgrave1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Palgrave KC (1977) <italic>Trees of Southern Africa.</italic> C. Struik Publ.: Capetown.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Sousa1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barata</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>CCN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Chimpanzee Oil-Palm Use in Southern Cantanhez National Park, Guinea-Bissau</article-title>. <source>Am J Primatol</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>485</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Ogunjemite1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunjemite</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashimi</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Okeyoyin</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The chimpanzee community of German-Fort, and the potentials for the development of tourism-base management of Gashaka-Gumti National Park, Nigeria</article-title>. <source>J Sustain Develop Africa</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Humle1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Humle T (2003) Culture and variation in wild chimpanzee behaviour: a study of three communities in West Africa. <italic>PhD diss</italic> (University of Sterling, Scotland, UK).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Sanz1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strindberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onononga</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Distinguishing between the nests of sympatric chimpanzees and gorillas</article-title>. <source>J Appl Eco</source> <volume>44(2)</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Sept2"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sept</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Shadows on a changing landscape: comparing nesting patterns of hominids and chimpanzees since their last common ancestor</article-title>. <source>Amer J Primatol</source> <volume>46(1)</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Basabose1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basabose</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamagiwa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Factors affecting nesting site choice in chimpanzees at Tshibati, Kahuzi-Biega National Park: influence of sympatric gorillas</article-title>. <source>Int J Pramatol</source> <volume>23(2)</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>282</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Petre1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petre</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hynen</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beudels-Jamar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>First assessment of chimpanzee (<italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes</italic>) density and bedding behaviour in the Pongara National Park, Gabon</article-title>. <source>Pan Africa News</source> <volume>14(2)</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Mulavwa1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulavwa</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nest groups of wild bonobos at Wamba: selection of vegetation and tree species and relationships between nest group size and party size</article-title>. <source>Amer J Primatol</source> <volume>72(7)</volume>: <fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Kano1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kano T (1992) The last ape: pygmy chimpanzee behavior and ecology (Stanford University Press, Stanford) 248.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-HernandezAguilar1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Aguilar</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stanford</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Chimpanzee nesting patterns in savanna habitat: environmental influences and preferences</article-title>. <source>Amer J Primatol</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>979</fpage>–<lpage>994</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Izawa1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Izawa K, Itani J (1966) Chimpanzees in Kasekati basin, Tanganyika: (1) Ecological study in the rainy season 1963–1964. Kyoto: Kyoto Univ. African Studies.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Ogawa1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanamori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mukeni</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The discovery of chimpanzees in the Lwazi River area, Tanzania: a new southern distribution limit</article-title>. <source>Pan Africa News</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Ogawa2"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamenya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Chimpanzees in the Ntakata and Kakungu areas, Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Prim Conserv</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Ogawa3"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Idani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pintea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Aguilar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Sleeping parties and nest distribution of chimpanzees in the savanna woodland, Ugalla, Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Int J Pramatol</source> <volume>28(6)</volume>: <fpage>1397</fpage>–<lpage>1412</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Ndimuligo1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ndimuligo SA (2008) Assessment of chimpanzee (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) population and habitat Kwitanga Forest, western Tanzania. (WiredSpace).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0095361-Ghiglieri1"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ghiglieri MP (1984) The chimpanzees of the Kibale Forest (Columbia University Press, New York).</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>