<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-27291</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052792</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Epidemiology</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Non-clinical medicine</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Socioeconomic aspects of health</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Nutrition</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Malnutrition</subject>
              <subject>Obesity</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Pediatrics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Growth retardation</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Public health</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Child health</subject>
              <subject>Socioeconomic aspects of health</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Anthropometry</subject>
              <subject>Biological anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
          <subject>Pediatrics and Child Health</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Comparative Study on Nutritional Status and Body Composition of Urban and Rural Schoolchildren from Brandsen District (Argentina)</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Urban-Rural Differences in Nutritional Status</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cesani</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Florencia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Garraza</surname>
            <given-names>Mariela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bergel Sanchís</surname>
            <given-names>María Laura</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Luis</surname>
            <given-names>María Antonia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Torres</surname>
            <given-names>María Fernanda</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Quintero</surname>
            <given-names>Fabián Aníbal</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Oyhenart</surname>
            <given-names>Evelia Edith</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Instituto de Genética Veterinaria. Facultad de Ciencias Veterinarias, Universidad Nacional de La Plata, UNLP-CONICET CCT La Plata, La Plata, Provincia de Buenos Aires, Argentina</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Facultad de Ciencias Naturales y Museo (UNLP), La Plata, Provincia de Buenos Aires, Argentina</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Facultad de Filosofía y Letras, Universidad de Buenos Aires (UBA), Ciudad Autónoma de Buenos Aires, Argentina</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Berthold</surname>
            <given-names>Heiner K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Charité University Medicine Berlin, Germany</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mfcesani@fcnym.unlp.edu.ar</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MFC EEO. Performed the experiments: MFC MAL MFT FAQ EEO. Analyzed the data: MFC MG MLBS EEO. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MFC MAL MFT FAQ EEO. Wrote the paper: MFC MG MLBS MAL MFT FAQ EEO.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>7</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e52792</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Cesani et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The purpose of this study was to analyze whether nutritional status and body composition varies according to the environment of residence (urban or rural) of children in the Brandsen district (Argentina). Weight, height, arm circumference and tricipital and subscapular skinfolds were performed in 1368 schoolchildren aged 3 to 14. NHANES III reference was used to estimate nutritional status -underweight, stunting, wasting, overweight, and obesity- and to evaluate body composition -deficit and excess of adipose (DA, EA) and muscular (DM, EM) tissues of the arm-. Central fat distribution (CFD) was estimated using the subscapular-tricipital index. A structured questionnaire was implemented to evaluate socio-environmental characteristics. Nutritional categories based on body size and body composition were compared between urban and rural areas of residence using Chi-squared tests (χ2). The results indicated for the total sample: 1.1% underweight, 6.9% stunting, 0.4% wasting, 12.1% overweight, 9.7% obesity, 22.0% DM, 2.5% EM, 0.1% DA, 17.6% EA, and 8.5% CFD. Significant differences between urban and rural areas were found only for CFD. The socio-environmental analysis showed that while access to public services and housing quality was significantly better in the urban area, a considerable number of city households lived under deficient conditions, lacked health insurance and had low socioeconomic level. Fifty-three percent of the undernourished children had DM without urban-rural significant differences, and none of them showed DA. In the overweight plus obesity group, 62.8% presented EA, 6.4% EM, 4.7% DM, and 22.8% CFD. The highest percentages of DM and CFD were recorded in rural areas (p = 0.00). We conclude that the child population shows the “double burden” of malnutrition. The environment of residence does not promote any differentiation in the nutritional status. Nevertheless, the increment of central adiposity and, in some cases of muscle deficit in rural children, suggests a consumption of unbalanced diet.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by ANPCyT (Agencia Nacional de Promoción Científica y Tecnológica, PICT 14095)and UNLP (Universidad Nacional de La Plata, 11/N428). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="7"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>A considerable body of literature has documented the rural-urban health disparity in children and adults from developing countries. Most of these studies were focused on discrepancies in child nutritional status, and demonstrated that, on average, urban children are less likely to suffer stunting and underweight <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Ruel1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Haddad1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Menon1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Sahn1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Fotso1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Fotso2">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-VandePoel1">[7]</xref>. Nevertheless, the urban advantage has been fading in the last decades, since the fast changes in the diet and lifestyle of city dwellers -resulting from industrialization, urbanization and globalization-, have triggered marked consequences on the health and nutritional status of the populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Fotso2">[6]</xref>. Urban diets include a large consumption of fat-rich food, more sugar, and more processed foods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Popkin1">[8]</xref> and the accompanying lifestyle is less physically active <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Garrett1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-King1">[10]</xref>. The types of jobs available in urban areas are often more sedentary than those in rural areas, causing changes in physical activity levels. Likewise, changes in leisure-time activities and the different types of transportation available (e.g. buses, cars) result in more sedentary lifestyles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Popkin2">[11]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Katzmarzyk1">[12]</xref>. As a result, an increasing amount of overweight and obese people has been recorded in urban areas throughout the world.</p>
      <p>Moreover, there is growing recognition of the emergence of a “double burden” of malnutrition, with under- and over-nutrition occurring simultaneously among different population groups in developing countries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Popkin3">[13]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Khor1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Food1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-VarelaSilva1">[16]</xref>. Accordingly, in Argentina undernourishment and overweight have been reported to coexist in many populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Bejarano1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Bolzn1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Cesani1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Ministerio1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Oyhenart1">[21]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Zonta1">[22]</xref>. In addition, it was noted that overweight and obese children could simultaneously present excess of fat tissue and deficit of muscle when they live under impoverished residence conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Oyhenart2">[23]</xref>. Such results illustrate the complexity of this phenomenon and highlight the importance of studying body composition as an essential complement to studies of nutritional assessment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-MarrodanSerrano1">[24]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Since 2005, our research team has been working in the Brandsen district (Argentina) analyzing nutritional status in the preschool children population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Oyhenart3">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Luis1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Cesani2">[27]</xref>. We have analyzed urban- rural differences and reported the coexistence of undernutrition, overweight and obesity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Cesani1">[19]</xref>. Even so, while undernutrition was prevalent in suburban areas where the worst social and environmental conditions for optimal growth of children were observed, the highest rates of obesity were recorded in rural areas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Cesani1">[19]</xref>. Nevertheless, we have not yet analyzed older children or compared body composition between urban and rural areas. Therefore, the aim of this paper was to analyze whether nutritional status and body composition varies according to the environment of residence (urban or rural) of children in the Brandsen district.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Ethics statement</title>
        <p>This study was approved by the University of La Plata (UNLP), local authorities, and educational and sanitary staff of Brandsen district. Research protocols followed the principles outlined in the Helsinki Declaration and successive modifications as well as those under the National Law N° 25.326 on the protection of personal data.</p>
        <p>The study's goals and procedures were explained during meetings held in each school. Informed consent was signed by the children's parents. Children whose parents did not sign the forms were not measured. In addition, the children themselves were consulted and only those who agreed (orally) were included in the study.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Population</title>
        <p>Brandsen is a district located in the northern area of Buenos Aires Province; its major city is Coronel Brandsen which is situated just a few kilometers away from the cities of La Plata and Buenos Aires (35°10′S, 58°13′W) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0052792-g001">Figure 1</xref>). According to the last Argentine National Census (2010), the maximum total population was 26.352 inhabitants, with 85% concentrated in urban areas and the other 15% either distributed in smaller towns (fewer than 2,000 inhabitants) or spread in rural areas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Instituto1">[28]</xref>. Although both agriculture and agro industry contribute to regional economy, it is the third sector which participates with a greater percentage of Gross Domestic Product (GDP) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Instituto1">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Instituto2">[29]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0052792-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Geographic location of Brandsen District (Buenos Aires, Argentina).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Sample</title>
        <p>A cross-sectional anthropometric study was performed in 1368 children (48% boys 52% girls), aged 3 to 14 years, attending urban (Coronel Brandsen town) and rural (Jeppener, Altamirano, Gómez, and Oliden villages) schools of Brandsen district (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052792-t001">Table 1</xref>). We employed the criteria suggested by the Instituto de Estadísticas y Censos de Argentina (INDEC) to determine whether a population was urban or rural. Their criterion considers as “urban” any population with more than 2000 inhabitants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Instituto2">[29]</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0052792-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Sample composition.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0052792-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban Population</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural Population</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–3.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4–4.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–5.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6–6.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7–7.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8–8.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9–9.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10–10.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11–11.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12–12.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13–13.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14–14.9</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1368</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">651</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">717</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">970</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Data were collected from 20 public educational institutions (kindergarten and elementary school), representing 70% of the total schools of the district. Children with chronic diseases or pathological conditions existing at the moment of the study were excluded.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Anthropometric study</title>
        <p>The anthropometric study was carried out following standardized protocols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Lohman1">[30]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The following variables were recorded: age: obtained from the identification cards or from the school's records; body weight (Kg): measured on a digital scale (accuracy, 100 g) with the subjects lightly clothed (the weight of the clothes being subtracted); height (cm): using a portable vertical anthropometer (accuracy, 1 mm); arm circumference (AC): (cm) using an inextensible tape measure (accuracy, 1 mm); tricipital and subscapular skinfolds (TF and SF) (mm): with a Lange caliper using constant pressure (accuracy, 1 mm). Body-mass index (BMI) was calculated as weight (kg) divided by squared height (m<sup>2</sup>).</p>
        <p>To estimate nutritional status, the NHANES III reference was used. The cut-off value was &lt;5th percentile to determine low weight-for-age (underweight), low height-for-age (stunting), and low weight-for-height (wasting). Individuals were classified as overweight or obese when their BMI was in the 85th through 95th percentile or above the 95th percentile, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Frisancho1">[31]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Body composition was estimated on the basis of total (TA), muscle (MA) and fat (FA) areas following Frisancho <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Frisancho1">[31]</xref>.<disp-formula id="pone.0052792.e001"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pone.0052792.e002"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pone.0052792.e003"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></p>
        <p>A cut-off point of &lt;5th percentile and &gt;95th was used to determine deficit and excess of adipose (DA, EA) and muscular (DM, EM) tissues of the arm. Finally, fat distribution (central or peripheral) was evaluated using the subscapular-tricipital index (STI) calculated as the ratio between subscapular and tricipital skinfolds (STI = <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Deurenberg1">[32]</xref>. A STI score higher than 1 was considered as an indicator of high risk of central fat distribution (CFD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Martnez1">[33]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Socio-environmental study</title>
        <p>A structured questionnaire, completed by the parents, was implemented to evaluate socio-environmental characteristics, and to measure housing variables by means of information regarding structural and physical amenities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Cesani2">[27]</xref>. These characteristics provided information about interior and exterior housing conditions.</p>
        <p>We asked about: building materials (type of materials used in their construction: low-quality prefab, fired-brick masonry, makeshift materials, and so forth); source of drinking water (piped water system, protected well, rain-tank storage, or unprotected well); wastewater disposal (sewage system or septic tanks (cesspool)); fuel for cooking and heating (piped gas, bottled gas (cylinder), kerosene, or firewood); pavement; electricity, waste collection, and critical crowding (more than three persons per room).</p>
        <p>Regarding socio-economic status (SES), the following variables were considered: lodging or home-tenure status (house owner, lease holder, or free lodging); parental education (elementary, high school, university); parental job (employed or formal worker, unskilled worker or unqualified worker who performs mostly temporary jobs, informal worker or without work contract, autonomous worker or freelance jobs, and unemployed); health insurance (medical insurance at the expense of the employer or paid by the person -fee for service health insurance plans-); public assistance (referring to national or local programs from government agencies, NGOs, or other entities, that benefit poor families by supplementing their food budget -nutritional support- and/or by providing cash relief to the heads of households -monetary support-; farming (animal husbandry, orchard, or horticulture).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Nutritional categories based on body size and body composition were compared between urban and rural areas of residence using Chi-squared tests (χ2). All statistical procedures were made with SPSS 12.0 statistical program.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052792-t002">Table 2</xref> shows the results of the socio-environmental analysis. Although most of the urban and rural houses were built with fired-brick masonry, the quality of building materials was lower in the rural area. With the exception of electricity, urban households had better access to public services (pavement, piped water system, waste collection and sewage system). In regards to the fuel for cooking and heating, less than 30% of the families of the district had piped gas. Thus, bottled gas (cylinder) was used as main fuel. Additionally, in the rural area a large amount of families used firewood as an alternative source of fuel.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0052792-t002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t002</object-id>
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Socio-environmental analysis.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0052792-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Percentages (%)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">χ<italic>2</italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>p</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>HOUSING VARIABLES</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Building materials</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.62</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fired-brick masonry</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low-quality prefab</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Makeshift materials</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others materials</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Availability of public services</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pavement</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.53</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piped water system</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.88</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electricity</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.700</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waste collection</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.76</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wastewater disposal (sewage system)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.01</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Fuel for cooking and heating</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piped gas</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.39</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottled gas (cylinder)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.89</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Firewood</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.89</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Critical Crowding</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.320</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>SOCIOECONOMIC STATUS VARIABLES</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Lodging or home-tenure status</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.83</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House owner</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lease holder</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free lodging</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Parental Education</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Father</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.71</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school and University</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elementary school</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Data</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Mother</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.24</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High school and University</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elementary school</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Data</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Parental Job</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Father</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.697</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Formal and Free Lance Job</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unqualified and Informal Job</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unemployed</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Data</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Mother</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.62</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Formal and Free Lance Job</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unqualified and Informal Job</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unemployed</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Data</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Health insurance</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.927</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Nutritional support</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.03</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Monetary support</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.251</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Animal husbandry</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.52</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Orchard or horticulture</bold>
                  <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.31</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label>*</label>
            <p>The percentage indicate the presence of the variable.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Critical crowding was high in both urban and rural populations, reaching percentages of 49.4 and 45.5 respectively. On the other hand, most of the families owned their homes, but this type of accommodation was more frequent in the urban area, while in the rural areas, 31% of households had free hosting.</p>
      <p>Regarding parental education, city-dwellers accredited higher educational levels. Similarly, a greater percentage of parents with formal or free lance jobs were recorded in the urban area. However, the differences between urban and rural areas were only statistically significant for the mothers.</p>
      <p>The amount of families with health insurance and monetary support was similar in urban and rural areas. However, city-dwellers received more nutritional support from government agencies, NGOs or other entities, than those in rural areas. Conversely, orchard farming and animal husbandry for consumption were more frequent among rural residents.</p>
      <p>The analysis of nutritional status indicated that 1.1% of the total sample (urban plus rural population) suffered underweight, 6.9% stunting, 0.4% wasting, 12.1% overweight, and 9.7% obesity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052792-t003">Table 3</xref>). Differences between boys and girls were observed only for stunting (<italic>X<sup>2</sup>:</italic>5.02, p: 0.025) and obesity (<italic>X<sup>2</sup>:</italic>50.56; p: 0.033) at the age 10.0–10.9. Therefore, data for both sexes were pooled for subsequent statistical analyses.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0052792-t003" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t003</object-id>
        <label>Table 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Differences in prevalence of underweight, stunting, wasting, overweight and obesity between urban and rural areas.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0052792-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nutritional Status</td>
                <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Prevalence (%)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>X</italic>
                  <sup>2</sup>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>p</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Underweight</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stunting</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.209</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wasting</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.591</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overweight</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.715</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.951</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Prevalence of undernutrition, overweight and obesity was similar in both urban and rural areas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052792-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p>
      <p>The results of the body composition analysis are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052792-t004">Table 4</xref>. Twenty-two percent of the children had DM, 2.5% EM, 0.1% DA, 17.6% EA, and 8.5% CFD. Significant differences between urban and rural areas were found only for central fat distribution (X2: 22.61; p: 0.000) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052792-t004">Table 4</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0052792-t004" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t004</object-id>
        <label>Table 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Differences in deficit and excess of muscular, adipose tissues and central fat distribution between urban and rural areas.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0052792-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body Composition</td>
                <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Prevalence (%)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>X</italic>
                  <sup>2</sup>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>p</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deficit of muscular tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excess of muscular tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.420</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deficit of adipose tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.365</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excess of adipose tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Fat Distribution</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.61</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
      </table-wrap>
      <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052792-t005">Table 5</xref> shows the analysis of body composition in undernourished and overweight plus obesity groups. A total 53.0% of the undernourished children had muscular tissue deficit without significant urban-rural differences, and none of them showed deficit of adipose tissue. In the overweight plus obesity group, 62.8% of the children presented EA, 6.4% EM, 4.7% DM, and 22.8% CFD. Significant differences between rural and urban areas were recorded for deficit of muscular tissue and central fat distribution (with highest percentages in rural areas) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0052792-t005">Table 5</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0052792-t005" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t005</object-id>
        <label>Table 5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Differences in body composition of undernourished and overweight plus obesity groups between urban and rural areas.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0052792-t005-5" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0052792.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</td>
                <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Prevalence (%)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>X</italic>
                  <sup>2</sup>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>p</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Undernutrition</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deficit of muscular tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6785</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deficit of adipose tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>Overweight+Obesity</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deficit of muscular tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0224</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excess of muscular tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5429</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excess of adipose tissue</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5735</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Fat Distribution</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.65</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion and Conclusions</title>
      <p>The nutritional status of a community is an important indicator of its quality of life. This study provides new evidence of the nutritional situation of Argentinean children, and particularly of those living in Brandsen. Like many authors have observed in other Latin American populations, a low percentage of undernutrition (predominantly stunting) and high percentage of overweight and obesity were found <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Ministerio1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Oyhenart1">[21]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-deOnis1">[34]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Barra1">[35]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Lamounier1">[36]</xref>. Furthermore, similar results obtained in a previous work carried out in Brandsen lend support to the observed trend, which is characteristic of countries in nutritional transition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Cesani1">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Cesani2">[27]</xref>. Over several years, Popkin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Popkin4">[37]</xref> has extensively analyzed the environmental factors associated to the obesity pandemic, and he has linked the changes in dietary patterns with those in physical activity to explain the nutrition transition that has been observed all over the world and mainly in developing countries.</p>
      <p>Some authors have pointed out that cities are much more advanced along this nutritional transition than the countryside, since they have experienced the greatest increase of overweight and obesity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Shetty1">[38]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Mendez1">[39]</xref>. In urban contexts the range of food choices is greater and prices are generally lower. On the other hand, urban employments often demand less physical exertion than rural ones, and a greater proportion of women work away from home and are too busy to shop for, prepare and cook healthy meals at home <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Food1">[15]</xref>. Nevertheless, we did not find urban-rural differences in overweight and obesity rates. According to Bogin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Bogin1">[40]</xref>, the migration of people, goods, and services along a path from urban to rural areas produces a “rural–urban continuum”, and rural families have greater access to food variety and quantity. Brandsen is a relatively small district, and the distance between rural and urban areas is relatively short, allowing uninterrupted connection between the countryside and the city. At the same time, in Argentina the mechanization of agricultural work, the improvement of public transport and the increased acquisition of motorized transport, have led to a significant reduction of physical activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Britos1">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Daz1">[42]</xref>.</p>
      <p>No urban-rural differences were found in prevalence of underweight, stunting or wasting. The notion that urban children are less likely to suffer undernutrition than their rural counterparts is based on the idea that urbanization entails better access to food, services and employment opportunities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-VandePoel1">[7]</xref>. However, in many cities of developing countries, not everyone is able to benefit equally and it is currently common to find great heterogeneity within a given urban context. According to Dufour and Piperata <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Food2">[43]</xref> cities contain more than one type of urban environment and the population that inhabits them is distributed according to SES. This statement suggests that cities are not uniform in terms of their health status. In agreement with these authors, the analysis of the socio-environmental survey showed that while access to public services like piped water, sewage system, waste collection, etc., and housing quality was significantly better in the urban area, a considerable number of city households lived under sanitary deficient conditions, lacked health insurance and had low socioeconomic level. The internal socio-environmental heterogeneity of Coronel Brandsen city could explain the lack of differences in the nutritional status of urban and rural children.</p>
      <p>The assessment of body composition is important to evaluate nutrition and health status. Skinfold measurement is extremely common in epidemiological studies because they are inexpensive and simple to perform and allow the estimation of muscular and fat tissues from simple algorithms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Heyward1">[44]</xref>. In this study, the body composition analysis showed that the amount of muscular and fat tissues of the arm was similar in all the children analyzed and independent of the environment of residence. Conversely, central fat distribution was more frequent in rural children. Although fat deposition patterns are known to be basically ruled by genetics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Wardle1">[45]</xref>, they are also associate to particular socio-cultural and environmental conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Bouchard1">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Bouchard2">[47]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-LandaetaJimenez1">[48]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-RuizdeLa1">[49]</xref>. The mechanism by which trunk fat deposition influences cardiovascular risk factors is not completely understood. However, central fat distribution is an important predictor of increase in plasma triglycerides, HDL cholesterol, systolic blood pressure, and left ventricular mass in children and adolescents <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Stephen1">[50]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Kopelman1">[51]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Zimmet1">[52]</xref>. Accordingly, these results may indicate that rural children are more prone to health problems.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, body composition analysis in undernourished children indicated that about half of them had less muscular mass. Also, 63% of overweight and obese children presented excess of adipose tissue and 5% of them, reduction of muscular mass. This paradoxical coexistence was more evident in rural children, leading us to think that the diet eaten by these children was low in proteins and high in carbohydrates and lipids. Although we did not analyze food habits, Aguirre's <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Aguirre1">[53]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Aguirre2">[54]</xref> arguments support our interpretation. This author suggested that during the past decades in Argentina, a single pattern of consumption was replaced by two different types of diets: the “poor people's food and rich people's food”. The former is based on carbohydrates, fats and sugars and is cheaper, and the latter, which includes meat, dairy, fruits and vegetables rich in micronutrients, is more expensive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Aguirre1">[53]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Aguirre2">[54]</xref>. Therefore, those children who consume diets with excessive amounts of carbohydrate and lipids but deficient in protein, are expected to present overweight or obesity and muscular deficit at the same time. In addition, the significant reduction of physical activity registered in all Argentinean children <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Comit1">[55]</xref>, and especially in those of rural population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0052792-Daz1">[42]</xref>, could explain this paradoxical coexistence of obesity and reduced muscular mass.</p>
      <p>The results obtained indicate the necessity of implementing policies and programs to improve socio-environmental conditions and allow better access to good nutrition for these children in order to protect their health and quality of life.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors are grateful to the local authorities, to the educational and sanitary staff of Brandsen district the Ministry for their valuable assistance and collaboration, and to the guardians and parents for allowing us to make measurements on their children. We also wish to thank Dr. Cecilia Morgan for editing the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Ruel1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ruel M, Garrett J, Morris S, Maxwell D, Oshaug O, <etal>et al</etal>.. (1998) Urban challenges to food and nutrition security: A review of food security, health, and care giving in the cities. FCND Discussion Paper 51. Washington: International Food Policy Research Institute.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Haddad1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Are urban poverty and undernutrition growing?</article-title> <source>World Dev</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1891</fpage>–<lpage>1904</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Menon1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Socio-economic differentials in child stunting: results from 11 DHS data sets</article-title>. <source>Food Nutr Bull</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>282</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Sahn1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stifel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Urban-rural inequality in living standards in Africa</article-title>. <source>J Afr Econ</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>564</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Fotso1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fotso</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Child health inequities in developing countries: differences across urban and rural areas</article-title>. <source>IJEqH</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Fotso2">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fotso</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Urban-rural differentials in child malnutrition: Trends and socioeconomic correlates in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <source>Health Place</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-VandePoel1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van de Poel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Urbanization, Health and Inequality in the Developing World</article-title>. <source>Thesis to obtain the degree of Doctor from the Erasmus University Rotterdam</source>. <fpage>186</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Popkin1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The nutrition transition in the developing world</article-title>. <source>Dev Policy Rev</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>597</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Garrett1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruel</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Stunted child–overweight mother pairs: Prevalence and association with economic development and urbanization</article-title>. <source>Food and Nut Bull</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-King1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Housmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brownson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Determinants of leisure time physical activity in rural compared with urban older and ethnically diverse women in the United States</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>–<lpage>672</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Popkin2">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon-Larsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The nutrition transition: worldwide obesity dynamics and their determinants</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source> <volume>28 Suppl 3</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Katzmarzyk1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katzmarzyk</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The physical activity transition</article-title>. <source>JPAH</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Popkin3">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Global nutrition dynamics: the world is shifting rapidly toward a diet linked with noncommunicable diseases</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Khor1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khor</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Food-based approaches to combat the double burden among the poor: challenges in the Asian context</article-title>. <source>Asia Pac J Clin Nutr</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Food1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Food and Agriculture Organization (2012) The nutrition transition and obesity. FOCUS, The developing world's new burden: obesity. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/FOCUS/E/obesity/obes2.htm" xlink:type="simple">www.fao.org/FOCUS/E/obesity/obes2.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Aug 31.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-VarelaSilva1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varela-Silva</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azcorra</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Nutritional Dual-Burden in Developing Countries- How is it assessed and what are the health implications?</article-title> <source>Coll Antropol</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Bejarano1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bejarano</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dipierri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quispe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Evolución de la prevalencia de sobrepeso, obesidad y desnutrición en escolares de San Salvador de Jujuy</article-title>. <source>Arch Argent Pediatr</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Bolzn1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolzán</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brawerman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Evaluación nutricional antropométrica de la niñez pobre del norte argentino: Proyecto encuNa</article-title>. <source>Arch Argent Pediatr</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>555</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Cesani1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cesani</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zonta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forte</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Estado nutricional y parasitosis intestinales en niños residentes en zonas urbana, periurbana y rural del partido de Brandsen (Buenos Aires, Argentina)</article-title>. <source>Rev Arg Antropol Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Ministerio1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ministerio de Salud de la Nación. Encuesta Nacional de Nutrición y Salud (2007) Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.msal.gov.ar/htm/Site/ennys/site" xlink:type="simple">http://www.msal.gov.ar/htm/Site/ennys/site</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Aug 31.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Oyhenart1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oyhenart</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dahinten</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bejarano</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Estado nutricional infanto juvenil en Argentina: variación regional</article-title>. <source>Rev Arg Antrop Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Zonta1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zonta</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oyhenart</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Navone</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Nutritional vulnerability in Mbyá-Guaraní adolescents and adults from Misiones, Argentina</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Biol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>600</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Oyhenart2">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oyhenart</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quintero</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cesani</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Estado nutricional y composición corporal de niños pobres residentes en barrios periféricos de La Plata (Argentina)</article-title>. <source>Rev Panam Salud Pública</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-MarrodanSerrano1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrodan Serrano</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos Beneit</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mesa Santurino</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabañas Armesilla</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>González-Montero de Espinosa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Técnicas analíticas en el estudio de la composición corporal. Antropometría frente a sistemas de bioimpedancia bipolar y tetrapolar</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Diet Hosp</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Oyhenart3">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oyhenart</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orden</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forte</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Transición nutricional en tres ciudades con diferente complejidad urbano ambiental</article-title>. <source>Rev Arg Antrop Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Luis1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>López Armengol</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orden</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cesani</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Estado nutricional y parasitosis en la población escolar de Brandsen: una experiencia de articulación entre Universidad y Comunidad. Revista de la Escuela Superior de Trabajo Social. UNLP</article-title>. <source>Escenarios</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Cesani2">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cesani</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quintero</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Sobrepeso y obesidad en escolares de Brandsen en relación a las condiciones socio-ambientales de residencia</article-title>. <source>Arch Argent Pediatr</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Instituto1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Instituto Nacional de Estadística y Censos (INDEC) (2010) Censo Nacional de Población, Hogares y Vivienda. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.censo2010.indec.gov.ar" xlink:type="simple">http://www.censo2010.indec.gov.ar</ext-link> Accessed 2012 Aug 31.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Instituto2">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Instituto Nacional de Estadística y Censos (INDEC) (2004) Censo Nacional de Población, Hogares y Vivienda. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.indec.gov.ar" xlink:type="simple">http://www.indec.gov.ar</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Aug 31.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Lohman1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lohman TG, Roche AF, Martorell R (1988) Anthropometric. Standarization Reference Manual. Illinois: Human Kinetics. 184 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Frisancho1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Frisancho R (2008) Anthropometric Standards: An Interactive Nutritional Reference of Body Size and Body Composition for Children and Adults. Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press. 335 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Deurenberg1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deurenberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pieters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hautvast</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The assessment of the body fat percentage by skinfold thickness measurements in childhood and young adolescence</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Martnez1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devesa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bacallao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Indice subescapular/tricipital: valores percentilares en niños y adolescentes cubanos</article-title>. <source>ALAN</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-deOnis1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Onis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blossner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Prevalence and trends of overweight among preschool children in developing countries</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1032</fpage>–<lpage>1039</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Barra1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barría</surname><given-names>PMR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amigo</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Transición nutricional: una revisión del perfil latinoamericano</article-title>. <source>ALAN</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Lamounier1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamounier</surname><given-names>JÁ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Transição epidemiológica nutricional em criançase adolescentes argentinos de áreas carentes</article-title>. <source>Rev Paul Pediatr</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Popkin4">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Using research on the obesity pandemic as a guide to a unified vision of nutrition</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nutr</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>724</fpage>–<lpage>729</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Shetty1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Nutrition transition in India</article-title>. <source>Public health Nutrition</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Mendez1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mendez MA, Popkin BM (2005) Globalization, urbanization, and nutritional change in the developing world. eJADE 1: 220–241. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/es/ESA/ejade/vol_1/vol_1_2/cover_en.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.fao.org/es/ESA/ejade/vol_1/vol_1_2/cover_en.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Aug 31.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Bogin1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bogin B (1999) Patterns of human growth, 2nd ed. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 472 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Britos1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Britos S, Clacheo R, Grippo B, O'Donnell A, Pueyrredón P, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2004) Obesidad en Argentina: ¿Hacia un nuevo fenotipo? Reporte del Centro de Estudios sobre Nutrición Infantil (CESNI). Buenos Aires: CESNI. 58 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Daz1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Díaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tringler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Díaz</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geronimi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Control de la presión arterial y prevalencia de hipertensión arterial en niños y adolescentes de una población rural de Argentina: Datos preliminares del Proyecto Vela</article-title>. <source>Arch Argent Pediatr</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Food2">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Food and Agriculture Organization (2012) The nutrition transition and obesity. FOCUS, The developing world's new burden: obesity. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/FOCUS/E/obesity/obes2.htm" xlink:type="simple">www.fao.org/FOCUS/E/obesity/obes2.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Aug 31.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Heyward1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Heyward V, Wagner D (2004) Applied body composition assessment. Champaign, IL: Human Kinetics. 268 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Wardle1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carnell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haworth</surname><given-names>CMA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Plomin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Evidence for a strong genetic influence on childhood adiposity despite the force of the obesogenic environment</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>398</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Bouchard1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perusse</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leblanc</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theriault</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Inheritance of the amount and distribution of human body fat</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Bouchard2">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Després</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pascale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Genetic and Nongenetic Determinants of Regional Fat Distribution</article-title>. <source>Endocr Rev</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-LandaetaJimenez1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Landaeta-Jimenez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Escalante</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Adiposidad y patrón de grasa en jóvenes venezolanos por estrato social</article-title>. <source>ALAN</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>–<lpage>136</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-RuizdeLa1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz de La</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de La Masa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Composición corporal de mujeres obesas de 20 a 40 años de edad de nivel socioeconómico alto y bajo</article-title>. <source>Rev Chil Nutr</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>257</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Stephen1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sprecher</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Association of Body Fat Distribution and Cardiovascular Risk Factors in Children and Adolescents</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>545</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Kopelman1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopelman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Health risks associated with overweight and obesity</article-title>. <source>Obes Rev</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Zimmet1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alberti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The metabolic syndrome in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Diabetes</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Aguirre1">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Estrategias de consumo: qué comen los argentinos que comen? Buenos Aires: Colección Políticas públicas</article-title>. <source>CIEPP</source> <fpage>288</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Aguirre2">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Aguirre P (2011) Consecuencias del ajuste en la alimentación. Voces en Fénix 7: 52–59. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vocesenelfenix.com.ar" xlink:type="simple">www.vocesenelfenix.com.ar</ext-link>. Accessed 2012 Aug 30.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0052792-Comit1">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">Comité Nacional de Medicina del Deporte Infanto-Juvenil, Subcomisión de Epidemiología</collab> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Consenso sobre factores de riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular en pediatría. Sedentarismo</article-title>. <source>Arch Argent Pediatr</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>