<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-08967</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Earth sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Paleontology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Paleobiology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cultural anthropology</subject>
              <subject>Paleoanthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Archaeology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Archaeological excavation</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Reality of Neandertal Symbolic Behavior at the Grotte du Renne, Arcy-sur-Cure, France</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Neandertal Symbolic Behavior at Grotte du Renne</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Caron</surname>
            <given-names>François</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>d'Errico</surname>
            <given-names>Francesco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Del Moral</surname>
            <given-names>Pierre</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Santos</surname>
            <given-names>Frédéric</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zilhão</surname>
            <given-names>João</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique Bordeaux Sud-Ouest, Institut de Mathématiques de Bordeaux, Université de Bordeaux, Talence, France</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Unité Mixte de Recherche 5199 De la Préhistoire à l'Actuel: Culture, Environnement et Anthropologie, Université de Bordeaux, Talence, France</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Institute for Archaeology, History, Cultural and Religious Studies, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Seminari d'Estudis i Recerques Preistòriques, Universitat de Barcelona/Instituciò Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avançats, Barcelona, Spain</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Frayer</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Kansas, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">f.derrico@pacea.u-bordeaux1.fr</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: FC FD PD FS JZ. Performed the experiments: FC. Analyzed the data: FC FD PD JZ. Wrote the paper: FC FD JZ.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e21545</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Caron et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>The question of whether symbolically mediated behavior is exclusive to modern humans or shared with anatomically archaic populations such as the Neandertals is hotly debated. At the Grotte du Renne, Arcy-sur-Cure, France, the Châtelperronian levels contain Neandertal remains and large numbers of personal ornaments, decorated bone tools and colorants, but it has been suggested that this association reflects intrusion of the symbolic artifacts from the overlying Protoaurignacian and/or of the Neandertal remains from the underlying Mousterian.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title>
          <p>We tested these hypotheses against the horizontal and vertical distributions of the various categories of diagnostic finds and statistically assessed the probability that the Châtelperronian levels are of mixed composition. Our results reject that the associations result from large or small scale, localized or generalized post-depositional displacement, and they imply that incomplete sample decontamination is the parsimonious explanation for the stratigraphic anomalies seen in the radiocarbon dating of the sequence.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions/Significance</title>
          <p>The symbolic artifacts in the Châtelperronian of the Grotte du Renne are indeed Neandertal material culture.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the European Research Council (FP7/2007/2013/ERC Grant TRACSYMBOLS n°249587). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>For most of the 20th century, personal ornaments, systematic pigment use and elaborate bone technology were associated with the co-emergence of “Cro-Magnon” people and the Upper Paleolithic (beginning in Western Europe with the Châtelperronian) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-LeroiGourhan1">[1]</xref>. Over the last three decades, a number of findings challenged this view <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-DeGiorgio1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho2">[9]</xref>, namely: (a) in Africa, ornaments, pigments and abstract decoration occur among the immediate ancestors of modern humans; (b) anatomical modernity emerged earlier in Africa; (c) burial ritual, jewelry and body painting are known among Middle Paleolithic European Neandertals; (d) where the Châtelperronian is found with diagnostic fossils, these are of Neandertals, not modern humans; (e) the earliest evidence for anatomical modernity in Europe post-dates by many millennia the emergence of the Châtelperronian, corroborating the Neandertal authorship of the latter; (f) no sudden change or accretion is observed in the early stages of symbolic material culture but rather a discontinuous pattern of asynchronous emergence, disappearance and re-emergence of its features among both ‘modern’ and ‘archaic’ populations of the two continents. As a result, most paleoanthropologists now acknowledge that “symbolic thinking” and “modern behavior” are not species-specific features of anatomically modern humans and that Neandertals were the makers of a symbolic material culture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico2">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Nowell1">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The Châtelperronian levels (VIII, IX and X) of a French cave site, the Grotte du Renne (Arcy-sur-Cure, Burgundy), document the association between Neandertal remains and large numbers of personal ornaments, bone tools (some of which are decorated), and colorants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Although excavated (by A. Leroi-Gourhan) between 1949 and 1963 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-LeroiGourhan2">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Schmider1">[15]</xref>, the techniques used were modern (stratigraphic digging and area exposure of occupation surfaces, spatial plotting of key finds and features, systematic sieving of the deposits), and the geological reality of the described succession—confirmed by limited excavation of a stratigraphic baulk carried out in 1998 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-David1">[16]</xref>—is uncontroversial. Even so, the following concerns have been voiced with respect to the homogeneity of the artifact assemblages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-White1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref>: (a) no investigation of potential refitting of stone tools across levels has been carried out, so the extent to which the Grotte du Renne sequence was affected by post-depositional disturbance cannot be assessed; (b) the existence of overlying Protoaurignacian, Aurignacian/Gravettian and Gravettian levels (VII, VI and V, respectively) and the fact that some ornament types present in the Châtelperronian sequence (e.g., pierced fox teeth) are common in later Early Upper Paleolithic (EUP) technocomplexes raise the possibility that the symbolic artifacts found in the Châtelperronian are intrusive from above; (c) conversely, as the habitation structures built by the first Châtelperronian occupants of the site conceivably disturbed the underlying Middle Paleolithic levels (XI–XIV), the Neandertal remains recovered in levels VIII–X could be intrusive from below.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0021545-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Grotte du Renne, Châtelperronian symbolic artifacts.</title>
          <p>Personal ornaments made of perforated and grooved teeth (1–6, 11), bones (7–8, 10) and a fossil (9); red (12–14) and black (15–16) colorants bearing facets produced by grinding; bone awls (17–23). 1–9 courtesy of M. Vanhaeren, 12–16 courtesy of H. Salomon, 17–23 modified after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico3">[24]</xref>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>On the basis of these concerns, three alternatives to the stratigraphic integrity of the Châtelperronian levels of the Grotte du Renne are conceivable: (a) the personal ornaments, bone tools and colorants are Protoaurignacian or later and the Neandertal remains are Mousterian, so the site's Châtelperronian lacked symbolic artifacts and is of unknown authorship (hereafter Hypothesis 1); (b) the personal ornaments are Protoaurignacian or later, so the site's Châtelperronian, although made by Neandertals, lacked symbolic artifacts, as the colorants and bone tools may be regarded as purely functional (hereafter Hypothesis 2); and (c) the personal ornaments, bone tools and colorants are Châtelperronian, but the Neandertal remains are Mousterian, so the Châtelperronian may well have been made by modern humans instead (hereafter Hypothesis 3).</p>
      <p>In the following, the distributions of ornaments, bone tools, colorants, pigment processing tools and human teeth are compared with those of diagnostic stone tools: Levallois flakes (Mousterian); Châtelperron points and convergent sidescrapers, the latter as a proxy for the <italic>racloir châtelperronien</italic>, a tool type that Leroi-Gourhan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-LeroiGourhan3">[21]</xref> defined as characteristic of the site's Châtelperronian but is not discriminated as such in available inventories; Dufour bladelets and their unretouched blanks (Protoaurignacian). Using this tested taphonomic approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho3">[22]</xref>, we assess whether the final condition represented by the observed distributions can be derived by post-depositional disturbance from any of the initial conditions implied by Hypotheses 1–3, which, statistically, are our null hypotheses. Our results reject them. Therefore, the alternative view—the association between symbolic artifacts, Châtelperronian stone tools and diagnostic Neandertal fossils characteristic of levels VIII–X is genuine and reflects the behavior of the Grotte du Renne's Neandertal occupants—stands unrefuted.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Of the different post-depositional processes that can affect an archeological site <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Brantingham1">[23]</xref>, generalized, large scale disturbance can be rejected from further consideration in this case because the diagnostic artifacts, upon which the different levels were assigned to different technocomplexes, would have become scrambled and the sequence would have been recognized from the outset as stratigraphically mixed. As shown by the distributions for levels VII–XIV (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021545-t001">Table 1</xref>), nothing can be farthest from the truth, as 100% of all Levallois flakes were recovered in Mousterian levels XI–XIV, 99% of all Châtelperronian points were recovered in Châtelperronian levels VIII–X, and 100% of the bladelets (both Dufour bladelets and unretouched blanks) were recovered in Protoaurignacian level VII.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0021545-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>Grotte du Renne. Stratigraphic distribution of key finds<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0021545-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Levels</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ornaments</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pigments</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Workedbone</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Neandertalteeth</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dufourbladelets</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Châtelperronpoints</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Levalloisflakes</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unretouchedbladelets</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Convergentsidescraprers</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VII</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">287</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2800</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VIII</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IX</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">286</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1183</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">284</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XI</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XII</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XIII</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XIV</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p>*In order to simplify, and also because inventories of the different find categories are unavailable for them, levels VI and above are not considered here.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>Conceivably, two other mechanisms could have created the notional contradiction between a stratigraphic distribution of lithic diagnostics that matches expectations in &gt;99% of the instances and the putative displacement of entire categories of items found in association with such diagnostics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Brantingham1">[23]</xref>. One such mechanism is localized, large scale displacement reaching non-adjacent levels of the stratigraphy (e.g., as a result of mammal burrowing or subsurface anthropogenic intervention); the other is small scale, gradual and cumulative displacement of individual objects across the entire sequence through geological or pedogenetic processes (e.g., as a result of cryoturbation or root/worm activity).</p>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Localized, large scale displacement</title>
        <p>The stratigraphic consistency of vertical distributions does not counter, per se, that unrecognized disturbance of a particular area of a given level may explain the presence in that stratigraphic unit of find categories otherwise absent from intact areas. For instance, in the case of Châtelperronian level X of the Grotte du Renne, the ornaments and other symbolic items could correspond to a subsurface cache created by level VII Protoaurignacian people that burrowing animals subsequently moved further down, while the Neandertal remains could come from a discrete accumulation (related to e.g. secondary burial) that Châtelperronian construction activity or animal burrowing subsequently moved up from Mousterian levels XI–XII.</p>
        <p>The expected outcome of the displacement of such find clusters is a pattern where the original concentration, even if diluted by the disturbance process, would be preserved to some extent, defining a scatter with a clear center close to its original location and increasingly sparse toward the periphery. In contrast to such an expectation, the personal ornaments in level X feature a homogeneous, low density distribution across the entire excavated surface, with most finds coming from outside the area of densest Protoaurignacian occupation, while the bone awls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico3">[24]</xref> form two broad clusters that coincide with the location of the Châtelperronian habitation features (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g002">Figures 2</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g003">3</xref>). The Neandertal remains are also scattered and, although found outside the habitation features, were recovered well inward of the dripline, countering the notion that they reflect dumping at the cave entrance of Mousterian sediments removed by Châtelperronian construction activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The apparent concentration against the East wall reflects the presence of three groups of teeth from three different individuals, interpreted as the in situ disintegration of single mandibular or maxillary pieces <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Bailey1">[5]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0021545-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Grotte du Renne distributions.</title>
            <p>Left: personal ornaments from Châtelperronian levels VIII–X plotted against the most densely occupied area of Protoaurignacian level VII. Right: Neandertal remains from Châtelperronian levels VIII–X plotted against the habitation features in level X. The areas in grey are hearths.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0021545-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Grotte du Renne, distribution of bone awls, ornaments and pigment processing tools.</title>
            <p>Top: in Protoaurignacian level VII. Bottom: in Châtelperronian level X. The areas in grey are hearths.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0021545-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Distribution of the Neandertal remains in Châtelperronian levels VIII–X of the Grotte du Renne; after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Bailey1">[<bold>5]</bold></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-BarYosef2">[19<bold/>]</xref>, modified.</title>
            <p>In the plan (above), the black circles are diagnostic teeth, the white circles are teeth whose features are consistent with (but do not prove) assignment to the Neandertals, the white square is the immature temporal bone, and the red lines indicate the position of the stratigraphic profiles shown middle and bottom.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Another hypothesis is that the Neandertal teeth derived by progradation from stratigraphically lower but topographically higher Mousterian deposits <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-BarYosef2">[19]</xref>. Conceivably, this could have happened southward of row 8 and westward of row C, because of the marked slope of the strata outside the Mousterian dripline. Most teeth (80%), however, were found inward of this dripline, where the stratification of the Châtelperronian deposits is horizontal. Most were also found against the eastern wall of the cave—14 out of the 22 securely provenanced to level X (64%) came from rows C–D of the grid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Given this spatial distribution, the presence of Neandertal teeth in level X cannot result from progradation processes associated with the westward dip of immediately underlying Mousterian level XI. Such processes are gravity-driven, so they could have diplaced material into the adjacent Y-B rows lower down but not into the exact same C–D rows higher up. Rather than the 25 Neandertal teeth in Châtelperronian level X reflecting downslope erosion of the Mousterian deposits towards the center of the cave, it is the two teeth in Mousterian levels XI–XII that likely correspond to downward displaced items, as is the case with the few bone awls and Châtelperron points also found in levels XI–XII <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico2">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico3">[24]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The distribution of ornaments, bone tools, pigments and pigment processing tools <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Julien1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-deBeaune1">[29]</xref> is congruent with the placement of the habitation features recognized (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g003">Figures 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g005">5</xref>). In Protoaurignacian level VII, there is a concentration on the eastern side of the cave, almost exclusively in bands B–D, where the few pigments and pigment processing tools were associated with hearths (a large spot of red pigment was also noted toward the entrance). In Châtelperronian level X, the spatial distribution of the abundant pigments changes slightly between sublevels but, in agreement with the location of the tools for pigment processing, maximum concentrations systematically occur inside the features identified in the central and northwestern parts of the cave, where most ornaments and bone tools were also found. These patterns strengthen the case for the stratigraphic integrity of levels VII and X and further counter the notion that the symbolic items found therein were differentially affected by post-depositional disturbance.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0021545-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Spatial distribution of colorants by weight in Châtelperronian level X (all sublevels included); data from</title>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Couraud1">[<bold>27</bold>]</xref><bold>.</bold> Top left, all colors (14,580 g); top right, red (10,520 g); bottom left, black (3,961 g); bottom right, yellow (99.6 g). Bubble sizes reflect the relative frequency per grid unit and were calculated by assigning the following values to the four weight classes given in the data source: [0.1–10 g]  = 10 g; [10–50 g]  = 50 g; [50–100 g];  = 100 g; [&gt;100 g]  = 150 g. Major concentrations are apparent despite the smoothing of the distributions caused by the quantification procedure and they coincide with the habitation features. The grey areas are hearths.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Generalized, small scale displacement</title>
        <p>Limited post-depositional movement across the boundaries of adjacent levels is a ubiquitous feature of cave and rockshelter stratigraphies. The Grotte du Renne is unlikely to have been immune to such processes, and excavation error can result in the misassignment of finds from the interface between different units. Indeed, as with the two awls in the Mousterian that probably come from Châtelperronian level X, four small ornamental ivory fragments from uppermost Châtelperronian level VIII probably originated in the immediately overlying Protoaurignacian <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico2">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho4">[30]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Do such ordinary post-depositional mechanisms suffice to support any of the Hypotheses 1–3 above? Intuitively, no, because (a) explaining the “advanced” finds made in the Châtelperronian levels as entirely intrusive from the later EUP in levels VII or above faces the problem that most such finds came from level X, not level VIII, and (b) although most Neandertal remains from the Châtelperronian were in level X, the notion that adjacent Mousterian levels XI–XII seeded the fossils recovered in the immediately overlying unit faces the problem that only 6% would have remained put <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico2">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho4">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho5">[31]</xref>.</p>
        <p>In order to more rigorously test whether the operation of this mechanism could be held responsible for the observed distributions, we modeled it as a random process whereby the final condition (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021545-t001">Table 1</xref>) derives from the initial condition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s005">Table S1</xref>) as a result of small scale displacements affecting the entire thickness of the deposits concerned here (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). In each case, the results of the goodness of fit test reject, for a probability threshold of 0.01, the possibility that the observed distribution can be the outcome of the disturbance, via the modeled mechanism, of a sequence presenting any of the original distributions implied by Hypotheses 1–3. Under Hypotheses 1 and 2, the distribution of the items putatively introduced from level VII or above would have to feature a gradual decrease with depth instead of the observed marked concentration in level X (which is all the more remarkable in the colorants' case as, by weight, the observed totals are 0.45 kg in level VII and 14.58 kg in level X; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021545-t002">Table 2</xref>). Likewise, under Hypothesis 3, the upwardly displaced Neandertal remains would have to be in much smaller numbers than those remaining in situ. Finally, under any of the hypotheses, the displacements would significantly affect the diagnostic stone tool types: under Hypotheses 1 and 2 it is extremely unlikely than no bladelets accompanied the downward displacement of the ornaments and under Hypothesis 3 it is extremely unlikely that no Levallois flakes accompanied the upward displacement of the Neandertal remains.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0021545-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>Stratigraphic distribution of colorants (by weight, in grams) at Grotte du Renne; data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Couraud1">[27]</xref>.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0021545-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Levels</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cultural Attribution</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Red</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yellow</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gravettian</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1179.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1207.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VI</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aurignacian/Gravettian</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">196.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">345.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VII</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Protoaurignacian</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">404.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">451.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VIII</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Châtelperronian</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">966.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">231.7</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1226.1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IX</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Châtelperronian</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1749.3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">476.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2242.9</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Châtelperronian</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,520.2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3961</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14,580.8</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XI</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mousterian</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TOTAL</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,064.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4731.6</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">335.4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,131.5</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100.0</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
        <p>Assuming generalized, small scale disturbance, the worst case scenario for the stratigraphic integrity of the Grotte du Renne is one where, against the geological evidence, the three Châtelperronian levels (VIII–X) are conflated into a single occupation, and post-depositional displacement is modeled as occurring between two adjacent blocks only—for the ornaments, involving overlying Protoaurignacian level VII, and, for the Neandertal teeth, involving underlying Mousterian levels XI–XII (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Even so, the observed distribution of the lithic diagnostics implies that, for the predicted initial distributions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s005">Table S1</xref>) and a probability threshold of 0.01, no more than 1 ornament (Hypothesis 2) or 7 Neandertal teeth (Hypothesis 3) could have found their way into that single Châtelperronian block (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s004">Figure S3</xref>), whereas the observed totals are 39 and 29, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Since the observed vertical and horizontal distribution patterns cannot be derived by post-depositional disturbance from the initial set of conditions implied by Hypothesis 1–3, we conclude that the association between Châtelperron points, personal ornaments, bone tools, colorants and Neandertal remains found at the Grotte du Renne is genuine. In contrast, using Bayesian statistics applied to the stratigraphic distribution of bone tools and human-modified faunal remains directly dated by radiocarbon, a recent assessment of the site's integrity argued for significant problems because more than one third of the dates turned out to be outliers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Our results show that the reason for this anomaly must be sought elsewhere, as the distribution of the lithic diagnostics sets strict limits to the potential disturbance of the other find categories, including those addressed by the radiocarbon study and not considered here (such as the faunal remains). For instance, 8 (out of 21) Châtelperronian samples came out younger than or overlapping with the ∼36.5 ka <sup>14</sup>C BP limit set by chronostratigraphic patterns for the beginning of the Protoaurignacian in Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho6">[32]</xref>. But, since 0 out of 287 Dufour bladelets and 0 out of 2800 unretouched bladelets intruded, (a) the probability that those 8 samples correspond to intrusive items is &lt;1e-18 and (b) the probability that more than one dated Châtelperronian sample is displaced from level VII is &lt;0.01 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s004">Figure S3</xref>). Given these probabilities, it is clear that the accuracy of the results obtained should be treated as an open issue, which invalidates the outlier test—in this context, a simple conclusion of the premise that the radiocarbon results are accurate.</p>
      <p>Under this light, the Grotte du Renne's radiocarbon dating history is very instructive. Given that, in agreement with predictions made on the basis of archeological criteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho6">[32]</xref>, the new ages for Protoaurignacian level VII fell in the ∼34.5–36.5 ka <sup>14</sup>C BP range, the underlying Châtelperronian levels VIII–X should be chronometrically older. However, only 2 out of the 17 results (12%) previously published for the Châtelperronian of the Grotte du Renne satisfied such a condition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref>, which is the case for at least 13 of the new samples (62%). This progress can only have come from ameliorated measurement and pretreatment techniques (e.g., ultrafiltration) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-BronkRamsey1">[33]</xref>, not from the site's stratigraphic integrity having improved over the years. In this context, the parsimonious explanation for why a minority of the new results came out younger than expected should be based on (a) the poor preservation of collagen at the site, as reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref>, and (b) the incomplete decontamination of a number of samples.</p>
      <p>The impact that even trace amounts of contaminants have on samples whose ages are close to the limit of applicability of radiocarbon is huge. For instance, if a sample is 40,000 years old, as little as 0.6% of a contaminant dated to the time of the excavation of the finds, 50 years ago, would suffice to produce a measured age of 35,000. The Grotte du Renne's faunal remains and bone tools were extensively preserved with glues and consolidants, and indeed this was the single site among those dated by the Oxford-led project to assess the chronology of the Middle-to-Upper Paleolithic transition in Europe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham2">[34]</xref> where such kinds of samples, otherwise rejected as unsuitable, were used—in fact, at the Grotte du Renne, they represent as much as 84% of the determinations.</p>
      <p>To circumvent the problems of potential contamination the radiocarbon study used a solvent sequence phase of pretreatment before collagen extraction whenever visual inspection indicated curatorial preservation. In one case, Poly-Vinyl Acetate (PVA) was identified. This <sup>14</sup>C-free material cannot be the cause for results younger than expected but the study also found that it was impossible to rule out trace contamination from this or other sources. That some remained indeed is indicated by (a) the C:N value of 3.7 associated with one of the Châtelperronian results (OxA-X-2226-7), which the study accepted despite acknowledging that it indicated the presence of exogenous carbon, (b) the C:N value of 3.6, also above the OxA threshold for acceptance, obtained for a sample from level X dated to ∼23.1 ka <sup>14</sup>C BP (OxA-X-2222-21), (c) the vertical distribution of the few dates for unconsolidated samples, which are fully consistent with stratigraphy and, at the 95.7% confidence level, with the ∼36.5 ka <sup>14</sup>C BP boundary for the Protoaurignacian (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g006">Figure 6</xref>), (d) the fact that outliers only occur in samples from level IX or below (all dates for uppermost Châtelperronian level VIII and those above correlate perfectly with stratigraphic depth), and (e) the results for Mousterian level XII, younger than those obtained for well dated occurrences of the Châtelperronian elsewhere in France, namely at Roc-de-Combe and the eponymous site of the Grotte des Fées <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho3">[22]</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0021545-g006" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g006</object-id>
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Plot of age (mean value and 2σ confidence interval) against stratigraphic provenience of the new radiocarbon dates for the Grotte du Renne; data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[<bold>20</bold>]</xref>.</title>
          <p>Levels VIII–X are Châtelperronian.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>These level XII results play a critical role in the outlier analysis underpinning reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref> 's interpretation that the Grotte du Renne sequence is significantly disturbed. In the framework of the Bayesian approach followed, the results for level XII constrain the age of the overlying units, for instance making the date of 48,700±3600 <sup>14</sup>C BP (OxA-X-2279-44) for level X appear too old for its stratigraphic position and, hence, as an intrusion form the underlying Mousterian. In fact, when that ∼48.7 ka <sup>14</sup>C BP result is statistically compared one-to-one with those for the same level accepted by the outlier analysis (for instance, using the tools in the Calib 6.0 software, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://calib.qub.ac.uk/calib/" xlink:type="simple">http://calib.qub.ac.uk/calib/</ext-link>), all come out as identical.</p>
      <p>More importantly, accepting the outcome of the outlier analysis should have invalidated the use of Bayesian modeling to reconstruct the chronology of the site—if significant movement across levels occurred, the stratigraphic position of a given sample cannot be used to constrain the probability distribution associated with its determined age. This is because, in that case, the real chronological order of the samples, an a priori requirement of the modeling, must be considered unknown—once significant post-depositional displacement is posited, stratigraphic provenance cannot be taken as an indicator of relative age. For instance, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g002">Figure 2</xref> of reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref>, the two level XII samples are used to define the lower chronological boundary of the Châtelperronian but this assumes that the samples are in situ. However, if, as the authors claim, as much as 30% of their 31 determinations are outliers and this implies post-depositional disturbance, then we cannot reject the possibility that those samples represent instead intrusions from overlying Châtelperronian X, as otherwise suggested by the presence of a Châtelperronian bone awl in that level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-dErrico3">[24]</xref>.</p>
      <p>To be consistent with the results of the outlier analysis, the start of the sequence in reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref> 's age model should be given by the ∼48.7 ka <sup>14</sup>C BP result for level X because, if the latter is statistically distinct from the others from the same level and deemed to be stratigraphically displaced, then it can only have been displaced from the Mousterian. This carries the implication that the beginning of the Mousterian phase should be represented by that ∼48.7 ka <sup>14</sup>C BP result, not, as assumed by the model, by the two results in the ∼37–38 ka <sup>14</sup>C BP range obtained for level XII, which, in turn, significantly decreases the number of outliers. The distortion imposed on the data by reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref> 's unwarranted use of Bayesian modeling also impacts the estimated duration of the sequence. This is readily apparent when comparing its <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0021545-g002">figures 2</xref> (modeled calibrated dates) and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s003">S2</xref> (unmodeled calibrated dates): in the former, the succession of levels XII to VI spans some 5000 years, while the latter suggests that it may in fact correspond instead to as much as 10,000.</p>
      <p>Given the above, the interpretation of the anomalously young results for the Grotte du Renne should be identical to that for similary consolidated bone samples whose collagen was similarly poorly preserved and whose sample chemistry similarly failed to meet all the standards of the (same) dating laboratory—namely, the two Neandertal bones from Vindija dated at Oxford, which treated them as minimum ages only <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham3">[35]</xref>. But even if the accuracy of all the new radiocarbon results for the Grotte du Renne is accepted, it can be calculated (given the 38% putatively displaced Châtelperronian samples this implies, and assuming that all finds are equally susceptible to displacement), for a probability threshold of 0.01, that at least 8 of the 39 ornaments and 5 of the Neandertal teeth in Châtelperronian levels VIII–X cannot be intrusive (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s001">Text S1</xref>). Obviously, this calculation ignores the modeling boundaries imposed by the distribution of the diagnostic stone tools, as if their cultural and chronological attributes were meaningless and the Châtelperronian and Protoaurignacian labels void to begin with. The point, however, is that even this unrealistic scenario fails to reject that at least a part of the Grotte du Renne's Neandertal teeth and symbolic artifacts are truly in situ.</p>
      <p>Finally, we note that recent re-analysis of the Quinçay rockshelter, the other major Châtelperronian site featuring ornaments (six pierced teeth of deer, fox and wolf), showed that there is little ground to question its stratigraphic integrity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Granger1">[36]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Roussel1">[37]</xref>. A small component of retouched bladelets is found in all levels but in association with the cores whence the corresponding blanks were extracted and those cores are of typical Châtelperronian technique. This material cannot represent intrusion from overlying Aurignacian levels, which are non-existent at Quinçay, where the Châtelperronian sequence was sealed by collapsed limestone slabs several meters long and ∼50 cm thick.</p>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <p>Our results reject the notion that the association of symbolic artifacts with Neandertals at the Grotte du Renne results from large scale localized or small scale generalized displacement of artifacts and human remains. They imply that the parsimonious explanation for the anomalies observed in the radiocarbon dating of the sequence is incomplete decontamination of the bone samples used. Moreover, the Grotte du Renne is not alone. Similar, and even earlier evidence of Neandertal symbolically mediated behaviors has now been produced for the Middle Paleolithic of Iberia and Italy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho2">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Peresani1">[38]</xref>, and there is sufficient ground to postulate that coeval material from the French Châtelperronian, the Italian Uluzzian <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-RielSalvatore1">[39]</xref>, and a number of sites in Central and Western Europe with less clear-cut stratigraphic patterns <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho4">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho5">[31]</xref> is also Neandertal-associated. While recent Grotte du Renne research developments have been claimed to herald the bursting of the Neandertal ornament “bubble” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Mellars1">[40]</xref>, our results and their wider context show that such news were “greatly exaggerated.” The Châtelperronian levels of the Grotte du Renne do stand for Neandertal symbolism.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>To assess post-depositional displacement of human remains we used loose teeth (given their small size and mobility and the fact that, except for a temporal fragment, no other human skeletal parts were recovered at the Grotte du Renne), and only considered those unambiguously provenanced to a specific grid unit. In ornament counts, fragments of possibly the same object were considered separately. These criteria explain the minor differences with previously published inventories <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho4">[30]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Zilho5">[31]</xref>. We used a continuous time model positing that the different items can move from one level to the next at a given rate, which we assume to be the same for both the direction of the movement (upward or downward) and the category concerned because no significant difference in physical properties (size, weight or density) exists that justifies discriminating in this regard between, say, a Dufour bladelet, a Neandertal tooth or a pierced fox canine. From top to bottom, and using available radiometric information <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Higham1">[20]</xref>, we set the upper time limits for the formation of the different stratigraphic units at 40.5 (VII), 41.5 (VIII), 43.0 (IX), 44.5 (X), 46.0 (XI), 47.5 (XII), 49.0 (XIII) and 50.5 (XIV) thousand calendar years ago (but found the results of the exercise to be unchanged even if the age of the lower, undated units was moved back in time by several millennia). We then estimated, for each hypothesis, the rate parameter that best fitted, according to the Pearson chi square statistic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Agresti1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Wasserman1">[42]</xref>, the transformation between the initial and final conditions. This best fitted rate parameter provides the best trade-off regarding objects that have not moved (e.g. Dufour or unretouched bladelets) and objects that have moved (e.g. Neandertal teeth or ornaments) under the different hypotheses. We then conducted a goodness of fit test to assess the likelihood that the final distribution was generated from the hypothesized initial distributions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s005">Table S1</xref>) via the model. Using the best fitted rate parameter for each hypothesis, we obtained expected final distributions for each find category and probabilities that any given item moved from any given level to another (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s006">Tables S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s007">S3</xref>). These distributions were then compared with the observed final distributions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0021545-t001">Table 1</xref>) to assess the goodness of fit of the model associated with each hypothesis. This goodness of fit is measured by the Pearson chi square statistic, which provides a positive measure of discrepancy between the expected and true final distributions of objects. Having concluded that small scale, generalized displacement failed to account for significant movement in some find categories and none in others, we then calculated, using the Bayes theorem <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0021545-Bernardo1">[43]</xref>, the probability that items from the key find categories (Neandertal teeth and personal ornaments) had moved into the Châtelperronian from the overlying Protoaurignacian or the underlying Mousterian under the constraints posed by the distribution of diagnostic stone tools. A technical description of our statistical approach is provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0021545.s001">Text S1</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0021545.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Hypothesis testing, continuous time model and probability models.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0021545.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Realization from the continuous time model, for an object starting in level XI.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(TIFF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0021545.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>a: <italic>S</italic> in function of λ for Hypothesis 1; b: <italic>S</italic> in function of λ for Hypothesis 2, c: <italic>S</italic> in function of λ for Hypothesis 3.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0021545.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>a: probability that k ornaments over a set of 47 (the total number of ornaments from levels VII and VIII–X) are intrusive, given the number of intruded Dufour bladelets and unretouched bladelets; b: probability that k Neandertal teeth over a set of 31 (the total number of Neandertal teeth from levels XI–XII and VIII–X) have moved from levels XI–XII to levels VIII–X, given the number of Levallois flakes that have moved; c: probability that k samples over a set of 26 (the total number of dated samples from levels VII and VIII–X) are intrusive, given the number of intruded Dufour bladelets and unretouched bladelets.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0021545.s005" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Predicted initial distribution of finds for the different tested hypotheses.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0021545.s006" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Expected final values </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>E</italic>
            </bold>
            <bold> (rounded) associated to the best fitted λ for the different tested hypotheses.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0021545.s007" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0021545.s007" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Values π associated to the best fitted λ for the different hypotheses.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Hélène Salomon, for allowing us to use unpublished images of Grotte du Renne colorants, and Michèle Julien and Marian Vanhaeren for giving us permission to use images of personal ornaments and for providing updated information on their spatial distribution.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-LeroiGourhan1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leroi-Gourhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1964</year>             <article-title>Les religions de la Préhistoire.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Presses Universitaires de France</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">164</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-DeGiorgio1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Giorgio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Explaining worldwide patterns of human genetic variation using a coalescent-based serial founder model of migration outward from Africa.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>16057</fpage>             <lpage>16062</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Rightmire1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rightmire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Middle and later Pleistocene hominins in Africa and Southwest Asia.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>106</volume>             <fpage>1604</fpage>             <lpage>1605</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-dErrico1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>d'Errico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Evolution, Revolution or Saltation scenario for the emergence of modern cultures?</article-title>             <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source>             <volume>366,1567</volume>             <fpage>1060</fpage>             <lpage>1069</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Bailey1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hublin</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Dental remains from the Grotte du Renne at Arcy-sur-Cure (Yonne).</article-title>             <source>J Hum Evol</source>             <volume>50</volume>             <fpage>485</fpage>             <lpage>508</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Jacobs1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deacon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grün</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Ages for the Middle Stone Age of Southern Africa: Implications for Human Behavior and Dispersal.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>322</volume>             <fpage>733</fpage>             <lpage>735</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-dErrico2">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>d'Errico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilhão</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baffier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelegrin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>Neanderthal acculturation in western Europe? A critical review of the evidence and its interpretation.</article-title>             <source>Curr Anthropol</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>S1</fpage>             <lpage>S44</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Zilho1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilhão</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Neandertals and moderns mixed, and it matters.</article-title>             <source>Evol Anthropol</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>183</fpage>             <lpage>195</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Zilho2">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilhão</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angelucci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Badal-Garcia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>d'Errico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Symbolic use of marine shells and mineral pigments by Iberian Neandertals.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>1023</fpage>             <lpage>1028</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Conard1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>A critical view of the evidence for a southern African origin of behavioral modernity.</article-title>             <source>South Af Archaeol Soc</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>175</fpage>             <lpage>179</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Hovers1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hovers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The Middle-to-Upper Paleolithic Transition: What News?</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camps</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Sourcebook of Paleolithic Transitions: Methods, theories, and interpretations</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>             <fpage>455</fpage>             <lpage>462</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Langley1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarkson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Behavioural Complexity in Eurasian Neanderthal Populations.</article-title>             <source>Cambridge Archaeological Journal</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>289</fpage>             <lpage>307</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Nowell1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Defining Behavioral Modernity in the Context of Neandertal and Anatomically Modern Human Populations.</article-title>             <source>Annu Rev Anthropol</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>437</fpage>             <lpage>452</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-LeroiGourhan2">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leroi-Gourhan</surname><given-names>Arl</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leroi-Gourhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1964</year>             <article-title>Chronologie des grottes d'Arcy-sur-Cure (Yonne). I : Climats du quaternaire récent. II : Industries du Paléolithique supérieur.</article-title>             <source>Gallia Préhistoire</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>36</fpage>             <lpage>64</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Schmider1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmider</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>L'organisation de l'habitat aurignacien.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmider</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>L'Aurignacien de la Grotte du Renne</source>             <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>CNRS éditions</publisher-name>             <fpage>15</fpage>             <lpage>24</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-David1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Connet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lhomme</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miskovsky</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Le Châtelperronien de la grotte du Renne à Arcy-sur-Cure (Yonne). Données sédimentologiques et chronostratigraphiques.</article-title>             <source>Bulletin de la Société Préhistorique Française</source>             <volume>98</volume>             <fpage>207</fpage>             <lpage>230</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-White1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2001</year>             <article-title>Personal ornaments from the Grotte du Renne at Arcy-sur-Cure.</article-title>             <source>Athena Rev</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>41</fpage>             <lpage>46</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-BarYosef1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bar-Yosef</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Neanderthals and modern humans: A different interpretation.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conard</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>When Neanderthals and Modern Humans Met</source>             <publisher-loc>Tübingen, Germany</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Kerns-Verlag</publisher-name>             <fpage>467</fpage>             <lpage>482</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-BarYosef2">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bar-Yosef</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bordes</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Who were the makers of the Châtelperronian culture?</article-title>             <source>J Hum Evol</source>             <volume>59</volume>             <fpage>586</fpage>             <lpage>593</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Higham1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Chronology of the Grotte du Renne (France) and implications for the context of ornaments and human remains within the Châtelperronian.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>20234</fpage>             <lpage>20239</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-LeroiGourhan3">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leroi-Gourhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1968</year>             <article-title>Le petit racloir châtelperronien.In La Préhistoire,Problèmes et Tendances.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazières</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>CNRS éditions</publisher-name>             <fpage>275</fpage>             <lpage>282</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Zilho3">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilhão</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>d'Errico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bordes</surname><given-names>J-G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenoble</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Texier</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Analysis of Aurignacian interstratification at the Châtelperronian-type site and implications for the behavioral modernity of Neandertals.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>12643</fpage>             <lpage>12648</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Brantingham1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brantingham</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surovell</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waguespack</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>NA</surname></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Modeling post-depositional mixing of archaeological deposits.</article-title>             <source>J Anthropol Archaeology</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>517</fpage>             <lpage>540</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-dErrico3">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>d'Errico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liolios</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhaeren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baffier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Many awls in our argument. Bone tool manufacture and use in the Châtelperronian and Aurignacian levels of the Grotte du Renne at Arcy-sur-Cure.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilhão</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>d'Errico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <publisher-loc>Lisbon, Portugal</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Instituto Português de Arqueologia</publisher-name>             <fpage>247</fpage>             <lpage>270</lpage>             <comment>The Chronology of the Aurignacian and of the Transitional Technocomplexes. Dating, Stratigraphies, Cultural Implications</comment>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Julien1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baffier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liolios</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>L'outillage en matières dures animales.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmider</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>L'Aurignacien de la Grotte du Renne</source>             <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>CNRS éditions</publisher-name>             <fpage>217</fpage>             <lpage>250</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Taborin1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taborin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Les objets de parure.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmider</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>L'Aurignacien de la Grotte du Renne</source>             <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>CNRS éditions</publisher-name>             <fpage>253</fpage>             <lpage>256</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Couraud1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Couraud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1991</year>             <article-title>Les pigments des grottes d'Arcy-sur-Cure (Yonne).</article-title>             <source>Gallia Préhistoire</source>             <volume>33</volume>             <fpage>17</fpage>             <lpage>52</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Salomon1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Les matières colorantes au début du Paléolithique supérieur: sources, transformations et fonctions.</article-title>             <publisher-name>PhD dissertation, University of Bordeaux</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-deBeaune1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Beaune</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>L'outillage sur galet.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmider</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>L'Aurignacien de la Grotte du Renne</source>             <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>CNRS éditions</publisher-name>             <fpage>199</fpage>             <lpage>213</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Zilho4">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilhão</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>The emergence of ornaments and art: an archeological perspective on the origins of ‘Behavioral Modernity’.</article-title>             <source>J Arch Res</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>1</fpage>             <lpage>54</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Zilho5">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilhão</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Aliens from outer time?Why the “Human Revolution”is wrong and where do we go from here?</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Condemi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weniger</surname><given-names>G-C</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Continuity and Discontinuity in the Peopling of Europe</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>             <fpage>331</fpage>             <lpage>366</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Zilho6">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zilhão</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>d'Errico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>An Aurignacian “Garden of Eden” in southern Germany? An alternative interpretation of the Geissenklösterle and a critique of the Kulturpumpe model.</article-title>             <source>Paléo</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>69</fpage>             <lpage>86</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-BronkRamsey1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronk Ramsey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Improvements to the pretreatment of bone at Oxford.</article-title>             <source>Radiocarbon</source>             <volume>51</volume>             <fpage>337</fpage>             <lpage>3360</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Higham2">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>European Middle and Upper Palaeolithic radiocarbon dates are often older than they look: problems with previous dates and some remedies.</article-title>             <source>Antiquity</source>             <volume>85</volume>             <fpage>235</fpage>             <lpage>249</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Higham3">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Revised direct radiocarbon dating of the Vindija G1 Upper Paleolithic Neandertals.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>103</volume>             <fpage>553</fpage>             <lpage>557</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Granger1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lévêque</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>Parure castelperronienne et aurignacienne: étude de trois séries inédites de dents percées et comparaisons. C. R. Acad. Sci.</article-title>             <source>Paris</source>             <volume>325</volume>             <fpage>537</fpage>             <lpage>543</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Roussel1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roussel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soressi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>La Grande Roche de la Plématrie à Quinçay (Vienne). L'évolution du Châtelperronien revisitée.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buisson-Catil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Primault</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Préhistoire entre Vienne et Charente - Hommes et sociétés du Paléolithique</source>             <publisher-loc>Villefranche-de-Rouergue</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Association des Publications Chauvinoises</publisher-name>             <fpage>203</fpage>             <lpage>219</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Peresani1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peresani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romandini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tagliacozzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Late Neandertals and the intentional removal of feathers as evidenced from bird bone taphonomy at Fumane Cave 44 ky B.P., Italy.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>108</volume>             <fpage>3888</fpage>             <lpage>3893</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-RielSalvatore1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riel Salvatore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>What is a transitional industry? The Uluzzian of southern Italy as a case study.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camps</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Sourcebook of Paleolithic Transitions</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>             <fpage>377</fpage>             <lpage>396</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Mellars1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mellars</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Neanderthal symbolism and ornament manufacture: the bursting of a bubble?</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>             <volume>23</volume>             <fpage>20147</fpage>             <lpage>20148</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Agresti1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agresti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Categorical Data Analysis.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Wiley-Interscience</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Wasserman1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>All of Statistics: A Concise Course in Statistical Inference.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0021545-Bernardo1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AFM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <article-title>Bayesian Theory.</article-title>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Wiley and Sons</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>