<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-25277</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Sensory perception</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Psychoacoustics</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Engineering</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Architectural engineering</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Human factors engineering</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Industrial engineering</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Industrial research</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Non-clinical medicine</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Environmental health</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Public health</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Environmental health</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Physics</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Classical mechanics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Acoustics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Physical laws and principles</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Acoustics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Economic anthropology</subject>
              <subject>Social anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Economics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microeconomics</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Urban economics</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Economic anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Psychology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Applied psychology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Industrial psychology</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavior</subject>
              <subject>Experimental psychology</subject>
              <subject>Social psychology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Sociology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Social research</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
          <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
          <subject>Physics</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Influence of Social and Behavioural Characteristics of Users on Their Evaluation of Subjective Loudness and Acoustic Comfort in Shopping Malls</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Evaluation of Acoustics in Shopping Malls</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Meng</surname>
            <given-names>Qi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>Jian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>School of Architecture, Harbin Institute of Technology, Harbin, China</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>School of Architecture, University of Sheffield, Sheffield, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Charrier</surname>
            <given-names>Isabelle</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Universite Paris Sud, France</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mengq@hit.edu.cn</email> (QM); <email xlink:type="simple">j.kang@sheffield.ac.uk</email> (JK)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: QM JK. Performed the experiments: QM JK. Analyzed the data: QM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: QM. Wrote the paper: QM.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e54497</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Meng, Kang</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A large-scale subjective survey was conducted in six shopping malls in Harbin City, China, to determine the influence of social and behavioural characteristics of users on their evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort. The analysis of social characteristics shows that evaluation of subjective loudness is influenced by income and occupation, with correlation coefficients or contingency coefficients of 0.10 to 0.40 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05 or <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). Meanwhile, evaluation of acoustic comfort evaluation is influenced by income, education level, and occupation, with correlation coefficients or contingency coefficients of 0.10 to 0.60 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05 or <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). The effect of gender and age on evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort is statistically insignificant. The effects of occupation are mainly caused by the differences in income and education level, in which the effects of income are greater than that of education level. In terms of behavioural characteristics, evaluation of subjective loudness is influenced by the reason for visit, frequency of visit, and length of stay, with correlation coefficients or contingency coefficients of 0.10 to 0.40 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05 or <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). Evaluation of acoustic comfort is influenced by the reason for visit to the site, the frequency of visit, length of stay, and also season of visit, with correlation coefficients of 0.10 to 0.30 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05 or <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). In particular, users who are waiting for someone show lower evaluation of acoustic comfort, whereas users who go to shopping malls more than once a month show higher evaluation of acoustic comfort. On the contrary, the influence of the period of visit and the accompanying persons are found insignificant.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>The work was supported by the China Natural Science Foundation (No. 50928801), the PR China Ministry of Education Foundation for PhD Bases (20112302110045) and the Harbin Technological Innovation Fund (2012RFXXS046). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>There are about 20,000 shopping malls in China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Song1">[1]</xref>. Harbin City, for example, has 30 shopping malls, while 15 more will be constructed before 2020 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Zhao1">[2]</xref>. The evaluation of acoustic environment in such spaces has been paid increasing attention by users, researchers and governmental organisations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Ministry1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-General1">[4]</xref>. While some studies have been carried out in terms of acoustic environment in shopping malls, the main focus has been on noise control <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Deng1">[5]</xref> and also, only limited types of shopping mall, such as underground shopping centres, have been considered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Tang1">[6]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Tang2">[7]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Previous studies suggested that the sound environment evaluation of a space depends strongly on the social characteristics of the users, such as gender, age, income, occupation, and education, as well as their behavioural characteristics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Zimer1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-DellaCrociata2">[24]</xref>. Mehrabian <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Mehrabian1">[12]</xref> indicated a slight tendency for women to be more sensitive to sound than men, and evidence suggests that females generally have a higher arousal level than males <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Croome1">[13]</xref>. In terms of age influence, Yang and Kang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yang1">[14]</xref> found in their research on urban open public spaces that users are more favourable of, or tolerant towards sounds relating to nature with the increase of age. With regards to the education factor, Yu and Kang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yu1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yu3">[17]</xref> indicated that the correlation coefficients for natural sounds are predominantly negative, suggesting that people tend to prefer natural sounds more with the increase in education level. For human sounds, mixed positive and negative correlation coefficients are found. Kang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref> indicated that the behavioural characteristics of users may also play an important role, and sound quality of an urban area may depend on how long people have been living there <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-SchulteFortkamp1">[19]</xref>. Similarly, Bull <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Bull1">[20]</xref> found that people with stereos may have different sound evaluation from others. Bertoni et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Bertoni1">[21]</xref> also stated that sound experience is important, but Job et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Job1">[22]</xref> obtained contradictory results. Della Crociata et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-DellaCrociata1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-DellaCrociata2">[24]</xref> indicated that users' acoustic satisfaction is highly correlated with perceived acoustic intensity and is influenced by sources of acoustic annoyance. Cultural factors play an important role as well; hence, the effect of social and behavioural factors vary significantly between different countries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Zhang1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Zhang2">[26]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Consequently, the present study is conducted to examine the influence of social and behavioural factors on evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort in different types of shopping mall, based on a series of subjective surveys. The social factors considered include gender, age, income, occupation, and education; whereas the behavioural factors include the reason for visit, frequency of visit, length of stay, period of visit, and number of accompanying partners.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Ethics statement</title>
        <p>This study was approved by the Degree Committee of the School of Architecture, Harbin Institute of Technology (this governing body is equipped with an ethical review board). In the questionnaire the names of individual participants were not included, and participants provided their written informed consent to participate in this study. Participants aged 17 were accompanied by their parents.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Survey sites</title>
        <p>The field study was conducted through a questionnaire survey at selected case study sites in Harbin, China. Harbin, the capital city of Heilongjiang province, is a typical large city in China, characterised by a continental climate, with four highly distinguishable seasons. The population is about 10 million, and its economic development is at medium level in China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Zhao1">[2]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The 30 existing shopping malls in Harbin were first divided into two groups based on their space types, that was, 12 were considered as single-space type, where the space was generally of a single volume and it was seen as one room on the plan, and 18 were multiple–space type, where the space consisted of multiple volumes and on the plan there were more than one linked rooms. This division according to space types was based on previous studies stating that space types are an important factor affecting the evaluation of acoustics in indoor spaces because reverberation time (RT) and sound pressure level (SPL) may vary in different space types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Chen1">[27]</xref>. Three shopping malls from each space type were randomly selected as final samples. The six case study shopping malls were Qiu Lin, Tong Ji, Man Ha Dun, Suo Fei Ya, Jin An, and Hui Zhan, among which Qiu Lin, Man Ha Dun and Hui Zhan were single-space type, the others were multiple–space type. Details about these shopping malls are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t001">Table 1</xref>. It is noted that Hui Zhan is a typical underground shopping mall, with which comparison could be made between under- and above-ground shopping malls.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t001</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Basic information of the survey sites.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0054497-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sites</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size (m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sound sources</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NI</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aver. SPL (dBA)</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aver. SL</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aver. AC</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31000</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background music, music from shops, PA system, footsteps, surrounding speech, air-conditioning</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.31</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10000</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background music, vendors' shouting, music from shops, sounds from toys, surrounding speech, footsteps, air-conditioning</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.28</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28700</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background music, vendors' shouting, music from shops, sounds from toys, surrounding speech, footsteps, air-conditioning</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.43</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32000</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background music, music from shops, PA system, footsteps, surrounding speech, air-conditioning</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">285</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.80</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45000</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background music, music from shops, PA system, footsteps, surrounding speech, air-conditioning</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.31</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30000</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Background music, vendors' shouting, music from shops, PA system, footsteps, surrounding speech, air-conditioning, water</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">690</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.42</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>The basic information includes size, sound sources, the number of interviews conducted, average SPL, average subjective loudness (1, very quiet; 2, quiet; 3, neither quiet nor loud; 4, loud; and 5, very loud) and acoustic comfort (1, very uncomfortable; 2, uncomfortable; 3, neither comfortable nor uncomfortable; 4, comfortable; and 5, very comfortable). ‘NI’ means number of interviews, ‘Aver. SL’ means average evaluation of subjective loudness, and ‘Aver.AC’ means average evaluation of acoustic comfort.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Questionnaire survey</title>
        <p>Around 100 to 700 valid questionnaires were obtained in every shopping mall from autumn 2011 to summer 2012. In total, 2,134 questionnaires were received. Previous studies suggested that 100 valid questionnaires are appropriate to evaluate the acoustics of a particular place <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yu3">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref>, whereas to examine the effects of users' social or behavioural factors a considerably larger number of questionnaires would be needed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref>. The interviewees in the case study sites were randomly selected, and based on the initial data analysis, their educational and social backgrounds, as well as on-site behaviours (such as waiting for someone, walking around, shopping or passing by), were considered as representatives <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Job1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Zhang2">[26]</xref>. Generally 10–15 fixed survey positions were used, which were equally distributed at every survey site, and more than 20 meters from each other <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The questionnaire included four parts, according to the framework suggested by Kang <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref>, considering user, space, sound, and environment. The first part was about a user's basic information in terms of social characteristics (such as gender, age, income, education level, and occupation) and behavioural characteristics (such as what they are doing, frequency of visit, time of visit, and accompanying persons). The second part was on the evaluation of space, especially the evaluation of reverberation and space perception. The third part was about sound sources and the evaluation of loudness. The final part was the evaluation of other environmental factors, such as temperature, humidity, and lighting. The questionnaire was introduced as an enquiry on general environmental conditions, instead of concentrating solely on acoustic environment, to avoid possible bias towards the acoustic aspect <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang2">[28]</xref>. The questionnaire's reliability and validity were tested before the actual field surveys <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Meng1">[29]</xref>.</p>
        <p>A five-point bipolar category scale was used in the questionnaire. Evaluation of subjective loudness was divided into five levels: 1- very quiet; 2- quiet; 3- neither quiet nor loud; 4- loud; and 5- very loud. Evaluation of acoustic comfort was also divided into five levels: 1- very uncomfortable; 2- uncomfortable; 3- neither comfortable nor uncomfortable; 4- comfortable; and 5- very comfortable. For other questions and scales in the questionnaire, more details can be found from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Meng1">[29]</xref>.</p>
        <p>The surveys covered four seasons because previous studies in urban open public spaces indicated that seasons may affect users' evaluation of acoustics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yu3">[17]</xref>. Moreover, the surveys were conducted at various times of day, from morning to afternoon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yang1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref>. Three time periods were considered, namely, 09:00 to 11:59 (morning), 12:00 to 14:59 (midday), and 15:00 to 17:59 (afternoon).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Objective measurements</title>
        <p>The sound level measurement was conducted immediately after each questionnaire interview, and the microphone of the sound level meter was positioned near the location of questionnaire interview and more than 1 m away from any reflective surfaces and 1.2 m to 1.5 m <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref> above the floor to avoid the effect of sound reflections. The sound level meter was set into slow-mode, and reading was taken every 3 s to 5 s. A total of 100 measurement data were obtained in each survey position, and the corresponding A-weighted equivalent continuous sound level, LAeq, was derived <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang3">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Meng2">[32]</xref>. In other words, after each interview a 300–500 s measurement was made. Simultaneously, other environmental factors, such as air temperature, relative humidity, and lighting were also measured at the survey positions corresponding to every sound level measurement <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Liu1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Huang1">[34]</xref>, although in this paper, due to the limitation of space, these data are not included and analysed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Data analysis</title>
        <p>SPSS 15.0 was used to establish a database with all the subjective and objective results <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Pallant1">[35]</xref>. The data were analysed using the following: Chi-square correlations (two-tailed) for factors with three or more categories of ranked variables; Chi-square contingency correlations (two-tailed) for factors with three or more categories for categorical variables; and mean differences t-test (two-tailed) for factors with two categories. Both linear and nonlinear correlations were considered <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Li1">[36]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Social characteristics</title>
        <sec id="s3a1">
          <title>Gender</title>
          <p>Although previous studies suggested that the effect of gender on sound annoyance evaluations is generally insignificant <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Fields1">[37]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Miedema1">[38]</xref>, they are more focused on urban open spaces. In this study, the mean difference in evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort was determined between males and females of every survey site, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t002">Table 2</xref>. It is interesting to note that in shopping malls, again, no significant (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.1) difference was observed between males and females.</p>
          <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t002" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t002</object-id>
            <label>Table 2</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Relationships between social characteristics and evaluation of subjective loudness, as well as acoustic comfort.</title>
            </caption>
            <alternatives>
              <graphic id="pone-0054497-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
              <table>
                <colgroup span="1">
                  <col align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                </colgroup>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Gender</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Age groups</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Education level</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Income</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Occupation</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey sites</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.02</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.33<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.36<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.41<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.42<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.08</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.38<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.40<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.36<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.37<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.46<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.51<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.07</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.45<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.47<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </alternatives>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="nt102">
                <label/>
                <p>The table includes mean difference between males and females, chi-square test correlation coefficients forage groups, income, education level, and chi-square test contingency coefficients for occupation, where the significance levels are also shown, with ** indicating p&lt;0.01, and *indicating p&lt;0.05. SL represents evaluation of subjective loudness, and AC represents evaluation of acoustic comfort.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a2">
          <title>Age</title>
          <p>Previous studies indicated that different age groups may have different evaluations of the sound environment and sound preference, possibly because of their long-term experience <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-SchulteFortkamp1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Bertoni1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yang2">[39]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Jin1">[40]</xref>. In this study, the users' age were divided into 7 groups, namely, &lt; = 17, 18 to 24, 25 to 34, 35 to 44, 45 to 54, 55 to 64, and &gt; = 65 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yu3">[17]</xref>. The relationships between age groups and evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t002">Table 2</xref>. It can be seen that there is no significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.1) among the age groups in terms of evaluation of subjective loudness or acoustic comfort. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t003">Table 3</xref> further examines whether there are some tendencies that certain age groups would rate the evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort more extremely. It seems that no such tendencies are observed.</p>
          <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t003" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t003</object-id>
            <label>Table 3</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Differences among age groups in terms of evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort.</title>
            </caption>
            <alternatives>
              <graphic id="pone-0054497-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
              <table>
                <colgroup span="1">
                  <col align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                </colgroup>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey sites</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very loud</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very quiet</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very comfortable</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very uncomfortable</td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–44</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; = 65</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25–34</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25–34</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45–54</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55–64</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 17</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25–34</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–24</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55–64</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45–54</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–24</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–24</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–44</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–44</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55–64</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45–54</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; = 65</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18–24</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35–44</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </alternatives>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a3">
          <title>Education level</title>
          <p>In China, educational level can be divided into 6 groups, namely, (1) non literate, (2) primary school, (3) junior middle school, (4) senior middle school, special school or technical school, (5) college graduates, and (6) graduate or higher <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Huang1">[34]</xref>. In this study, only three people were at the level of non literate, so only the five other levels were considered. The relationships between education level and evaluation of subjective loudness, as well as acoustic comfort, are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t002">Table 2</xref>. No significant (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.1) difference was found between education level and subjective loudness, but the correlation between education level and acoustic comfort was from −0.30 to −0.50 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). In other words, the higher the users' education level is, the lower the acoustic comfort is.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a4">
          <title>Income</title>
          <p>The users' income level was divided into 6 groups, namely, &lt; = 1000, 1001–2000, 2001–3000, 3001–4000, 4001–5000, and &gt; = 5001 Yuan (1 Yuan ≈0.15 US dollar) per month <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Li1">[36]</xref>. The correlations between users' income and evaluation of subjective loudness, as well as acoustic comfort, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t002">Table 2</xref>, where the income is measured by US dollar, are from 0.10 to 0.40 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01), and from −0.30 to −0.60 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01), respectively. In other words, the higher the users' income is, the higher the users' evaluation of subjective loudness is, but the lower the evaluation of acoustic comfort is.</p>
          <p>The relationships between users' income and evaluation of subjective loudness, as well as acoustic comfort, are also illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0054497-g001">Figure 1</xref>. It is interesting to note that, both evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort change significantly when the income level changes from 301 to 450 US dollar per month, which is approximately the average income of people in Harbin, namely 2,450 Yuan per month (≈367 US dollar) in 2011 and 2,518 Yuan per month (≈378 US dollar) in 2012 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-HarbinStatistical1">[41]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-HarbinStatistical2">[42]</xref>. In other words, it seems that in terms of evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort, there is a significant difference between people with “lower than average income (&lt;2000 Yuan)” and “higher than average income (&gt;3000 Yuan)”, with a mean difference of 0.31 to 0.52 on subjective loudness (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01), and of 0.49 to 0.76 on acoustic comfort (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01).</p>
          <fig id="pone-0054497-g001" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.g001</object-id>
            <label>Figure 1</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Relationships between users</title>
              <p>' <bold>average income and their evaluation of acoustics.</bold> (a) Between income and evaluation of subjective loudness; (b) Between income and evaluation of acoustic comfort.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a5">
          <title>Occupations</title>
          <p>The users' occupations were divided into 11 groups, namely, farmer, soldier, worker, service worker, technical worker, teacher, officer, student, self-employed individual, housewife, retiree, and unemployed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Lin1">[43]</xref>. The relationships between users' occupations and evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t002">Table 2</xref>, showing Chi-square contingency correlation of 0.10 to 0.30 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) and 0.10 to 0.30 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05), respectively. In other words, with different occupations, evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort also differ.</p>
          <p>The occupations that corresponded to extreme evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t004">Table 4</xref>. It can be seen that farmers tend to select ‘very loud’ for evaluation of subjective loudness, and their evaluation of subjective loudness is 0.06 to 0.12 higher than that of the other occupations (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) in four out of six survey sites, namely Qiu Lin, Tong Ji, Man Ha Dun and Hui Zhan. Given that farmers usually live in a relatively quiet environment, they may feel nosier when they go to shopping malls in big cities. However, they may not necessarily feel the acoustic environment is unconformable, as can also be seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t004">Table 4</xref>. In the questionnaire, one farmer stated that “I would like to be surrounded by noisy crowd.” It is also interesting to note that soldiers may have higher evaluation of acoustic comfort than others, with a mean difference of 0.02 to 0.07 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) in four survey sites, namely Qiu Lin, Suo Fei Ya, Jin An, and Hui Zhan.</p>
          <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t004" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t004</object-id>
            <label>Table 4</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Differences among occupations in terms of evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort.</title>
            </caption>
            <alternatives>
              <graphic id="pone-0054497-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
              <table>
                <colgroup span="1">
                  <col align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                </colgroup>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey sites</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very loud</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very quiet</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very comfortable</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very uncomfortable</td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmer</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worker</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soldier</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teacher</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmer</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retire</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmer</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmer</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worker</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self employed individual</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmer</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retire</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Officer</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soldier</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retire</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Technical man</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soldier</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soldier</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmer</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soldier</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soldier</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retire</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </alternatives>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Behavioural characteristics</title>
        <sec id="s3b1">
          <title>Reason for visit</title>
          <p>Users generally have four purposes for coming to the survey sites, namely, shopping, walking, passing by, and waiting for someone. The relationships between the reason for visit and evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t005">Table 5</xref>. The contingency correlation between the reason for visit and evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort was from 0.10 to 0.20 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) and from 0.10 to 0.30 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05), respectively. In other words, the users' evaluation of acoustic evaluation may be influenced by their different reasons for visit to the shopping malls.</p>
          <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t005" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t005</object-id>
            <label>Table 5</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Relationship between behavioural characteristics and evaluation of subjective loudness, as well as acoustic comfort.</title>
            </caption>
            <alternatives>
              <graphic id="pone-0054497-t005-5" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
              <table>
                <colgroup span="1">
                  <col align="left" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                  <col align="center" span="1"/>
                </colgroup>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Reason for visit</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Frequency of coming</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Season</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Period of visit</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Length of stay</td>
                    <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Accompanying persons</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey sites</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.26<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.24<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.30<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.16<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.23<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.33<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.33<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.27<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.27<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.22<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.18<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<italic><sup>*</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.14<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.01</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </alternatives>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="nt103">
                <label/>
                <p>The table includes mean difference between persons with partners and without, chi-square test correlation coefficients for frequency of coming, income, education level, and chi-square test contingency coefficients for reason for visit, where the significance levels are also shown, with ** indicating p&lt;0.01, and * indicating p&lt;0.05. SL represents evaluation of subjective loudness, and AC represents evaluation of acoustic comfort.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>The average evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort with different reasons for visit in all survey sites are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0054497-g002">Figure 2</xref>. It can be seen that the users who came for shopping generally have lower evaluation of subjective loudness but higher evaluation of acoustic comfort, with a mean difference of 0.11 to 0.45 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) and 0.15 to 0.58 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) respectively, compared with other reasons. Conversely, the users who came to wait for someone generally have higher evaluation of subjective loudness, but lower evaluation of acoustic comfort, with a mean difference of 0.13 to 0.51 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) and 0.09 to 0.49 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05 or <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01), respectively, compared with other purposes. This is likely because the users who are concentrating on shopping may pay decreased attention to the acoustic environment; whereas those who are waiting for someone could have increased attention.</p>
          <fig id="pone-0054497-g002" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.g002</object-id>
            <label>Figure 2</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Effects of users' reason for visit on their evaluation of acoustics.</title>
              <p>(a) Evaluation of subjective loudness; (b) Evaluation of acoustic comfort.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3b2">
          <title>Frequency of visit</title>
          <p>The users' frequency of visit to a certain place and its influence on their evaluation of subjective loudness or acoustic comfort has been mentioned in previous studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Zhang1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Fields1">[37]</xref>. In this study, the users' frequency of visit to shopping malls was divided into 5 categories, namely, first time, rarely (at least once a year), sometimes (at least once a month), often (at least once a week), and frequently (more than three times a week). The relationships between the frequency of visit and evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t005">Table 5</xref>. It can be seen that both evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are influenced by the frequency of visit, with correlation of −0.10 to −0.40 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) in evaluation of subjective loudness, and 0.10 to 0.30 in evaluation of acoustic comfort, respectively. In other words, with the increase in the frequency of visit, the users' evaluation of subjective loudness is lower, but the evaluation of acoustic comfort is higher. This suggests that when users are more familiar with the environment of a certain space, such as shopping malls, they would have a better acoustic evaluation.</p>
          <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0054497-g003">Figure 3</xref> presents the average evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort in all survey sites with increasing frequency of visit. It is interesting to note that in terms of evaluation of subjective loudness, there is a significant change from “once a year” to “once a month” (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01), by0.52 to 0.81 in different sites. Meanwhile, the change in acoustic comfort is also significant, by 0.58 to 1.17 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01).</p>
          <fig id="pone-0054497-g003" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.g003</object-id>
            <label>Figure 3</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Relationships between users' frequency of visit and their evaluation of acoustics.</title>
              <p>(a) Between frequency of visit and evaluation of subjective loudness; (b) Between frequency of visit and evaluation of acoustic comfort.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3b3">
          <title>Time of visit</title>
          <p>In this study, “time” was considered at three levels, namely seasons (from autumn to summer), period of visit (morning, midday, and afternoon); and length of stay (less than 1 hour, 1 to 2 hours, 2 to 3 hours, 3 to 4 hours, and more than 4 hours).</p>
          <list list-type="alpha-lower">
            <list-item>
              <p><italic>Seasons</italic>. The relationships between seasons and evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t005">Table 5</xref>. No significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.1) was observed between seasons in terms of evaluation of subjective loudness, but significant differences were noted between seasons in terms of evaluation of acoustic comfort, with contingency correlation coefficients of 0.10 to 0.20 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05). This is perhaps because the evaluation of acoustic comfort is more related to the evaluation of other aspects of physical comfort, such as the heat and humidity conditions, and users in summer and winter usually give better evaluation for the indoor environment due to more comfortable thermal conditions in shopping malls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Meng3">[44]</xref>, as one customer stated: “I prefer to shop in the malls in summer because they have air conditioning”.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><italic>Period of visit</italic>. No significant (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.1) correlation was found between the period of visit and evaluation of subjective loudness, and also between the period of visit and acoustic comfort (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t005">Table 5</xref>). While in urban open spaces the period of visit was found to be influential on the soundscape evaluation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Nilsson1">[45]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Szeremeta1">[46]</xref>, perhaps because better lighting evaluation may bring better acoustic evaluation, in indoor shopping malls this may not be the case.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><italic>Length of stay</italic>. The length of stay in a certain place is considered to have some influence on evaluation of acoustic comfort, as indicated in several previous studies, although those studies concerned evaluation of subjective loudness rather than acoustic comfort <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Southworth1">[47]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Mao1">[48]</xref>. The relationships between the length of stay and evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t005">Table 5</xref>, where it can be seen that the correlation coefficients are −0.10 to −0.40 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01), and 0.10 to 0.30 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05), respectively. In other words, the users will have lower evaluation of subjective loudness and higher acoustic comfort when their length of stay is longer.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>The relationships between the length of stay and evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort are also shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0054497-g004">Figure 4</xref>. It can be seen that in terms of evaluation of subjective loudness there is a significant decrease from “less than 1 hour” to “1–2 hours”, with a mean difference of 0.52 to 0.98 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) at different sites, whereas in terms of evaluation of acoustic comfort there is a significant increase, with a mean difference of 0.37 to 0.86 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). Such changes in evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort continue with increasing length of stay until ‘3–4 hours’, although the rate of change is much slower. Conversely, when the length of stay is greater than 4 hours, evaluation of subjective loudness will increase and the acoustic comfort will decrease. Similar results were also obtained in a previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Chen1">[27]</xref>.</p>
          <fig id="pone-0054497-g004" position="float">
            <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.g004</object-id>
            <label>Figure 4</label>
            <caption>
              <title>Relationshipsbetween users' length of stay and their evaluation of acoustics.</title>
              <p>(a) Between length of stay and evaluation of subjective loudness; (b) Between length of stay and evaluation of acoustic comfort.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3b4">
          <title>Accompanying persons</title>
          <p>Previous studies in urban open public spaces suggested that the acoustic evaluation might be different with accompanying persons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yu3">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Meng1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Yang3">[49]</xref>. In this study, however, no significant difference was obtained (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.1) between the users with accompanying persons and without, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t005">Table 5</xref>, in terms of evaluation of subjective loudness as well as acoustic comfort. A possible reason for this difference is that the users staying outdoors may pay more attention to their partners, compared to indoor spaces like shopping malls.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Previous studies noted that there are interrelationships between social characteristics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Cosmas1">[50]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Reingold1">[51]</xref>. This is also the case in this study, in terms of income, education level, and occupation, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t006">Table 6</xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t006" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t006</object-id>
        <label>Table 6</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Relationships among income, education level, and occupation.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0054497-t006-6" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t006" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey sites</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income and education level</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation and income</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation and education level</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt104">
            <label/>
            <p>The table shows chi-square test correlation coefficients between income and education level, and chi-square test contingency coefficients between occupation and income as well as education level, where the significance levels (2-tailed) are also shown, with ** indicating p&lt;0.01, and * indicating p&lt;0.05.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Relationships between occupation and evaluation of acoustic comfort are generally insignificant when income or education level is in a certain range. For example, considering the income “between 151 and 300 US dollar” or the education level of “graduate or higher,” the results in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t007">Table 7</xref> indicate that generally there is no significant correlation between occupation and evaluation of acoustic comfort. Meanwhile, for a given occupation, such as “worker”, there are significant correlations between income and evaluation of acoustic comfort, with correlation coefficients of −0.30 to −0.60, as well as between education level and evaluation of acoustic comfort, with correlations of −0.30 to −0.50, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t008">Table 8</xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t007" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t007</object-id>
        <label>Table 7</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Relationships between occupation and evaluation of acoustic comfort.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0054497-t007-7" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t007" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey sites</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation and acoustic comfort with come fixed</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation and acoustic comfort with education level fixed</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<sup>*</sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt105">
            <label/>
            <p>The table shows chi-square test contingency coefficients between occupation and evaluation of acoustic comfort, when income or education is fixed at a level, namely income is from 151 to 300 US dollar, education level is graduate or higher, where the significance levels (2-tailed) are also shown, with ** indicating p&lt;0.01, and *indicating p&lt;0.05.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t008" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t008</object-id>
        <label>Table 8</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Relationships between users' evaluation of acoustic comfort and income, as well as education level.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0054497-t008-8" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t008" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey sites</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.40<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.36<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.45<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.42<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.41<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.40<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.39<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.38<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.53<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.50<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.49<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.47<italic><sup>**</sup></italic></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt106">
            <label/>
            <p>The table shows chi-square test correlation coefficients between income or education level and evaluation of acoustic comfort, when occupation is fixed as worker, where the significance levels (2-tailed) are also shown, with ** indicating p&lt;0.01, and * indicating p&lt;0.05.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>A multiple regression analysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Wayne1">[52]</xref> was then carried out to identify whether income or education level is more important for the evaluation of acoustic comfort. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t009">Table 9</xref> shows that the <italic>R<sub>adj</sub><sup>2</sup></italic>, ranged 0.263 to 0.377, is significant (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) in all survey sites. Income is found to be generally more important than education level with regards to influencing the evaluation of acoustic comfort because it has higher absolute values, from 0.047 to 0.233, of standardised coefficient in all survey sites.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0054497-t009" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t009</object-id>
        <label>Table 9</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The effect of users' income and education on evaluation of acoustic comfort.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0054497-t009-9" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0054497.t009" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey sites</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>R</italic>
                  <sub>adj</sub>
                  <sup>2</sup>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standardised coefficient</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qiu Lin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.312</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.332**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.285**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tong Ji</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.410**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.207**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Man Ha Dun</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.365</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.338**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.109**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suo Fei Ya</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.378**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.145**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jin An</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.377</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.350**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.202**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hui Zhan</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Income</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.331**</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education level</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.254**</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt107">
            <label/>
            <p>The table shows multiple regression analysis <italic>R</italic><sub>adj</sub><sup>2</sup> with standardised coefficient between income or education level and evaluation of acoustic comfort, where the significance levels (2-tailed) are also shown, with <sup>**</sup> indicating <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>It is noted that based on the data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0054497-t005">Table 5</xref>, it can be shown that the space type of shopping malls, namely single- or multiple- space type, have no significant effect on users' evaluation of acoustics.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Based on questionnaire surveys and measurements conducted in six shopping malls in Harbin City, China, this study examines the sound environment in terms of the users' social and behavioural characteristics.</p>
      <p>In terms of social characteristics, evaluation of subjective loudness is influenced by income and occupation, with correlation coefficients or contingency coefficients of 0.10 to 0.40. The evaluation of acoustic comfort is influenced by income and education level, with correlation coefficients or contingency coefficients of 0.10 to 0.60. The effect of gender and age on the evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort is statistically insignificant.</p>
      <p>In terms of behavioural characteristics, evaluation of subjective loudness is influenced by the reason for visit, frequency of visit, and length of stay, with correlation coefficients or contingency coefficients of 0.10 to 0.40. evaluation of acoustic comfort is influenced by the reason for visit, frequency of visit, length of stay, and season, with correlation coefficients of 0.10 to 0.30. The users who were waiting for someone were found to give lower evaluation of acoustic comfort compared those who were shopping; the users who went to shopping malls more than once a month were found to have higher evaluation of acoustic comfort; and the users who stayed in shopping malls from 2 to 4 hours were likely to give better evaluation of acoustic comfort evaluation compared to those who stayed longer or shorter.</p>
      <p>Between different space types of shopping malls it seems that there is no significant difference in terms of acoustic evaluation.</p>
      <p>The findings of this study can contribute to a better understanding of acoustic environment in shopping malls, and are also useful for the establishment of acoustic comfort prediction models based on artificial neural networks (ANN) and support vector machine (SVM), which are currently being developed. It is also of great interest to compare different kinds of shopping malls, using the same methodology. Correspondingly, a cross-cultural comparison between the UK and China is planned <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang4">[53]</xref>. Finally, it is important to relate the evaluation of acoustic comfort to the sound fields of shopping malls, where the space forms are often special such as long or flat spaces, for which much theoretical work has been carried out <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang5">[54]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0054497-Kang11">[60]</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Song1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Song F (2011) Sound Environment in Comprehensive Shopping Malls. PhD Thesis. Harbin: Harbin Institute of Technology.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Zhao1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zhao MD (2009) The Eastern Moscow: Harbin City. Harbin: Harbin Press. (In Chinese).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Ministry1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ministry of Environmental Protection of the People's Republic of China (2008) Emission Standard for Community Noise (GB22337–2008). Beijing: Chinese Environmental Science Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-General1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">General Administration of Quality Supervision, Inspection and Quarantine of the People's Republic of China (2008) Environmental Quality Standard for Noise (GB3096–2008). Beijing: Chinese Environmental Science Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Deng1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>How to control the noise in shopping malls</article-title>. <source>Chinese Public Health</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Tang1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tang ZZ, Kang J, Jin H (2009) Sound field and soundscape in underground shopping streets. Proceedings of Euronoise 2009, Edinburgh, Scotland, UK.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Tang2">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Acoustic environment in underground shopping streets in north China, Journal of Harbin Institute of Technology</article-title>. <volume>18(sup2)</volume>: <fpage>354</fpage>–<lpage>359</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Zimer1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellermeier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Psychometric properties of four measures of noise sensitivity: a comparison</article-title>. <source>Journal of Environmental Psychology</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>302</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Karlsson1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The acoustic environment as a public domain</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Acoustic Ecology</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Ellermeier1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellermeier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eigenstetter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Psychoacoustic correlates of individual noise sensitivity</article-title>. <source>J Acoust Soc Am</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1464</fpage>–<lpage>1473</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Woolley1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Woolley H (2003) Urban open spaces. London: Spon Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Mehrabian1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mehrabian A (1976) Public Places and Private Spaces – The Psychology of Work, Play, and Living Environments. New York: Basic Books Inc. Publisher.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Croome1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Croome DJ (1977) Noise, Building and People. Oxford: Pergamon Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Yang1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Acoustic comfort evaluation in urban open public spaces</article-title>. <source>Appl Acoust</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Yu1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Modeling subjective evaluation of soundscape quality in urban open space: An artificial neural network approach</article-title>. <source>J Acoust Soc Am</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>1163</fpage>–<lpage>1174</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Yu2">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Effects of social, demographical and behavioural factors on the sound level evaluation in urban open spaces</article-title>. <source>J Acoust Soc Am</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>783</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Yu3">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Factors influencing the sound preference in urban open spaces</article-title>. <source>Appl Acoust</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>622</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kang J (2006) Urban sound environment. London: Taylor &amp; Francis incorporating Spon.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-SchulteFortkamp1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Schulte-Fortkamp B, Nitsch W (1999) On soundscapes and their meaning regarding noise annoyance measurements. Proceedings of Inter-Noise, Fort Lauderdale, FL, USA.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Bull1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bull M (2000) Sounding out the City: Personal Stereos and the Management of Everyday Life. London: Berg Publishers.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Bertoni1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bertoni D, Franchini A, Magnoni M, Tartoni P, Vallet M (1993) Reaction of people to urban traffic noise in Modena, Italy. Proceedings of the 6th Congress on Noise as a public Health Problem, Noise, and Man, Nice, France.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Job1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Job RFS, Hafield J, Carter NL, Peploe P, Taylor R, <etal>et al</etal>.. (1999) Reaction to noise: the roles of soundscape, enviroscape and psychscape. Proceedings of Inter-Noise, Fort Lauderdale, USA.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-DellaCrociata1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Della Crociata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martellotta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A measurement procedure to assess indoor environment quality for hypermarket workers</article-title>. <source>Building and Environment</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-DellaCrociata2">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Della Crociata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martellotta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Acoustic comfort evaluation for hypermarket workers</article-title>. <source>Building and Environment</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Zhang1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Towards the evaluation, description and creation of soundscape in urban open spaces</article-title>. <source>Environ Plann B Plann Des</source> <volume>34(1)</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Zhang2">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Subjective evaluation of urban environment: a case study in Beijing</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Environment and Pollution</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Chen1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Acoustic comfort in shopping mall atrium spaces: a case study in Sheffield Meadow hall</article-title>. <source>Architectural Science Review</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang2">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Semantic differential analysis of the soundscape in urban open public spaces</article-title>. <source>Building and Environment</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Meng1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Meng Q (2010) Research and Prediction on Soundscape in Underground Shopping Streets. PhD Thesis. Harbin: Harbin Institute of Technology.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang3">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Effects of individual sound sources on the subjective loudness and acoustic comfort in underground shopping streets, Sci Total Environ</article-title>. <volume>435–436</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Brown1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Soundscapes and environmental noise management</article-title>. <source>Noise Control Engr J</source> <volume>58(5)</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Meng2">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Soundscape evaluation in different types of underground shopping streets</article-title>. <source>Journal of Harbin Institute of Technology</source> <volume>18(sup2)</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Liu1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mochida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A measurement study on the indoor climate of a college classroom</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Ventilation</source> <volume>10(3)</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Huang1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A study on the effects of thermal, luminous, and acoustic environments on indoor environmental comfort in offices</article-title>. <source>Build Environ</source> <volume>49(1)</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Pallant1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pallant J (2005) SPSS survival manual (2nd ed.). UK: Open University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Li1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Li LS (2006) Design Investigation. Beijing: China Architecture &amp; Building Press. (In Chinese).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Fields1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Effect of personal and situational variables on noise annoyance in residential areas</article-title>. <source>J Acoust Soc Am</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>2753</fpage>–<lpage>2763</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Miedema1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miedema</surname><given-names>HME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Exposure-response relationships for transportation noise</article-title>. <source>J Acoust Soc Am</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>3432</fpage>–<lpage>3445</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Yang2">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Yang W, (2000) Soundscape in Urban Open Public Spaces: Comparison between Beijing and Sheffield. MSc Thesis. Sheffield: University of Sheffield.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Jin1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jin H, Meng Q, Kang J (2009) Subjective evaluation of acoustic comfort in underground shopping streets. Proceedings of Inter-noise, Ottawa, Canada.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-HarbinStatistical1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Harbin Statistical Bureau (2011) Statistical Yearbook of Harbin-2011. Beijing: China Statistics Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-HarbinStatistical2">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Harbin Statistical Bureau (2012) Statistical Yearbook of Harbin-2012. Beijing: China Statistics Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Lin1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lin N (2001) Social capital: a theory of structure and action. London: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Meng3">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The influence of users' behavioural characteristics on the evaluation of subjective loudness and acoustic comfort in underground shopping streets</article-title>. <source>Hua Zhong Architecture</source> <volume>28(5)</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage> (In Chinese)..</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Nilsson1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Soundscape quality in suburban green areas and city parks</article-title>. <source>Acta Acust United Ac</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>857</fpage>–<lpage>864</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Szeremeta1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szeremeta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zannin</surname><given-names>PHT</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Analysis and evaluation of soundscapes in public parks through interviews and measurement of noise</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source> <volume>407(24)</volume>: <fpage>6143</fpage>–<lpage>6149</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Southworth1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Southworth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>The sonic environment of cities</article-title>. <source>Environment and Behaviour</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Mao1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Recent progress in hearing perception of loudness</article-title>. <source>Technical Acoustics</source> <volume>28(6)</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>696</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Yang3">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Soundscape and sound preferences in urban squares</article-title>. <source>Journal of Urban Design</source> <volume>10(1)</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Cosmas1">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosmas</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Lifestyle and consumption patterns</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consumer Research</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Reingold1">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reingold</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Inner-city firms and the employment problem of the urban poor: Are poor people really excluded from jobs located in their own neighbourhoods</article-title>. <source>Economic Development Quarterly</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Wayne1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wayne WD, James CT (1979) Business Statistics, Basic Concepts and Methodology. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang4">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Comparison of speech intelligibility between English and Chinese</article-title>. <source>J Acoust Soc Am</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>1216</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang5">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Reverberation in rectangular long enclosures with geometrically reflecting boundaries</article-title>. <source>Acustica</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>516</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang6">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Acoustics in long enclosures with multiple sources</article-title>. <source>J Acoust Soc Am</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>985</fpage>–<lpage>989</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang7">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Sound attenuation in long enclosures</article-title>. <source>Building and Environment</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang8">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Improvement of the STI of multiple loudspeakers in long enclosures by architectural treatments</article-title>. <source>Appl Acoust</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang9">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A method for predicting acoustic indices in long enclosures</article-title>. <source>Appl Acoust</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang10">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Scale modelling for improving the speech intelligibility from multiple loudspeakers in long enclosures by architectural acoustic treatments</article-title>. <source>Acustica</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0054497-Kang11">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Reverberation in rectangular long enclosures with diffusely reflecting boundaries</article-title>. <source>Acta Acust United Ac</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>