<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-02362</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102772</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognitive science</subject><subj-group><subject>Cognition</subject><subj-group><subject>Decision making</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Sensory perception</subject><subj-group><subject>Vision</subject><subj-group><subject>Color vision</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Applied psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Industrial psychology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Attitudes (psychology)</subject><subject>Collective human behavior</subject><subject>Experimental psychology</subject><subject>Human relations</subject><subject>Social psychology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Computer and information sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Computer networks</subject><subj-group><subject>Internet</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Survey research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Culture</subject><subject>Social theory</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Science of Style: In Fashion, Colors Should Match Only Moderately</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">The Science of Style</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>Kurt</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strohminger</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kassam</surname><given-names>Karim S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Psychology, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Psychology, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Social and Decision Sciences, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastian</surname><given-names>Brock</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of New South Wales, Australia</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">kurtgray@unc.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: KG PS NS KK. Performed the experiments: KG PS. Analyzed the data: KG PS. Wrote the paper: KG PS NS KK.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<elocation-id>e102772</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Gray et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Fashion is an essential part of human experience and an industry worth over $1.7 trillion. Important choices such as hiring or dating someone are often based on the clothing people wear, and yet we understand almost nothing about the objective features that make an outfit fashionable. In this study, we provide an empirical approach to this key aesthetic domain, examining the link between color coordination and fashionableness. Studies reveal a robust quadratic effect, such that that maximum fashionableness is attained when outfits are neither too coordinated nor too different. In other words, fashionable outfits are those that are moderately matched, not those that are ultra-matched (“matchy-matchy”) or zero-matched (“clashing”). This balance of extremes supports a broader hypothesis regarding aesthetic preferences–the Goldilocks principle–that seeks to balance simplicity and complexity.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This study was funded by departmental funds at University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="3"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Every day, people ask themselves the question: “What to wear?” People want outfits that are maximally fashionable, and this isn’t mere vanity: clothing influences perceived and signaled social identity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Berger1">[1]</xref>, employment outcomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Forsythe1">[2]</xref>, romantic success <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Hoult1">[3]</xref>, and even cognitive processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Adam1">[4]</xref>. Despite its universal human importance and vast financial worth–the fashion industry is valued at $1.7 trillion (more than double the entire U.S. federal science budget) –there is little empirical psychological research on the objective features which make something fashionable. In this study, we provide an empirical approach to fashionableness, through judgments of color combinations. We uncover practical implications for daily life, and in doing so speak to a broader theory in aesthetics and human preferences–the Goldilocks Principle.</p>
<p>The Goldilocks Principle represents a tradition of philosophical thought stretching back millennia: Aristotle’s Golden mean, Buddha’s middle way, and Confucius’ Doctrine of the Mean all represent a balance between two extremes. The Goldilocks Principle has psychological support in a variety of domains, as infants prefer looking at visual sequences that are neither too complex, nor too simple <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Kidd1">[5]</xref>, and optimum psychological well-being–i.e., flow–is achieved when experiences balance simplicity and complexity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Csikszentmihalyi1">[6]</xref>. The optimal distinctiveness model of social identity suggests that when developing a sense of self, we strive to strike a harmonious balance between similarity with others and individual distinctiveness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Brewer1">[7]</xref>. Furthermore, judgments of facial attractiveness across cultures are predicted by averageness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Apicella1">[8]</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Langlois1">[9]</xref>, suggesting that the aesthetic ideal is found not at the extremes, but rather in balance.</p>
<p>In terms of fashion, there are two popular approaches to style that represent “extremes.” On one hand, we often speak as if the most fashionable outfits are those that fully coordinate or “match” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Patel1">[10]</xref>. This suggests that pairing the same or similar colors with each other may be the key to fashion. On the other hand, fashion is often about being noticed, and so we might want color combinations that maximally differ from each other and “pop” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Espinoza1">[11]</xref>. Between these two extremes, the Goldilocks Principle suggests that the best color combinations are those that are neither too similar (“matchy-matchy”) nor too different (“clashing”).</p>
<p>In this paper, we investigate whether the Goldilocks Principle predicts fashionableness across diverse color combinations in both men’s and women’s outfits. Support for the principle would be illustrated by a “peak” in ratings, such that any linear trends between coordination and fashionableness should be qualified by a quadratic effect such that maximum fashionableness is achieved by moderate color coordination.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board at The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. All participants provided written informed consent prior to completing the study and were recruited through Amazon’s Mechanical Turk (mTurk). A total of 239 mTurk participants (69% women, <italic>M<sub>age</sub></italic> = 35.4, <italic>SD</italic><sub>age</sub> = 12.9) each saw 30 different color combinations, in one of four color palettes. Palettes 1 and 2 were in women’s clothing, and palettes 3 and 4 were in men’s clothing. Each palette included 4 colors, illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102772-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Out of 256 possible color combinations within each set, we selected combinations quasi-randomly to represent a range of coordination, from all matching to all different (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0102772-g001">Figure 1</xref> for sample outfits, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102772.s003">Table S1</xref> for all outfit combinations, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102772.s001">Figure S1</xref> for screen shots of fashionableness, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102772.s002">Figure S2</xref> for screen shots of coordination judgments).</p>
<fig id="pone-0102772-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102772.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Coordination/Matching (z-score).</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102772.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><sec id="s2a">
<title>Fashionableness Judgments</title>
<p>Participants rated clothing sets on how fashionable, good, and liked they were on five point Likert scales. Ratings were aggregated across participants to yield an overall fashionableness rating for each combination (all αs &gt;.95), which were Z-scored within each palette.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Coordination Calculations</title>
<p>Rather than solicit global ratings of coordination, participants rated the coordination of all possible pairs of color swatches within each palette through 3 items–coordinated, matching and similar–answered on five point Likert scales (α’s &gt;.81). These pairwise judgments were aggregated for each outfit, and Z-scored within each palette, to create an overall coordination score. Thus, combinations with all similar or highly coordinated colors (e.g., only shades of green) received high scores whereas those with very different colors (e.g., red, blue, black, grey) received low scores (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0102772.s005">Materials and Methods S1</xref> for additional detail on these calculations).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Analysis</title>
<p>Curve estimation was used to assess linear and quadratic effects of coordination on fashionableness. Women’s and men’s clothing were analyzed separately.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Women’s Clothing</title>
<p>Analyses revealed a significant linear trend, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .18, <italic>F</italic> (1, 58) = 13.04, <italic>p</italic> = .001, such that more coordination was linked to more fashionableness, consistent with the general importance of matching. Importantly, however, this linear trend was qualified by the predicted quadratic effect, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .44, <italic>F</italic> (2, 57) = 22.23, <italic>p</italic>&lt;.001, such that peak fashionableness was achieved by moderately coordinated combinations. This quadratic effect accounted for twice as much variance as the linear effect.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Men’s Clothing</title>
<p>Analyses did not reveal a significant linear trend, <italic>F</italic>&lt;1, but did reveal the predicted quadratic trend, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .28, <italic>F</italic> (2, 57) = 11.18, <italic>p</italic>&lt;.001, such that peak fashionableness was again achieved by moderately coordinated combinations.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>These data suggest a simple answer to the question “what to wear?” Select a color combination that is neither completely uniform, nor completely different. Certainly, moderate matching is not the only key to fashion, which varies across time and culture and depends upon many factors including cut, design, and trendiness. However, these studies reveal that, with all other factors held constant, the Goldilocks principle predicted judgments across four different color palettes in both men’s and women’s clothing. To examine the external validity of these findings, future research should test this idea in naturalistic settings, such as in magazines and runway shows.</p>
<p>These results are consistent with both centuries of philosophical thought and more recent psychological studies on the importance of “the middle way.” The Goldilocks principle may also explain aesthetic judgments beyond fashion, reflecting a basic principle of human preference that seeks to balance simplicity and complexity, order and disorder. Indeed, people prefer music that balances melodic simplicity and complexity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0102772-Huron1">[12]</xref>. This quantitative analysis of fashion is only a first step in empirical aesthetics, but it highlights the utility of bringing science to art; psychological science can help explain the important but often invisible judgments of daily life.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0102772.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102772.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Rating a sample outfit combination.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102772.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102772.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Rating a sample color pair.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102772.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102772.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Clothing combinations by color palette.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102772.s004" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102772.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Cronbach’s Alphas for scales used.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102772.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102772.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Materials and Methods S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Extended materials &amp; methods.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0102772.s006" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0102772.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Results S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Extended results.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Adam Waytz for helpful comments.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Berger1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Who drives divergence? Identity signaling, outgroup dissimilarity, and the abandonment of cultural tastes</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>607</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.95.3.593" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/0022-3514.95.3.593</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Forsythe1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forsythe</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Effect of applicant’s clothing on interviewer’s decision to hire</article-title>. <source>J Appl Soc Psychol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1579</fpage>–<lpage>1595</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Hoult1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoult</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name> (<year>1954</year>) <article-title>Experimental measurement of clothing as a factor in some social ratings of selected American men</article-title>. <source>Am Sociol Rev</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Adam1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galinsky</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Enclothed cognition</article-title>. <source>J Exp Soc Psychol</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>918</fpage>–<lpage>925</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jesp.2012.02.008" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jesp.2012.02.008</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Kidd1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piantadosi</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aslin</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Goldilocks Effect: Human Infants Allocate Attention to Visual Sequences That Are Neither Too Simple Nor Too Complex</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e36399</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0036399" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0036399</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Csikszentmihalyi1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Csikszentmihalyi M (1990) Flow: The psychology of optimal experience. Harper &amp; Row.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Brewer1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The social self: on being the same and different at the same time</article-title>. <source>Pers Soc Psychol Bull</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0146167291175001" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/0146167291175001</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Apicella1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Apicella</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marlowe</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Facial averageness and attractiveness in an isolated population of hunter-gatherers</article-title>. <source>Perception</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1813</fpage>–<lpage>1820</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1068/p5601" xlink:type="simple">10.1068/p5601</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Langlois1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roggman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Attractive faces are only average</article-title>. <source>Psychol Sci</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.1990.tb00079.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1467-9280.1990.tb00079.x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Patel1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Patel N (2013) Wear the trend: monochrome. Vogue India. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vogue.in/content/wear-trend-monochrome-springsummer-2013" xlink:type="simple">http://www.vogue.in/content/wear-trend-monochrome-springsummer-2013</ext-link>. Accessed 2013 Dec 4.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Espinoza1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Espinoza J (2011) Spanish fashion designer Agatha Ruiz de la Prada practices staying in bed. Wall Str J. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704709304576124012375977474.html" xlink:type="simple">http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704709304576124012375977474.html</ext-link>. Accessed 2013 Dec 17.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0102772-Huron1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Huron D (2006) Sweet anticipation: music and the psychology of expectation. Cambridge, Mass. u.a.: MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>