<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0177369</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-07503</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Culture</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Social discrimination</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Geometry</subject><subj-group><subject>Radii</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Demography</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Survey research</subject><subj-group><subject>Surveys</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Europe</subject><subj-group><subject>Greece</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Social discrimination</subject><subj-group><subject>Racial discrimination</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Extending trust to immigrants: Generalized trust, cross-group friendship and anti-immigrant sentiments in 21 European societies</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Trust, contact and anti-immigrant sentiments</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>van der Linden</surname>
<given-names>Meta</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Hooghe</surname>
<given-names>Marc</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>de Vroome</surname>
<given-names>Thomas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Van Laar</surname>
<given-names>Colette</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Centre for Citizenship and Democracy, University of Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>European Research Centre on Migration and Ethnic Relations, Utrecht University, Utrecht, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Center for Social and Cultural Psychology, University of Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Renzaho</surname>
<given-names>Andre M. N.</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Western Sydney University, AUSTRALIA</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p><list list-type="simple"> <list-item>
<p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> ML MH TV CL.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Data curation:</bold> ML.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> ML TV.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Methodology:</bold> ML MH TV.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Visualization:</bold> ML.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> ML.</p></list-item> <list-item>
<p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> ML MH TV CL.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">meta.vanderlinden@kuleuven.be</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>8</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e0177369</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>21</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>26</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>van der Linden et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0177369"/>
<abstract>
<p>The aim of this study is twofold. First, we expand on the literature by testing whether generalized trust is negatively related to anti-immigrant sentiments in Europe. Second, we examine to what extent the relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments is dependent upon cross-group friendships. We apply multilevel linear regression modeling to representative survey data enriched with levels of ethnic diversity covering 21 European countries. Results show that both generalized trust and cross-group friendship are negatively related to anti-immigrant sentiments. However, there is a negligible positive relation between generalized trust and cross-group friendship (<italic>r</italic> = .10), and we can clearly observe that they operate independently from one another. Hence, trusting actors are not more likely to form more cross-group friendships, and cross-group friendship do not lead to the development of more generalized trust. Instead, the findings show that generalized trust leads immigrants too to be included in the radius of trusted others and, as a consequence, the benign effects of generalized trust apply to them as well. We conclude that the strength of generalized trust is a form of generalization, beyond the confines of individual variations in intergroup experiences.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="award001">
<funding-source>
<institution-wrap>
<institution-id institution-id-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000781</institution-id>
<institution>European Research Council</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</funding-source>
<award-id>ERC-2011-ADG</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Hooghe</surname>
<given-names>Marc</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<funding-statement>The authors acknowledge the funding by the European Research Council, ERC Advanced Grant ‘Linkage between citizens and the state’. Grant number: ERC-2011-ADG, and URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://erc.europa.eu" xlink:type="simple">https://erc.europa.eu</ext-link>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"/>
<table-count count="3"/>
<page-count count="13"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>Data from the European Social Survey—Round 1 is available free of charge for non-commercial use and can be downloaded from this website: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.europeansocialsurvey.org/download.html?file=ESS1e06_4&amp;y=2002" xlink:type="simple">http://www.europeansocialsurvey.org/download.html?file=ESS1e06_4&amp;y=2002</ext-link>.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Most studies have consistently noted that the ethnic-cultural majority in Europe is anxious about immigration and its impact on society [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref007">7</xref>]. Constrict theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref008">8</xref>] has hypothesized that exposure to ethnic diversity leads people to withdraw from others and social life to the extent that they trust others less and intergroup relations deteriorate. Contact theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref009">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref011">11</xref>], however, proposes a more optimistic view by showing that people living in ethnically diverse contexts have more contact with immigrants which increases trust and improves intergroup relations. Although the two theories have different predictions regarding the consequences of ethnic diversity for anti-immigrant sentiments, both perspectives point toward the importance of trust in others in establishing more positive intergroup relations. Particularly generalized trust is considered an essential building block for social cohesion in communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref012">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref014">14</xref>]. Generalized trust is defined as the basic expectation that most people can be trusted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref015">15</xref>]. Generalized trust is an abstract outlook toward people in general, encompassing a wide circle of unfamiliar others (e.g. strangers, fellow citizens, foreigners). As it can be assumed that attitudes toward familiar others will be mainly positive, generalized trust is expected to have a positive impact primarily on attitudes toward those who are unfamiliar and often have different background characteristics than the actor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref014">14</xref>]. This has been confirmed by recent studies which have linked generalized trust to increased levels of tolerance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref016">16</xref>] and lower levels of religious and racial prejudice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref017">17</xref>].</p>
<p>However, the literature remains divided as to how this negative relationship between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments can be explained, or more specifically how dependent this relation is upon intergroup contact. Hence, it is unclear whether generalized trust is an evaluation grounded in concrete experiences or whether generalized trust is a personal predisposition that is innate or developed early in life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref018">18</xref>]. Empirical research lends some support to the idea that intergroup contact builds trust, which in turn reduces negative intergroup attitudes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref019">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref021">21</xref>]. However, this notion has mostly been supported for other types of trust, such as outgroup (or intergroup) trust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref022">22</xref>], but might not be replicated for generalized trust in particular [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref014">14</xref>], this is the focus point of the current study. Outgroup trust and generalized trust are two very different concepts: Outgroup trust is an attitudinal measure of trustworthiness of a particular outgroup [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref024">24</xref>], while generalized trust is a general disposition to what extent one trusts (unfamiliar) others in general [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref014">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref025">25</xref>]. It is therefore unlikely that findings of studies that include outgroup trust simply generalize to hypotheses including generalized trust. The extent to which generalized trust is linked to intergroup contact has important implications for the role of generalized trust in explaining anti-immigrant sentiments. If generalized trust is indeed not experience based [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref014">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref025">25</xref>], the robustness of generalized trust to outside influences makes it a crucial factor for peaceful coexistence. Generalized trust would operate as a notion of a benefit of the doubt that should be extended toward all potential interaction partners, whether or not interaction has already taken place [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref027">27</xref>].</p>
<p>In sum, the aim of the current paper is to a) expand existing literature by examining to what extent generalized trust is negatively related to anti-immigrant sentiments, and b) examine whether this relationship is dependent upon positive intergroup contact, i.e. cross-group friendships. Immigration as discussed in this study includes all people who have migrated from their country of birth to their current country of residence. We contribute to the literature on anti-immigrant sentiments in the following ways. First, most studies on the relation between generalized trust and contact did not directly measure contact but included proxy variables such as voluntary engagement or membership [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref018">18</xref>]. These studies did not find evidence for a relation between contact and generalized trust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref028">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref029">29</xref>]. However, these results remain unpersuasive as voluntary engagement does not necessarily imply intergroup contact. Moreover, studies that have included a direct measure of intergroup contact only focused on contact with familiar others or ingroup members. Glanville, Andersson and Paxton found that people who relatively often engage in various forms of socializing with friends, relatives, and neighbors have higher levels of generalized trust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref030">30</xref>]. However, it is unclear whether this finding holds for intergroup contact with people who have different background characteristics such as immigrants. Hence, the current study does include a direct measure of intergroup contact between ethnic-cultural majority members and immigrants. Second, studies on generalized trust and contact that have measured contact only focus on the <italic>frequency</italic> of contact, but do not directly measure the <italic>quality</italic> of intergroup contact [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref020">20</xref>]. This is surprising since especially positive intergroup contact has been hypothesized to aid the development of trust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref031">31</xref>]. Therefore, we take into account the role of cross-group friendships for the relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments. Cross-group friendships have been proven to be more effective in improving intergroup attitudes than other forms of intergroup contact [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref032">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref034">34</xref>]. Hence, cross-group friendships are likely to be a particularly effective form of intergroup contact to possibly facilitate a negative relationship between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments. Third, we use multilevel analysis on representative individual-level survey data (e.g. cross-group friendship, generalized trust, and anti-immigrant sentiments) from the European Social Survey covering 21 countries enriched with a society-level indicator of ethnic diversity (i.e. the percentage of immigrants in a country). With this approach, we answer the call for multilevel approaches to place the study of anti-immigrant sentiments in real-world contexts that include actual daily experience with cultural diversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref035">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref036">36</xref>].</p>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>The inclusion of immigrants in the circle of trusted others</title>
<p>Generalized trust can be considered “as one of the most important synthetic forces within society” (p. 393–394) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref013">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref037">37</xref>] with a multitude of positive outcomes: “Virtually all research suggests that generalized trust has beneficial effects on individuals, communities, the workplace, institutions and, indeed, nations. Trust makes people healthier, happier, and more hospitable” (p. 462) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref038">38</xref>]. The extent to which these benign effects of generalized trust apply to attitudes toward immigrants as well depends on whether immigrants are included in our trusting judgments, which has been debated. In other words, generalized trust must apply to some extent to immigrants for the negative relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments to occur. Fukuyama was among the first to distinguish between the level and the radius of generalized trust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref039">39</xref>]: How wide a circle do people imagine as “most people” when they answer the standard trust question “Generally speaking, would you say that most people can be trusted or that you need to be very careful when dealing with people?” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref040">40</xref>]. In their pioneering work, Delhey and colleagues examine the radius of generalized trust across 51 countries and revealed that in most countries generalized trust both predicts ‘ingroup trust’ (i.e. trust in family, neighbors, and people known personally) as well as ‘outgroup trust’ (i.e. trust in people met for the first time, people from a different religion and nationality). They conclude that “in most places, respondents do imagine a wider circle of people when answering the standard, unspecified question” (p. 800) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref040">40</xref>]. A similar study was performed by Van Hoorn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref041">41</xref>] who showed that especially individualistic cultures are characterized by a broader radius of trust, which is applicable to the European societies studied in the current research.</p>
<p>Based on these studies of the radius of generalized trust, Reeskens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref016">16</xref>] explored the degree to which trusting individuals are actually outward reaching toward marginalized societal groups. Reeskens found a negative relation between generalized trust and social distance with regard to cultural minorities, with social distance examined in a rather broad set of social groups, namely people of a different race, immigrants and foreign workers, Muslims, Jews, and people with large families. Ekici and Yucel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref017">17</xref>] also found a positive relationship between generalized trust and a similar measure of social distance, namely willingness to live next to a neighbor from a different race or religion. Even though both studies do not focus specifically on anti-immigrant sentiments, we expect that it is likely that generalized trust includes immigrants as well. We hypothesize a negative relationship between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments in European societies (H1).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>The role of cross-group friendship for the relationship between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments</title>
<p>If there is indeed a negative relationship between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments, how does this relationship come about? For other types of trust, such as outgroup trust, there exists empirical support for the conditional role of intergroup contact for building trust between groups in order to improve relations between groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref019">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref021">21</xref>]. In other words, intergroup contact is argued to affect people’s willingness to trust members of other groups extending the prejudice-reducing effect of contact [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref031">31</xref>]. However, for generalized trust, the role of contact is less clear. There is an ongoing debate about whether generalized trust is built from personal experiences, such as intergroup contact, or whether generalized trust is a more fixed predisposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref042">42</xref>]. Based on the literature on the origins of trust, we can consider two general perspectives on the role of intergroup contact for the relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments, which have been summarized well by Freitag and Traunmüller [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref015">15</xref>]: The first theoretical perspective considers trust an evaluation of a person’s “social environment and therefore grounded in <italic>concrete experiences of trustworthiness</italic> [emphasis in the original] in social interaction”. The second perspective considers trust “a general propensity either innate or learned early in life and is thus primarily a <italic>personal predisposition</italic> [emphasis in the original]” (p. 787). Concrete experiences of trustworthiness as described in the first theoretical perspective have mostly been found to shape trust in a particular outgroup that does not necessarily extend to outgroups with other demographic characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref019">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref021">21</xref>]. Generally, the second theoretical perspective is considered more relevant for generalized trust, because trust in most people from a variety of different groups—even strangers from outgroups one has never met—cannot completely rest on personal experience. Uslaner argues that “we don’t learn to trust ‘most people’ by evidence. We can’t meet most people. Nor can we generalize from the people we know to ‘most people’”, so generalized trust is not “a judgment that others are trustworthy, but rather that we should treat strangers <italic>as if they were trustworthy</italic> [emphasis in the original]” (p. 7) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref014">14</xref>]. Uslaner considers generalized trust as an optimistic worldview that is likely inherited through socialization rather than acquired through an accumulation of experiences: It is “a general outlook on human nature and <italic>mostly</italic> [emphasis in the original] does not depend on personal experiences or upon the assumption that others are trustworthy” (p. 17) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref025">25</xref>].</p>
<p>Based on above arguments we expect that cross-group friendships and generalized trust are not related (H2). In addition, we also test for a moderation effect, because, even if cross-group friendship and generalized trust are not correlated, generalized trust could still moderate the association between cross-group friendships and anti-immigrant sentiments. However, again based on the above arguments, we do not expect that the negative relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments is dependent upon cross-group friendships (H3).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>The consequences of ethnic diversity for anti-immigrant sentiments</title>
<p>Ethnic diversity sets the stage for the above mentioned hypotheses on the role of generalized trust and cross-group friendships for anti-immigrant sentiments. The consequences of ethnic diversity for social cohesion have been sharply debated. The robustness of generalized trust has been the subject of Putnam’s controversial constrict theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref008">8</xref>], which hypothesizes that “[. . .] people living in ethnically diverse settings appear to ‘hunker down’—that is, to pull in like a turtle” (p. 149). This would in turn deteriorate generalized trust and the quality of native-immigrant relations. A recent meta-analysis scrutinized the results of 90 studies that examined ethnic diversity in different geographical areas on different forms of social cohesion. The result has been ‘a cacophony of empirical findings’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref043">43</xref>]. Whether ethnic diversity is harmful to native-immigrant relations is in part determined by whether or not studies included measures of intergroup contact [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref022">22</xref>]. Studies that have measured ethnic diversity and ethnic or racial attitudes—but not individual-level intergroup contact—appear to treat context-level diversity as a ‘proxy’ for contact, and, thus, presume that individual-level contact variables are not needed; this subset of papers tends to show more pessimistic consequences of diversity. Studies that have included measures of intergroup contact generally found that intergroup contact cancelled out any direct negative consequences of ethnic diversity on racial attitudes or trust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref044">44</xref>]. However, these studies focused on other types of trust than generalized trust.</p>
<p>To our knowledge, there is only one study that has included measures of intergroup contact and generalized trust when examining the relation between ethnic diversity and anti-immigrant sentiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref045">45</xref>]. In their multilevel analysis of local communities in Belgium, Hooghe and De Vroome found that citizens living in ethnically diverse communities do not hold more negative attitudes toward immigrants. The current research further adds to this study by a) taking a cross-national approach to examine whether this finding holds for 21 European societies, and b) examining the consequences of ethnic diversity with and without inclusion of cross-group friendship and generalized trust, to show the potential differences in strength regarding its relation with anti-immigrant sentiments. We hypothesize that ethnic diversity does not predict an increase in anti-immigrant sentiments (H4).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Data and respondents</title>
<p>The first wave of the European Social Survey (ESS-1) from 2002 was used. The ESS is a cross-national survey with representative samples covering 22 different European countries. We chose the ESS-1, because it measures a broad spectrum of anti-immigrant attitudes and it is one of the few large-scale cross-national surveys that include a measure for intergroup contact. The ESS is carried out with hour-long face-to-face interviews focusing on topics such as immigration, citizenship and socio-political issues. Respondents were selected through strict random probability sampling and the survey was translated to fit each country’s native language through rigorous translation protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref046">46</xref>]. The following 22 countries participated in the ESS-1: Austria, Belgium, the Czech Republic, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom. In total, 42,359 respondents participated. Israel was excluded from the analysis due to the unique nature of the immigration context in that country. Moreover, because we were primarily interested in the host population’s perspective on immigration, all non-citizens and respondents who stated that they were part of an ethnic minority group were excluded from the analyses, leaving 32,748 respondents. We employed two weights that were delivered with the data; a population weight to take the size of each country into account and a design weight to correct for non-response bias.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Variables</title>
<p>On the country level, ethnic diversity within a country was added to the data. Ethnic diversity was operationalized with <italic>international migrant stock</italic> data derived from The World Bank, which is the number of inhabitants born in a country other than that in which they live (including refugees). We calculated percentages of international migrant stock to take into account what proportion this number bears to the population of the country. Since the ESS-1 dates from 2002, with some fieldwork already in 2001, the international migrant stock dates from the year 2000, which was just before the data for the ESS-1 was collected.</p>
<p>On the individual level, two individual-level independent variables were also included: <italic>Cross-group friendship</italic> was measured with the following item: “Do you have any friends who have come to live in [country] from another country?” (1 = <italic>no none at all</italic>, 2 = <italic>yes a few</italic>, 3 = <italic>yes several</italic>). Since we expected to find the largest decrease in anti-immigrant sentiments for respondents who had cross-group friendships as compared to no cross-group friendships it was converted into a dummy variable (0 = <italic>no immigrant friends</italic>, 1 = <italic>immigrant friends</italic>). <italic>Generalized trust</italic> was measured with the following three items on an eleven-point Likert scale; i.e. “Generally speaking, would you say that most people can be trusted, or that you can’t be too careful in dealing with people?” (0 = <italic>you can’t be too careful</italic>, 10 = <italic>most people can be trusted</italic>), “Do you think that most people would try to take advantage of you if they got the chance, or would they try to be fair?” (0 = <italic>most people would try to take advantage of me</italic>, 10 = <italic>most people would try to be fair</italic>), and “Would you say that most of the time people try to be helpful or that they are mostly looking out for themselves?” (0 = <italic>people mostly look out for themselves</italic>, 10 = <italic>people mostly try to be helpful</italic>). Analysis shows that the internal coherence of the scale is more than acceptable, α<sub>all countries</sub> = .77. Also, previous studies offer evidence for the measurement equivalence of generalized trust across European societies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref047">47</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref049">49</xref>].</p>
<p>Moreover, a wide range of demographic variables were included in ESS-1. The following variables were included to control for several potentially spurious effects. First, <italic>gender</italic> was included as a control variable, because women tend to have more tolerant attitudes toward immigrants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref050">50</xref>]. Second, <italic>age</italic> was calculated based on the respondent’s year of birth and was included because older respondents are generally more negatively biased toward immigrants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref050">50</xref>]. Third, <italic>years of education</italic> was measured with “How many years of full-time education have you completed?” for comparability between countries. Fourth, we included income satisfaction as a proxy for household income, because of the large number of missing answers on the question about actual household income. <italic>Income satisfaction</italic> was measured with “Which of these descriptions comes closest to how you feel about your household’s income nowadays?” on a 4-point scale (1 = <italic>finding it very difficult on present income</italic>, 4 <italic>= living comfortably on present income</italic>). Education and income satisfaction were included as control variables because people in more vulnerable positions in the social system (i.e. low income, low education level) are more likely to hold negative attitudes toward immigrants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref051">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref052">52</xref>]. Last, we controlled for religiosity, because in some cases it has been linked to negative intergroup attitudes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref017">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref053">53</xref>]. <italic>Religiosity</italic> was measured with “Apart from special occasions such as weddings and funerals, about how often do you attend religious services nowadays?” on a 7-point scale (1 = <italic>never</italic>, 2 = <italic>less often</italic>, 3 = <italic>only on special holy days</italic>, 4 = at least once a month, 5 = once a week, 6 = <italic>more than once a week</italic>, and 7 = <italic>every day</italic>).</p>
<p>The dependent variable <italic>anti-immigrant sentiments</italic> was measured with three items on eleven-point Likert scales, i.e. “Would you say it is generally bad or good for a [country]’s economy that people come to live here from other countries?” (0 = <italic>bad for the economy</italic>, 10 = <italic>good for the economy)</italic>, “Would you say that [country]’s cultural life is generally undermined or enriched by people coming to live here from other countries?” (0 = <italic>cultural life undermined</italic>, 10 = <italic>cultural life enriched)</italic>, and “Is [country] made a worse or a better place to live by people coming to live here from other countries?” (0 = <italic>worse place to live</italic>, 10 = <italic>better place to live)</italic>. Afterwards, the three statements were reverse coded in which higher scores reflected higher levels of anti-immigrant sentiments to aid interpretation of the results. This three-item scale is considered as a solid and one-dimensional measurement of anti-immigrant sentiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref005">5</xref>]. Principal component analyses were conducted for each country separately to examine whether these three statements formed an equally coherent scale for each country, α<sub>all countries</sub> = .80.</p>
<p>An overview of the range, means, and standard deviations of these variables is provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0177369.t001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0177369.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0177369.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Descriptive statistics of variables used in the analysis.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0177369.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0177369.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="justify"/>
<th align="center">Min.</th>
<th align="center">Max.</th>
<th align="center">Mean/proportion</th>
<th align="center">SD</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><italic>Country-level variable</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">International migrant stock</td>
<td align="center">2.14</td>
<td align="center">32.27</td>
<td align="center">8.93</td>
<td align="center">5.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify"><italic>Individual-level variables</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Anti-immigrant sentiments</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">4.87</td>
<td align="center">1.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Generalized trust</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">5.16</td>
<td align="center">2.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Cross-group friendship</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0.45</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Gender</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">0.53</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Age</td>
<td align="center">14</td>
<td align="center">110</td>
<td align="center">47.09</td>
<td align="center">18.28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Years of education</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">40</td>
<td align="center">11.80</td>
<td align="center">4.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Religiosity</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">7</td>
<td align="center">2.66</td>
<td align="center">1.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Income satisfaction</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">3.09</td>
<td align="center">0.81</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p><italic>Source</italic>: ESS-1; The World Bank.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Plan of analysis</title>
<p>The data was analyzed as follows. As a first step, mean levels of the main variables were examined per country, i.e. anti-immigrant sentiments, international migrant stock, cross-group friendships, and generalized trust. Next, these variables were analyzed by means of multilevel analysis to take into account the nested structure of the data and to control for possible confounding variables. Preceding the multilevel analysis, all variables (except for the dichotomous variables and the dependent variable) were grand mean centered. The multilevel models were organized into four stages. In Model 1, we ran an analysis using the demographic control variables (gender, age, years of education, religiosity, and income satisfaction) and international migrant stock to examine the relationship of ethnic diversity with anti-immigrant sentiments (H4). In Model 2, we added in cross-group friendship. In Model 3, we then added in generalized trust to examine its relation with anti-immigrant sentiments (H1). In addition, comparing Model 2 and 3 allows us to test how much of that relationship is accounted for by cross-group friendship, i.e. how much of the variance in anti-immigrant sentiments is uniquely explained by generalized trust (H2). In Model 4, we tested an individual-level interaction between generalized trust and cross-group friendship to examine whether the relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments is dependent upon cross-group friendship (H3). The results for the steps discussed in this plan of analysis are presented in the results section below.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>An overview of the country means for anti-immigrant sentiments is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0177369.g001">Fig 1</xref>. As can be observed, the level of anti-immigrant sentiments was lowest in the Scandinavian countries, and highest in Greece.</p>
<fig id="pone.0177369.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0177369.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Country means for anti-immigrant sentiments (10 = <italic>very high level of anti-immigrant sentiments</italic>).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0177369.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0177369.t002">Table 2</xref> illustrates the percentage of international migrant stock and the mean levels of cross-group friendships and generalized trust in a country. It appeared that the countries in which there were negative attitudes toward immigrants are not necessarily the countries that have the highest levels of ethnic diversity. It is noticeable, however, that citizens in countries with high levels of anti-immigrant sentiments also report less generalized trust and cross-group friendships. Individual-level correlations revealed a significant negative relationship between having cross-group friendships and anti-immigrant sentiments, <italic>r</italic> = -.27, <italic>p</italic> = &lt; .001. Moreover, there was a significant negative relationship between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments, <italic>r</italic> = -.32, <italic>p</italic> = &lt; .001. However, we noticed a very low correlation between generalized trust and having immigrant friends, <italic>r</italic> = .10, <italic>p</italic> = &lt; .001. This could suggest that even though both cross-group friendship and generalized trust are negatively related to anti-immigrant sentiments, they are not necessarily related to each other.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0177369.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0177369.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Percentage of international migrant stock, percentage of respondents having immigrant friends, and mean levels of generalized trust in 21 European societies.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0177369.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0177369.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Country</th>
<th align="center">Percentage of international migrant stock</th>
<th align="center">Percentage of people having immigrant friends</th>
<th align="center">Mean level of generalized trust</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">Poland</td>
<td align="center">2.14</td>
<td align="center">43</td>
<td align="center">3.79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Finland</td>
<td align="center">2.85</td>
<td align="center">41</td>
<td align="center">6.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Hungary</td>
<td align="center">2.91</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">4.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Italy</td>
<td align="center">3.73</td>
<td align="center">35</td>
<td align="center">4.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Spain</td>
<td align="center">4.35</td>
<td align="center">35</td>
<td align="center">4.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Czech Republic</td>
<td align="center">4.42</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">4.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Portugal</td>
<td align="center">6.17</td>
<td align="center">43</td>
<td align="center">4.32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Norway</td>
<td align="center">6.65</td>
<td align="center">54</td>
<td align="center">6.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Greece</td>
<td align="center">6.70</td>
<td align="center">29</td>
<td align="center">3.41</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Denmark</td>
<td align="center">6.95</td>
<td align="center">46</td>
<td align="center">6.85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">United Kingdom</td>
<td align="center">8.13</td>
<td align="center">43</td>
<td align="center">5.37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Belgium</td>
<td align="center">8.57</td>
<td align="center">44</td>
<td align="center">4.98</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Slovenia</td>
<td align="center">8.77</td>
<td align="center">52</td>
<td align="center">4.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Netherlands</td>
<td align="center">9.96</td>
<td align="center">41</td>
<td align="center">5.74</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Ireland</td>
<td align="center">10.11</td>
<td align="center">42</td>
<td align="center">5.80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">France</td>
<td align="center">10.31</td>
<td align="center">65</td>
<td align="center">4.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Sweden</td>
<td align="center">11.19</td>
<td align="center">67</td>
<td align="center">6.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Germany</td>
<td align="center">12.14</td>
<td align="center">46</td>
<td align="center">5.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Austria</td>
<td align="center">12.44</td>
<td align="center">50</td>
<td align="center">5.27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Switzerland</td>
<td align="center">21.75</td>
<td align="center">73</td>
<td align="center">5.79</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Luxembourg</td>
<td align="center">32.27</td>
<td align="center">74</td>
<td align="center">5.19</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p><italic>Note</italic>: The international migrant stock was derived from The World Bank, 2000.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Following preliminary analyses in SPSS 22, the xtmixed procedure in Stata 13 with full maximum likelihood estimation and robust standard errors was used to analyze the data. First, a null model (intercept-only model) with the dependent variable anti-immigrant sentiments was estimated. Based on the null model, the intraclass correlation (ICC) was calculated, which indicated that the percentage of variance at the country level indeed called for multilevel techniques of analysis; 11.34%. Substantively, this means that countries indeed differed with regard to anti-immigrant sentiments. Next, multilevel analyses were performed in four stages as was outlined in the plan of analysis. The results are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0177369.t003">Table 3</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0177369.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0177369.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Multilevel regression models of ethnic diversity, cross-group friendship, and generalized trust predicting anti-immigrant sentiments.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0177369.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0177369.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Model 1</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Model 2</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Model 3</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Model 4</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center">B</th>
<th align="center">Robust S.E.</th>
<th align="center">B</th>
<th align="center">Robust S.E.</th>
<th align="center">B</th>
<th align="center">Robust S.E.</th>
<th align="center">B</th>
<th align="center">Robust S.E.</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">International migrant stock</td>
<td align="center">-.040<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.011</td>
<td align="center">-.030<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">**</xref></td>
<td align="center">.012</td>
<td align="center">-.026<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn005">*</xref></td>
<td align="center">.013</td>
<td align="center">-.024</td>
<td align="center">.015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Cross-group friendship</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">-.640<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.038</td>
<td align="center">-.612<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.035</td>
<td align="center">-.602<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.033</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Generalized trust</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">-.227<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.012</td>
<td align="center">-.230<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.013</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Cross-group friendship <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn005">*</xref> generalized trust</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.007</td>
<td align="center">.015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Control variables</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Gender</td>
<td align="center">.029</td>
<td align="center">.040</td>
<td align="center">.011</td>
<td align="center">.037</td>
<td align="center">.030</td>
<td align="center">.032</td>
<td align="center">.032</td>
<td align="center">.032</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Age</td>
<td align="center">.001</td>
<td align="center">.001</td>
<td align="center">-.002</td>
<td align="center">.001</td>
<td align="center">-.001</td>
<td align="center">.001</td>
<td align="center">-.001</td>
<td align="center">.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Years of education</td>
<td align="center">-.116<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.010</td>
<td align="center">-.103<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.010</td>
<td align="center">-.093<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.009</td>
<td align="center">-.094<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.009</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Religion</td>
<td align="center">-.000</td>
<td align="center">.015</td>
<td align="center">-.003</td>
<td align="center">.014</td>
<td align="center">.012</td>
<td align="center">.013</td>
<td align="center">.012</td>
<td align="center">.013</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Income satisfaction</td>
<td align="center">-.259<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.023</td>
<td align="center">-.255<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.021</td>
<td align="center">-.177<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.022</td>
<td align="center">-.177<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.023</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Intercept</td>
<td align="center">4.878<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.119</td>
<td align="center">5.175<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.117</td>
<td align="center">5.154<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.109</td>
<td align="center">5.155<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">***</xref></td>
<td align="center">.109</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Variance components</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Variance country level</td>
<td align="center">0.275</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">0.257</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.213</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.222</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Variance individual level</td>
<td align="center">3.033</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">2.945</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">2.795</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">2.791</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Variance random slope</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.019</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Model fit</italic></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">R<sup>2</sup> country level</td>
<td align="center">.363</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.405</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.507</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.486</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">R<sup>2</sup> individual level</td>
<td align="center">.102</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.128</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.172</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center">.174</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p><italic>Note</italic>. Entries are the result of a multilevel regression analysis of the ESS 2002 dataset.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p>Sign.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn003"><p>*** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn004"><p>** <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn005"><p>* <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Model 1 revealed that international migrant stock significantly predicted a decrease in anti-immigrant sentiments, <italic>b</italic> = -.04, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. In more ethnically diverse countries there was less prejudice against immigrants. The same model was tested with inflow of foreigners derived from the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) instead of international migrant stock, with similar results, <italic>Z</italic><sub><italic>inflow</italic></sub> = -2.82, <italic>p</italic> = .005 and <italic>Z</italic><sub><italic>stock</italic></sub> = -3.54, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. This result in part supports H4 that ethnic diversity does not predict an increase in anti-immigrant sentiments. However, the evidence also goes one step further by showing that in fact ethnic diversity is <italic>negatively</italic> related to anti-immigrant sentiments. Hence, ethnic diversity does not lead people to ‘hunker down’ as anti-immigrant sentiments are clearly lower in more diverse societies. Self-evidently, this does not yet imply any causality as it is also likely that immigrants are more strongly attracted to societies with lower levels of anti-immigrant sentiments.</p>
<p>Model 2 demonstrated that cross-group friendship significantly predicted a decrease in anti-immigrant sentiments, <italic>b</italic> = -.64, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001. Also, Model 3 revealed that generalized trust significantly predicted a decrease in anti-immigrant sentiments, <italic>b</italic> = -.23, <italic>p</italic> = &lt; .001. This is in line with H1 and shows that immigrants too are included in judgments of generalized trust. Moreover, it can be observed that including generalized trust in the analysis considerably strengthened the explained variance of the model. Indeed, all other variables kept their level of significance, indicating that generalized trust contributed to the theoretical strength of the analysis. The b-coefficient of cross-group friendship, too, remained almost identical, implying that generalized trust did not play a role in the attitudinal effect of cross-group friendships. Subsequently, Model 4 demonstrated that generalized trust was also not a moderator for the relation between cross-group friendship and anti-immigrant sentiments. Thus, support is found for H2 and H3: Cross-group friendships and generalized trust are not associated (H2), and the negative relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments is not dependent upon cross-group friendships (H3).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion and conclusion</title>
<p>The current study has several important findings. First, in line with expectations, results showed that both generalized trust and cross-group friendships were substantially negatively related to the occurrence of anti-immigrant sentiments. These findings are compatible with earlier research efforts showing that generalized trust has indeed a wide circle of trusted others in which immigrants are also included [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref016">16</xref>]. Trusting actors extend this positive worldview generally to members of society, including the ones that do not share the same ethnic or cultural characteristics. Second, we can clearly observe that generalized trust and cross-group friendship operated independently from another. So, it was not the case that more trusting respondents were more likely to form more cross-group friendships or that, vice versa, cross-group friendship leads to the development of generalized trust. While in some of the previous literature a positive relationship was found between intergroup contact and other forms of trust, such as outgroup trust [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref019">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref021">21</xref>], in the current research we did not find a similar relationship for generalized trust. Future research could help us explain the difference between outgroup trust and generalized trust in this regard. Third, the results confirm earlier research by showing that ethnic diversity does not lead to higher levels of anti-immigrant sentiments. In fact the opposite phenomenon is more likely to occur as there is much more diversity in countries with low levels of anti-immigrant sentiments.</p>
<p>A caveat to be noted here is that we only control for cross-sectional relations, so it is quite well possible that either immigrants are more strongly attracted to countries with lower levels of anti-immigrant sentiments, or that other, for example, economic or cultural elements are related both to the attractiveness toward immigrants as to levels of anti-immigrant sentiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref054">54</xref>]. Moreover, the generalizability of the findings may be limited by the use of less recent data from 2002. Studies have suggested that anti-immigrant sentiments may fluctuate over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref055">55</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref057">57</xref>], which means that current levels of anti-immigrant sentiments may be different than was reported in this research. Similar changes or increases can be expected for levels of ethnic diversity. However, there is no indication that the <italic>nature</italic> of the examined relations between ethnic diversity, generalized trust, and cross-group friendships on the one hand, and anti-immigrant sentiments on the other hand, have changed over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref005">5</xref>]. Last, it is important to bear in mind that the current study used the proportion or inflow of inhabitants born in a country other than that in which they live (including refugees) as an operationalization of ethnic diversity, which is in line with much research. However, there are many other possible operationalizations of ethnic diversity. For instance, in future investigations, ethnic diversity could be considered more broadly and also examine religious diversity or linguistic diversity. Particularly linguistic diversity may impede the prejudice-reducing effects of intergroup contact but may leave the negative relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments intact. In addition, it might be worthwhile for future research to examine the role of <italic>change</italic> in ethnic diversity for anti-immigrant sentiments. A sudden increase in ethnic diversity may evoke perceptions of intergroup threat that drowns out the opportunity for intergroup contact [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0177369.ref022">22</xref>].</p>
<p>The main finding of the current analysis therefore is that the negative relationship between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments is not dependent upon cross-group friendships. In trying to understand the effects of generalized trust, there is at least one mechanism that we can already exclude. It is not the case that more trusting people have an easier time to develop cross-group friendships, and that as a result of these friendships, they develop more positive attitudes toward immigrants. If this was the case, both effects would not operate independently from another. Apparently, generalized trust has a much more direct relation with anti-immigrant sentiments. Individuals with high levels of trust also include immigrants in their broad, encompassing conception of the ‘others’ in society. Given the broad radius of the generalized trust concept, it indeed makes no sense to exclude a substantial part of the population of one’s society from a general expression of trust. This does imply that the relation between generalized trust and anti-immigrant sentiments to some degree might even be tautological, as they can be interpreted as two opposite formulations of the same concept. While generalized trust expresses the idea that all members of society should be included, anti-immigrant sentiments explicitly starts from the assumption that at least a substantial part of the population should not belong to society as a whole. The strength of generalized trust apparently is a form of generalization, beyond the confines of actual experiences with immigrants, and in this case the generalization ran in exactly the opposite direction as the generalization that is also present in anti-immigrant sentiments. Both trusting and non-trusting people are equally likely to be confronted with some of the more negative consequences of increased diversity, such as increased competition in the labor market. A difference, however, might be that while those less trusting generalize these kind of experiences into a general negative attitude, those with higher generalized trust levels–even with exactly the same experiences–do not embark on this kind of generalization.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Citrin</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sides</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Immigration and the imagined community in Europe and the United States</article-title>. <source>Polit Stud</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname> <given-names>EGT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staerklé</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Migration and multiculturalism</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Huddy</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sears</surname> <given-names>DO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Oxford handbook of political psychology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>. p. <fpage>852</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nussbaum</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <source>The new religious intolerance: Overcoming the politics of fear in an anxious age</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Anti-immigrant attitudes in Europe: Outgroup size and perceived ethnic threat</article-title>. <source>Eur Sociol Rev</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semyonov</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raijman</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gorodzeisky</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The rise of anti-foreigner sentiment in European societies, 1988–2000</article-title>. <source>Am Sociol Rev</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zick</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Küpper</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hövermann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <source>Intolerance, prejudice and discrimination: A European Report</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Friedrich-Ebert Foundation</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zick</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pettigrew</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ethnic prejudice and discrimination in Europe</article-title>. <source>J Soc Issues</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Putnam</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <article-title>E pluribus unum: Diversity and community in the twenty-first century. The 2006 Johan Skytte prize lecture</article-title>. <source>Scan Polit Stud</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allport</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name>. <source>The nature of prejudice</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Perseus Books</publisher-name>; <year>1954</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettigrew</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intergroup contact theory</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Psychol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.psych.49.1.65" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.psych.49.1.65</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012467</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewstone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>An integrative theory of intergroup contact</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Soc Psychol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Putnam</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <source>Bowling alone: The collapse and revival of American community</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Simon &amp; Schuster</publisher-name>; <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sztompka</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <source>Trust</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1999</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uslaner</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>. <source>Segregation and mistrust: Diversity, isolation, and social cohesion</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.; <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freitag</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Traunmüller</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spheres of trust: An empirical analysis of the foundations of particularised and generalised trust</article-title>. <source>Eur J Polit Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>782</fpage>–<lpage>803</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeskens</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>But who are those “most people” that can be trusted? Evaluating the radius of trust across 29 European societies</article-title>. <source>Soc Indic Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekici</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yucel</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>What determines religious and racial prejudice in Europe? The effects of religiosity and trust</article-title>. <source>Soc Indic Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Negative experiences and trust: A causal analysis of the effects of victimization on generalized trust</article-title>. <source>Eur Sociol Rev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenworthy</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voci</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramiah</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tausch</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewstone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Building trust in a postconflict society: An integrative model of cross-group friendship and intergroup emotions</article-title>. <source>J Conflict Resolut</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1041</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al Ramiah</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewstone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Neighborhood ethnic diversity and trust: The role of intergroup contact and perceived threat</article-title>. <source>Psychol Sci</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797613508956" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/0956797613508956</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24434239</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewstone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kenworthy</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cairns</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intergroup trust in Northern Ireland</article-title>. <source>Personal Soc Psychol Bull</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewstone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Consequences of diversity for social cohesion and prejudice: The missing dimension of intergroup contact</article-title>. <source>J Soc Issues</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <source>Trust and trustworthiness</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Russell Sage Foundation</publisher-name>.; <year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardin</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <source>Trust</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uslaner</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>. <source>The moral foundations of trust</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bar-Tal</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>From intractable conflict through conflict resolution to reconciliation: Psychological analysis</article-title>. <source>Polit Psychol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadler</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shnabel</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intergroup reconciliation: Instrumental and socio-emotional processes and the needs-based model</article-title>. <source>Eur Rev Soc Psychol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Ingen</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bekkers</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Generalized trust through civic engagement? Evidence from five national panel studies</article-title>. <source>Polit Psychol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bekkers</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trust and volunteering: Selection or causation? Evidence from a 4 year panel study</article-title>. <source>Polit Behav</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glanville</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paxton</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Do social connections create trust? An examination using new longitudinal data</article-title>. <source>Soc Forces</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tropp</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The role of trust in intergroup contact: Its significance and implications for improving relations between groups</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tropp</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finchilescu</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tredoux</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Improving intergroup relations: Building on the legacy of Thomas F Pettigrew</source>. <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. p. <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tropp</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aron</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pettigrew</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cross-group friendships and intergroup attitudes: A meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source>Personal Soc Psychol Rev</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Laar</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidanius</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effects of ingroup and outgroup friendships on ethnic attitudes in college: A longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Gr Process Intergr Relations</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonofakou</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewstone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voci</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paolini</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tausch</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <chapter-title>The impact of direct and extended cross-group friendships on improving intergroup relations</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tropp</surname> <given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finchilescu</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tredoux</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Improving intergroup relations</source>. <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. p. <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettigrew</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>. <article-title>The advantages of multilevel approaches</article-title>. <source>J Soc Issues</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>615</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettigrew</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Looking to the future</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Dovidio</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewstone</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glick</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esses</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, editors. <source>The SAGE handbook of prejudice, stereotyping, and discrimination</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>. p. <fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmel</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <source>Gesamtausgabe 11 Soziologie: Untersuchungen über die Formen der Vergesellschaftung</source>. <publisher-loc>Frankfurt am Main</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Suhrkamp</publisher-name>; <year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname> <given-names>REN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname> <given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yonkoski</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lupton</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giancola</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Determinants and consequences of social trust</article-title>. <source>Sociol Inq</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuyama</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>. <source>Trust. The social virtues and the creation of prosperity</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delhey</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welzel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>How general is trust in “most people”? Solving the radius of trust problem</article-title>. <source>Am Sociol Rev</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>786</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hoorn</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Individualist–collectivist culture and trust radius: A multilevel approach</article-title>. <source>J Cross Cult Psychol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paxton</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glanville</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Is trust rigid or malleable? A laboratory experiment</article-title>. <source>Soc Psychol Q</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Meer</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tolsma</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ethnic diversity and its effects on social cohesion</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Sociol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christ</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lolliot</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swart</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stolle</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tausch</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Contextual effect of positive intergroup contact on outgroup prejudice</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3996</fpage>–<lpage>4000</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1320901111" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1320901111</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24591627</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooghe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Vroome</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>The perception of ethnic diversity and anti-immigrant sentiments: A multilevel analysis of local communities in Belgium</article-title>. <source>Ethn Racial Stud</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynn</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Developing quality standards for cross-national survey research: five approaches</article-title>. <source>Int J Soc Res Methodol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooghe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reeskens</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stolle</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trappers</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ethnic diversity and generalized trust in Europe: A cross-national multilevel study</article-title>. <source>Comp Polit Stud</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeskens</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hooghe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cross-cultural measurement equivalence of generalized trust. Evidence from the European Social Survey (2002 and 2004)</article-title>. <source>Soc Indic Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>515</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torpe</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lolle</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identifying social trust in cross-country analysis: Do we really measure the same?</article-title> <source>Soc Indic Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Rourke</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinnott</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The determinants of individual attitudes towards immigration</article-title>. <source>Eur J Polit Econ</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>838</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvacho</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zick</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haye</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>González Gutierrez</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manzi</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kocik</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>On the relation between social class and prejudice: The roles of education, income, and ideological attitudes</article-title>. <source>Eur J Soc Psychol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zick</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The relation of formal education to prejudice: Its reliability, validity and explanation</article-title>. <source>Eur J Soc Psychol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheepers</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gijsberts</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coenders</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ethnic exclusionism in European countries: Public opposition to civil rights for legal migrants as a response to perceived ethnic threat</article-title>. <source>Eur Sociol Rev</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooghe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trappers</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meuleman</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reeskens</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Migration to European countries: A structural explanation of patterns, 1980–2004</article-title>. <source>Int Migr Rev</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>476</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meuleman</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidov</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Billiet</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Changing attitudes toward immigration in Europe, 2002–2007: A dynamic group conflict theory approach</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>352</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19827179</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coenders</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheepers</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Support for ethnic discrimination in the Netherlands 1979–1993: Effects of period, cohort, and individual characteristics</article-title>. <source>Eur Sociol Rev</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0177369.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coenders</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheepers</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Changes in resistance to the social integration of foreigners in Germany 1980–2000: Individual and contextual determinants</article-title>. <source>J Ethn Migr Stud</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>