<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-06076</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Heredity</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Genotypes</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Human genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Clinical genetics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genetic counseling</subject>
              <subject>Genetic testing</subject>
              <subject>Personalized medicine</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Epidemiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Genetic epidemiology</subject>
              <subject>Pharmacoepidemiology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Non-clinical medicine</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Health care policy</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Ethnic differences</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cultural anthropology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Ethnic groups</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Sociology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Demography</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Ethnic groups</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject>
          <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology</subject>
          <subject>Non-Clinical Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic Background of Patients from a University Medical Center in Manhattan: Implications for Personalized Medicine</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Genetic Diversity Background in Patients</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Tayo</surname>
            <given-names>Bamidele O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Teil</surname>
            <given-names>Marie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Tong</surname>
            <given-names>Liping</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Qin</surname>
            <given-names>Huaizhen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Khitrov</surname>
            <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Weijia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Quinbin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gottesman</surname>
            <given-names>Omri</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaofeng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pereira</surname>
            <given-names>Alexandre C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cooper</surname>
            <given-names>Richard S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bottinger</surname>
            <given-names>Erwin P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Preventive Medicine and Epidemiology, Loyola University Chicago Stritch School of Medicine, Maywood, Illinois, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Charles R. Bronfman Institute for Personalized Medicine, Mount Sinai School of Medicine, New York, New York, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Biostatistics and Epidemiology, Case Western University, Cleveland, Ohio, United States of America</addr-line>       </aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>University of Sao Paulo Medical School, Sao Paulo, Brazil</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Toland</surname>
            <given-names>Amanda Ewart</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Ohio State University Medical Center, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">btayo@lumc.edu</email> (BOT); <email xlink:type="simple">erwin.bottinger@mssm.edu</email> (EPB)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: EPB RSC. Performed the experiments: GK WZ QS MT. Analyzed the data: BOT LT HQ WZ XZ OG RSC EPB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: BOT XZ. Wrote the paper: BOT RSC EPB. Provided Brazilian population genetic data set: ACP.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e19166</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tayo et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>The rapid progress currently being made in genomic science has created interest in potential clinical applications; however, formal translational research has been limited thus far. Studies of population genetics have demonstrated substantial variation in allele frequencies and haplotype structure at loci of medical relevance and the genetic background of patient cohorts may often be complex.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods and Findings</title>
          <p>To describe the heterogeneity in an unselected clinical sample we used the Affymetrix 6.0 gene array chip to genotype self-identified European Americans (N = 326), African Americans (N = 324) and Hispanics (N = 327) from the medical practice of Mount Sinai Medical Center in Manhattan, NY. Additional data from US minority groups and Brazil were used for external comparison. Substantial variation in ancestral origin was observed for both African Americans and Hispanics; data from the latter group overlapped with both Mexican Americans and Brazilians in the external data sets. A pooled analysis of the African Americans and Hispanics from NY demonstrated a broad continuum of ancestral origin making classification by race/ethnicity uninformative. Selected loci harboring variants associated with medical traits and drug response confirmed substantial within- and between-group heterogeneity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>As a consequence of these complementary levels of heterogeneity group labels offered no guidance at the individual level. These findings demonstrate the complexity involved in clinical translation of the results from genome-wide association studies and suggest that in the genomic era conventional racial/ethnic labels are of little value.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement> The Andrea and Charles Bronfman Philantropies (to EPB); NIH grant National Heart Lung and Blood Institute RO1 HL53353 (to RC). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>With the dramatic decline in the cost of sequencing and the availability of well annotated databases genomic research is moving rapidly toward the clinical arena <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Ashley1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Collins1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Hawken1">[3]</xref>. Risk loci have been identified for many common diseases and while they collectively explain a small proportion of the heritable risk modest effects have been noted for markers associated with conditions such as focal segemental glomerular sclerosis, hyperlipidemia, Crohn's disease, adult macular degeneration, type 2 diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis, schizophrenia and bipolar disorder, and coronary artery disease among others <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Musunuru1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Behar1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-McPherson1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Franke1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Chen1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Voight1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Samani1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Stahl1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Purcell1">[12]</xref>. Of more immediate clinical relevance has been the discovery of genetic variants which influence the action of pharmacologic agents <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Shurin1">[13]</xref>. Because these loci are unlikely to have been under selective pressure, variants altering drug metabolism have in some cases increased to reasonable frequency and can be associated with large effects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Urban1">[14]</xref>. As more geographic populations are studied with high density genotype arrays it is also becoming apparent that allele frequencies for the relevant markers can vary widely <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Behar1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Adeyemo1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Adeyemo2">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Hassanein1">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>These emerging data must be incorporated into a strategy that positions genomic medicine for a clinical role. Because virtually all risk loci have been identified via proxy markers, it cannot be assumed that the haplotypes that are being identified in the populations where the original findings are made will carry the causal mutations in other geographically separated groups. For example, a recent analysis of the three HapMap populations showed considerable heterogeneity of allele frequencies for loci associated with 26 common diseases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Adeyemo2">[16]</xref>. Likewise, the fat mass and obesity associated (<italic>FTO</italic>) locus, which has the strongest known association with obesity in Europeans, shows a complex and inconsistent pattern in African-origin populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Adeyemo1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Hassanein1">[17]</xref>. The generalizability of the current generation of published risk markers in all racial/ethnic groups cannot therefore be taken for granted.</p>
      <p>In the initial phase much of the interest in molecular studies of population differentiation was focused on large continental groupings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Price1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Rosenberg1">[20]</xref>. Fine-scale population structure has now been examined using dense genotype data in Europe and North America, and somewhat more limited data has become available from Latin America, Africa and Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Price1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Tian1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Tian2">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Wang1">[23]</xref>. Most of these studies have attempted to identify “source” populations and describe migration and other demographic patterns over a historical framework <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Tian1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Wang1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Tishkoff1">[24]</xref>. In a sense, therefore, this research has been “backward looking”, as formalized in the Human Diversity Project <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Li1">[25]</xref>. However migration and gene flow between populations that had historically been geographically distant has accelerated in the modern era and many large metropolitan areas are now exceedingly diverse. Considered as a “city region”, New York City had an estimated population of 20 million; in 2005 36% of the residents of New York City proper were foreign born, speaking 170–200 languages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-New1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Rosenwaike1">[27]</xref>. In this cosmopolitan setting the standard US racial/ethnic categories – ie, black, white, Hispanic, Asian – become particularly problematic.</p>
      <p>Mount Sinai Medical Center serves a diverse community in northern Manhattan with outpatient visits totaling 800,000/year. The Charles R. Bronfman Institute for Personalized Medicine at Mount Sinai has initiated a program of research aimed at translating the growing body of evidence on genetic susceptibility for chronic disease and drug responsiveness into clinical practice. As an initial step we collected dense genotype data on a sample of 977 outpatients served by our institution who self-identified into 3 major racial/ethnic groups. Genotype array analysis was used to assess patterns of gene flow between the groups and consistency and distribution of haplotypes at a series of loci known to predispose to common disease or influence the metabolism of drugs.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Ethics statement</title>
        <p>This research study was reviewed and approved by the ethics review board of the Program for the Protection of Human Subjects (PPHS) of Mount Sinai School of Medicine under project # HSD09-00030. The Mount Sinai Biobank Project (IRB # 07-0529 0001 02 ME) is an IRB-approved research protocol with IRB-approved informed consent forms. All study participants provided written informed consent.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Participant recruitment</title>
        <p>Study participants were recruited from the Biobank Program of the Institute of Personalized Medicine at Mount Sinai Medical Center. The primary sample consisted of 1030 self-identified African Americans, European Americans or Hispanics. The majority of the Hispanic participants were from the Caribbean, primarily the Dominican Republic and Puerto Rico. One subject from each group and one CEPH trio family were replicated for the purpose of quality control of genotype data. The project was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Boards of both Mount Sinai Medical Center and Loyola University Chicago Stritch School of Medicine.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Genotyping and quality assessment</title>
        <p>Genotyping was carried out on genomic DNA from 1030 subjects using the Affymetrix 6.0 gene chip. Genotyping was performed in batches and within each batch samples were randomized with respect to race/ethnicity, gender and diagnostic status. Selected samples from each race plus a CEPH trio sample were also replicated in each batch for the purpose of assessing batch effect on genotypes. Quality control procedures were performed with the Whole Genome Analysis software (Golden Helix) and PLINK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Purcell2">[28]</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/purcell/plink/" xlink:type="simple">http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/purcell/plink/</ext-link>). The chip analysis provided data on 909,600 SNPs of which 905,384 mapped to the dbSNP rsID. Of the 1030 samples, those that broadly failed genotyping (n = 36), had gender inconsistency (n = 5) or had missing genotype proportion &gt;0.05 (n = 7) were excluded. Similarly, 60,869 SNPs with missing genotype rate &gt;5% and 10,889 SNPs with MAF&lt;0.01 were excluded. Using the data on batch-replicated samples, mean genotype concordance rate between batches was estimated to be 99.65±0.08%. Investigation of batch effect on genotypes revealed 1,236 SNPs with substantial deviations associated with batch effect and these were dropped. In addition, SNPs found to have significantly differential missing rates (n = 217) between patients with specific diagnoses and those failing Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) test (<italic>p-value = 0.001</italic>) (n = 2,587) were also excluded. We estimated inbreeding coefficients and genome-wide identity-by-descent (IBD) sharing among pairs of samples using the software PLINK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Purcell2">[28]</xref>. Finally, one additional sample with an inbreeding coefficient greater than four standard deviations of the mean coefficient was dropped. There was no significant evidence of excess sharing of IBD proportion either due to sample contamination, duplication, or cryptic relatedness. The final quality-controlled cleaned dataset thus consisted of 977 unrelated adult subjects – 324 African Americans, 326 European Americans and 327 Hispanics with genome-wide information on 829,586 SNPs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Creation of marker sets for population structure analysis</title>
        <p>For population structure analysis the cleaned dataset was merged with datasets from the International HapMap Project <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Frazer1">[29]</xref> and prior studies conducted by the Department of Preventive Medicine at Loyola. The HapMap data consisted of samples of African ancestry in the southwest USA (ASW) (n = 71) and of Mexican ancestry in Los Angeles, California (MEX) (n = 71). Descriptions of the sample, genotyping and quality control of the genotype data have been provided elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Frazer1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-A1">[30]</xref>. The Loyola dataset consisted of a population-based Yoruba sample from Nigeria (YOR) (n = 334), African Americans from Maywood, IL (AMW) (n = 204), and Brazilians (BRZ) (n = 109). The YOR and AMW samples were recruited as controls in a study of genetics of hypertension <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Kang1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Cooper1">[32]</xref>. Data from appropriate Native American groups were not available. The genotype data were generated on Affymetrix 6.0 chip and details of the samples, genotyping and quality control procedures have been described elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Kang1">[31]</xref>. There were 1770 samples in the combined dataset with genotypes on 599,857 SNPs. The sample genotyping rate in the combined dataset was &gt;0.99 and the MAF of every SNP in each of the subpopulations was at least 0.01.</p>
        <p>Two different marker sets were created from the combined dataset for population structure analysis. These markers were chosen to ensure that the SNPs were not in strong linkage disequilibrium (LD) and to make the analysis computationally efficient. For the first marker set, we excluded SNPs with missing genotype rate &gt;0.1%, then used the software PLINK <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Purcell2">[28]</xref> to prune the remaining 238,533 SNPs using pairwise linkage disequilibrium <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> maximum threshold of 0.2 in 50 SNP widows, shifting and recalculating every 5 SNPs. The resulting subset of SNPs consisted of 100,133 SNPs distributed across the genome. The second marker set was created based on average genetic distance difference <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between African and European ancestral populations. Using the HapMap allele frequencies, data for samples of Yoruba in Ibadan, Nigeria (YRI) and CEPH (Utah residents with ancestry from northern and western Europe) (CEU), <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was computed as the sum of the absolute differences between the allele frequencies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Atzmon1">[33]</xref> in the two samples. SNPs with <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> were then excluded from the combined dataset and the remaining 67,124 SNPs were pruned using <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> maximum threshold of 0.2 in 50 SNP widows, shifting and recalculating every 5 SNPs. The resulting subset consisted of 28,783 SNPs spread across the genome. The two marker sets were subsequently used separately for population structure analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Principal component and multidimensional scaling analysis</title>
        <p>Principal component analysis was performed with the Whole Genome Analysis software (Golden Helix). The first two components had large eigenvalues compared to the remaining components. These two components were therefore extracted and used as covariates to adjust for stratification in the candidate gene association analysis in the samples of African Americans and Hispanic Americans as described below. Also, using the genome-wide identity-by-state (IBS) estimated with PLINK, we performed multidimensional scaling analysis on the matrix of IBS. Distributions of samples on the first to fourth dimensions were used to assess clustering and diversity within and between the groups.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Global and local ancestries</title>
        <p>To evaluate potential discrepancies between global and local population structures or ancestries in the samples we use the method of squared coefficients of canonical correlation <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as described by Qinet al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Qin1">[34]</xref>. Briefly, let <italic>N</italic> denote the sample size, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denote the <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> matrix consisting of the first <italic>K</italic> global principal components (PCs), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> denote the <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> matrix consisting of the first <italic>K</italic> local PCs in a local window. The coefficient of multiple-determination <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the linear regression of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> on <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The <italic>j<sup>th</sup></italic> largest squared coefficient of canonical correlation <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the <italic>j<sup>th</sup></italic> largest coefficient of determination between any linear combination of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> columns and any linear combination of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> columns. The local PCs were computed from the local 20 Mb-window defined on each autosome. Squared coefficient was computed as the square of the largest canonical correlation between the first 10 local PCs of each local 20 Mb-window and the first 10 global PCs in each population sample. For this evaluation, we restricted analysis to the three Biobank samples (ANY, ENY and HNY) and three external comparison samples (AMW, BRZ and HapMap CEU).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Structure analysis</title>
        <p>Structure analysis was performed separately for the two marker sets using the software STRUCTURE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Rosenberg2">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Falush1">[36]</xref>. STRUCTURE applies a Bayesian model-based clustering algorithm to assign subjects into pre-assumed <italic>K</italic> ancestral populations each of which is characterized by a set of allele frequencies at each SNP. Based on their allele frequency profiles for the loci and under the assumption that loci are at HWE and linkage equilibrium within each population (racial group), the subjects are then probabilistically assigned to populations, or jointly to two or more populations if their genotypes indicated recent gene flow. For each of the two marker sets, analysis was run under an assumed number of ancestral populations ranging from <italic>K</italic> = 2 to <italic>K</italic> = 7. Analysis parameters included admixture model, correlated allele frequencies among populations, estimation of separate alpha for each population, and burn-in period of 20,000 iterations followed by 10,000 Markov chain Monte Carlo replications. Graphical displays of results of population structure were produced using the program DISTRUCT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Rosenberg2">[35]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Linkage disequilibrium and haplotype analysis</title>
        <p>To compare LD structure and organization of haplotypes harboring published disease loci or loci that alter drug metabolism we carried out analyses of obesity-related (viz, fat mass and obesity associated (<italic>FTO</italic>) and melanocortin 4 receptor (<italic>MC4R</italic>)), and pharmacogenomic variants (viz, solute carrier organic anion transporter family, member 1B1 (<italic>SLCO1B1</italic>) and cytochrome P450, family 4, subfamily F, polypeptide 2 (<italic>CYP4F2</italic>)). This analysis was restricted to the Biobank sample. The software Haploview <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Barrett1">[37]</xref> was used to compute estimates of pair-wise LD by the standard D-prime method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Devlin1">[38]</xref> and haplotype blocks defined by the confidence interval <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Gabriel1">[39]</xref> using the standard parameter setting. All available SNPs in each gene were included in the analysis but comparisons between groups were restricted to haplotypes and LD blocks bearing or flanking the selected published disease or pharmacogenomic variants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2i">
        <title>Candidate gene association analysis for body mass index (BMI)</title>
        <p>We carried out single SNP test for association between BMI and SNPs in <italic>FTO</italic> and <italic>MC4R</italic> genes. For each racial group, BMI was log-transformed to approximate trait normality. The residuals controlling for age and sex were standardized and used in association analysis with the SNPs. Only an additive genetic model was tested. The association analysis for the African-American and Hispanic samples was adjusted for population structure by inclusion of principal components as covariates.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The primary study sample was drawn from the 7,266 consented adult patients enrolled in Mount Sinai Medical Center Biobank from September 2007 to December 2009. Although the institution serves a diverse community in northern Manhattan, sampling was limited to self-identified African American (ANY), European American (ENY) and Hispanic (HNY) participants. Characteristics of the 977 individuals included in these analyses are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0019166-t001">Table 1</xref>, including the frequencies of a set of common chronic conditions (asthma, CKD, diabetes and morbid obesity). All population structure analyses additionally included the ASW, MEX, YOR, AMW and BRZ samples (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Methods</xref>). The combined sample size including all population groups was 1770 and 2 separate pruned genotype marker sets with 100,133 and 28,732 SNPs were chosen, as described. Because the results from both marker sets were broadly similar, only results from the larger marker set are presented here.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0019166-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>Characteristics of subjects.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0019166-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">African Americans</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European Americans</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic Americans</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N (% females)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">324 (50.31)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">326 (41.10)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">327 (49.54)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">977 (46.98)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.69±13.77</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.55±14.39</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.11±13.72</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.79±14.20</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diagnosis (#without)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">217 (107)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88 (238)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">217 (110)</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">522 (455)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">320</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CKD</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Obesity</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">202</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Asthma</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p><italic>Mean ± SD</italic>.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Multidimensional scaling of identity by state pair-wise distances</title>
        <p>To assess the within- and between-group clustering and diversity we performed multidimensional scaling analysis on the matrix of estimated IBS pair-wise distances and extracted the first four dimensions. Plots of the samples in the 1<sup>st</sup> vs. 2<sup>nd</sup>, 2<sup>nd</sup> vs. 3<sup>rd</sup>, and 3<sup>rd</sup> vs. 4<sup>th</sup> dimensions are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g001">Figure 1</xref>; the upper panel describes all available population samples, including those from Nigeria and Brazil, while the lower panel is restricted to the 3 groups of patients from New York. Based on the 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> dimension, the YOR sample formed a distinct non-overlapping cluster separated from all other samples, while the ENY sample also formed a small cluster. However, as best seen with extraction of the 2<sup>nd</sup> dimension (middle panel, upper row), the groups designated as MEX, BRZ and HNY showed much greater dispersion, while partially overlapping with the ANY and ENY samples. This pattern is clearly consistent with recent gene flow from geographically distant populations among the Latin American groups. As anticipated, the three Biobank samples (ANY, ENY and HNY) tended to cluster with samples from similar reference population groups (i.e., ANY with AMW and ASW; and HYN with both the BRZ and MEX samples). When restricted to the Biobank samples, the HNY sample can be observed to cluster between the ANY and ENY samples and exhibited high within-group diversity which resulted in the observed dispersion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019166-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Multidimensional scaling plots for all samples (TOP) and only biobank samples (BOTTOM).</title>
            <p>Plots of subjects in the 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> dimensions (left column), 2<sup>nd</sup> and 3<sup>rd</sup> dimensions (middle column), and 3<sup>rd</sup> and 4<sup>th</sup> dimensions right column). Abbreviation for samples: African American biobank sample (ANY); European American biobank sample (ENY); Hispanic American biobank sample (HNY); African ancestry in Southwest USA (ASW); Mexican ancestry in Los Angeles, California (MEX); Yoruba from Nigeria (YOR); African American from Maywood, Illinois (AMW); Brazilians from Brazil (BRZ).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Global and local ancestry</title>
        <p>The squared canonical correlation coefficients for the evaluation of discrepancies between global and local ancestry for each of the Biobank samples and corresponding external comparison samples are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g002">Figure 2</xref>. In each sample, the squared coefficient is the largest canonical correlation between the first 10 local PCs of a 20 Mb-window and the first 10 global PCs. Criteria for choice of top 10 PCs and window size for local ancestry evaluation are as described in our previous study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Qin2">[40]</xref>. In each sample, we observed variation in the distributions of the squared canonical correlation coefficients from one autosome to the other, showing that ancestry or population structure is not uniform across the genome. It is expected that local genomic regions could be subject to varying forms of population structure as a result of natural selection, demographic history differences and local random fluctuations of admixture, among others <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Qin1">[34]</xref>. These differential distributions of local population structures are also, to some extent, evident between samples of similar ancestry and this could have been amplified by sampling variation or genotype batch effects associated with the genotype calling algorithms of different platforms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Chierici1">[41]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Hong1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Hong2">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Leek1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Miclaus1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Miclaus2">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Zhang1">[47]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019166-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Canonical correlation based on window-wide local PCs for biobank samples and selected external samples.</title>
            <p>Each circle represents the squared coefficient of the largest canonical correlation between the first 10 local PCs of a local 20 Mb-window and the first 10 global PCs. Abbreviation for samples: African American biobank sample (ANY); European American biobank sample (ENY); Hispanic American biobank sample (HNY); African American from Maywood, Illinois (AMW); CEPH (Utah residents with ancestry from northern and western Europe (CEU); Brazilians from Brazil (BRZ).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Population structure</title>
        <p>We carried out further analysis of population diversity using the software STRUCTURE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Both the YOR and ENY samples were assigned to separate populations. Evidence of recent gene flow was can be seen as shared colors that correspond to the proportions from each ancestral group. The ANY (and also AMW and ASW) sample exhibited a higher proportion of ancestry from Africa than from Europe. On the other hand, the HNY sample on average exhibited higher proportion of ancestry from Europe than from Africa. We likewise observed more within-population variation of individual ancestral proportions in the HNY sample. As <italic>K</italic> increased from 2, each sample with the exception of the YOR showed varied levels of admixture of the assumed ancestral populations. Closer inspection indicated that the admixture seen in ANY and HNY best supports the presence of 2 and 3 ancestral populations, respectively. In addition, evaluation of model estimates for the different values of <italic>K</italic> indicated a better fit for <italic>K</italic> = 2 and K = 3 for the ANY and HNY samples, respectively.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019166-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Population structure results for ancestral populations <italic>K</italic> = 2 to <italic>K</italic> = 6.</title>
            <p>Each subject is represented by a thin vertical line colored in proportion to their estimated ancestry within each cluster. The colors represent the proportion of inferred ancestry from each of the ancestral populations within each specific K value. Abbreviation for samples: African American biobank sample (ANY); European American biobank sample (ENY); Hispanic American biobank sample (HNY); African ancestry in Southwest USA (ASW); Mexican ancestry in Los Angeles, California (MEX) ; Yoruba from Nigeria (YOR); African American from Maywood, Illinois (AMW); Brazilians from Brazil (BRZ).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>While clear differences exist in terms of the proportion of continental ancestry between the Hispanics and African Americans in this sample, this result is in part an artifact of the use of group labels. In fact, ancestral heritage at the individual level among persons from these two groups is best represented as a continuum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019166-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Population structure results for <italic>K</italic> = 2 ancestral populations sorted by ancestry proportions for African American biobank sample (ANY) and Hispanic American biobank sample (HNY) (Top) and pooled sample of both ANY and HNY (Bottom).</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>LD structure and haplotypes harboring published disease variants</title>
        <p>To assess within–population group LD structure and the distributions of haplotypes harboring known disease variants, we selected published obesity and pharmacogenomic variants that were genotyped in our Biobank sample of African Americans, European Americans and Hispanic Americans. For obesity variants, we selected 7 <italic>FTO</italic> SNPs (rs1421085, rs1121980, rs8057044, rs8050136, rs9939609, rs9941349 and rs9930506) and 2 <italic>MC4R</italic> SNPs (rs17782313 and rs12970134). For pharmacogenomic variants, we selected rs4149056 and rs11045819 in the <italic>SLCO1B1</italic> gene and rs2108622 in the <italic>CYP4F2</italic> gene. The <italic>SLCO1B1</italic> variants affect response to 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A (statins) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Kivisto1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Link1">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Nishizato1">[50]</xref> and the CYP4F2 variant affects response to warfarin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Ashley1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-PerezAndreu1">[51]</xref>. We included all available SNP genotypes in these genes in the determination of the LD blocks and hyplotypes within each group. Here, we present results from same region across groups for the purpose of comparison.</p>
        <p>Results of the LD structure and distribution of haplotypes bearing <italic>FTO</italic> and <italic>MC4R</italic> variants are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g005">Figures 5a and 5b</xref>. Substantial differences were observed between groups in the number and length of LD blocks in the targeted regions. For instance, in the <italic>FTO</italic> region there were 5 LD blocks in the African American sample, 2 LD blocks in the European Americans, and 4 in the Hispanics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g005">Figure 5a</xref>). Similarly in the <italic>MC4R</italic> region, there were 6, 2 and 4 LD blocks in the African American, European American and Hispanic American samples, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g005">Figure 5b</xref>). The observed strength of LD within blocks varied widely between groups just as the number of haplotypes in every block also varied between the three groups. As a result of the variation in the number and length of the LD blocks, haplotypes bearing or flanking the susceptibility variants were clearly not always comparable.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019166-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>a:</bold> Linkage disequilibrium structure (Top) and organization of haplotypes harboring published obesity variants (rsIDs indicated with blue boxes) in <bold>FTO</bold> gene in biobank sample of African Americans (left column), European Americans (middle column), and Hispanic Americans (right column). <bold>b:</bold> Linkage disequilibrium structure (Top) and organization of haplotypes harboring published obesity variants (rsIDs indicated with blue boxes) in <bold>MC4R</bold> gene in biobank sample of African Americans (left column), European Americans (middle column), and Hispanic Americans (right column).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Similar discordance between LD structures and haplotype distributions was observed for the pharmacogenomic variants. In the <italic>SLCO1B1</italic> gene, there were 4, 1 and 5 LD blocks with widely different number of haplotypes in the African American, European American and Hispanic American samples, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g006">Figure 6a</xref>). It is important to note that the length of the single block in the European-American sample spanned the same region in which multiple blocks were found in the other two groups. As a consequence few SNPs tagging this haplotype would be observed in the African-American and Hispanic samples making it difficult to validate associations originally discovered in European Americans. Results for the <italic>CYP4F2</italic> variants are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g006">Figure 6b</xref>. Again, the racial groups differ from each other in terms of length of LD block and number of haplotypes.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019166-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>a:</bold> Linkage disequilibrium structure (Top) and organization of haplotypes harboring published pharmacogenomic variants (rsIDs indicated with blue boxes) in <bold>SLCO1B1</bold> gene in biobank sample of African Americans (left column), European Americans (middle column), and Hispanic Americans (right column). <bold>b:</bold> Linkage disequilibrium structure (Top) and organization of haplotypes harboring published pharmacogenomic variants (rsIDs indicated with blue boxes) in <bold>CYP4F2</bold> gene in biobank sample of African Americans (left column), European Americans (middle column), and Hispanic Americans (right column).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3e">
        <title>Candidate gene association</title>
        <p>As an illustrative example, results of comparative association analysis of the association between BMI and haplotypes tagged by published SNPs in the <italic>FTO</italic> and <italic>MC4R</italic> loci are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g007">Figure 7</xref>. Although these loci have provided the strongest signals for adioposity, the effect sizes are admittedly modest (≤∼1.3 for BMI&gt;30) and therefore large sample sizes are required to obtain stable results. Nonetheless, it is clear that among European Americans the association is consistent across this region, while highly variable for African Americans and Hispanics. The <italic>MC4R</italic> region includes fewer haplotypes and the underlying effect size is smaller than for <italic>FTO</italic>, and is therefore less informative. The pattern in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g007">Figure 7</xref>, however, suggests that the association with BMI is less well captured by the common haplotypes than for the other ethnic groups.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019166-g007" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g007</object-id>
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <title>BMI associations with published obesity variants in FTO (Top) and MC4R (Bottom) genes in the three biobank samples.</title>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019166.g007" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Genomic technology has rapidly transformed the character of biomedical research, however the translational impact of this new science for clinical medicine remains undefined. Some investigators have suggested that the current state of knowledge justifies sequencing individual patients' genomes and placing this information in the electronic medical record, although others hold that the current utility of genome sequence data is still far too limited, while the storage burden and interpretation are unsupportable, and this state of affairs is unlikely to change in the foreseeable future <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Collins1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Shurin1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Hamburg1">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Ormond1">[53]</xref>. Clearly more incremental steps will be required in order to adapt genomic science for clinical purposes and evaluate its contribution to patient outcomes. One of the most immediate challenges is the need to quantify and properly account for the genetic diversity present in clinical populations. Formal research studies have virtually always stratified on a conventional descriptor of population structure and diversity is subsequently assessed within and between groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Rosenberg1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Wang1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc2">[54]</xref>. While this approach has been useful in describing global patterns, others have argued that it narrowly “packages” our view of human variation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Weiss1">[55]</xref>. Even more problematic in the clinical arena, racial/ethnic labels can vary widely by geographic location and time (eg, Hispanic and Asian) and cosmopolitan cities now include many individuals whose genetic heritage is drawn from multiple continental origins.</p>
      <p>The analyses presented here attempt to capture the pattern of genetic diversity in patients seen at a major medical center in New York City. Consistent with previous studies of population genetics, broad ancestral clustering is apparent in the 3 patient groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Wang1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc2">[54]</xref>. At the same time, wide divergence is seen in the Hispanic samples. Using the traditional perspective that “packages” geographic populations, these sub-clusters roughly represent Mexican Americans, persons of Caribbean origin (who would overlap with Brazilians), and a third group that clusters with African Americans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc2">[54]</xref>. Conversely, if one dispenses with the conventional labels and relies solely on genotype the Hispanics in the NY sample can be appropriately merged with the African Americans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019166-g003">Figure 3</xref>). These data forcefully underscore the diminishing relevance of the descriptors currently used for the two principle minority groups in the US.</p>
      <p>A complementary layer of complexity is demonstrated by the illustrative examples based on genetic variants associated with common traits and drug response. As is well recognized, both the spectrum of allele frequencies for “causal” mutations and proxy haplotypes can vary widely across population groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Adeyemo1">[15]</xref>. As this phenomenon has become better appreciated, the relevance of “diagnosis by proxy” using race/ethnicity to predict genotype, has dissipated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Cooper2">[56]</xref>. Since the vast majority of current findings from GWAs are based on SNPs that tag the relevant haplotype, until the “causal mutation” is known for these findings it may not be possible to transfer this information from the original study population, virtually always of European ancestry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Adeyemo1">[15]</xref>. The relevance of cross-population haplotype diversity was perhaps most clearly demonstrated in the analyses that defined the causal mutation at the <italic>SORT1</italic> locus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Musunuru1">[4]</xref>. A variant at this locus confers the largest effect on LDL-cholesterol of any known common allele <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Musunuru1">[4]</xref>. While a broad haplotype carrying numerous SNPs was captured on GWAs in a European-origin sample, the apparent causal mutation was isolated to a smaller haplotype present in persons of African descent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Musunuru1">[4]</xref>. It must be assumed, therefore, that proxy haplotypes cannot be used for individual-level patient analyses.</p>
      <p>While the sample included in this study was restricted to a single hospital the inferences are generalizable to most urban centers in the US. The combination of rapid changes in migration away from Europe and the realization that very few genetic variants are sufficiently differentiated even between historically unrelated populations mean that clinical decisions about genotypic effects will require very detailed knowledge of the locus in question, and analyses of individual patients. In a sense, therefore, much of the research emphasizing continental origin and ancestry stands in contradiction to the clinical imperative and a shift away from a paradigm that is founded on racial/ethnic categories will be required. We would suggest that this shift in perspective will be one of many required before genomic science can be fully adapted to use in the clinical arena.</p>
      <p>This report has limitations which must be recognized. The racial/ethnic background of patient populations will, of course, vary widely across the US the specific composition observed in New York may not be observed. We did not have access to appropriate data on Native Americans that might have helped define genetic ancestry of migrants from Mexico or other parts of Central and South America. Recent analyses by Bryc <italic>et al</italic> demonstrate the heterogeneity with Hispanics sub-groups and our data are consistent with their results, albeit weighted toward persons from the Caribbean <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Wang1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019166-Bryc2">[54]</xref>. We also recognize that clinical testing must take place in approved laboratories and will be restricted to genotypes that have been widely validated as relevant for patient outcomes therefore data from GWAs must be filtered extensively before application in any group. This process of defining the functional variant will by itself de-emphasize the broad framework of race/ethnicity.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, based on a consecutive series of patients from an urban medical center in New York City we demonstrate that a spectrum of mixed ancestry is emerging in the largest US minority groups. While consistent with previous descriptive studies, when viewed from the clinical perspective this evidence invites a re-evaluation of the relevance of racial/ethnic labels. In combination with evidence of locus heterogeneity within and between populations, this picture of extensive gene flow lends credence to the argument that the transfer of historical population labels which reflect language and other social categories onto patient samples will in many cases be unwarranted.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank the participants from New York City, United States, for participating in the “Mount Sinai IPM Biobank Program” and the participants from Ibadan, Nigeria for their willing participation in the “Genetics of Hypertension in Blacks” project.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Ashley1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashley</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Clinical assessment incorporating a personal genome.</article-title>             <source>Lancet</source>             <volume>375</volume>             <fpage>1525</fpage>             <lpage>1535</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Collins1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Has the revolution arrived?</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>464</volume>             <fpage>674</fpage>             <lpage>675</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Hawken1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawken</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kustra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The utility and predictive value of combinations of low penetrance genes for screening and risk prediction of colorectal cancer.</article-title>             <source>Hum Genet</source>             <volume>128</volume>             <fpage>89</fpage>             <lpage>101</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Musunuru1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musunuru</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank-Kamenetsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahfeldt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>From noncoding variant to phenotype via SORT1 at the 1p13 cholesterol locus.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>466</volume>             <fpage>714</fpage>             <lpage>719</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Behar1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosset</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tzur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yudkovsky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>African ancestry allelic variation at the MYH9 gene contributes to increased susceptibility to non-diabetic end-stage kidney disease in Hispanic Americans.</article-title>             <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>1816</fpage>             <lpage>1827</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-McPherson1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pertsemlidis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavaslar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A common allele on chromosome 9 associated with coronary heart disease.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>316</volume>             <fpage>1488</fpage>             <lpage>1491</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Franke1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radford-Smith</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide meta-analysis increases to 71 the number of confirmed Crohn's disease susceptibility loci.</article-title>             <source>Nat Genet</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>1118</fpage>             <lpage>1125</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Chen1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stambolian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Branham</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Othman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Genetic variants near TIMP3 and high-density lipoprotein-associated loci influence susceptibility to age-related macular degeneration.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>7401</fpage>             <lpage>7406</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Voight1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voight</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinthorsdottir</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Twelve type 2 diabetes susceptibility loci identified through large-scale association analysis.</article-title>             <source>Nat Genet</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>579</fpage>             <lpage>589</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Samani1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samani</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hengstenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Genomewide association analysis of coronary artery disease.</article-title>             <source>N Engl J Med</source>             <volume>357</volume>             <fpage>443</fpage>             <lpage>453</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Stahl1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raychaudhuri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remmers</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eyre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide association study meta-analysis identifies seven new rheumatoid arthritis risk loci.</article-title>             <source>Nat Genet</source>             <volume>42</volume>             <fpage>508</fpage>             <lpage>514</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Purcell1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Donovan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Common polygenic variation contributes to risk of schizophrenia and bipolar disorder.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>460</volume>             <fpage>748</fpage>             <lpage>752</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Shurin1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shurin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nabel</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Pharmacogenomics–ready for prime time?</article-title>             <source>N Engl J Med</source>             <volume>358</volume>             <fpage>1061</fpage>             <lpage>1063</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Urban1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Race, ethnicity, ancestry, and pharmacogenetics.</article-title>             <source>Mt Sinai J Med</source>             <volume>77</volume>             <fpage>133</fpage>             <lpage>139</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Adeyemo1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adeyemo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shriner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doumatey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>FTO genetic variation and association with obesity in West Africans and African Americans.</article-title>             <source>Diabetes</source>             <volume>59</volume>             <fpage>1549</fpage>             <lpage>1554</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Adeyemo2">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adeyemo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotimi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Genetic variants associated with complex human diseases show wide variation across multiple populations.</article-title>             <source>Public Health Genomics</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>72</fpage>             <lpage>79</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Hassanein1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassanein</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akylbekova</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Fine mapping of the association with obesity at the FTO locus in African-derived populations.</article-title>             <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>2907</fpage>             <lpage>2916</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Bryc1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryc</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oksenberg</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide patterns of population structure and admixture in West Africans and African Americans.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>786</fpage>             <lpage>791</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Price1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascali</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Discerning the ancestry of European Americans in genetic association studies.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Genet</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e236</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Rosenberg1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cann</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Genetic structure of human populations.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>298</volume>             <fpage>2381</fpage>             <lpage>2385</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Tian1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosoy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ransom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belmont</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Analysis of East Asia genetic substructure using genome-wide SNP arrays.</article-title>             <source>PLoS One</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>e3862</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Tian2">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plenge</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ransom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villoslada</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Analysis and application of European genetic substructure using 300 K SNP information.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Genet</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e4</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Wang1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedoya</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Geographic patterns of genome admixture in Latin American Mestizos.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Genet</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e1000037</fpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Tishkoff1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tishkoff</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedlaender</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranciaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>The genetic structure and history of Africans and African Americans.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>324</volume>             <fpage>1035</fpage>             <lpage>1044</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Li1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Absher</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Southwick</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casto</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Worldwide human relationships inferred from genome-wide patterns of variation.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>319</volume>             <fpage>1100</fpage>             <lpage>1104</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-New1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <collab xlink:type="simple">New York City: Department of City Planning</collab>             <year>2004</year>             <source>The Newest New Yorkers 2000: Immigrant New York in the New Millennium</source>             <publisher-loc>New York City</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Department of City Planning, Population Division</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Rosenwaike1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenwaike</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1972</year>             <source>Population History of New York City</source>             <publisher-loc>Syracuse, NY</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Syracuse University Press</publisher-name>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Purcell2">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Todd-Brown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>559</fpage>             <lpage>575</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Frazer1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballinger</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuve</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>A second generation human haplotype map of over 3.1 million SNPs.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>449</volume>             <fpage>851</fpage>             <lpage>861</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-A1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>A haplotype map of the human genome.</article-title>             <source>Nature</source>             <volume>437</volume>             <fpage>1299</fpage>             <lpage>1320</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Kang1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tayo</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lettre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Genome-wide association of anthropometric traits in African- and African-derived populations.</article-title>             <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>2725</fpage>             <lpage>2738</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Cooper1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotimi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ataman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osotimehin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <article-title>The prevalence of hypertension in seven populations of west African origin.</article-title>             <source>Am J Public Health</source>             <volume>87</volume>             <fpage>160</fpage>             <lpage>168</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Atzmon1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atzmon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe'er</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Abraham's children in the genome era: major Jewish diaspora populations comprise distinct genetic clusters with shared Middle Eastern Ancestry.</article-title>             <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>             <volume>86</volume>             <fpage>850</fpage>             <lpage>859</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Qin1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tayo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Interrogating local population structure for fine mapping in genome-wide association studies.</article-title>             <source>Bioinformatics</source>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Rosenberg2">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>distruct: a program for the graphical display of population structure.</article-title>             <source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>137</fpage>             <lpage>138</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Falush1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falush</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data: linked loci and correlated allele frequencies.</article-title>             <source>Genetics</source>             <volume>164</volume>             <fpage>1567</fpage>             <lpage>1587</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Barrett1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Haploview: analysis and visualization of LD and haplotype maps.</article-title>             <source>Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>21</volume>             <fpage>263</fpage>             <lpage>265</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Devlin1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Risch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>A comparison of linkage disequilibrium measures for fine-scale mapping.</article-title>             <source>Genomics</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>311</fpage>             <lpage>322</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Gabriel1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>The structure of haplotype blocks in the human genome.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>296</volume>             <fpage>2225</fpage>             <lpage>2229</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Qin2">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tayo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Interrogating local population structure for fine mapping in genome-wide association studies.</article-title>             <source>Bioinformatics</source>             <volume>26</volume>             <fpage>2961</fpage>             <lpage>2968</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Chierici1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chierici</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miclaus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furlanello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>An interactive effect of batch size and composition contributes to discordant results in GWAS with the CHIAMO genotyping algorithm.</article-title>             <source>Pharmacogenomics J</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>355</fpage>             <lpage>363</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Hong1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Assessing sources of inconsistencies in genotypes and their effects on genome-wide association studies with HapMap samples.</article-title>             <source>Pharmacogenomics J</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>364</fpage>             <lpage>374</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Hong2">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Evaluating variations of genotype calling: a potential source of spurious associations in genome-wide association studies.</article-title>             <source>J Genet</source>             <volume>89</volume>             <fpage>55</fpage>             <lpage>64</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Leek1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scharpf</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simcha</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Tackling the widespread and critical impact of batch effects in high-throughput data.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>733</fpage>             <lpage>739</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Miclaus1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miclaus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chierici</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Variability in GWAS analysis: the impact of genotype calling algorithm inconsistencies.</article-title>             <source>Pharmacogenomics J</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>324</fpage>             <lpage>335</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Miclaus2">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miclaus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfinger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chierici</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furlanello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Batch effects in the BRLMM genotype calling algorithm influence GWAS results for the Affymetrix 500 K array.</article-title>             <source>Pharmacogenomics J</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>336</fpage>             <lpage>346</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Zhang1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miclaus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chierici</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Assessment of variability in GWAS with CRLMM genotyping algorithm on WTCCC coronary artery disease.</article-title>             <source>Pharmacogenomics J</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>347</fpage>             <lpage>354</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Kivisto1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kivisto</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Influence of drug transporter polymorphisms on pravastatin pharmacokinetics in humans.</article-title>             <source>Pharm Res</source>             <volume>24</volume>             <fpage>239</fpage>             <lpage>247</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Link1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Link</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>SLCO1B1 variants and statin-induced myopathy–a genomewide study.</article-title>             <source>N Engl J Med</source>             <volume>359</volume>             <fpage>789</fpage>             <lpage>799</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Nishizato1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishizato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ieiri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawabata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Polymorphisms of OATP-C (SLC21A6) and OAT3 (SLC22A8) genes: consequences for pravastatin pharmacokinetics.</article-title>             <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>554</fpage>             <lpage>565</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-PerezAndreu1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Andreu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roldan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Barbera</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corral</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Pharmacogenetic relevance of CYP4F2 V433M polymorphism on acenocoumarol therapy.</article-title>             <source>Blood</source>             <volume>113</volume>             <fpage>4977</fpage>             <lpage>4979</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Hamburg1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamburg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>The path to personalized medicine.</article-title>             <source>N Engl J Med</source>             <volume>363</volume>             <fpage>301</fpage>             <lpage>304</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Ormond1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ormond</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudgins</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Challenges in the clinical application of whole-genome sequencing.</article-title>             <source>Lancet</source>             <volume>375</volume>             <fpage>1749</fpage>             <lpage>1751</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Bryc2">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryc</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karafet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno-Estrada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Colloquium paper: genome-wide patterns of population structure and admixture among Hispanic/Latino populations.</article-title>             <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <supplement>Suppl 2</supplement>             <fpage>8954</fpage>             <lpage>8961</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Weiss1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Does history matter?</article-title>             <source>Evolutionary Anthropology: Issues, News, and Reviews</source>             <volume>19</volume>             <fpage>92</fpage>             <lpage>97</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019166-Cooper2">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Race and genomics.</article-title>             <source>N Engl J Med</source>             <volume>348</volume>             <fpage>1166</fpage>             <lpage>1170</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>