<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149392</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-31297</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject><subj-group><subject>Childhood obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Obesity</subject><subj-group><subject>Childhood obesity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Body mass index</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Body mass index</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Families</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Metabolic disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Dyslipidemia</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Lipids</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age groups</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropometry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropometry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Lipids</subject><subj-group><subject>Lipid profiles</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Body Mass Index Is Better than Other Anthropometric Indices for Identifying Dyslipidemia in Chinese Children with Obesity</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">BMI and Children Dyslipidemia</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Yanna</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>Zixian</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Jing</surname>
<given-names>Jin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Jun</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Yajun</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Xiuhong</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>Wenhan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Li</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>Yu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Maternal and Child Health, School of Public Health, Global Health Institute, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Institute of Child and Adolescent Health, School of Public Health, Peking University, Peking, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>van Wouwe</surname>
<given-names>Jacobus</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>TNO, NETHERLANDS</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: YZ ZS YJ. Performed the experiments: YZ ZS XL YC WY. Analyzed the data: YZ ZS YJ JJ JM LG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JJ JM XL YC. Wrote the paper: YZ ZS YJ.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">jinyu@mail.sysu.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>10</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<elocation-id>e0149392</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>27</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>1</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Zhu et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149392"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Body mass index (BMI), waist circumference (WC), and waist-to-hip ratio (WHR) are used in screening and predicting obesity in adults. However, the best identifier of metabolic complications in children with obesity remains unclear. This study evaluated lipid profile distribution and investigated the best anthropometric parameter in association with lipid disorders in children with obesity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>A total of 2243 school children aged 7–17 years were enrolled in Guangzhou, China, in 2014. The anthropometric indices and lipid profiles were measured. Dyslipidemia was defined according to the US Guidelines for Cardiovascular Health and Risk Reduction in Children and Adolescents. The association between anthropometry (BMI, WC, and WHR) and lipid profile values was examined using chi-square analysis and discriminant function analysis. Information about demography, physical activity, and dietary intake was provided by the participant children and their parents.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Children aged 10–14 and 15–17 years old generally had higher triglyceride values but lower median concentration of total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol compared with children aged 7–9 years old (all <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). These lipid parameters fluctuated in children aged 10–14 years old. The combination of age groups, BMI, WC and WHR achieved 65.1% accuracy in determining dyslipidemic disorders. BMI correctly identified 77% of the total dyslipidemic disorders in obese children, which was higher than that by WHR (70.8%) (<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The distribution of lipid profiles in Chinese children differed between younger and older age groups, and the tendency of these lipid levels remarkably fluctuated during 10 to 14 years old. BMI had better practical utility in identifying dyslipidemia among school-aged children with obesity compared with other anthropometric measures.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China, Award Number 81302424 (Recipient: Yanna Zhu); Specialized Research Fund for the Doctoral Program of Higher Education of China, Award Number 20130171120056 (Recipient: Yanna Zhu); Special Research Grant for Non-profit Public Service of the Ministry of Health of China, Award Number 201202010 (Recipient: Jun Ma); The Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities in Sun Yat-sen University, Award Number 15ykpy09; (Recipient: Yanna Zhu); and Guangdong Provincial Natural Science Foundation, Award Number 2015A030313175 (Recipient: Yanna Zhu).</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="1"/>
<table-count count="4"/>
<page-count count="11"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>The anonymized, de-identified, minimal data set is within the Supporting Information file.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Childhood obesity is a serious public threat because of its various metabolic complications and related risks of cardiovascular diseases (CVDs), such as dyslipidemia, hypertension, and diabetes mellitus, which is already potentially present at an early age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref003">3</xref>]. Cardiovascular risk factors undergo a slow and sub-clinical evolution and usually include the prevalence of abnormalities in lipid metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref004">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref006">6</xref>]. For example, 3.9% to 9.4% of Chilean children aged 11.4 ± 0.97 years old exhibited a clinical form of dyslipidemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref007">7</xref>]. Likewise, approximately one in every five American youth had an adverse lipid concentration of total cholesterol (TC) or high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref008">8</xref>]. However, few studies have examined blood lipids levels in children stratified by age and gender in low- and middle-income countries such as China.</p>
<p>Many studies have suggested variations in the ability of body mass index (BMI), waist circumference (WC) and waist-to-hip ratio (WHR) in predicting cardiovascular risk factors in adults, which may differ with ethnicity and age groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref010">10</xref>]. Child overweight and obesity are often defined by BMI in both clinical practice and biomedical research instead of WC or WHR. Although BMI remains the most popular obesity measurement tool, its main limitation over WC and WHR is its inability to consider body fat distribution. Given the differences in growth status between children and adults, best anthropometry measure to identify adiposity in children remains unclear.</p>
<p>This study aimed to evaluate the distribution of serum lipid levels in Chinese children stratified by age and gender and to estimate the discriminative abilities of BMI, WC, and WHR in screening the risks of dyslipidemia in children with obesity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Material and Method</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Design and Study Subjects</title>
<p>The study was a series of cross-sectional health and nutrition surveys conducted by student constitution and local authorities to provide representative prevalence data of the health conditions of children in Guangzhou, China. The study population finally comprised 2243 children aged 7–17 years old who were randomly selected from elementary and middle schools in Guangzhou City in 2014. All children were asked to complete questionnaires, including information on physical activities and dietary intake, with parents completing the demographic information (birth weight, delivery mode, household income, etc.). Participants who refused to finish the questionnaires or did not have complete anthropometric and demographic data were excluded from this analysis (n = 157). Study protocols were approved by the Ethical Committee of the Peking University. All children and their parents voluntarily signed the informed consents.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Questionnaire Assessment</title>
<p>The self-reported questionnaires were created based on previously tested and validated questions, including questions of demographics, physical activities (vigorous-intensity activities, moderate-intensity activities, walking and sedentary behavior), and dietary intake (breakfast, sugary drinks, fruit, vegetable, and meat). The participant were asked the following five questions regarding physical activities: “How many days and how often per day did you go on vigorous-intensity activities (running, basketball, football, bodybuilding exercises, etc.), moderate-intensity activities (table tennis, moving something light, dancing, etc.) and walking in the last seven days?” The average outdoor duration per day in the last week was classified into four categories (&lt;1.0, 1–2, 2–4 and &gt;4 h/day). Children were also asked the following: “How many hours did you spend in sedentary behavior (sitting or lying still at school and home, not including sleeping) in the last seven days?” To determine their dietary intake of vegetable, meat, fruit and breakfast, children were asked the following: “How many days did you have breakfast last week and how many servings of each dietary intake did you have last week?” and “How many cups of sugary drinks did you have last week?” One serving of sugar-sweetened beverage was 250 mL.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Anthropometric Measurements</title>
<p>The anthropometric measurements, including height, weight, hip circumference (HC), WC and blood pressure, of all participants were measured by experienced technicians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref011">11</xref>]. Body weight was measured using a scale to the nearest 0.1 kg (Hengxing RGT-140, Jiangsu, PRC), and standing height was measured to the nearest 0.1 cm using a fixed stadiometer (Yilian TZG, Jiangsu, PRC). WC and HC were also measured to the nearest 0.1 cm. BMI and WHR were then calculated. The systolic and diastolic blood pressures of children were measured after 5 min in a seated position using a sphygmomanometer (Yutu XJ1ID, Shanghai, PRC).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Laboratory Analysis</title>
<p>Venous blood samples were collected from children following an overnight fast for 12 h. Serum was separated by centrifugation at 1500×g for 15 min at 4°C within 2 h and stored at −80°C until testing. Serum levels of triglycerides (TG), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C), TC and HDL-C were examined using commercial colorimetric kits (Biosino Biotechnology Company Ltd, Beijing, China) and an automated analyzer (Hitachi Co Ltd) in accordance with previous document [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref012">12</xref>]. The inter- and intra- assay coefficients of variation for all measured lipid parameters were less than 5%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Definition of Abnormal Lipid Levels and Obesity</title>
<p>The 2011 reference data on serum levels of lipids for children according to the US Guidelines for Cardiovascular Health and Risk Reduction in Children and Adolescents were used to estimate whether the lipid indicators of each child were at a normal stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref013">13</xref>]. However, TG was divided in two definitions based on age. Therefore, the highest borderline TG values for ages 0–9 and 10–19 year old (&gt; 99 and &gt; 129 mg/dL, respectively) were used in this assay in both sexes. In accordance with the guideline of the Working Group on Obesity in China, children with &lt;85th percentile BMI for age were considered as normal weight, those with ≥85th but &lt;95th percentile BMI were considered overweight, and those with ≥95th percentile BMI were considered obese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref014">14</xref>]. Subjects with ≥ 95th percentile of WC based on Chinese population percentiles were classified as having abdominal obesity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref015">15</xref>]. Male children with WHR of ≥ 0.90 and female children with WHR of ≥ 0.85 were classified as obese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref016">16</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 21.0. Statistically significant differences in median concentration of all serum lipids (TC, TG, HDL-C and LDL-C) stratified by gender and age groups were determined using Student’s <italic>t</italic>-test and analysis of variance (ANOVA). Discriminant function analysis was performed stepwise to test the ability of independent variables (BMI, WC, WHR, age groups, birth weight, physical activities, and dietary intake) in predicting dyslipidemia or non-dyslipidemia. Sensitivity and specificity were also calculated. The categorical variables (delivery mode, household income, and breakfast) were described in both genders by the proportion of participants falling into each category and were evaluated using Chi-square analysis. This type of analysis was also used to compare the proportion of obese children with each item of dyslipidemia in different anthropometric groups. A <italic>P</italic> value of &lt; 0.05 was considered significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Baseline Characteristics of Study Population</title>
<p>A total of 2243 children with age ranging from 7 to 17 years old were enrolled in this study. The characteristics of the study population, such as demography, lipid profiles, anthropometry, physical activities, and dietary intake, were summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0149392.t001">Table 1</xref>. In terms of lipid profile, boys had significantly lower median concentration of TC, TG, and LDL-C compared with girls (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Boys presented higher values of birth weight and anthropometry than girls (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), except for HC (<italic>P</italic> = 0.437). After comparing the duration of different intensity activities, only vigorous-intensity activities and walking behavior reached a statistical significance between two genders, with <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and <italic>P</italic> = 0.021, respectively. In addition, consumption of sugary drinks and meat was higher in boys than in girls (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Other factors in this study did not significantly differed between boys and girls.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0149392.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Descriptive Characteristics of Children Ranging from 7 to 17 Years Old in Guangzhou, 2014 (<italic>n</italic> = 2243).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0149392.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center"/>
<th align="center">Boys</th>
<th align="center">Girls</th>
<th align="center">Total</th>
<th align="center">P-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">*</xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="5"><bold>Demography</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Sample size (<italic>n</italic>), %</td>
<td align="center">1118 (49.8)</td>
<td align="center">1125 (50.2)</td>
<td align="center">2243 (100)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Age<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref> (years)</td>
<td align="center">10.95 (± 3.16)</td>
<td align="center">10.66 (± 3.05)</td>
<td align="center">10.80 (± 3.11)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Birth Weight<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref> (g)</td>
<td align="center">3308.7 (± 463.1)</td>
<td align="center">3203.0 (± 470.8)</td>
<td align="center">3254.7 (± 429.9)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Delivery Mode (<italic>n</italic>), %</td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="char" char=".">0.26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Natural Delivery</td>
<td align="center">519 (23.1)</td>
<td align="center">518 (23.1)</td>
<td align="center">1037 (46.2)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Cesarean Delivery</td>
<td align="center">437 (19.5)</td>
<td align="center">483 (21.5)</td>
<td align="center">920 (41.0)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Unknown</td>
<td align="center">162 (7.2)</td>
<td align="center">124 (5.5)</td>
<td align="center">286 (12.8)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Household Income (<italic>n</italic>), %</td>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="justify"/>
<td align="char" char=".">0.338</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">≤ 2000 CNY/month</td>
<td align="center">22 (0.98)</td>
<td align="center">17 (0.76)</td>
<td align="center">39 (1.74)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">~ 5000 CNY/month</td>
<td align="center">109 (4.86)</td>
<td align="center">118 (5.26)</td>
<td align="center">227 (10.12)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">~ 8000 CNY/month</td>
<td align="center">146 (6.52)</td>
<td align="center">171 (7.62)</td>
<td align="center">317 (14.14)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Unknown</td>
<td align="center">841 (37.49)</td>
<td align="center">819 (36.51)</td>
<td align="center">1660 (74.00)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="5"><bold>Anthropometry</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Height (cm)</td>
<td align="center">145.0 (133.0, 166.5)</td>
<td align="center">145.1 (131.7, 158.3)</td>
<td align="center">145.1 (132.5, 160.7)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Weight (kg)</td>
<td align="center">40.4 (28.4, 54.9)</td>
<td align="center">36.5 (26.2, 47.0)</td>
<td align="center">38.3 (27.3, 50.3)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Body Mass Index (BMI) (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td align="center">17.86 (15.57, 20.71)</td>
<td align="center">16.79 (14.79, 19.19)</td>
<td align="center">17.30 (15.17, 19.85)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Waist Circumference (WC) (cm)</td>
<td align="center">64.2 (71.8, 84.9)</td>
<td align="center">62.3 (56.0, 69.0)</td>
<td align="center">63.0 (56.0, 70.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Hip Circumference (HC)(cm)</td>
<td align="center">75.8 (65.1, 84.9)</td>
<td align="center">75.5 (65.0, 84.3)</td>
<td align="center">75.8 (65.0, 84.6)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.437</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Waist-Hip Ratio (WHR)</td>
<td align="center">0.86 (0.82, 0.90)</td>
<td align="center">0.84 (0.80, 0.88)</td>
<td align="center">0.81 (0.85, 0.89)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Systolic Blood Pressure (mmHg)</td>
<td align="center">99.00 (91.00, 105.00)</td>
<td align="center">94.00 (89.00, 100.00)</td>
<td align="center">97.00 (90.00, 101.50)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Diastolic Blood Pressure (mmHg)</td>
<td align="center">61.00 (59.00, 67.00)</td>
<td align="center">60.00 (57.00, 64.00)</td>
<td align="center">61.00 (58.00, 66.00)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="5"><bold>Lipid profile</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Total Cholesterol (TC) (mmol/L)</td>
<td align="center">4.14 (3.71, 4.68)</td>
<td align="center">4.26 (3.82, 4.76)</td>
<td align="center">4.20 (3.67, 4.71)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Triglyceride (TG) (mmol/L)</td>
<td align="center">0.76 (0.59, 0.98)</td>
<td align="center">0.80 (0.63, 0.80)</td>
<td align="center">0.78 (0.61, 1.03)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">HDL Cholesterol (mmol/L)</td>
<td align="center">1.35 (1.16, 1.56)</td>
<td align="center">1.38 (1.19, 1.59)</td>
<td align="center">1.36 (1.17, 1.57)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.132</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">LDL Cholesterol (mmol/L)</td>
<td align="center">2.24 (1.86, 2.69)</td>
<td align="center">2.31 (1.92, 2.77)</td>
<td align="center">2.28 (1.89, 2.75)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="5"><bold>Physical activities time spent, median</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Vigorous-Intensity Activities (minute/d)</td>
<td align="center">140.0 (60.0, 315.0)</td>
<td align="center">90.0 (20.0, 200.0)</td>
<td align="center">120.0 (40.0, 240.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Moderate-Intensity Activities (minute/d)</td>
<td align="center">120.0 (40.0, 240.0)</td>
<td align="center">100.0 (40.0, 210.0)</td>
<td align="center">105.0 (40.0, 210.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.206</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Walking (minute/d)</td>
<td align="center">210.0 (120.0, 420.0)</td>
<td align="center">210.0 (116.3, 420.0)</td>
<td align="center">210.0 (120.0, 420.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.021</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Sedentary Behavior Time Spent (hour/week)</td>
<td align="center">38.5 (14.0, 56.0)</td>
<td align="center">37.9 (14.0, 56.0)</td>
<td align="center">38.5 (14.0, 56.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.853</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="5"><bold>Dietary intake</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">Sugary Drink Consumption (mL/week)</td>
<td align="center">250.0 (0.0, 1000.0)</td>
<td align="center">250.0 (0.0, 750.0)</td>
<td align="center">250.0 (0.0, 750.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Breakfast Intake Every Day (<italic>n</italic>), %</td>
<td align="center">910 (40.57)</td>
<td align="center">958 (42.71)</td>
<td align="center">1868 (83.28)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.086</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Fruit (servings/week)</td>
<td align="center">7.0 (4.0, 12.0)</td>
<td align="center">7.0 (5.0, 12.0)</td>
<td align="center">7.0 (4.0, 12.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.181</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Vegetable (servings/week)</td>
<td align="center">14.0 (7.0, 14.0)</td>
<td align="center">14.0 (7.0, 14.0)</td>
<td align="center">14.0 (7.0, 14.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.662</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Meat (servings/week)</td>
<td align="center">7.0 (7.0, 14.0)</td>
<td align="center">7.0 (7.0, 14.0)</td>
<td align="center">7.0 (7.0, 14.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p><sup>a</sup>Mean (± standard deviation) presented</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p>Median (Interquartile range) presented unless otherwise stated. HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p>*<italic>P</italic>-value was calculated using chi-square test for categorical variable and two independent samples <italic>t-</italic>test for continuous variable between genders.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015">
<title>Distribution of Lipid Profile in Children Stratified by Sex and Age</title>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0149392.t002">Table 2</xref>, the distribution of serum lipids of the sample substantially varied and all indicators demonstrated markedly significant differences among ages based on ANOVA method (all <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). To further analyze the influence of age groups on lipid profiles, we divided ages into three groups: 7–9, 10–14 and 15–17 year old. We then found that compared with children aged 7–9 years old, the two older age groups tended to have lower median concentration of TC, HDL-C, and LDL-C and higher TG (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0149392.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Median Concentration (IQR) of the Lipid Profile among Children Aged 7–17 Years in This Study (<italic>n</italic> = 2243).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0149392.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center">Age(y)</th>
<th align="center">TG (mmol/L)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
<th align="center">TC (mmol/L)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
<th align="center">HDL-C (mmol/L)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
<th align="center">LDL-C (mmol/L)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center">7–</td>
<td align="center">0.69 (0.56, 0.85)</td>
<td align="center">4.33 (3.85, 4.76)</td>
<td align="center">1.43 (1.25, 1.66)</td>
<td align="center">2.33 (1.94, 2.80)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">8–</td>
<td align="center">0.72 (0.56, 0.89)</td>
<td align="center">4.29 (3.85, 4.87)</td>
<td align="center">1.45 (1.24, 1.67)</td>
<td align="center">2.33 (1.97, 2.80)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">9–</td>
<td align="center">0.74 (0.57, 0.96)</td>
<td align="center">4.44 (3.99, 4.95)</td>
<td align="center">1.42 (1.25, 1.61)</td>
<td align="center">2.51 (2.15, 2.93)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">10–</td>
<td align="center">0.81 (0.62, 1.10)</td>
<td align="center">4.43 (4.01, 4.98)</td>
<td align="center">1.42 (1.25, 1.62)</td>
<td align="center">2.49 (2.07, 3.00)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">11–</td>
<td align="center">0.77 (0.59, 1.03)</td>
<td align="center">4.02 (3.44, 4.70)</td>
<td align="center">1.39 (1.21, 1.55)</td>
<td align="center">2.12 (1.76, 2.94)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">12–</td>
<td align="center">0.96 (0.72, 1.24)</td>
<td align="center">4.05 (3.65, 4.55)</td>
<td align="center">1.30 (1.15, 1.50)</td>
<td align="center">2.10 (1.73, 2.43)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">13–</td>
<td align="center">0.79 (0.65, 1.05)</td>
<td align="center">4.00 (3.62, 4.44)</td>
<td align="center">1.27 (1.14, 1.49)</td>
<td align="center">2.12 (1.81, 2.46)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">14–</td>
<td align="center">0.82 (0.65, 0.95)</td>
<td align="center">3.81 (3.41, 4.23)</td>
<td align="center">1.18 (1.03, 1.38)</td>
<td align="center">2.10 (1.68, 2.41)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">15–</td>
<td align="center">0.85 (0.69, 1.13)</td>
<td align="center">4.02 (3.63, 4.53)</td>
<td align="center">1.27 (1.10, 1.46)</td>
<td align="center">2.20 (1.84, 2.59)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">16–</td>
<td align="center">0.87 (0.70, 1.10)</td>
<td align="center">4.02 (3.60, 4.42)</td>
<td align="center">1.24 (1.10, 1.45)</td>
<td align="center">2.15 (1.83, 2.56)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">17–</td>
<td align="center">0.89 (0.61, 1.05)</td>
<td align="center">3.94 (3.67, 4.60)</td>
<td align="center">1.34 (1.13, 1.49)</td>
<td align="center">2.07 (1.79, 2.66)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">7–9</td>
<td align="center">0.71 (0.57, 0.90)</td>
<td align="center">4.35 (3.90, 4.83)</td>
<td align="center">1.43 (1.25, 1.65)</td>
<td align="center">2.38 (1.99, 2.82)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">10–14</td>
<td align="center">0.84 (0.66, 1.13)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">4.13 (3.73, 4.66)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">1.33 (1.16, 1.53)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">2.23 (1.86, 2.67)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">15–17</td>
<td align="center">0.85 (0.69, 1.10)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">4.02 (3.61, 4.48)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004"><sup>c</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">1.26 (1.11, 1.46)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004"><sup>c</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn005"><sup>d</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">2.18 (1.81, 2.59)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004"><sup>c</sup></xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglyceride. Median (interquartile range) presented unless otherwise stated.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p><sup>a</sup> Significant levels by ANOVA among ages.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn003"><p><sup>b</sup> Significant levels by ANOVA among three age groups.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn004"><p><sup>c</sup> Significant differences between age groups using <italic>t</italic>-test analysis (7–9-year old group as reference category).</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn005"><p><sup>d</sup> Significant differences between age groups using <italic>t</italic>-test analysis (10–14-year old group as reference category).</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>We further explored each lipid profile item to evaluate whether the trends observed in the total lipid profile were generalized by sex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149392.g001">Fig 1</xref>). In children aged 10–14 years old, the TC, HDL-C, and LDL-C levels decreased with the increase in ages in both genders and declined to a valley at 14 years (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149392.g001">Fig 1B, 1C and 1D</xref>). The tendency of TG fluctuated intensively from 10 to 14 years old and reached a peak level at 12 years old (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149392.g001">Fig 1A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0149392.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Distribution of Lipid Profile in Boys and Girls Aged 7–17 Years Old (<italic>n</italic> = 2243).</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Variables to Predict Dyslipidemia in Children Determined by Discriminant Function Analysis</title>
<p>We involved different variables (BMI, WC, WHR, age group, birth weight, physical activities, and dietary intake) in the discriminant function analysis to analyze which variable contributed to predicting dyslipidemia. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0149392.t003">Table 3</xref> showed that a combination of four variables (BMI, WC, WHR, and age groups) was selected to correctly classify children into the dyslipidemia or non-dyslipidemia groups. The model with the BMI alone correctly classified 67.9% of the dyslipidemia better than the other three variables (WC, WHR, and age groups).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0149392.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Results of Discriminant Function Analysis for Classifying Dyslipidemia among Children (<italic>n</italic> = 2243).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0149392.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center">Variables</th>
<th align="center">Standardized Discriminant Function Coefficients</th>
<th align="center">Accuracy</th>
<th align="center">Sensitivity</th>
<th align="center">Specificity</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify">Age groups (y)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.445</td>
<td align="char" char=".">53.6%</td>
<td align="char" char=".">56.3%</td>
<td align="char" char=".">47.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.484</td>
<td align="char" char=".">67.9%</td>
<td align="char" char=".">85.0%</td>
<td align="char" char=".">28.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">WC (cm)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.396</td>
<td align="char" char=".">67.2%</td>
<td align="char" char=".">84.3%</td>
<td align="char" char=".">28.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify">WHR</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.397</td>
<td align="char" char=".">54.0%</td>
<td align="char" char=".">51.8%</td>
<td align="char" char=".">58.9%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>Formula: Z = 0.445 age groups (y) +0.484 BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>) + 0.396 WC (cm) +0.397 WHR</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p>BMI, body mass index; WHR, waist to hip ratio; WC, waist circumference.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Percentage of Dyslipidemia in Children with Obesity as Defined by BMI, WC and WHR</title>
<p>The proportion of children with dyslipidemia was shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0149392.t004">Table 4</xref>. Based on the established cut-off points, the proportion of high TG and LDL-C in obese children group defined by the combination of BMI, WC, and WHR was higher than those in other groups (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), whereas the combination of BMI and WC had the highest proportion of high TC and low HDL-C (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). After evaluating the number of dyslipidemic disorders, over 70.8% of obese subjects had at least one risk factor (high TG, high TC, high LDL-C, or low HDL-C). Among obese children, the percentage of having all four cardiovascular risk factors was between 3.6% and 8.9% by all six measures of obesity, with the highest proportion for those defined by the combination of BMI, WC, and WHR. In addition, the percentage for dyslipidemic disorders in children with obesity was higher as defined by BMI (77%) than that as defined by WHR (70.8%), with <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0149392.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Proportion of Lipid Disorders in Children Defined by BMI, WC, and WHR (<italic>n</italic> = 2243).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0149392.t004g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" rowspan="2"/>
<th align="center" colspan="6">Obesity (as defined by)</th>
<th align="center" rowspan="2">P-value <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn005"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">BMI (<italic>n</italic> = 177)</th>
<th align="center">WC (<italic>n</italic> = 431)</th>
<th align="center">WHR (<italic>n</italic> = 1154)</th>
<th align="center">BMI + WC (<italic>n</italic> = 171)</th>
<th align="center">WC + WHR (<italic>n</italic> = 360)</th>
<th align="justify">BMI + WC + WHR (<italic>n</italic> = 146)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="8"><bold>Dyslipidemia (<italic>n</italic>), %</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">High TG</td>
<td align="center">96 (54.2)</td>
<td align="center">197 (45.7)</td>
<td align="center">403 (34.9)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="center">95 (55.6)</td>
<td align="center">170 (47.2)</td>
<td align="center">84 (57.5)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">High TC</td>
<td align="center">97 (54.8)</td>
<td align="center">189 (43.9)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="center">525 (45.5)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="center">94 (55.0)</td>
<td align="center">161 (44.7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="center">78 (53.4)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Low HDL-C</td>
<td align="center">65 (36.7)</td>
<td align="center">154 (35.7)</td>
<td align="center">270 (23.4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="center">65 (38.0)</td>
<td align="center">123 (34.2)</td>
<td align="center">54 (37.0)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">High LDL-C</td>
<td align="center">57 (32.2)</td>
<td align="center">116 (26.9)</td>
<td align="center">299 (25.9)</td>
<td align="center">55 (32.2)</td>
<td align="center">106 (29.4)</td>
<td align="center">48 (32.9)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.163</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="justify" colspan="8"><bold>Number of dyslipidemic factors (<italic>n</italic>), %</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">1 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn004"><sup>#</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">138 (77%)</td>
<td align="center">326 (75.6%)</td>
<td align="center">817 (70.8%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="center">144 (84.2%)</td>
<td align="center">272 (75.6%)</td>
<td align="center">120 (82.2%)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">101 (57%)</td>
<td align="center">223 (51.7%)</td>
<td align="center">481 (41.7%) <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003">**</xref></td>
<td align="center">107 (62.6%)</td>
<td align="center">194 (53.9%)</td>
<td align="center">92 (63.0%)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.081</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">45 (25.4%)</td>
<td align="center">86 (20.0%)</td>
<td align="center">157 (13.6%)</td>
<td align="center">45 (26.3%)</td>
<td align="center">74 (20.6%)</td>
<td align="center">39 (26.7%)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">&lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">13 (7.3%)</td>
<td align="center">21 (4.9%)</td>
<td align="center">42 (3.6%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="center">13 (7.6%)</td>
<td align="center">20 (5.6%)</td>
<td align="center">13 (8.9%)</td>
<td align="char" char=".">0.016</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p>HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglyceride; BMI, body mass index; WHR, waist to hip ratio; WC, waist circumference.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p>* <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 level</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn003"><p>** <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 level</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn004"><p><sup>#</sup> The proportion of children with obesity who had at least one risk factor of dyslipidemia (high TG, high TC, high LDL-C, or low HDL-C).</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn005"><p><sup>a</sup> <italic>P</italic>-value was calculated using chi-square test for category variables. These tests were done to compare among all groups.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>With the rapidly increasing prevalence of obesity among children in recent years, a great interest has been given in exploring the relationship between bodily stoutness and blood lipids in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref002">2</xref>]. BMI, WC, and WHR were often used to define obesity. However, whether these anthropometric parameters can be used to identify obesity-related complications has not been thoroughly examined. The present study found that the distribution of serum lipid levels in younger groups (aged 7–9 years old) was significantly different from those in other two older age groups (10–14 and 15–17 year old) among Chinese children. Furthermore, the tendency of these lipid parameters remarkably fluctuated in children aged 10–14 years old. Four variables were selected (age groups, BMI, WC, and WHR) via stepwise discriminant procedure and produced 65.1% accuracy in dyslipidemia determination. BMI was better in predicting dyslipidemia in children with obesity compared with WC and WHR.</p>
<p>Yip <italic>et al</italic>. demonstrated that lipid levels, such as TC, LDL-C, HDL-C, and apo B, showed gender-related differences among 525 subjects in early school and adolescent ages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref017">17</xref>]. These results are consistent with the present finding that boys have significantly lower median concentration of TC, TG, and LDL-C than girls. In addition, we found that a sharp decrease in TC, HDL-C, and LDL-C, whereas the tendency of TG intensively fluctuated during 10–14 years. The fluctuation in TG in children aged 10–14 years may be attributed to their transitioning from pre-pubertal to pubertal status. Previous studies among school-aged children proposed that the significant reductions in the levels of lipid profiles were associated with the hormones produced during puberty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref019">19</xref>]. However, a retrospective analysis reported that no differences in lipids were found in 43 girls treated with gonadotropin-releasing hormone analog for at least 2 years compared with those untreated during 3-year follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref020">20</xref>]. Together with other research groups, we speculate that the girls had a relatively protective tendency when they entered the puberty years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref021">21</xref>]. The role of hormone on levels of lipid profiles during puberty may depend, to some extent, on the duration of observation and the study population. Thus, the relationship between lipids and hormonal levels needs to be further explored in a larger population-based longitudinal study, which can be useful in tracking changes in lipids during the maturation process.</p>
<p>As reported previously, children with overweight and obesity are more likely to experience dyslipidemia and related CVD risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref022">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref026">26</xref>]. A case-control study observed that children with obesity aged 7–10 years old defined by BMI had 2.17 times greater risks of high TC and hypertension than non-obese children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref023">23</xref>]. Another study reported that obesity, rather than being overweight, was more positively correlated with adverse alterations in the lipid profiles in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref025">25</xref>]. Some previous studies have showed that BMI, WC, and WHR were independent predictors of cardiovascular risk factors, such as in predicting dyslipidemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref027">27</xref>]. However, a recent study conducted in children and adolescents demonstrates that WC and WHR are practical measures of abdominal fat mass and are related to increased muscle or distribution of excess fat in the body [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref028">28</xref>]. Therefore, measures of adiposity need to be further examined to determine the ability of these measures to identify children at the risk of dyslipidemia. To elucidate this point, the present study confirmed that BMI, instead of WC or WHR, produced a better role in correctly classifying children into dyslipidemia or non-dyslipidemia groups by using stepwise disciminant analysis.</p>
<p>Furthermore, this study conducted among Chinese children showed that a combination of BMI, WC, and WHR yielded the highest proportion for those with one of the lipid disorders. Adiposity greatly contributed to adverse HDL-C and TG levels, which can be explained by visceral fat accumulation and excess liver exposure to fatty acids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref029">29</xref>]. Although more children were identified with at least one dyslipidemic risk factors using the combination of obesity indices (BMI, WC, and WHR) than BMI alone, no statistical significance was found between these two anthropometric groups. In additon, measures of central adiposity (WC and/or WHR) appeared to identify dyslipidemia in older individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref010">10</xref>]. In accordance with the previous study, WC and WHR were similarly performed after adjustment for age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149392.ref030">30</xref>]. The present study proposed that BMI may be a better and appropriate risk predictor of dyslipidemia in Chinese children than other anthropometric indices.</p>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Strengths and Limitations</title>
<p>This study had several strengths. First, a cluster of potential risk factors, such as birth weight, physical activities, and dietary intake, were considered when exploring the relationship between BMI and CVD. Second, this study involved a wide rang of ages from 7 to 17 years to observe the secular trend of lipid profile. We found that lipid levels tended to remarkably fluctuate in children aged 10–14 years old. Therefore, the participants were divided into three age groups to further explore the relationship between anthropometric parameters and lipid profile values. However, this study also had limitations. A cross-sectional design was applied in this study, which cannot infer the causality of the relationships observed. Moreover, we were unable to conclude on the role of pubertal timing on the variations in serum lipids in this age group, as pubertal stage was not assessed in this population</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec020" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>We found different distributions of serum lipid levels among three age groups (7–9, 10–14, and 15–17 years old) in Chinese children and found significant fluctuations among these lipid parameters in children aged 10–14 years old. This study proved that BMI can be used as a simple and non-invasive method in predicting dyslipidemia in Chinese school-aged children with obesity compared with other anthropometric indices.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec021">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0149392.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149392.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Dataset</label>
<caption>
<title>Dataset of Body Mass Index Is Better than Other Anthropometric Indices for Identifying Dyslipidemia in Chinese Children with Obesity.</title>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors would like to acknowledge the children, their families and all the team involved in the study (fellows students, nurses, and technicians).</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matikainen</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taskinen</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Management of dyslipidemias in the presence of the metabolic syndrome or type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Curr Cardiol Rep</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11886-012-0309-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11886-012-0309-3</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22941588</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Okbi</surname> <given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamed</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edris</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Protective effect of clove oil and eugenol microemulsions on fatty liver and dyslipidemia as components of metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Med Food</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>17</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>764</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/jmf.2013.0033" xlink:type="simple">10.1089/jmf.2013.0033</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24611461</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietz</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health consequences of obesity in youth: childhood predictors of adult disease</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>518</fpage>–<lpage>525</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12224658</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietz</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berenson</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Risk factors and adult body mass index among overweight children</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>123</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>750</fpage>–<lpage>757</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1542/peds.2008-1284" xlink:type="simple">10.1542/peds.2008-1284</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19254998</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The contribution of childhood obesity to adult carotid intimamedia thickness</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Obesity</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>32</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>756</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/sj.ijo.0803798" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/sj.ijo.0803798</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227845</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tracking of blood pressure from childhood to adulthood: a systematic review and meta-regression analysis</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>25</issue>): <fpage>3171</fpage>–<lpage>3180</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.730366" xlink:type="simple">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.730366</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18559702</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barja Yáñez</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnaiz Gómez</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villarroel Del Pino</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domínguez de Landa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo Valenzuela</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farías Jofré</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Dyslipidemia in school-age Chilean children: prevalence and associated factors</article-title>. <source>Nutr Hosp</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>2079</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3305/nh.2015.31.5.8672" xlink:type="simple">10.3305/nh.2015.31.5.8672</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25929377</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kit</surname> <given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuklina</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostchega</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogden</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prevalence of and trends in dyslipidemia and blood pressure among US children and adolescents, 1999–2012</article-title>. <source>JAMA Pediatr</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2014.3216" xlink:type="simple">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2014.3216</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25599372</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camhi</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchard</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenway</surname> <given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The relationship of waist circumference and BMI to visceral, subcutaneous, and total body fat: sex and race differences</article-title>. <source>Obesity</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/oby.2010.248" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/oby.2010.248</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20948514</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liaw</surname> <given-names>YP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Waist-to-hip ratio is a better anthropometric index than body mass index for predicting the risk of type 2 diabetes in Taiwanese population</article-title>. <source>Nutr Res</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nutres.2010.08.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.nutres.2010.08.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20934599</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Sluijs</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Associations between eating frequency, adiposity, diet, and activity in 9–10 year old healthy-weight and centrally obese children</article-title>. <source>Obesity</source>. <year>2012</year> <month>Jul</month>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1462</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/oby.2012.72" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/oby.2012.72</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22436840</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Anthocyanin supplementation improves HDL-associated paraoxonase 1 activity and enhances cholesterol efflux capacity in subjects with hypercholesterolemia</article-title>.<source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2014</year>, <month>Feb</month>; <volume>99</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1210/jc.2013-2845" xlink:type="simple">10.1210/jc.2013-2845</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24285687</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><article-title>Expert panel on integrated guidelines for cardiovascular health and risk reduction in children and adolescents: summary report</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>128</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>S213</fpage>–<lpage>S256</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab>Working Group on obesity in China (WGOC)</collab>. <article-title>Body mass index cut-offs for overweight and obesity in Chinese children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi</source>. <year>2004</year>, <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname> <given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yt</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>ZH</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Waist circumference distribution of Chinese school-age children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Biomed Environ Sci</source>. <year>2010</year> <month>Feb</month>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20486431</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><article-title>Joint Committee for Developing Chinese guidelines on Prevention and Treatment of Dyslipidemia in Adults</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Xin Xue Guan Bing Za Zhi</source> <year>2007</year>, <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17711682</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yip</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelken</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lepage</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brotea</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adeli</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pediatric referenc interval for lipids and apolipoproteins on the VITRO 5,1 FS Chemistry System</article-title>. <source>Clin Biochem</source>. <year>2006</year> <month>Oct</month>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>10</issue>)<fpage>978</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16962571</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mascarenhas</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Titski</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brito</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boguszewski</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variability of lipid and lipoprotein concentrations during puberty in Brazilian boys</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>28</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1515/jpem-2013-0450" xlink:type="simple">10.1515/jpem-2013-0450</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25153571</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierce</surname> <given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuh</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of lifetime body mass index in the association between age at puberty and adult lipids: findings from men and women in a British birth cohort</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.annepidem.2010.05.015" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.annepidem.2010.05.015</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20696407</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colmenares</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gunczler</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lanes</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Higher prevalence of obesity and overweight without an adverse metabolic profile in girls with central precociouspuberty compared to girls with early puberty, regardless of GnRH analogue treatment</article-title>. <source>Int J Pediatr Endocrinol</source>. <year>2014</year>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1687-9856-2014-5" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1687-9856-2014-5</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24742263</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Survey on the levels of lipids in school-aged children of Beijing, Tianjin, Hangzhou, Shanghai, Chongqing and Nanning cities</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1005</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23290840</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luciana</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sylvia</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sociodemographic, anthropometric and dietary determinants of dyslipidemia in preschoolers</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>462</fpage>–<lpage>469</lpage></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coronelli</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Moura</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hypercholesterolemia and its risk factors among school children</article-title>. <source>Rev Saude Publica</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12488917</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcantara Neto</surname> <given-names>OD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname> <given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Assis</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto E de</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Factors associated with dyslipidemia in children and adolescents enrolled in public schools of Salvador, Bahia</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Epidemiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22782099</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribas</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santana da Silva</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Anthropometric indices: predictors of dyslipidemia in children and adolescents from north of Brazil</article-title>. <source>Nutr Hosp</source>. <year>2012</year> <month>Jul-Aug</month>; <volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1228</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3305/nh.2012.27.4.5798" xlink:type="simple">10.3305/nh.2012.27.4.5798</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23165566</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dietz</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berenson</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The relation of overweight to cardiovascular risk factors among childrenb and adolescents: the Bogalusa Heart Study</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>.<year>1999</year>; <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>1175</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10353925</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname> <given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fallows</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of body mass index (BMI), body adiposity index (BAI), waist circumference (WC), waist-to-hip ratio (WHR) and waist- to-height ratio (WHtR) as predictors of cardiovascular disease risk factors in an adult population in Singapore</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>e0122985</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0122985" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0122985</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25880905</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgos</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burgos</surname> <given-names>LT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname> <given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prá</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Relationship between anthropometric measures and cardiovascular risk factors in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>. <year>2013</year> <month>Oct</month>; <volume>101</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5935/abc.20130169" xlink:type="simple">10.5935/abc.20130169</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23979777</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Despres</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemieux</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamarche</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prud'homme</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moorjani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brun</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The insulin resistance-dyslipidemic syndrome: contribution of visceral obesity and therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149392.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalton</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmet</surname> <given-names>PZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jolley</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunstan</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Waist circumference, waist-hip ratio and body mass index and their correlation with cardiovascular disease risk factors in Australian adults</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>254</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14641796</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>