<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-38550</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0058965</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Behavioral ecology</subject>
              <subject>Biogeography</subject>
              <subject>Conservation science</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal behavior</subject>
              <subject>Population genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Zoology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal behavior</subject>
              <subject>Mammalogy</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biological anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Malagarasi River Does Not Form an Absolute Barrier to Chimpanzee Movement in Western Tanzania</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Chimpanzee Movement in Tanzania</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Piel</surname>
            <given-names>Alex K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Stewart</surname>
            <given-names>Fiona A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pintea</surname>
            <given-names>Lilian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yingying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ramirez</surname>
            <given-names>Miguel A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Loy</surname>
            <given-names>Dorothy E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Crystal</surname>
            <given-names>Patricia A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Learn</surname>
            <given-names>Gerald H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Knapp</surname>
            <given-names>Leslie A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sharp</surname>
            <given-names>Paul M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hahn</surname>
            <given-names>Beatrice H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Anthropology, University of California San Diego, San Diego, California, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Division of Biological Anthropology, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>The Jane Goodall Institute, Arlington, Virginia, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Departments of Medicine and Microbiology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff5">
        <label>5</label>
        <addr-line>Institute of Evolutionary Biology and Centre for Immunity, Infection and Evolution, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gursky-Doyen</surname>
            <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Texas A&amp;M University, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">akp34@cam.ac.uk</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AKP FAS LP. Performed the experiments: AKP FAS YL MAR DEL PAC GHL BHH. Analyzed the data: AKP FAS LP YL MAR DEL PAC GHL LAK PMS BHH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AKP FAS LP YL MAR DEL PAC GHL BHH. Wrote the paper: AKP FAS LP PAC LAK PMS BHH.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <elocation-id>e58965</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Piel et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Malagarasi River has long been thought to be a barrier to chimpanzee movements in western Tanzania. This potential geographic boundary could affect chimpanzee ranging behavior, population connectivity and pathogen transmission, and thus has implications for conservation strategies and government policy. Indeed, based on mitochondrial DNA sequence comparisons it was recently argued that chimpanzees from communities to the north and to the south of the Malagarasi are surprisingly distantly related, suggesting that the river prevents gene flow. To investigate this, we conducted a survey along the Malagarasi River. We found a ford comprised of rocks that researchers could cross on foot. On a trail leading to this ford, we collected 13 fresh fecal samples containing chimpanzee DNA, two of which tested positive for SIVcpz. We also found chimpanzee feces within the riverbed. Taken together, this evidence suggests that the Malagarasi River is not an absolute barrier to chimpanzee movements and communities from the areas to the north and south should be considered a single population. These results have important consequences for our understanding of gene flow, disease dynamics and conservation management.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>The authors thank The Nature Conservancy, Frankfurt Zoological Society, and the Jane Goodall Institute for financial and logistical support during this work, and the National Institutes of Health (R01 AI50529, R01 AI58715), the ARCUS Foundation and the United States Fish &amp; Wildlife Great Apes Fund for financial support. AKP &amp; FAS are also grateful to CARTA (Center for Academic Research &amp; Training in Anthropogeny) at UCSD for continued support of the long-term research in Ugalla. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Large mammals are capable of long-range dispersal provided suitable, contiguous habitat exists <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Lehman1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-MorroghBernard1">[4]</xref> but the influence of large rivers, specifically, in preventing movement of individuals has been documented in several species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ayres1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Telfer1">[7]</xref>. Geographic barriers are suggested to play a key role in the formation of species by preventing gene flow, resulting in the accumulation of genetic differences and ultimately divergence of populations into separate species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Wu1">[8]</xref>. A similar process of disrupted gene flow due to such geographic barriers is suggested to influence population structure within species. Such processes have been documented in each of the great apes: orangutans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Arora1">[9]</xref>, gorillas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Anthony1">[10]</xref>, bonobos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Eriksson1">[11]</xref>, and chimpanzees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Gonder1">[12]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Across Africa, much of the suitable chimpanzee habitat has disappeared since the early 1990s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Junker1">[13]</xref>. The loss, degradation, and fragmentation of suitable habitats can have a similar effect to natural barriers, thereby reducing the potential for dispersal and movement of such large-bodied mammals. Thus, understanding current, as well as historical, patterns of gene flow between and within populations has important implications for chimpanzee conservation and will aid in determining specific areas to preserve population connectivity in increasingly human-utilized landscapes.</p>
      <p>Chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) are widely distributed across equatorial Africa, and the formation of four sub-species (<italic>P.t. verus, P.t. ellioti, P.t. troglodytes, P.t. schweinfurthii</italic>) is, in part, attributed to large river systems that historically (and currently) prevent gene flow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Gonder1">[12]</xref>. Chimpanzees have a fluid social structure where sub-groups of individuals fission and fuse flexibly in response to ecological (fruit availability and distribution) or social (estrus females) factors. They live in communities characterized by linear male dominance hierarchies and territorial defense, often showing lethal inter-group aggression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Watts1">[14]</xref>. Most females (50–90%) disperse from their natal group at sexual maturity to reproduce in another community <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Mitani1">[15]</xref>, and in eastern chimpanzees especially, male migration rarely, if ever, occurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Schubert1">[16]</xref>. Given this female dispersal bias, mtDNA has commonly been used to reconstruct population history, both on large <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Becquet1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Gonder2">[18]</xref> and small <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Shimada1">[19]</xref> scales. In Guinea (Conakry), for example, Shimada and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Shimada1">[19]</xref> used this technique to examine population connectivity between the increasingly isolated Bossou chimpanzees and those from the Nimba community, which live in contiguous habitat stretching into Cote d'Ivoire. The authors found very few shared mtDNA variants across the two sites, suggesting minimal gene flow. However, the variants identified within each area are scattered throughout the subspecies, suggesting any genetic separation between these areas is recent. Thus, mtDNA markers can reveal both current and historic connectivity between chimpanzee communities.</p>
      <p>The range of the eastern chimpanzee (<italic>P.t. schweinfurthii</italic>) spans the Democratic Republic of Congo north of the Congo River, Uganda, Rwanda, Burundi and Tanzania <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Gonder1">[12]</xref>. In Tanzania, surveys have estimated as many as 2800 individuals, 75% of which live outside of national parks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Moyer1">[20]</xref>. Most of Tanzania's chimpanzees (∼2600) inhabit the Greater Mahale Ecosystem (GME, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g001">Figure 1</xref>), with only 110 estimated to remain in the Greater Gombe Ecosystem (GGE) containing Gombe National Park in the north, and &lt;80 in Loasi in the south of the country. The combination of forest-clearing, especially for agriculture, threatens important chimpanzee habitat, and has nearly isolated Gombe chimpanzees specifically <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Pintea1">[21]</xref>. Despite these threats, the presence of small clusters of chimpanzee nests in fragmented forest patches suggests there may still be some movement within the GGE landscape between Gombe and the GME.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0058965-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Greater Gombe, Masito-Ugalla and Greater Mahale Ecosystem (outlined in red dots).</title>
          <p>The predicted distribution of suitable chimpanzee nesting habitat was developed using the Mahalanobis distance model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Pintea3">[50]</xref>, updated with 2007–2012 nest data and 2007 vegetation cover from Landsat TM satellite imagery (green). A red cross indicates the location of the crossing point over the Malagarasi River (blue).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The GME is a 20,000 km<sup>2</sup> area bordered by the Ugalla River to the east and the Malagarasi to the north, and includes Mahale Mountains National Park to the west (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g001">Figure 1</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Kano1">[22]</xref>. The extent to which these rivers prevent chimpanzee movement is debated. There have been previous efforts both by air (L. Pintea, unpublished data) and by water (H. Ogawa, unpublished data), to investigate the impact of the Malagarasi as a biogeographical boundary, but direct evidence concerning whether chimpanzees are able to cross the river is lacking.</p>
      <p>The Malagarasi River begins near the Burundian border, is 475 km long, and has the largest watershed of all the rivers flowing into Lake Tanganyika. In the Miocene, the lower Malagarasi was the headwater of the Congo River; today, Lake Tanganyka serves as a holding basin for the Malagarasi, before its waters meet the Lukuga River <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Michel1">[23]</xref> and eventually the Atlantic Ocean <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Beadle1">[24]</xref>. The upper Malagarasi, on the other hand, was historically part of the Nile drainage, flowing towards Lake Victoria until later tectonic activity reversed its direction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Michel1">[23]</xref>. The river is more than 100 m wide for long stretches and in some parts crocodile can be seen. Moreover, the river banks are bordered by extensive stretches of miombo woodland plateau – a topographical feature that savanna chimpanzees rarely use for feeding or nesting (unpublished data). Given that chimpanzees are not known to swim <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-McGrew1">[25]</xref>, the extent to which this river is a boundary to chimpanzee movement has important implications. For example, such a boundary could impact chimpanzee ranging behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Moore1">[26]</xref>, population connectivity, and pathogen transmission <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell2">[28]</xref>, and thus has implications for conservation strategies and government policy.</p>
      <p>North of the river, but outside of Gombe, there is minimal evidence of chimpanzee presence. In the Lilanshimba area <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa1">[29]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa2">[31]</xref>, just north of the river (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g002">Figure 2</xref>), Ogawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa2">[31]</xref> proposed that two chimpanzee communities, totaling 32–45 individuals, may have existed prior to the establishment of the Lugufu refugee settlement in the 1990s. Recent evidence suggests that some of these chimpanzees may have survived to the present day, despite more than 100,000 refugees from the Democratic Republic of Congo inhabiting this settlement for 15 years until 2009. If the Malagarasi River were to form an absolute barrier, chimpanzees remaining in Gombe (∼110) and those in Lilanshimba (∼45) would be isolated from the larger GME population and would likely not represent a viable sub-population. In fact, Inoue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref> have recently proposed that the Malagarasi River represents a barrier to chimpanzee gene flow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Kano2">[30]</xref>. After examining 138 fecal samples, they found no shared mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) haplotypes between chimpanzees from Gombe (6 samples), about 90 km to the north of the Malagarasi River, and those from the Greater Mahale area (including Masito-Ugalla) south of the river. In fact, chimpanzees from south of the river were more similar, in mtDNA sequences, to individuals from Loasi (Lwazi), about 200 km further south near the southern end of Lake Tanganyika, and the authors argued that chimpanzees had historically reached the Greater Mahale area from the south <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0058965-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Location of the Malagarasi River ford.</title>
          <p>The location of the crossing point (red cross) is shown in relation to forest (dark green), woodland (brown) and water (blue). The chimpanzee distribution model is shown in light green, with land cover classes extracted from 2007 Landsat TM satellite image and draped over a digital elevation map (shaded relief from 90-m SRTM - Shuttle Radar Topography Mission – data). Yellow triangles depict the location of chimpanzee fecal samples.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In the current study, we integrate three independent data sets to re-evaluate the extent to which the Malagarasi is a boundary to chimpanzee movements. We use (1) previously published and new genetic data from chimpanzee fecal samples, (2) SIVcpz distribution, and (3) observations of the river itself. Specifically, we report here the discovery of a ford in the Malagarasi River that is sufficiently shallow for chimpanzees to readily cross. Furthermore, we found chimpanzee feces on the approach to and in the vicinity of this ford. Here we describe this evidence and discuss the implications of such a crossing place for current and historical gene flow between Masito-Ugalla and Greater Gombe Ecosystems.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Ethics Statement</title>
        <p>Permission to survey and collect noninvasive fecal samples from wild chimpanzees was provided to AKP (No. 2011-247-NA) and FAS (No. 2011-248-NA) by the national institutions TAWIRI (Tanzanian Wildlife Research Institute) and COSTECH (Commission for Science and Technology), whilst District governments in both Kigoma and Mpanda authorized the project and specifically AKP and FAS to survey on General (District) Land. Additionally, we met all ethical and legal requirements established by the American Society of Primatologists (ASP) for work on wild primates.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Study sites and sample collection</title>
        <p>We established a camp 19 km south of the Malagarasi River (at −5.40, 30.20) on 29 July 2012, in the middle of the dry season, with a subsequent camp (6 km from the river, at −5.28, 30.22) established on 3 August 2012. Camps were basic, selected for their proximity to water, away from any human habitation, and with the goal of minimizing disturbance to chimpanzees.</p>
        <p>Research teams used a combination of QuickBird, SPOT and Landsat satellite imagery and predictive distribution models of potential chimpanzee nesting habitat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Pintea2">[33]</xref> to decide where to target daily reconnaissance walks, with the goal of investigating forest patches lining the river systems and miombo woodland slopes for the presence of chimpanzees. These vegetation types are known to be preferred for chimpanzee nesting from previous surveys and research <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-HernandezAguilar1">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Stewart1">[35]</xref>. We recorded data on all chimpanzee nests, vocalizations, and fecal samples encountered, including GPS coordinates and apparent age (nest age was recorded according to state of decay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Stewart1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Plumptre1">[36]</xref>, from age 1 to 4 as follows: (1) leaves green and nest structure intact; (2) some leaves brown, but nest structure intact; (3) nest rotting and structure disintegrating; and (4) only the frame and &lt;5% of leaves remaining. Fecal samples were aged as follows: from 1–3 with 1  =  fresh, within 12 hours, 2  =  recent, within 1–2 days, and 3  =  old, dried and &gt;2 days. Whenever possible recent signs of chimpanzees were tracked by following trails in order to maximize fresh fecal sample collection success. Only fresh fecal samples were collected, usually from beneath chimpanzee night nests, or from following chimpanzee trails, when encountered during reconnaissance walks. Fecal samples were collected on 7 August 2012, and were preserved in an equal volume of RNA<italic>later</italic> (Life Technologies) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Keele1">[37]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-VanHeuverswyn1">[39]</xref>. Tubes were labeled with a sample number and GPS coordinates. Because of a lack of refrigeration, at small satellite camp locations, samples were kept at ambient temperature for up to one week before longer term storage at base-camps at 4°C in a DC refrigerator (Model number ARB, 47L) powered by a portable power system (4 Lucas 75Ah sealed batteries, and 2 Yingli 60 W crystalline solar panels). Samples were stored at 4°C for several weeks, but in some instances several months, before they were shipped to the Hahn laboratory, University of Pennsylvania, and stored at −20°C.</p>
        <p>Individual identification. All fecal samples were subjected to mitochondrial DNA analysis to confirm their species origin. Briefly, a 498 bp fragment of the mitochondrial D-loop region was amplified from fecal DNA, sequenced directly (using one primer which yielded 446 bp of sequence) and grouped into different haplotypes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Santiago1">[38]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Liu1">[40]</xref>. The evolutionary relationships of these haplotypes to each other and to a reference set of other available Tanzanian chimpanzee D-loop sequences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref> from the database were then determined by phylogenetic analysis. A neighbor-joining tree <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Saitou1">[41]</xref> was constructed based on the region where all sequences overlapped using CLUSTALW version 2.11 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Larkin1">[42]</xref> with distances corrected for multiple substitutions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Kimura1">[43]</xref>. Bootstrap confidence values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Felsenstein1">[44]</xref> are based on 1000 replicates.</p>
        <p>To identify the number of sampled individuals, fecal samples were genotyped at eight autosomal microsatellite loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">[27]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Keele1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Keele2">[45]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Wroblewski1">[47]</xref> with amplification products sized on an automated sequencer (Applied Biosystems). Sex was determined by amplifying a 218 bp fragment of the sex-linked amelogenin gene that contains a 6 bp insertion in the Y, but not the X chromosome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Sullivan1">[48]</xref>.</p>
        <p>SIVcpz detection. All fecal samples were also screened for the presence of HIV-1 cross-reactive antibodies by enhanced chemiluminescent Western immunoblot analysis modified for RNA<italic>later</italic> preserved specimens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Keele1">[37]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-VanHeuverswyn1">[39]</xref>. Sample integrity was examined using an IgG control. Western blot positive samples were tested for the presence of SIV nucleic acids by reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) amplification using SIVcpz specific <italic>pol</italic> primers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Li1">[49]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Forty-two chimpanzee nests were observed on 7 August 2012. Among these, only one was Age1, six were Age2, twenty-nine were Age3, and six were Age4. Following evergreen forest patches and pristine chimpanzee habitat, we identified a well-used trail that led from a forested mountain area approximately 5 km south of the Malagarasi River directly to the river itself (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g002">Figure 2</xref>). On this trail, we identified sixteen fresh chimpanzee fecal samples, indicating the recent presence of chimpanzees in very close proximity to the southern bank of the Malagarasi River.</p>
      <p>To confirm the origin of these fecal samples, we extracted DNA from all 16 specimens and amplified the D loop region of the mtDNA genome. Direct amplicon sequencing identified three samples that comprised fecal mixtures, which were excluded from further analysis. The remaining 13 samples yielded three different mtDNA haplotypes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0058965-t001">Table 1</xref>), all of which clustered with other eastern chimpanzee (<italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic>) sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g003">Figure 3</xref>). All three of the sequences had previously been found in samples from chimpanzees in Mahale National Park (MH32, MH37 and MH40), including one haplotype that has also been identified in chimpanzees in Gombe National Park (GM7). Thus, we compared results from the current samples to all known published haplotypes of eastern chimpanzees, creating a comprehensive dataset that allowed us to make inferences on gene flow.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0058965-g003" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g003</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Mitochondrial genetic diversity in chimpanzees from Tanzania.</title>
          <p>Mitochondrial DNA (D loop) sequences from chimpanzees sampled on the southern bank of the Malagarasi River (MR, red) are shown in relation to previously identified chimpanzee mitochondrial haplotypes from the Gombe Stream National Park (GM, blue) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Keele2">[45]</xref>, Mahale Mountains National Park (MH, green) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Liu1">[40]</xref> and Ugalla (UG, orange) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">[27]</xref>. Haplotypes reported by Inoue and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref> are shown in black. The tree was constructed using the neighbor joining method (asterisks denote bootstrap support values above 70%). The scale bars represents 0.003 substitutions per site.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0058965-t001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.t001</object-id>
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>SIVcpz infection in chimpanzees sampled near the Malagarasi river.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0058965-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
          <table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chimp ID<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample code</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collection date</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mtDNA haplotype<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref></td>
                <td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Microsatellite loci<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">d</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIVcpz fecal WB<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">e</xref></td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIVcpz fecal vRNA</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D18s536</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4s243</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D10s676</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D9s922</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D2s1326</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D2s1333</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4s1627</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D9s905</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ch-1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1338</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/173</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/227</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286/302</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232/260</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">314/318</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/225</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295/295</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1347</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/173</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/227</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286/302</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232/260</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">314/318</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/225</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295/295</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1348</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/173</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/227</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286/302</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232/260</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">314/318</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/225</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295/295</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1350</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/173</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/227</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286/302</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232/260</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">314/318</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/225</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295/295</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold/>5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Ch-2</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MR1349</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Aug-7-12</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>M</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MH32</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>137/173</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>200/227</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>174/174</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>280/302</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>228/252</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>318/334</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>221/233</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>295/295</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>pos</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>neg</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ch-3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR 1355</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133/173</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/231</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/194</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286/298</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248/248</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/318</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/233</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/295</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1340</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133/173</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/231</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/?</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/?</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248/248</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">302/?</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/233</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291/?</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ch-4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1339</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/157</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/231</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286/290</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/252</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306/318</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/233</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283/287</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1342</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/157</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/231</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286/290</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/252</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306/318</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/233</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283/287</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1344</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/157</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/231</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286/290</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/252</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306/318</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/233</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283/287</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Ch-5</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MR1343</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Aug-7-12</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>F</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MH37</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>137/173</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>223/227</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>174/174</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>290/290</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>228/252</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>314/318</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>221/229</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>287/287</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>pos</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>neg</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ch-6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1337</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133/137</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192/231</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290/302</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248/252</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318/334</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/233</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">287/295</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ch-7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MR1341</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aug-7-12</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH32</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137/149</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/227</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178/182</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">290/302</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/260</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">314/322</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221/221</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295/295</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neg</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>SIVcpz infected chimpanzees are indicated by boldface.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt102">
            <label>b</label>
            <p>F, female; M, male; n/a, not available.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt103">
            <label>c</label>
            <p>GM7, MH37 and MH32 haplotypes have previously been reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Liu1">[40]</xref>.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt104">
            <label>d</label>
            <p>?/?, Partial genotype due to sample degradation.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt105">
            <label>e</label>
            <p>WB, Western blot; pos, positive; neg, negative.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>To determine the number of individual chimpanzees, we subjected all mtDNA positive fecal samples to microsatellite analyses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0058965-t001">Table 1</xref>). One of these (MR1340) failed to yield a complete genotype, due to partial sample degradation. Since MR1340 shared the same mtDNA haplotype and three STR loci with sample MR1355, we conservatively classified it to represent the same individual (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0058965-t001">Table 1</xref>). The remaining 11 samples represented six additional individuals, indicating a total of seven sampled chimpanzees, including five males and two females (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0058965-t001">Table 1</xref>). Five of these individuals shared the same mtDNA haplotype (MH32). None of these samples exhibited the same genotype as individuals sampled in other areas of the Masito-Ugalla ecosystem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">[27]</xref>; unpublished).</p>
      <p>To determine whether any of the Malagarasi chimpanzees were SIVcpz infected, we tested all genotyped fecal samples for the presence of antibodies using a highly sensitive and specific Western blot approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Keele1">[37]</xref>. Interestingly, two of the sampled individuals, one male and one female, exhibited clear evidence of SIVcpz infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Sample MR1349 reacted strongly with multiple HIV-1 proteins, including the viral envelope (gp160), integrase (p31) and core (p24) proteins. Sample MR1343 was also Western blot positive, albeit only weakly, yielding diagnostic gp160 and p24 bands. Unfortunately, multiple attempts to amplify SIVcpz sequences from the two antibody positive samples failed, most likely due to partial sample degradation.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0058965-g004" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g004</object-id>
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evidence of SIVcpz infection on the southern bank of the Malagarasi River.</title>
          <p>Chimpanzee fecal samples were tested for HIV/SIV specific antibodies using an enhanced chemiluminescent Western blot approach and HIV-1 antigen containing strips. Samples from individuals (Ch-2 and Ch-5; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0058965-t001">Table 1</xref>) reacted with envelope, integrase and/or core proteins, indicating SIVcpz infection. Molecular weights of HIV-1 specific proteins are indicated. The banding pattern of plasma from an HIV-1 infected patient (pos at a 1∶10,000 dilution) and an uninfected human control (neg) are shown.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Finally, we found a natural shallow ford in the Malagarasi River, where investigators were able to cross the river in its entirety on foot, jumping from rock to rock. On examination of the area, we found two fecal samples on rocks in the riverbed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g005">Figure 5</xref>). These samples were not collected because they had dried up, and thus were not considered suitable for molecular analyses. However, careful inspection revealed that they each had the characteristic shape, size, and smell of chimpanzee feces. Taken together, these findings strongly suggest that chimpanzees approach and are able to cross the river, at least during the dry season.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0058965-g005" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g005</object-id>
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Photograph of location where researchers, and presumably chimpanzees, can cross the river.</title>
          <p>In the foreground is a dried chimpanzee fecal sample.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0058965.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Habitat loss from the conversion of forest and woodlands to agricultural land is one of the most significant threats to chimpanzee survival in Tanzania. Establishing the location of natural boundaries for Tanzania's chimpanzees has implications for how we interpret current and historical population connectivity and advise policy-makers on human land-use strategies that may have significant effects on chimpanzee habitat. The Malagarasi River has been proposed as a major biogeographical boundary that has impeded the movement of chimpanzees, as well as other mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref>. Such barriers have been well documented to have significant impacts on gene flow and overall genetic diversity in all three other apes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Arora1">[9]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Eriksson1">[11]</xref>, and thus the consequences for further chimpanzee fragmentation in Tanzania are significant for population viability as well as conservation strategy.</p>
      <p>Inoue et al.′s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref> recent study proposed two important features to the population genetic landscape in western Tanzania. By comparing mtDNA haplotypes from 138 samples between chimpanzees from Gombe and those from the GME south of the Malagarasi, they found no shared haplotypes. They drew two conclusions: First, that the Malagarasi River limits gene flow between these two regions. Second, and equally important, that the southern sampled areas (Wansisi Hilla, Mahale, Kalobwe, and Ugalla-Masito) represent a single population. Our results dispute both of these claims with important implications for conservation (see below). It is only by integrating comprehensive and independent data sets from (1) published haplotypes, (2) SIVcpz distribution, and (3) ground truthing that we can thoroughly address this important question of chimpanzee fragmentation.</p>
      <p>First, Inoue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref> had very few samples from Gombe. Comparing sequences from our more extensive sampling of the Gombe chimpanzee communities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell2">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Keele1">[37]</xref>, we find that mtDNA haplotypes A, C and R found by Inoue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref> in the GME (but not at Gombe) are identical to haplotypes GM9, GM7 and GM8 from Gombe chimpanzees (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Thus, the communities to the north and south of the Malagarasi are not as genetically distinct as reported. Second, we provide circumstantial evidence that the Malagarasi River does not, at least seasonally, present the physical barrier to individual chimpanzee movement that would prevent gene flow. We surveyed the southern bank of the river in the ‘Masito’ region for shallow areas that could be crossed without wading or swimming through deep water (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0058965-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Following a possible chimpanzee trail, we found one such ford. We also found recent chimpanzee nests and fresh knuckle prints leading right up to the riverbed, as well as 13 fecal samples confirmed to be of chimpanzee origin. Moreover, we found dried fecal samples of likely chimpanzee origin on rocks within the riverbed. Thus it appears that chimpanzees approach the river at this location and, at least in the dry season, would be able to cross it as researchers did.</p>
      <p>The idea that chimpanzees can cross the Malagarasi is further supported by earlier work describing the molecular epidemiology of simian immunodeficiency virus (SIVcpz). In that study, Rudicell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">[27]</xref> reported that chimpanzees from the Issa Valley community (in Ugalla, south of the river) share some mtDNA haplotypes with those from Gombe National Park. At the time, it was unknown whether this reflected recent gene flow across the river or more distant common ancestry. However, the results presented here would suggest the former. Furthermore, we also found closely related strains of SIVcpz infecting chimpanzees in Gombe and in the Issa Valley, respectively about 90 km north and 50 km south of the Malagarasi River <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">[27]</xref>, raising the possibility that these locations are epidemiologically linked. Together, these results strongly suggest that, in contrast to Inoue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref>, there is gene flow and also disease transmission across the Malagarasi River.</p>
      <p>If chimpanzees indeed frequently use the ford that we identified as a natural bridge, the implications are threefold. First, it suggests that the Greater Gombe and Masito-Ugalla regions might have historically had some gene flow, even if limited by season or rainfall, with chimpanzees on both sides being connected to a greater extent than previously thought <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref>. The possibility that these two systems are connected is important for conservationists and researchers alike, who seek to prevent additional chimpanzee communities from becoming isolated due to human disturbance. If the river is a barrier to chimpanzee movement, Lilanshimba chimpanzees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa2">[31]</xref> are unlikely to be a viable population, especially unless habitat connectivity can be restored to Gombe. If, however, the river is not an absolute barrier, then those chimpanzees are part of the GME and we should mobilize resources to protecting remaining habitat in the area, especially now that the nearby Lugufu Refugee Camp has been closed and there is a dramatic reduction in human pressure on the area.</p>
      <p>Second, since the discovery of SIVcpz in chimpanzees from Gombe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Santiago1">[38]</xref> and more recently, Ugalla <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">[27]</xref>, researchers have suspected a transmission path across the Malagarasi. The connectivity reported here may now explain how SIVcpz spread to chimpanzees south of the Malagarasi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">[27]</xref> and potentially be a threat to the other GME chimpanzees. Inoue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref> argue that close genetic distance across the GME suggests this area represents a single population. This is inconsistent with recent SIVcpz results that reveal no positive infections in over 400 samples collected across the southern GME (unpublished data). Thus, whilst it remains possible that a recent introduction of SIVcpz to the region from the north explains its absence in the south, a more parsimonious explanation is that the GME is actually not a single population. More investigation is necessary to confirm where potential barriers may exist within the GME.</p>
      <p>Finally, our data serve as a reminder that thorough investigation of potential ‘barriers’ is critical to confirm their actual role in chimpanzee population health, movements, and potential disease transmission. Since the mid 1960s, researchers have described the Malagarasi River as a boundary to chimpanzee movement, before thoroughly investigating possible routes across it. As a result, local conservation organizations designated two entirely different ‘Ecosystems’ (Greater Mahale to the south; Greater Gombe to the north). Our results suggest that this nomenclature is misleading. Further, currently a second large river has come under similar scrutiny. The Lugufu River runs parallel to the Malagarasi, south &lt;10 km near the Mkuyu village forest where chimpanzees have been observed. Knowing whether this is a permanent or merely seasonal barrier has important implications for conservation planning, especially regarding population viability assessment.</p>
      <p>Of course, the finding of chimpanzee fecal samples in close proximity to and within the Malagarasi riverbed does not provide conclusive evidence of connectivity across the river. However, Ogawa et al.′s <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Ogawa2">[31]</xref> description of chimpanzees living within the Lilanshimba area to the north of the river suggests that, rather than faced with imminent extermination, chimpanzees there may be able to move southward, escaping expanding human settlement, into more remote areas. Moreover, the natural bridge that we describe could have been used extensively in the past, thus explaining evidence of shared mtDNA haplotypes and closely related viral genotypes on both sides of the river. Although recent work has begun to shed light on the genetic relatedness of chimpanzees in western Tanzania <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0058965-Inoue1">[32]</xref>, more comprehensive field and genetic surveys are needed in Lilanshimba, Loasi, and the GME, to provide more detailed knowledge of western Tanzanian chimpanzee gene flow, ecology and disease susceptibility.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Fieldwork was made possible by the courageous efforts of Mashaka Alimas, Masumbuku Ahmedi, Mtunda Ahmedi, and Justina Bonifice, and permission to work in the area was granted by the local and district governments of Kigoma and Mpanda, as well as by TAWIRI (Tanzania Wildlife Research Institute) and COSTECH (Commission for Science and Technology). Thanks also to Jim Moore for consultation during portions of the fieldwork, and especially to Bill McGrew and Todd Disotell for helpful comments on a previous version of this paper.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Lehman1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Analysis of coyote mitochondrial-DNA genotype frequencies - estimation of effective number of alleles</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Forbes1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Genetic structure and migration in native and reintroduced Rocky Mountain wolf populations</article-title>. <source>Conservation Biology</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1226</fpage>–<lpage>1234</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Finnegan1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finnegan</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The complimentary role of genetic and ecological data in understanding population structure: a case study using moose (Alces alces)</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Wildlife Research</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-MorroghBernard1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrogh-Bernard</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morf</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chivers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krutzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Dispersal Patterns of Orang-utans (Pongo spp.) in a Bornean Peat-swamp Forest</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Primatology</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Ayres1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cluttonbrock</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>River boundaries and species range size in Amazonian primates</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>531</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Colyn1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gautierhion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verheyen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>A reappraisal of paleoenvironmental history in Central Africa - evidence for major fluvial refuge in Zaire basin</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biogeography</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>407</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Telfer1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Telfer</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Souquiere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abernethy</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruford</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Molecular evidence for deep phylogenetic divergence in Mandrillus sphinx</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2019</fpage>–<lpage>2024</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Wu1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genes and speciation</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Arora1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nater</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Schaik</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Noordwijk</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Effects of Pleistocene glaciations and rivers on the population structure of Bornean orangutans (Pongo pygmaeus)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>21376</fpage>–<lpage>21381</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Anthony1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson-Bawe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abernethy</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The role of Pleistocene refugia and rivers in shaping gorilla genetic diversity in central Africa</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>20432</fpage>–<lpage>20436</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Eriksson1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boesch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vigilant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Rivers influence the population genetic structure of bonobos (Pan paniscus)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>3425</fpage>–<lpage>3435</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Gonder1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonder</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghobrial</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kujawski</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evidence from Cameroon reveals differences in the genetic structure and histories of chimpanzee populations</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>4766</fpage>–<lpage>4771</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Junker1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Junker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boesch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>du Toit</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Recent decline in suitable environmental conditions for African great apes</article-title>. <source>Diversity and Distributions</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1077</fpage>–<lpage>1091</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Watts1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Boundary patrols and intergroup encounters in wild chimpanzees</article-title>. <source>Behaviour</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Mitani1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pepper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merriwether</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Demographic and social constraints on male chimpanzee behaviour</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Schubert1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoneking</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arandjelovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boesch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eckhardt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Male-Mediated Gene Flow in Patrilocal Primates</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Becquet1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becquet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Przeworski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genetic structure of chimpanzee populations</article-title>. <source>Plos Genetics</source> <volume>3</volume>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Gonder2">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonder</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Disotell</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oates</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>New genetic evidence on the evolution of chimpanzee populations and implications for taxonomy</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Primatology</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1103</fpage>–<lpage>1127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Shimada1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Humle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA genealogy of chimpanzees in the Nimba Mountains and Bossou, West Africa</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Primatology</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Moyer1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Moyer D, Plumptre A, Kamenya S, Athumani S, Sikombe S (2006) Surveys East of Mahale Mountains National Park. In: Moyer D, Plumptre A, Pintea L, Hernández-Aguilar A, Moore J <etal>et al</etal>.., editors. Survey of Chimpazees and Other Biopdiversity in Western Tanzania: Report to United States Fish and Wildlife Service. pp. 65.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Pintea1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Pintea L, Pusey A, Bolstad P, Bauer M (2006) Remote sensing of chimpanzee habitat change in Gombe National Park, Tanzania: implications for behavioral research and conservation. International Society of Primatology. Entebbe, Uganda. pp. Abst #49.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Kano1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>The chimpanzees of Filabanga, Western Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Primates</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Michel1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nkotagu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Malagarasi Aquatic Ecosystems: Biodiversity &amp; limnological functioning of the Malagarasi-Moyovosi wetlands, western Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Research Report</source></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Beadle1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Beadle LC (1974) The Inland Waters of Tropical Africa: An Introduction to Tropical Limnology. New York: Longman.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-McGrew1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">McGrew WC (1992) Chimpanzee Material Culture: Implications for Human Evolution. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. xvi, 277 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Moore1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Moore J (1992) "Savanna" chimpanzees. In: Nishida T, McGrew WC, Marler P, Pickford M, De Waal FBM, editors. Topics in Primatology Vol 1: Human Origins. Tokyo: University of Tokyo Press. pp. 99–118.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Rudicell1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudicell</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piel</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Learn</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>High Prevalence of Simian Immunodeficiency Virus Infection in a Community of Savanna Chimpanzees</article-title>. <source>Journal of Virology</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>9918</fpage>–<lpage>9928</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Rudicell2">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudicell</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wroblewski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Learn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Impact of Simian Immunodeficiency Virus Infection on Chimpanzee Population Dyanmics</article-title>. <source>PloS Pathogens</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Ogawa1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ogawa H, Sakamaki T, Idani G (2006) The influence of Congolese Refugees on chimpanzees in the Lilanshimba area, Tanzania. Pan Africa News: 21–22.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Kano2">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanamori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Distribution and density of wild chimpanzees of the northwestern bank of the Malagarasi River, Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Primate Research</source> <volume>15</volume>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Ogawa2">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mbalamwezi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A chimpanzee bed found at Tubila, 20 km from Lilanshimba habitat</article-title>. <source>Pan Africa News</source> <volume>18</volume>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Inoue1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tashiro</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue-Murayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Gene flow and genetic diversity of chimpanzees in tanzanian habitats</article-title>. <source>Primate Conservation</source> <volume>26</volume> online in advance of print.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Pintea2">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pintea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marvib</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bolstad</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pusey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Matching multiscale remote sensing data to inter- disciplinary conservation needs: The case of chimpanzees in Western Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Pecora 15/Land Satellite Information IV/ISPRS Commission I/FIEOS 2002 Conference Proceedings</source></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-HernandezAguilar1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Aguilar</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Chimpanzee nest distribution and site reuse in a dry habitat: implications for early hominin ranging</article-title>. <source>Journal of Human Evolution</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Stewart1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Living archaeology: Artefacts of specific nest-site fidelity in wild chimpanzees</article-title>. <source>Journal of Human Evolution</source></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Plumptre1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plumptre</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Nesting behavior of chimpanzees: Implications for censuses</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Primatology</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>485</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Keele1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keele</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Heuverswyn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Chimpanzee reservoirs of pandemic and nonpandemic HIV1</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>313</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>526</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Santiago1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lukasik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kamenya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bibollet-Ruche</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Foci of endemic simian immunodeficiency virus infection in wild-living eastern chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Virology</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>7545</fpage>–<lpage>7562</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-VanHeuverswyn1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Heuverswyn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lafay</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genetic diversity and phylogeographic clustering of SIVcpzPtt in wild chimpanzees in Cameroon</article-title>. <source>Virology</source> <volume>977</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Liu1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woroobey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keele</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bibollet-Ruche</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Molecular ecology and natural history of simian foamy virus infection in wild-living chimpanzee</article-title>. <source>Plos Pathogens</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000097</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Saitou1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>Molecular biology and evolution</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>406</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Larkin1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2947</fpage>–<lpage>2948</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Kimura1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Estimation of evolutionary distances between homologous nucleotide sequences</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>454</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Felsenstein1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap</article-title>. <source>Evolution</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>783</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Keele2">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keele</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terio</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rudicell</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Increased mortality and AIDS-like immunopathology in wild chimpanzees infected with SIVcpz</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>460</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>–<lpage>519</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Constable1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Constable</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashley</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pusey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Noninvasive paternity assignment in Gombe chimpanzees</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1279</fpage>–<lpage>1300</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Wroblewski1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wroblewski</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keele</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher-Stankey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Male dominance rank and reproductive success in chimpanzees, Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>77</volume>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Sullivan1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mannucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimpton</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>A rapid and quantitative DNA sex test: fluorescence-based PCR analysis of X-Y homologous gene amelogenin</article-title>. <source>BioTechniques</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>636</fpage>–<lpage>638, 640–631</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Li1">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Njango</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Learn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keele</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Eastern Chimpanzees, but not Bonobos, Represent a Simian Immunodeficiency Virus Reservoir</article-title>. <source>Journal of Virology</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>10776</fpage>–<lpage>10791</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0058965-Pintea3">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pintea L (2006) Workshop: predicting great ape distributions using element distribution modeling tools. International Journal of Primatology: Abst #465.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>