<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0158069</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-11996</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Mood disorders</subject><subj-group><subject>Depression</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Young adults</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject><subj-group><subject>Anxiety</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Emotions</subject><subj-group><subject>Anxiety</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematical and statistical techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Regression analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistics (mathematics)</subject><subj-group><subject>Statistical methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Regression analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and occupational health</subject><subj-group><subject>Global health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Religious faiths</subject><subj-group><subject>Catholicism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Facets of Spirituality Diminish the Positive Relationship between Insecure Attachment and Mood Pathology in Young Adults</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Attachment, Spirituality and Mood Pathology</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Hiebler-Ragger</surname>
<given-names>Michaela</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Falthansl-Scheinecker</surname>
<given-names>Johanna</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Birnhuber</surname>
<given-names>Gerhard</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Fink</surname>
<given-names>Andreas</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Unterrainer</surname>
<given-names>Human Friedrich</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>University Clinic of Psychiatry, Medical University Graz, Graz, Austria</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Center for Integrative Addiction Research (Grüner Kreis Society), Vienna, Austria</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Institute of Psychology, University of Graz, Graz, Austria</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Federici</surname>
<given-names>Stefano</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Perugia, ITALY</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AF HFU. Performed the experiments: GB JFS. Analyzed the data: MHR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AF. Wrote the paper: MHR HFU.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">human.unterrainer@uni-graz.at</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>23</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e0158069</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>23</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>9</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Hiebler-Ragger et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0158069"/>
<abstract>
<p>Traditionally, in attachment theory, secure attachment has been linked to parameters of mental health, while insecure attachment has been associated with parameters of psychopathology. Furthermore, spirituality and attachment to God have been discussed as corresponding to, or compensating for, primary attachment experiences. Accordingly, they may contribute to mental health or to mental illness. In this cross-sectional observational study, we investigate attachment styles (Avoidant and Anxious Attachment; ECR-RD), spirituality (Religious and Existential Well-Being; MI-RSWB), and mood pathology (Anxiety, Depression, Somatization; BSI-18) in 481 (76% female) young adults (age range: 18–30 years) who had a Roman Catholic upbringing. In accordance with previous research, we found insecure attachment to be associated with low levels of spirituality. Furthermore, insecure attachment and low levels of spirituality were associated with higher levels of mood pathology. In hierarchical regression analyses, only Anxious Attachment positively predicted all three dimensions of mood pathology while Existential Well-Being–but not Religious Well-Being–was an additional negative predictor for Depression. Our results underline that spirituality can correspond to the attachment style, or may also compensate for insecure attachment. Higher Existential Well-Being–comprised of facets such as hope for a better future, forgiveness and the experience of sense and meaning–seems to have an especially corrective effect on mood pathology, independent of attachment styles. Our findings emphasize the vital role of existential well-being in young adults’ affective functioning, which might be considered in prevention and treatment. Further research in clinical surroundings is recommended.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="0"/>
<table-count count="2"/>
<page-count count="9"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>Data may compromise the privacy of study participants and may not be shared publicly. Data are available upon request to the authors.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>In attachment theory, attachment is seen as a fundamental psychological and biological drive with evolutionary importance and far-reaching, complex consequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref001">1</xref>]. Formed by early family environment, our attachment system is continually active throughout the lifespan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref002">2</xref>]. It adaptively regulates psychological and physiological development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref003">3</xref>] and influences day-to-day person/environment transactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref004">4</xref>]. Ideally, it offers a ‘secure base’ from which a person can explore the world as well as a ‘safe haven’ to retreat to when frightened or stressed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref005">5</xref>]. While attachment research has already contributed immensely to our understanding of our social nature, ‘an important enterprise for the future is to consider how attachment is differentiated from, and integrated with, other features of development’ (p. 25) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref006">6</xref>].</p>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Attachment styles and mood pathology</title>
<p>In line with Mikulincer and Shaver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref007">7</xref>], two basic attachment dimensions can be differentiated: ‘Anxious Attachment’ (AX) and ‘Avoidant Attachment’ (AV). While attachment-secure individuals (low AX and low AV) are able to deal with stressful experiences by relying upon mental representations of previously received support or by actively seeking support in the present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref008">8</xref>], insecure individuals react by either hyperactivating (AX) or deactivating (AV) their ‘attachment behavioral system’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref005">5</xref>]. In response to an inconsistent caregiver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref009">9</xref>] anxious individuals develop hyperactivating strategies that reflect a compromise between the anger toward unavailable attachment figures and the intense need to be close to them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref010">10</xref>]. These strategies involve demanding care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref011">11</xref>], worry, and rumination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref012">12</xref>]. Accordingly, they often amplify distress and fail to regulate emotions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref007">7</xref>]. Following an appraisal that proximity seeking behaviors are unfruitful [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref013">13</xref>], avoidant individuals develop deactivating strategies that imply distrust in others and a desire to maintain self-reliance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref014">14</xref>]. These strategies reflect a compromise between a lack of visible negative emotions and high levels of unconscious unresolved distress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref015">15</xref>]. Hyperactivating and deactivating strategies link insecure attachment to elevated rates of disease through three mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref016">16</xref>]: Firstly, insecurely attached individuals have an increased susceptibility and a more extreme physiological response to stress. Secondly, they mostly use external methods (e.g., substance use) to regulate affect and thirdly, they have less effective help-seeking behavior, including an underuse of social support. Accordingly, studies have linked family adversity to a selective attention to negative stimuli in youth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref017">17</xref>] and to depressive symptoms among young and middle-aged adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref018">18</xref>]. On the other hand, secure attachment seems to have a protective effect against different risk beliefs and problematic behaviors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref019">19</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Attachment styles and spirituality</title>
<p>The relationship between believers and God, or other divine figures, often meets the established criteria of attachment relationships and therefore confers the same sorts of psychological advantages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref020">20</xref>]. The association between attachment styles and spirituality can be explained by two hypotheses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref020">20</xref>]: On the one hand, Bowlby’s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref021">21</xref>] correspondence hypothesis that mental models generalize across different attachment relationships may extend to the beliefs about, and the perceived relationships with, God. On the other hand, based on Ainsworth’s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref022">22</xref>] compensation hypothesis, an attachment to God may be developed by insecurely attached individuals as a surrogate for positive human attachment figures. Consequently, correspondence and compensation hypotheses can be seen as two pathways to and modes of being religious [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref023">23</xref>]. With the gradual replacement of early attachment figures by a romantic partner or friend [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref007">7</xref>], adolescence is a period of turbulence and uncertainty that coincides with ‘the age of religious awakening’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref024">24</xref>], characterized by an increased probability of religious conversion as well as of apostasy. In general, securely attached individuals experience only minor fluctuations in their spiritual belief system while insecurely attached individuals are likely to experience major fluctuations including, but not limited to, sudden conversions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref025">25</xref>]. These fluctuations seem to correspond with distressing life events that point to the need for emotional support [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref026">26</xref>].</p>
<p>The sense of having a secure attachment to God can be linked to the depth of spiritual well-being [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref027">27</xref>]. This linkage leads to a concept of spirituality as an ‘ability to experience and integrate meaning and purpose in existence through a connectedness with self, others or a power greater than oneself’ (p. 117) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref028">28</xref>]. In line with previous work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref029">29</xref>], this concept comprises an immanent kind of Existential Well-Being (EWB) and a transcendent kind of Religious Well-being (RWB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref030">30</xref>]. While RWB primarily relates to the relationship with God, EWB comprises life satisfaction and a conviction that life is meaningful but does not specifically refer to any higher power [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref031">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref032">32</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>The present study</title>
<p>The present study examines possible influences of spirituality and attachment style on mood pathology in young adults. Based on previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref019">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref033">33</xref>] we hypothesized that insecure attachment would be related to higher levels of mood pathology while higher EWB and RWB would be related to lower levels of mood pathology. Furthermore, considering the correspondence pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref024">24</xref>], spirituality develops from generalized mental attachment models and a general adoption of a primary caregiver’s values. Accordingly, we hypothesized that a more secure attachment would be related to higher EWB and RWB. Considering the compensation pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref024">24</xref>], spirituality develops through a controlled effort of regulating distress that runs counter to the mental attachment models developed in early life. Therefore, we also hypothesized that spirituality would have a diminishing effect on mood pathology even after attachment styles have been controlled for.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Material and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Sample description and procedure</title>
<p>The sample consisted of 481 participants drawn from a larger research project (<italic>n</italic> = 844) that investigated various personality parameters in students and post-graduates at the University of Graz, Austria. All questionnaires were completed online on a Lime Survey® platform. Participants were selected for our study if they had completed all relevant questionnaires, were students and/or held a university degree, and were between 18 and 30 years of age. As some studies indicate that religious orientations differ in their association with mood pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref033">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref034">34</xref>], we focused on the most common religious orientation in Austria and therefore included only participants with a Roman Catholic upbringing. This decision also relied on research indicating differences in the attachment to God between Catholics and the worldwide normal distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref035">35</xref>].</p>
<p>The study was carried out in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Ethical approval was granted by the Ethics Committee of the University of Graz, Austria.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Psychometric assessment</title>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Attachment</title>
<p>The <italic>Experience in Close Relationships—Revised</italic> (ECR-RD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref036">36</xref>] assesses ‘Anxious Attachment’ (AX) and ‘Avoidant Attachment’ (AV) in adults (18 items per scale). It employs a 7-point likert scale (1 = ‘absolutely disagree’ to 7 = ‘absolutely agree’). Cronbach’s α was .91 for AX and .92 for AV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref036">36</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Spirituality</title>
<p>The <italic>Multidimensional Inventory for Religious/Spiritual Well-bein</italic>g (MI-RSWB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref037">37</xref>] contains 48 items which form 6 subscales (8 items per scale). These subscales, ‘Hope Immanent’, ‘Forgiveness’ and ‘Experience of Sense and Meaning’, are components of a total Existential Well-Being (EWB) score, while ‘Hope Transcendent’, ‘General Religiosity’ and ‘Connectedness’ reflect a total Religious Well-Being (RWB) score. Each item is rated on a 6-point likert scale ranging from 1 (‘strongly disagree’) to 6 (‘strongly agree’). By summing up EWB and RWB a total amount of Religious/Spiritual Well-Being (RSWB) is calculated. Cronbach’s α was at least at .72 for all the sub-dimensions and .89 for RSWB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref038">38</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Mood pathology</title>
<p>The <italic>Brief Symptom Inventory-18</italic> (BSI-18) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref039">39</xref>] is a short version of the highly established Symptom-Checklist SCL-90-R. The amount of psychiatric burden (Somatization, Depression, and Anxiety) for the preceding seven days is assessed with 18 items (6 per scale). The BSI-18 employs a 5-point likert scale (0 = ‘absolutely not’ to 4 = ‘very strong’). The total for the 18 items generate the Global Severity Index (GSI). Cronbach’s α was at least at .79 for the sub-dimensions and .91 for the GSI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref039">39</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>Pearson`s correlation statistics were conducted in order to investigate the relationships between study variables. Hierarchical regression analyses were conducted to examine the influence of attachment and spirituality on the dimensions of mood pathology. To control for alpha inflation due to multiple comparisons alpha-level was set to <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The mean age of the participants was 23 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 2.93). 363 (76%) were female. 261 (54%) were in a romantic relationship. Only a few participants (<italic>n</italic> = 15; 3%) had children. The nationality of most of the participants (<italic>n</italic> = 441; 92%) was Austrian, 40 (8%) had other nationalities. For highest completed education level, 352 (73%) had a high school diploma while 129 (27%) had a university degree.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Hypothesis testing results</title>
<p>We conducted correlation analyses (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0158069.t001">Table 1</xref>) followed by hierarchical regression analyses (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0158069.t002">Table 2</xref>) to examine the influence of attachment and spirituality dimensions on mood pathology.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0158069.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0158069.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Descriptive characteristics and intercorrelations of study variables.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0158069.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0158069.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Measures</th>
<th align="center">α</th>
<th align="center">Min.</th>
<th align="center">Max.</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SD</italic></th>
<th align="left">1</th>
<th align="left">2</th>
<th align="left">3</th>
<th align="left">4</th>
<th align="left">5</th>
<th align="left">6</th>
<th align="left">7</th>
<th align="left">8</th>
<th align="left">9</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BSI-18</bold></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>1. Anxiety</bold></td>
<td align="center">.76</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">22</td>
<td align="center">4.57</td>
<td align="center">3.94</td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>2. Depression</bold></td>
<td align="center">.84</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">24</td>
<td align="center">5.09</td>
<td align="center">5.02</td>
<td align="left">.53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>3. Somatization</bold></td>
<td align="center">.72</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">19</td>
<td align="center">3.15</td>
<td align="center">3.53</td>
<td align="left">.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>4. GSI</bold></td>
<td align="center">.87</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">64</td>
<td align="center">12.80</td>
<td align="center">10.11</td>
<td align="left">.82<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.85<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>ECR-RD</bold></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>5. AX</bold></td>
<td align="center">.92</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">6.50</td>
<td align="center">3.11</td>
<td align="center">1.20</td>
<td align="left">.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>6. AV</bold></td>
<td align="center">.93</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">6.33</td>
<td align="center">2.45</td>
<td align="center">1.05</td>
<td align="left">.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>MI-RSWB</bold></td>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>7. EWB</bold></td>
<td align="center">.84</td>
<td align="center">42</td>
<td align="center">139</td>
<td align="center">107.02</td>
<td align="center">15.48</td>
<td align="left">-.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>8. RWB</bold></td>
<td align="center">.86</td>
<td align="center">38</td>
<td align="center">136</td>
<td align="center">76.65</td>
<td align="center">18.91</td>
<td align="left">-.11</td>
<td align="left">-.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.08</td>
<td align="left">-.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>9. RSWB</bold></td>
<td align="center">.90</td>
<td align="center">89</td>
<td align="center">267</td>
<td align="center">183.67</td>
<td align="center">29.99</td>
<td align="left">-.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.12</td>
<td align="left">-.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.84<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.90<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>**<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p>BSI-18 = Brief Symptom Inventory-18, GSI = Global Severity Index, ECR-RD = Experience in Close Relationships–Revised, AX = Anxious Attachment, AV = Avoidant Attachment, MI-RSWB = Multidimensional Inventory of Religious/Spiritual Well-Being, EWB = Existential Well-Being, RWB = Religious Well-Being, RSWB = Religious/Spiritual Well-Being.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0158069.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0158069.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Hierarchical regression analyses predicting mood pathology.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0158069.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0158069.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="2"/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Anxiety</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Depression</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Somatization</th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">GSI</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Step and predictor variable</th>
<th align="left"><italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>ΔR</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>β</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>ΔR</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>β</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>ΔR</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>β</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>ΔR</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="left"><italic>β</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Step 1</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.01</td>
<td align="left">.01</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.00</td>
<td align="left">.00</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>Sex</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.12</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.03</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Step 2</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>Sex</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.11</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.01</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>AX</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>AV</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.07</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.10</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.08</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Step 3</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.01</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.00</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left">.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>Sex</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.11</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.03</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>AX</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>AV</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.04</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.02</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.06</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>EWB</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.11</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.06</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">-.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><bold>RWB</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.03</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.10</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.01</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">.06</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>**<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p>Sex: 1 = male, GSI = Global Severity Index (BSI-18), AX = Anxious Attachment (ECR-RD), AV = Avoidant Attachment (ECR-RD), EWB = Existential Well-Being (MI-RSWB), RWB = Religious Well-Being (MI-RSWB).</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>As expected, correlation analyses showed that higher levels of AX and AV were associated with a higher level of mood pathology (AX: <italic>r</italic> = .43, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; AV: <italic>r</italic> = .24, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) and a lower level of RSWB (AX: <italic>r</italic> = -.38, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; AV: <italic>r</italic> = -.28, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). More specifically, the strongest correlations were found for AX with Depression (<italic>r</italic> = .48, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) and with EWB (<italic>r</italic> = -.38, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) respectively. Lower RSWB was also associated with a higher level of mood pathology (<italic>r</italic> = -.27, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). Here, the strongest correlation was found for EWB with Depression (<italic>r</italic> = -.42, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01).</p>
<p>In the hierarchical regression analyses, sex was entered as a control variable at Step 1 as we found higher levels of GSI in female compared to male participants (<italic>M</italic><sub>female</sub> = 13.51, <italic>M</italic><sub>male</sub> = 10.63; <italic>F</italic><sub>(1, 480)</sub> = 7.35, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). AX and AV were entered at Step 2, RWB and EWB at Step 3. The hierarchical regression analyses, including all predictors and the control variable, accounted for 12% of the variance in Anxiety (<italic>F</italic><sub>(5, 475)</sub> = 12.69, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01), 29% of the variance in Depression (<italic>F</italic><sub>(5, 475)</sub> = 38.80, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01), 8% of the variance in Somatization (<italic>F</italic><sub>(5, 475)</sub> = 8.75, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01), and 23% of the variance in GSI (<italic>F</italic><sub>(5, 475)</sub> = 28.95, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01).</p>
<p>At Step 1, sex was negatively related to Somatization and GSI (Somatization: <italic>β</italic> = -.18, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; GSI: β = -.12, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) but unrelated to Anxiety and Depression. At Step 2 and Step 3, <italic>β</italic> for sex changed only slightly.</p>
<p>At Step 2, AX was positively related to all three dimensions of mood pathology and GSI (Anxiety: <italic>β</italic> = .28, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; Depression: <italic>β</italic> = .42, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; Somatization: <italic>β</italic> = .18, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; GSI: <italic>β</italic> = .38, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). AV was not related to mood pathology.</p>
<p>At Step 3, AX was still positively related to all dimensions of mood pathology although β were smaller than at Step 2. AV was not related to mood pathology. RWB also had no significant relation to mood pathology while EWB was negatively related to Depression (<italic>β</italic> = -.33, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) and GSI (<italic>β</italic> = -.23, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) but unrelated to Anxiety and Somatization. Accordingly, only the models on Depression and GSI showed a significant increase in R<sup>2</sup> between Step 2 and Step 3 (Depression: <italic>ΔR</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = .07, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01; GSI: <italic>ΔR</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = .03, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study we sought to investigate the relationship between attachment and mood pathology as being possibly influenced by spirituality in a group of young adults. In accordance with previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref040">40</xref>], we found secure attachment as to be associated with a higher amount of Religious/Spiritual Well-being (RSWB) while insecure attachment and lower RSWB were associated with higher levels of mood pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref041">41</xref>]. This was especially pronounced for Depression. When attachment style and RSWB are considered together, only Anxious Attachment (AX), but not Avoidant Attachment (AV), positively predicted all three dimensions of mood pathology while Existential Well-Being (EWB), but not Religious Well-Being (RWB), was an additional negative predictor only for Depression. Results further suggest a mediating function of EWB on the positive relationship between insecure attachment and mood pathology.</p>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Attachment related coping strategies</title>
<p>The strong influence of AX on mood pathology might be explained through different coping strategies related to AX and AV: Impaired emotion regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref042">42</xref>] and amplified distress due to hyperactivating strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref007">7</xref>] likely contribute to our finding that AX predicts mood pathology with the strongest relation to depression. On the other hand, deactivating strategies reflect a compromise between a lack of visible negative emotions and high levels of unconscious distress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref015">15</xref>]. Our finding that AV does not predict mood pathology independent of AX underlines that in these ‘segregated’ mental systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref042">42</xref>] distressing material, including personal weaknesses, is excluded from the stream of consciousness. As these deactivation strategies are often unreliable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref043">43</xref>], it is possible that AV does increase psychopathology but that avoidant individuals are less likely to acknowledge their symptoms and to seek help. Accordingly, hyperactivating strategies seem to mediate AX and depressive symptoms while evidence for deactivating strategies as a mediator is mixed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref013">13</xref>] and should be further explored in future research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec017">
<title>Correspondence and compensation pathway</title>
<p>Our findings furthermore suggest that EWB, but not RWB, predicts mood pathology independent of attachment. This underlines previous research showing that RWB and EWB represent two independent concepts with different patterns of association to personality domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref044">44</xref>]. The correlation between RWB and mood pathology might simply occur because the relationship between believers and God often meet the established criteria of attachment relationships and therefore confers the same sorts of psychological advantages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref020">20</xref>]. However, while the relation between higher RSWB and more secure attachment supports the correspondence pathway, EWB also seems to bear a protective effect regarding mood pathology that is independent of attachment style. This in turn supports the compensation pathway. EWB includes immanent hope, forgiveness, and experience of sense and meaning, dimensions that do not require an attachment relationship with a higher power. Increased EWB may develop through the ‘secure base’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref005">5</xref>], formed by a secure attachment to primary caregivers and/or a higher power. This ‘secure base’ liberates the individual to perceive self and others as separate with wishes and needs of their own so that both autonomy and connectedness are developed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref001">1</xref>]. Interestingly, heightened autonomy, spirituality and self-acceptance also seem to have a positive effect on remission from disordered eating behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref045">45</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec018">
<title>Methodological Considerations</title>
<p>The presented results can only be interpreted in light of potential limitations. Accordingly, as the current research focused on young adults with Roman Catholic upbringing, results may not be generalizable to individuals from other religious backgrounds. However, the detailed evaluation of religious and spiritual well-being can be considered as a strength of our study. Simply measuring whether someone belongs to a religious denomination might have led to inconclusive results because it is likely not the same as having spiritual or religious practices and beliefs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref046">46</xref>].</p>
<p>Considering attachment, we only assessed current attachment style, while past experiences seem to be stronger predictors of religiosity, even though current attachment is largely based on these experiences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref047">47</xref>]. However, reliance on self-report measures that access primarily conscious attitudes and behaviors may be a limitation in the assessment of both current attachment and past experiences since AV is often not captured as it leads individuals to normalize and report positively about themselves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref048">48</xref>]. To better understand the implications of different attachment styles it may also be advisable to include constructs such as moral concern or mentalization in future studies. It has yet to be clarified whether deficits in this ability of self-projection that allows us to predict what others will think, feel or do in a certain situation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref049">49</xref>] constrain the belief in God [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref050">50</xref>] or are unrelated to religious and spiritual beliefs after moral concern has been controlled for [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref051">51</xref>].</p>
<p>Finally, within-person variability in mood pathology over time and non-ignorable non-response (e.g., if depressed individuals were unwilling to participate because of their depression) may lead to an overrepresentation of healthy individuals in our sample. Further research in a clinical setting is therefore warranted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec019">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Our study contributes to the fields of developmental and clinical psychology by emphasizing the vital roles of attachment and existential well-being in young adult’s mental health. It can therefore inform future studies on the importance of spiritual development across the span of adult life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0158069.ref052">52</xref>]. A higher existential well-being seems to be able to especially compensate for the negative impact of insecure attachment on mental health. Therefore, our findings have clear implications for prevention and treatment given that the relative importance of attachment styles and religious/spiritual well-being might help tailor interventions to better address the specific needs of young adults.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to acknowledge the work of Nikolas Bonatos for making helpful and invaluable critical comments to the manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>. <source>Addiction as an Attachment Disorder</source>. <publisher-loc>Plymouth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jason Aronson</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowlby</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>A secure base: Clinical applications of attachment theory</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>; <year>1988</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belsky</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment, mating, and parenting</article-title>. <source>Hum Nat</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02913039" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF02913039</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26197165</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheinbaum</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kwapil</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballespí</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitjavila</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chun</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silvia</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Attachment style predicts affect, cognitive appraisals, and social functioning in daily life</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>. Frontiers; <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2015.00296" xlink:type="simple">10.3389/fpsyg.2015.00296</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowlby</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Attachment and loss, Vol. 1: Attachment</chapter-title>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>; <year>1982</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaver</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Contributions of attachment theory and research: a framework for future research, translation, and policy</article-title>. <source>Dev Psychopathol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1415</fpage>–<lpage>1434</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0954579413000692" xlink:type="simple">10.1017/S0954579413000692</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24342848</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulincer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaver</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Attachment in adulthood: Structure, dynamics, and change</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Publications Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulincer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaver</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Security-Based Self-Representations in Adulthood: Contents and Processes</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Rholes</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Adult attachment: Theory, research, and clinical implications</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>. pp. <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blehar</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wall</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Patterns of attachment: Assessed in the strange situation and at home</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdal,NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>; <year>1978</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kobak</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Avoidance and its relationship with other defensive processes</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Belsky</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nezworski</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Clinical implications of attachment</source>. <publisher-loc>Hillsdal,NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>; <year>1988</year>. pp. <fpage>300</fpage>–<lpage>323</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulincer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaver</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereg</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment Theory and affect regulation: The dynamics, development, and cognitive consequences of attachment-related strategies</article-title>. <source>Motiv Emot</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1024515519160" xlink:type="simple">10.1023/A:1024515519160</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emotion regulation: influences of attachment relationships</article-title>. <source>Monogr Soc Res Child Dev</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>249</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1166148" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/1166148</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984163</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittkowski</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emotion regulation as a mediator in the relationship between attachment and depressive symptomatology: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>172C</volume>: <fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>444</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2014.10.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jad.2014.10.007</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaver</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulincer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment theory and research: Resurrection of the psychodynamic approach to personality</article-title>. <source>J Res Pers</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jrp.2004.09.002" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jrp.2004.09.002</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaver</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulincer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment-related psychodynamics</article-title>. <source>Attach Hum Dev</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/1461673021015417" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/1461673021015417</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12467506</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maunder</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment and psychosomatic medicine: developmental contributions to stress and disease</article-title>. <source>Psychosom Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>556</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/00006842-200107000-00006" xlink:type="simple">10.1097/00006842-200107000-00006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11485109</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kouros</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garber</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trajectories of individual depressive symptoms in adolescents: Gender and family relationships as predictors</article-title>. <source>Dev Psychol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>50</volume>: <fpage>2633</fpage>–<lpage>2643</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/a0038190" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/a0038190</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25329553</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller-Iglesias</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antonucci</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Complex Nature of Family Support Across the Life Span: Implications for Psychological Well-Being</article-title><source>. Dev Psychol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/a0038665" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/a0038665</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25602936</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lac</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crano</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvaro</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment theory and theory of planned behavior: An integrative model predicting underage drinking</article-title>. <source>Dev Psychol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1579</fpage>–<lpage>1590</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/a0030728" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/a0030728</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23127300</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Attachment, Evolution, and the Psychology of Religion</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>; <year>2005</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowlby</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Attachment and loss, Vol. 2: Separation: Anxiety and anger</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>; <year>1973</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachments across the life span</article-title>. <source>Bull N Y Acad Med</source>. <year>1985</year>;</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granqvist</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Attachment and religious representations and behavio</chapter-title><source>r</source>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassidy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaver</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Handbook of attachment: Theory, research and clinical applications</source>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>. pp. <fpage>906</fpage>–<lpage>933</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Argyle</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beit-Hallahmi</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The social psychology of religion</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge &amp; Kegan</publisher-name>; <year>1975</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granqvist</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment and Religiosity in Adolescence: Cross-Sectional and Longitudinal Evaluations</article-title>. <source>Personal Soc Psychol Bull</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0146167202282011" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/0146167202282011</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granqvist</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagekull</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Longitudinal Predictions of Religious Change in Adolescence: Contributions from the Interaction of Attachment and Relationship Status</article-title>. <source>J Soc Pers Relat</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>793</fpage>–<lpage>817</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0265407503206005" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/0265407503206005</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horton</surname> <given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malloy</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment Style, Spirituality, and Depressive Symptoms Among Individuals in Substance Abuse Treatment</article-title>. <source>J Soc Serv Res</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>324</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01488376.2014.896851" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/01488376.2014.896851</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unterrainer</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ladenhauf</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallner-Liebmann</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Different Types of Religious/Spiritual Well-Being in Relation to Personality and Subjective Well-Being</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychol Relig</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10508619.2011.557003" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/10508619.2011.557003</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellison</surname> <given-names>CW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spiritual well being: Conceptualization and measurement</article-title>. <source>J Psychol Theol</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>340</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unterrainer</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Religious/Spiritual Well-Being, Personality and Mental Health: A Review of Results and Conceptual Issues</article-title>. <source>J Relig Health</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10943-012-9642-5" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10943-012-9642-5</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22965652</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledbetter</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vosler-Hunter</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>An evaluation of the research and clinical usefulness of the Spiritual Well-Being Scale</article-title>. <source>J Psychol Theol</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unterrainer</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoeggl</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neuper</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kapfhammer</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Soul darkness? Dimensions of religious/ spiritual well-being among mood-disordered inpatients compared to healthy controls</article-title>. <source>Psychopathology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000336050" xlink:type="simple">10.1159/000336050</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22797574</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gearing</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lizardi</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Religion and Suicide</article-title>. <source>J Relig Health</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>48</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10943-008-9181-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10943-008-9181-2</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19639421</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loewenthal</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cinnirella</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evdoka</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Faith conquers all?: Beliefs about the role of religious factors in coping with depression among different cultural-religious groups in the UK</article-title>. <source>Br J Med Psychol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1348/000711201160993" xlink:type="simple">10.1348/000711201160993</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassibba</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Granqvist</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costantini</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gatto</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment and God representations among lay Catholics, priests, and religious: a matched comparison study based on the Adult Attachment Interview</article-title>. <source>Dev Psychol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1753</fpage>–<lpage>1763</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/a0013772" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/a0013772</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18999336</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrenthal</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dinger</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamla</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Funken</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schauenburg</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of the German Version of the Attachment Questionnaire “Experiences in Close Relationships—Revised” (ECR−RD)</article-title>. <source>Psychother Psychosom Medizinische Psychol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1055/s−2008−1067425" xlink:type="simple">10.1055/s−2008−1067425</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unterrainer</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname> <given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ladenhauf</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallner-Liebmann</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liebmann</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name>. <article-title>MI-RSB 48: The development of a multidimensional inventory of religious-spiritual well-being</article-title>. <source>Diagnostica</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1026/0012-1924/a000001" xlink:type="simple">10.1026/0012-1924/a000001</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unterrainer</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Multidimensional Inventory for Religious/Spiritual Well-Being (MI-RSWB): Norm values for the Austrian general population</article-title>. <source>Diagnostica</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1026/0012-1924/a000077" xlink:type="simple">10.1026/0012-1924/a000077</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ankerhold</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haase</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jäger</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tögel</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrich</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The usefulness of the Brief Symptom Inventory 18 (BSI-18) in psychotherapeutic patients</article-title>. <source>Psychother Psychosom Med Psychol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1055/s-0030-1270518" xlink:type="simple">10.1055/s-0030-1270518</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21337286</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lunaa</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hortona</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Newmanb</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malloyc</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>An Empirical Study of Attachment Dimensions and Mood Disorders in Inpatient Substance Abuse Clients: The Mediating Role of Spirituality</article-title>. <source>Addict Res Theory</source>. <year>2015</year>; <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3109/16066359.2015.1119267" xlink:type="simple">10.3109/16066359.2015.1119267</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell-Sills</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barlow</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Incorporating Emotion Regulation into Conceptualizations and Treatments of Anxiety and Mood Disorders</chapter-title>. In: <name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Handbook of emotion regulation</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>. pp. <fpage>542</fpage>–<lpage>559</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowlby</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Attachment and loss, Vol. 3: Sadness and depression</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>; <year>1980</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulincer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dolev</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaver</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Attachment-related strategies during thought suppression: ironic rebounds and vulnerable self-representations</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>940</fpage>–<lpage>956</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.87.6.940" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/0022-3514.87.6.940</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15598116</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Unterrainer</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ladenhauf</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moazedi</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallner-liebmann</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dimensions of Religious / Spiritual Well-Being and their relation to Personality and Psychological Well-Being</article-title>. <source>Pers Individ Dif</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2010.03.032" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.paid.2010.03.032</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Espíndola</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blay</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Long term remission of anorexia nervosa: factors involved in the outcome of female patients</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e56275</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0056275" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0056275</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23460796</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bos</surname> <given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snippe</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Jonge</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeronimus</surname> <given-names>BF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Preserving Subjective Wellbeing in the Face of Psychopathology: Buffering Effects of Personal Strengths and Resources</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>e0150867</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0150867" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0150867</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26963923</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granqvist</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivarsson</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broberg</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagekull</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Examining relations among attachment, religiosity, and new age spirituality using the Adult Attachment Interview</article-title>. <source>Dev Psychol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>590</fpage>–<lpage>601</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0012-1649.43.3.590" xlink:type="simple">10.1037/0012-1649.43.3.590</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17484573</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stein</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname> <given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fonagy</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>What do adult attachment scales measure?</article-title> <source>Bull Menninger Clin</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9524379</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inferences about mental states</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>364</volume>: <fpage>1309</fpage>–<lpage>1316</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2008.0318" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rstb.2008.0318</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19528012</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Norenzayan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gervais</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trzesniewski</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mentalizing deficits constrain belief in a personal God</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e36880</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0036880" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0036880</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22666332</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jack</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyatzis</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></name>. <article-title>Why Do You Believe in God? Relationships between Religious Belief, Analytic Thinking, Mentalizing and Moral Concern</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>e0149989</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0149989" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0149989</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27008093</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0158069.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McFadden</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Web and the Quilt: Alternatives to the Heroic Journey Toward Spiritual Development</article-title>. <source>J Adult Dev</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1011334411081" xlink:type="simple">10.1023/A:1011334411081</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>