<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-06671</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062962</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Life course epidemiology</subject><subject>Social epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subject>Retrospective studies</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Lifecourse epidemiology</subject><subject>Social epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Nephrology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Non-clinical medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care policy</subject><subj-group><subject>Health risk analysis</subject><subject>Health statistics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Health informatics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Public health</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavioral and social aspects of health</subject><subject>Tobacco control</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ethnic groups</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Smoking and Risk of Kidney Failure in the Singapore Chinese Health Study</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Smoking and Kidney Failure in Singapore</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Aizhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>Woon-Puay</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>Khuan Yew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Jian-Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jafar</surname><given-names>Tazeen Hasan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>National Registry of Diseases Office, Health Promotion Board, Singapore, Singapore</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Office of Clinical Sciences, Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School, Singapore, Singapore</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Epidemiology, Saw Swee Hock School of Public Health, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Division of Cancer Control and Population Sciences, University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Epidemiology, Graduate School of Public Health, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><addr-line>Laboratory of Cardiovascular and Renal Risk Reduction, Health Services &amp; Systems Research, Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School, Singapore, Singapore</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Remuzzi</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Mario Negri Institute for Pharmacological Research and Azienda Ospedaliera Ospedali Riuniti di Bergamo, Italy</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">tazeen.jafar@duke-nus.edu.sg</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>All authors declare that there are no competing interests.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: THJ. Performed the experiments: THJ WPK. Analyzed the data: AJ THJ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: WPK KYC JY. Wrote the paper: AJ WPK KYC JY THJ.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<elocation-id>e62962</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Jin et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract><sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>The relationship between smoking and risk of kidney failure, especially in people of Chinese origin, is not clear. We analyzed data from the Singapore Chinese Health Study to investigate whether smoking increases the risk of kidney failure.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Methods</title>
<p>The Singapore Chinese Health Study is a population-based cohort of 63,257 Chinese adults enrolled between 1993 and 1998. Information on smoking status was collected at baseline. Incidence of kidney failure was identified via record linkage with the nationwide Singapore Renal Registry until 2008. Kidney failure was defined by one of the following: 1) serum creatinine level of more than or equal to 500 µmol/l (5.7 mg/dl), 2) estimated glomerular filtration rate of less than 15 ml/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup>, 3) undergoing hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis, 4) undergone kidney transplantation. Cox proportional hazard regression analysis was performed for the outcome of kidney failure after adjusting for age, education, dialect, herbal medications, body mass index, sex, physician-diagnosed hypertension and diabetes mellitus.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Results</title>
<p>The mean age of subjects was 55.6 years at baseline, and 44% were men. Overall 30.6% were ever smokers (current or former) at baseline. A total of 674 incident cases of kidney failure occurred during a median follow-up of 13.3 years. Among men, smokers had a significant increase in the adjusted risk of kidney failure [hazard ratio (HR): 1.29; 95% CI: 1.02–1.64] compared to never smokers. There was a strong dose-dependent association between number of years of smoking and kidney failure, (p for trend = 0.011). The risk decreased with prolonged cessation (quitting ≥10 years since baseline). The number of women smokers was too few for conclusive relationship.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Limitation</title>
<p>Information on baseline kidney function was not available.</p>
</sec><sec>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Cigarette smoking is associated with increased risk of kidney failure among Chinese men. The risk appears to be dose- and duration-dependent and modifiable after long duration of cessation.</p>
</sec></abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The study was funded by National Institutes of Health, USA (RO1 CA55069, R35 CA53890, R01 CA80205, and R01 CA144034). No funding bodies had any role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Kidney failure is a rising public health problem globally with high morbidity and reduced quality of life. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Evans1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Lash1">[3]</xref>. The rapid increase in number of people with kidney failure, including those requiring or nearing the need for expensive renal replacement therapy, is in part due to the aging populations coupled with prolonged exposure to risk factors for kidney failure. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Levey1">[4]</xref> Smoking is recognized as one of the leading causes of preventable deaths globally predominantly from cardiovascular disease and cancer. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Lopez1">[5]</xref> Evidence from European origin population indicates that smoking may be associated with progression of chronic kidney disease (CKD), especially in men. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Hallan1">[6]</xref> However, there is scarcity of evidence on the relationship of smoking with kidney failure in non-European origin populations. Moreover, it is not known whether any potential relationship between smoking and kidney failure is dose-dependent, and, if so, is it modifiable. Asian populations have been shown to have greater susceptibility to CKD than European counterparts by virtue of a greater burden of many key risk factors, and there is evidence that CKD progresses to kidney failure faster in Asians. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Fischbacher1">[7]</xref> Furthermore, the burden of kidney failure is increasing rapidly in many Asian countries where implementation of tobacco control policies has been challenging. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Levey1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Zhang1">[8]</xref> However, it is unclear how smoking plays a role in the onset of kidney failure in Asians.</p>
<p>A clear understanding of the nature of association between smoking and kidney failure would be important for enhancing the understanding the epidemiology of CKD and for boosting smoking prevention and cessation efforts, especially among individuals at high risk for kidney failure in Asia.</p>
<p>We therefore analyzed data from the Singapore Chinese Health Study linked with the Singapore Renal Registry which maintains a record of all patients with kidney failure, treated with renal replacement therapy or managed conservatively, with the following objectives: 1) To determine the association between cigarette smoking status at baseline (former or current) with risk of kidney failure; 2) to assess whether there is a dose-dependent relationship between smoking intensity and duration and kidney failure risk, and 3) to assess whether quitting smoking reduces the risk of kidney failure.</p>
<p>We hypothesized that smoking would increase the risk of kidney failure; and that this risk would be dose dependent and modifiable with smoking cessation in men of Chinese origin.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Study Population</title>
<p>The Singapore Chinese Health Study is a population-based prospective cohort established between April 1993 and December 1998 through the recruitment of 63,257 Chinese men (n = 27,959) and women (n = 35,298), who were aged 45–74 years, and residing in public housing estates, where 86% of Singapore resided at that time. All participants belonged to one of the two major dialect groups, Hokkien or Cantonese, who originated from two contiguous prefectures in southern China. At recruitment, after obtaining informed consent, each study subject was interviewed in person by a trained interviewer using a structured questionnaire, which focused on history of tobacco and alcohol use, current diet, current physical activity, menstrual and reproductive history in women, medical history, and family history of cancer. Current diet was assessed using a validated 165-item, semi-quantitative food frequency questionnaire. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Hankin1">[9]</xref> The Institutional Review Board at the National University of Singapore approved this study. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Exposure Assessment</title>
<p>For cigarette smoking, the study population was divided into never, former and current smokers based on their choice of three possible responses to the following question, “Have you ever smoked at least one cigarette a day for 1 year or longer”. Subjects who answered “no” were classified as “never-smokers”, those who answered “yes, but I quit smoking” were classified as “former smokers”, and those who answered “yes, and I currently smoke” were classified as “current smokers”. Ever smokers (former or current) were then asked about age at smoking initiation (four categories: less than 15, 15–19, 20–29, and 30 years or older); number of cigarettes smoked per day (six categories: 6 or less, 7–12, 13–22, 23–32, 33–42, and 43 or more); and duration of smoking (five categories; less than 10, 10–19, 20–29, 30–39, 40 or more years). Former smokers were also asked how long they had quit smoking (seven categories; less than 1 year, 1–2 years, 3–4 years, 5–9 years, 10–14 years, 15–19 years, 20 or more years).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Case Ascertainment</title>
<p>Identification of incident kidney failure and deaths among cohort members was accomplished by record linkage analysis of the cohort database with the population-based Singapore Renal Registry. The nationwide renal registry has been in place since 1993 and has been shown to be comprehensive in its recording of kidney failure cases since 1999. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Mudur1">[10]</xref> The registry defines kidney failure by at least one of these criteria: 1) serum creatinine level of more than or equal to 500 µmol/l (5.7 mg/dl) 2) estimated glomerular filtration rate (GFR) of less than 15 ml/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> (based on either the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) Study equation, Cockcroft Gault equation, or 24 hour creatinine clearance) 3) undergoing hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis, 4) had undergone kidney transplant. All cases are then classified by disease etiology based on review of medical records. As of April 2008, only 27 cases were known to be lost to follow-up due to migration out of Singapore. As of 31 Dec 2008, 94 participants had kidney failure diagnosed before recruitment and were excluded from the analysis. A total of 674 incident kidney failure cases were identified from the remaining 62,583 participants included in the analyses. Among them, 56.9% had diabetic nephropathy, 15.7% primary glomerulonephritis and 12.7% nephrosclerosis.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Since the development of kidney failure follows a chronic process over time, we examined baseline characteristics of the entire cohort by duration of smoking for men and women. For each study subject, person-years were counted from the date of baseline interview to the date of kidney failure diagnosis, the date of death, date of last contact (for the few subjects who migrated out of Singapore) or December 31, 2008, whichever occurred first. The incidence rate of kidney failure was computed and 95% CI were generated using Poisson distribution.</p>
<p>Univariable and multivariable regression models were constructed and Cox proportional hazards regression analysis was performed to examine the associations between cigarette smoking and risk of developing kidney failure. Deaths from competing causes (ie non kidney failure deaths) were censored in the time to event analysis for the primary outcome of kidney failure. We first examined the association of current and former smokers, and number of cigarettes smoked with kidney failure in the entire cohort. The number of cigarettes smoked was grouped into 3 categories of 12 or less per day, 13–22/day, or 23 or more per day. Since studies in other populations have provided sex-specific estimates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Hallan1">[6]</xref>, our subsequent main analyses were stratified for men and women. To increase power of association with smoking status, we grouped former and current smokers as “ever” smokers. The duration of smoking (&lt;19 years; 19–39 years, 40 years or more) and time since quitting (quit for 1 year or less, quit &gt;1–9 years, and quit for 10 years or more) were regrouped into 3 categories each per distribution of data. The associations were measured by hazard ratios (HRs) and their corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) and p values (two-sided).</p>
<p>In the analysis considering smoking and kidney failure, the model included the following baseline covariates: age, body mass index, dialect (Hokkein, Cantonese), education level, history of physician diagnosed hypertension, diabetes, known heart disease or stroke, alcohol use and intake of ginseng. These factors are known to be associated with kidney failure in other studies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Klag1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Lai1">[12]</xref> For the analysis by duration of smoking and smoking cessation, we performed tests for trend by entering ordinal categorical variables as continuous variables in the Cox regression models. We also tested for interaction between age and duration of smoking, number of cigarettes smoked with age at initiation of smoking. We performed analyses for the whole population and also for men and women separately. Sensitivity analysis were performed after retaining the original categories of smoking status as in the questionnaire for years of smoking (five categories) and quit smoking (seven categories), and after excluding kidney failure cases occurred within first 5 years post-enrollment, to reduce the impact of outcome on the change of smoking behavior, as above.</p>
<p>All regression analyses were conducted using SAS statistical software version 9.2 (SAS institute, Cary, NC). Two-sided <italic>P</italic>s &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Of the 63163 subjects, 44.1% were men. Among men, 41.9% were never smokers, and 8.3%, 30.3%, and 19.6% smoked for &lt;19, 19–39, and 40 years or more, respectively. Among women, 91.1% were never smokers, and 1.5%, 3.6%, and 3.6% smoked for &lt;19, 19–39, and 40 years or more. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t001">Table 1</xref> shows baseline characteristics of the participants by duration of smoking. Men who smoked were more likely to be less educated, consume alcohol, have diabetes, heart disease and stroke, and these associations were stronger with longer duration of smoking. During a median follow-up of 13.3 year, and 774,434 person years, 674 (1%) developed incident kidney failure with an overall crude incidence rate of 0.87 (0.81–0.94) per 1000 person years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t002">Table 2</xref>), and age-standardized incidence rate of 0.83 per 1000 person years.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0062962-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Baseline characteristic of individuals by smoking status in Singapore Chinese Health Study.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062962-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N = 63163</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Men N = 27907</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Women N = 35256</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Men ever smokers(years of smoking)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Women ever smokers(years of smoking)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never smokerN = 11706</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; = 40 yearsN = 5491</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20–39 yearsN = 8467</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 19 yearsN = 2243</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never smokerN = 32153</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; = 40 yearsN = 1290</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20–39 yearsN = 1274</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 19 yearsN = 539</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P for trend</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age at recruitment (mean, SD)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5 (8.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.38 (7.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.38 (6.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.61 (7.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.37 (7.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.83 (7.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.07 (5.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.10 (7.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.77 (8.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Education %</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> No formal education</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17308 (27.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">877 (7.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1197 (21.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">827 (9.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (7.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12341 (38.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">897 (69.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">740 (58.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">273 (50.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Primary</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28001 (44.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5051 (43.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3433 (62.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4698 (55.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1097 (48.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12725 (39.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">345 (26.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444 (34.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208 (38.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Second &amp;above</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17854 (28.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5778 (49.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">861 (15.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2942 (34.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">990 (44.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7087 (22.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (3.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (7.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (10.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dialect %</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Cantonese</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29239 (46.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5756 (49.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2039 (37.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3414 (40.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1111 (49.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15444 (48.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">611 (47.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">569 (44.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295 (54.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Hokkein</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33924 (53.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5950 (50.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3452 (62.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5053 (59.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1132 (50.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16709 (52.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679 (52.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">705 (55.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244 (45.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>History of hypertension %</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14985 (23.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3062 (26.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1159 (21.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1667 (19.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">633 (28.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7754 (24.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">271 (21.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">301 (23.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 (25.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>History of diabetes %</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5673 (9.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1005 (8.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">510 (9.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">686 (8.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215 (9.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2850 (8.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172 (13.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171 (13.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (11.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.641</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>History of heart disease%</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2589 (4.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">449 (3.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393 (7.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">423 (5.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (4.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1028 (3.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (7.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (5.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (5.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.194</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>History of stroke %</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">947 (1.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (1.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164 (3.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (1.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (1.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">384 (1.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (2.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (1.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.216</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alcohol</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Never</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55853 (88.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9848 (84.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4281 (77.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6255 (73.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1771 (78.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30831 (95.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1197 (92.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1171 (91.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">499 (92.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.421</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Weekly</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5105 (8.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1486 (12.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">690 (12.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1423 (16.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354 (15.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1017 (3.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (3.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (5.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (4.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Daily</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2205 (3.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372 (3.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">520 (9.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">789 (9.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 (5.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">305 (1.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (3.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (3.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (3.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BMI (mean, SD)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1 (3.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3 (3.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2 (3.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9 (3.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5 (3.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3 (3.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6 (3.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0 (3.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2 (3.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ginseng</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold> Never</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52582 (83.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10009 (85.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4755 (86.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7258 (85.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1866 (83.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26142 (81.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1082 (83.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1044 (82.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">426 (79.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1–3/month</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2884 (4.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">442 (3.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233 (4.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339 (4.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (4.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1587 (4.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (5.7)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (5.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (5.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1–3/week</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6039 (9.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">963 (8.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (7.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">686 (8.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214 (9.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3482 (10.8)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103 (8.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (10.3)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (12.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4–6/week and more</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1658 (2.6)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">292 (2.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (2.0)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184 (2.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (2.5)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">942 (2.9)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (2.4)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (2.2)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (3.1)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0062962-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Incidence of Kidney Failure by Smoking Status in Singapore Chinese Health Study.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062962-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Men ever smoker (years of smoking)</td>
<td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Women ever smoker(years of smoking)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never smoker</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; = 40 years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20–39 years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 19 years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never smoker</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; = 40 years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20–39 years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; = 19 years</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Persons</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63163</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11706</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5491</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8467</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2243</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32153</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1290</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1274</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">539</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Person-years</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">774434.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144629.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56769.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102753.7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27097.8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407116.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14116.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15498.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6452.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Median of follow-up</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Kidney Failure (N)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">674</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">327</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Incidence rate per 1000 py</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.870 (0.805–0.936)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.802 (0.656–0.948)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.268 (0.975–1.561)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.866 (0.686–1.046)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.996 (0.621–1.372)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.803 (0.716–0.890)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.063 (0.525–1.600)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.355 (0.775–1.934)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.085 (0.281–1.889)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>The hazard rates (95% CI) of kidney failure by smoking status are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t003">Tables 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t004">4</xref>, and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t005">5</xref>. In the entire cohort, smoking was associated with increased risk of kidney failure [hazard ratio (HR), 1.42; 95% confidence interval (CI): 1.07–1.87] for former smokers, and [HR (95% CI): 1.28 (0.98–1.65)] for current smokers: [p for trend = 0.04], adjusted for age, body mass index, dialect, education level, history of physician diagnosed hypertension, diabetes, known heart disease or stroke, alcohol use and intake of ginseng compared to never smokers. The risk increased with increased number of cigarettes (p for trend = 0.03) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t003">Table 3</xref>). Among men, ever smokers had a significant increase in the risk of kidney failure [adjusted HR (95% CI): (1.29 1.02–1.64)], compared to never smokers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t004">Table 4</xref>). There was a strong dose-dependent association between duration of smoking and kidney failure (p for trend = 0.011). Men who had smoked for 40 years or more at baseline had significantly increased adjusted risk of kidney failure compared to men who never smoked [HR (95% CI): 1.56 (1.23–2.21)]. These relationships seemed to be similar in women with unadjusted hazard rate of kidney failure was [HR (95% CI)] 1.51 (1.10–2.08)] in ever versus never smokers, and with increasing duration of smoking (p for trend 0.01), albeit the adjusted risks were not statistically significant. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t005">Table 5</xref>, the risk of kidney failure remained significantly elevated even 1–9 years after smoking cessation. However, the adjusted HR decreased to 1.02 at 10 years or greater after quitting. A similar pattern was observed in women, albeit no significant association was observed in the adjusted model due to small case numbers among women.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0062962-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Risk of Kidney Failure by Smoking Status in Singapore Chinese Cohort Study.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062962-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking status</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number Kidney Failure</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">*</xref>Adjusted HR (95% CI)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Never smoker (n = 43859)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">443</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Former smoker (n = 6976)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 (1.07–1.87)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Current smoker (n = 12327)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (0.98–1.65)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P trend</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Never smoker (n = 43859)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">443</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ever smoked &lt; = 12 cigarettes/day (n = 7693)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (1.00–1.61)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ever smoked 13–22 cigarettes/day (7331)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.88–1.50)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ever smoked &gt; = 23 cigarettes/day (n = 4280)</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (1.01–1.84)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P trend</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>*</label><p>Model adjusted for age, body mass index, dialect (Hokkein, Cantonese), education level, history of physician diagnosed hypertension, diabetes, known heart disease or stroke, alcohol use and intake of ginseng.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0062962-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Unadjusted &amp; Adjusted Risk of Kidney Failure in Chinese Men and Women by Smoking Status.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062962-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Men</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Women</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking Status</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unadjusted Hazard Ratio (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref>Multivariable Adjusted HazardRatio (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unadjusted Hazard Ratio (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref>Multivariable Adjusted Hazard Ratio (95% CI)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Never vs</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ever</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (1.01–1.61)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 (1.02–1.64)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51 (1.10–2.08)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.85–1.62)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Never Smoker vs</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Duration of smoking &lt;19 years</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (0.83–1.91)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 (0.77–1.78)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (0.65–2.90)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (0.56–2.51)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Duration of smoking 20–39 years</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.82–1.43)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (0.90–1.58)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 (1.09–2.64)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 (0.82–2.00)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Duration of smoking &gt;40 years</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 (1.23–2.21)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 (1.13–2.14)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 (0.81–2.29)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.62–1.76)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P trend</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.435</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Never smoker was defined as those who have not ever smoked at least one cigarette a day for 1 year or longer.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Ever smoker was defined as those who have ever smoked at least one cigarette a day for 1 year or longer.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>*</label><p>Model adjusted for age, body mass index, dialect (Hokkein, Cantonese), education level, history of physician diagnosed hypertension, diabetes, known heart disease or stroke, alcohol use and intake of ginseng.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0062962-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption>
<title>Association of smoking cessation with Kidney Failure in Singapore Chinese Health Study.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0062962-t005-5" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0062962.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking Status</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Person years</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number Kidney Failure</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unadjusted Hazard Ratio (95% CI)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multivariable **Adjusted Hazard Ratio (95% CI)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Men</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Never Smoker vs.</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11705</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144623</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quit smoking &lt;1 year</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20633</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.73–1.92)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (0.77–2.08)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quit smoking 1–9 years</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1856</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26472</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17 (1.54–3.06)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 (1.29–2.60)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quit smoking &gt;10 years</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2333</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37880</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 (0.95–1.95)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.71–1.47)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P trend</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3301</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Women</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Never Smoker vs.</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32152</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407106</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">326</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quit smoking &lt;1 year</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">234</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2636</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 (0.46–4.50)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 (0.40–3.91)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quit smoking 1–9 years</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">353</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3846</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 (1.55–5.82)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 (0.83–3.14)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quit smoking &gt;10 years</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4929</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 (0.55–3.20)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.32–1.92)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P trend</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label>*</label><p>Model adjusted for age, body mass index, dialect (Hokkein, Cantonese), education level, history of physician diagnosed hypertension, diabetes, known heart disease or stroke, alcohol use and intake of ginseng.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Finally, the sensitivity analysis revealed consistent results with respect to the main associations as well as the dose dependency of the relationship between smoking and kidney failure, and the threshold of 10 years since quitting for the risk to reduce substantially.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our in-depth analysis data on 63,163 subjects followed over a median of 13.3 years with 674 incident kidney failure in the Singapore Chinese Health Study showed an increased risk of kidney failure that correlated with duration of smoking in men. The adjusted risk estimate decreased in men who quit smoking after prolonged cessation, although it was still significantly elevated in those who had quit for less than 10 years. The direction of relationship between smoking and kidney failure were similar in women however the numbers were too small to be conclusive.</p>
<p>Our findings in Chinese men are consistent with observations of the Multiple Risk Factor Intervention Trial (MRFIT) which studied 332,544 men and documented that smoking was significantly associated with an increased risk for kidney failure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Klag1">[11]</xref>. Our study is novel in demonstrating the dose-relationship between smoking and kidney failure in non-European origin population (unadjusted p trend 0.007, adjusted p trend = 0.01). This association has been previously documented between number of cigarettes smoked and albuminuria and decline in kidney function, however not with the hard outcome of kidney failure. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-PintoSietsma1">[13]</xref> Our results are also among the first to suggest that prolonged smoking cessation &gt;10 years since baseline may reduce this risk back to the level of a non-smoker (HR = 1.02 (0.71–1.47) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t005">Table 5</xref>, column 4, row 1). This finding is consistent with those recently reported in Europeans in the HUNT Study. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Hallan1">[6]</xref> However, we did not find a clear graded trend with increasing years of smoking cessation and kidney failure (adjusted trend p = 0.22) indicating the possibility of a threshold duration. Overall, these findings support the notion of shared risk factors for CVD and kidney disease. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Cravedi1">[14]</xref> However, they also contrast with the effects of smoking on CVD which have been shown to reduce immediately within 2–3 years of smoking cessation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Doll1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Ikeda1">[17]</xref>While we are unable to evaluate the pathophysiology of the association, smoking is known to affect endothelial cell function and nitric oxide production leading to vasoconstriction and vascular damage. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Tsuchiya1">[18]</xref> It is highly conceivable that these mechanisms contribute, at least in part, to the progressive renal damage associated with smoking.</p>
<p>It is also important to underscore that the incidence of kidney failure (674 cases in a cohort of 63,163 over 13.4 years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0062962-t002">Table 2</xref>)) is higher in our study than previously reported in European origin populations such as the MRFIT (814 individuals developed kidney failure among a cohort of 332,544 men over 16 years), HUNT, and other studies in European-origin populations, and consistent with high incidence of kidney failure reported in the Southeast Asian population in Taiwan. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-McAlister1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Hwang1">[20]</xref> It remains to be studied whether this variation is due to a greater prevalence, faster progression of CKD, or both, or perhaps improved survival from competing causes in the Chinese population with a different sociodemographic profile than their Western counterparts. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Muntner1">[21]</xref> Nevertheless our findings indicate that smoking contributes to the burden of kidney failure.</p>
<p>The major strengths of our findings are the large, representative, population based cohort with well documented information on smoking status linked with a robust renal registry, and all results regarding key relationships with smoking status (dose response with regard to duration and intensity) were consistent in direction in sensitivity analysis in the entire cohort. A limitation of the study is the lack of information on baseline kidney function including serum creatinine or albuminuria, and non-kidney failure deaths were censored in the analysis. This precluded evaluation of the effect of smoking on other causes (especially cardiovascular deaths) in earlier stages on CKD. Clearly such a relationship will magnify the detrimental effect of smoking across the spectrum of CKD as smoking has been shown to predict CVD and cancer deaths in this cohort. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Lim1">[22]</xref> However, our main objective was to determine the relationship of smoking with kidney failure which we were able to demonstrate. Second, data on reno-protective antihypertensive medications including blockers of renin-angiotensin, and reduction in blood pressure or albuminuria during follow-up were not available. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Jafar1">[23]</xref> We were therefore not able to determine any potential interaction between these factors with smoking status on kidney failure. However, our multivariable model accounted for hypertension and diabetes at baseline, both leading causes of kidney failure, as well as predictors of progression. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Klag1">[11]</xref> A third limitation is the possibility that the observed relationship between smoking and kidney failure is confounded by unmeasured social determinant (household income, neighborhood poverty index) including access to healthcare known to be associated with kidney failure. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Powe1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Hossain1">[27]</xref> Nevertheless, the reduction in risk of kidney failure with smoking cessation is highly suggestive of an independent predictive and causal nature of the association. Finally the number of women smokers was too low to detect any significant associations, and it is possible that clinically meaningful interactions (eg with sociodemographic factors) remained undetected. Future research on larger pooled data may provide further valuable insights in potential heterogeneity of the relationship of smoking with kidney failure in these subgroups.</p>
<p>In summary, our results on analysis of the Singapore Chinese cohort indicate a strong predictive association of ever smoking with kidney failure, which increases with the duration of smoking. This risk reduces back to the level of a non-smoker only after very prolonged duration of smoking cessation. Our findings have tremendous implications for public policy globally, especially in Southeast Asian countries and China. The number of people with kidney failure in this region is increasing rapidly with aging populations. Despite the global initiative of the World Health Assembly and ratification of the Framework Convention on Tobacco Control (FCTC), over 1 billion people smoke globally, a substantial proportion of the population of Chinese origin is exposed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Yach1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0062962-Yang1">[29]</xref> Our results suggest that if left unchecked, a further escalation in the number of people with kidney failure is expected. Immediate action is therefore needed for intensifying tobacco control efforts through legislative action, taxation, public education, collaborative partnership to reduce the supply and demand of tobacco and provision of smoking cessation services, and targeted intervention for individuals at high risk of kidney failure.</p>
</sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank Siew-Hong Low of the National University of Singapore for supervising the field work of the Singapore Chinese Health Study and Renwei Wang for maintenance of the cohort database. We also thank the Singapore Renal Registry for assistance with the identification of kidney failure and mortality outcomes via database linkages. Finally, we acknowledge the founding, long-standing Principal Investigator of the Singapore Chinese Health Study – Mimi C. Yu. Presentation of this work: The abstract based on this work has been presented at the 1st International Public Health Conference in Singapore September 2012, and at the 45th Annual Kidney Week in November, 2012 at San Diego, CA.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Evans1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Manninen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garrison</surname><given-names>LP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blagg</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gutman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>The quality of life of patients with end-stage renal disease. N Engl J Med</article-title>. <volume>312(9)</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-KurellaTamura1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurella Tamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Covinsky</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chertow</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landefeld</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Functional status of elderly adults before and after initiation of dialysis. N Engl J Med</article-title>. <volume>361(16)</volume>: <fpage>1539</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Lash1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gadegbeku</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Quality of life in the African American Study of Kidney Disease and Hypertension: effects of blood pressure management. Am J Kidney Dis</article-title>. <volume>47(6)</volume>: <fpage>956</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Levey1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levey</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coresh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Chronic kidney disease. Lancet</article-title>. <volume>379(9811)</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Lopez1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ezzati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Global and regional burden of disease and risk factors, 2001: systematic analysis of population health data</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <volume>367(9524)</volume>: <fpage>1747</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Hallan1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallan</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Smoking is a risk factor in the progression to kidney failure. Kidney Int</article-title>. <volume>80(5)</volume>: <fpage>516</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Fischbacher1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischbacher</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhopal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Unwin</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Microalbuminuria is more frequent in South Asian than in European origin populations: a comparative study in Newcastle, UK. Diabet Med</article-title>. <volume>20(1)</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Zhang1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Prevalence of chronic kidney disease in China: a cross-sectional survey. Lancet</article-title>. <volume>379(9818)</volume>: <fpage>815</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Hankin1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hankin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stram</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Singapore Chinese Health Study: development, validation, and calibration of the quantitative food frequency questionnaire. Nutr Cancer</article-title>. <volume>39(2)</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Mudur1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mudur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>India launches national rural health mission. BMJ</article-title>. <volume>330(7497)</volume>: <fpage>920</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Klag1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klag</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whelton</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neaton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brancati</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Blood pressure and end-stage renal disease in men. N Engl J Med</article-title>. <volume>334(1)</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Lai1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Increased risks of chronic kidney disease associated with prescribed Chinese herbal products suspected to contain aristolochic acid. Nephrology (Carlton)</article-title>. <volume>14(2)</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-PintoSietsma1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto-Sietsma</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hillege</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Zeeuw</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Smoking is related to albuminuria and abnormal renal function in nondiabetic persons. Ann Intern Med</article-title>. <volume>133(8)</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Cravedi1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cravedi P, Remuzzi G (2008) Treating the kidney to cure the heart. Kidney Int Suppl. (111): S2–3.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Doll1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doll</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Mortality in relation to smoking: 20 years' observations on male British doctors. Br Med J</article-title>. <volume>2(6051)</volume>: <fpage>1525</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Rosenberg1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Decline in the risk of myocardial infarction among women who stop smoking. N Engl J Med</article-title>. <volume>322(4)</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Ikeda1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ninomiya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuhara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Smoking cessation improves mortality in Japanese men: the Hisayama study. Tob Control</article-title>. <volume>21(4)</volume>: <fpage>416</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Tsuchiya1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shindo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Smoking a single cigarette rapidly reduces combined concentrations of nitrate and nitrite and concentrations of antioxidants in plasma. Circulation</article-title>. <volume>105(10)</volume>: <fpage>1155</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-McAlister1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McAlister</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Covvey</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wigle</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Randomised controlled trial of computer assisted management of hypertension in primary care. Br Med J (Clin Res Ed)</article-title>. <volume>293(6548)</volume>: <fpage>670</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Hwang1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Epidemiology, impact and preventive care of chronic kidney disease in Taiwan. Nephrology (Carlton)</article-title>. <volume>15</volume> Suppl 2<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Muntner1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muntner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coresh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powe</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klag</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The contribution of increased diabetes prevalence and improved myocardial infarction and stroke survival to the increase in treated end-stage renal disease. J Am Soc Nephrol</article-title>. <volume>14(6)</volume>: <fpage>1568</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Lim1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lim SH, Tai BC, Yuan JM, Yu MC, Koh WP (2011) Smoking cessation and mortality among middle-aged and elderly Chinese in Singapore: the Singapore Chinese Health Study. Tob Control.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Jafar1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jafar</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maschio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Progression of chronic kidney disease: the role of blood pressure control, proteinuria, and angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibition: a patient-level meta-analysis. Ann Intern Med</article-title>. <volume>139(4)</volume>: <fpage>244</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Powe1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Powe</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melamed</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Racial disparities in the optimal delivery of chronic kidney disease care. Med Clin North Am</article-title>. <volume>89(3)</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Johnson1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sidelinger</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palinkas</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Ethnic differences and treatment trajectories in chronic kidney disease. J Health Care Poor Underserved</article-title>. <volume>19(1)</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Xue1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eggers</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agodoa</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Longitudinal study of racial and ethnic differences in developing end-stage renal disease among aged medicare beneficiaries. J Am Soc Nephrol</article-title>. <volume>18(4)</volume>: <fpage>1299</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Hossain1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goyder</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rigby</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>El Nahas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>CKD and poverty: a growing global challenge. Am J Kidney Dis</article-title>. <volume>53(1)</volume>: <fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Yach1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>WHO Framework Convention on Tobacco Control. Lancet</article-title>. <source>2003</source> <volume>361(9357)</volume>: <fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0062962-Yang1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Findings from 2010 Global Adult Tobacco Survey: implementation of MPOWER policy in China. Biomed Environ Sci</article-title>. <volume>23(6)</volume>: <fpage>422</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>