<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-01170</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017372</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Cognitive neuroscience</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Motor reactions</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Mathematics</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Applied mathematics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Game theory</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Diagnostic medicine</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Clinical neurophysiology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Electromyography</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Economic anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Economics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Economic geography</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Economic man</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Economic anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Geography</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Economic geography</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Economic man</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Psychology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Experimental psychology</subject>
              <subject>Social psychology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Sociology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Social research</subject>
              <subject>Social theory</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Physiology</subject>
          <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
          <subject>Mathematics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Electromyographic Activity of Hand Muscles in a Motor Coordination
                    Game: Effect of Incentive Scheme and Its Relation with Social
                    Capital</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">EMG and Social Capital in Coordination
                    Games</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Censolo</surname>
            <given-names>Roberto</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Craighero</surname>
            <given-names>Laila</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ponti</surname>
            <given-names>Giovanni</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Rizzo</surname>
            <given-names>Leonzio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Canto</surname>
            <given-names>Rosario</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Fadiga</surname>
            <given-names>Luciano</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>University of Ferrara, Ferrara, Italy</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>The Italian Institute of Technology, Genova, Italy</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gribble</surname>
            <given-names>Paul</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The University of Western Ontario, Canada</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">fdl@unife.it</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LF RC. Performed the experiments: LC
                        RC LF LR GP. Analyzed the data: LR RC GP RC LF. Wrote the paper: RC LF
                        LC.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e17372</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Censolo et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
                terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>A vast body of social and cognitive psychology studies in humans reports
                        evidence that external rewards, typically monetary ones, undermine intrinsic
                        motivation. These findings challenge the standard selfish-rationality
                        assumption at the core of economic reasoning. In the present work we aimed
                        at investigating whether the different modulation of a given monetary reward
                        automatically and unconsciously affects effort and performance of
                        participants involved in a game devoid of visual and verbal interaction and
                        without any perspective-taking activity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title>
          <p>Twelve pairs of participants were submitted to a simple motor coordination
                        game while recording the electromyographic activity of First Dorsal
                        Interosseus (FDI), the muscle mainly involved in the task. EMG data show a
                        clear effect of alternative rewards strategies on subjects' motor
                        behavior. Moreover, participants' stock of relevant past social
                        experiences, measured by a specifically designed questionnaire, was
                        significantly correlated with EMG activity, showing that only low social
                        capital subjects responded to monetary incentives consistently with a
                        standard rationality prediction.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions/Significance</title>
          <p>Our findings show that the effect of extrinsic motivations on performance may
                        arise outside social contexts involving complex cognitive processes due to
                        conscious perspective-taking activity. More importantly, the peculiar
                        performance of low social capital individuals, in agreement with standard
                        economic reasoning, adds to the knowledge of the circumstances that makes
                        the crowding out/in of intrinsic motivation likely to occur. This may help
                        in improving the prediction and accuracy of economic models and reconcile
                        this puzzling effect of external incentives with economic theory.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work has been accomplished with the contribution of the European Community
                    Grants Robot-Cub and Poeticon and of the Fondazione Cassa di Risparmio di
                    Ferrara. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis,
                    decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="9"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The assumption of <italic>Homo Oeconomicus</italic> at the basis of economic
                reasoning entails the prediction that individuals should respond to incentives,
                altering costs and benefits associated to available choices, in an manner consistent
                with a self-regarding behavior. Since the early 70's , however, a large body of
                empirical research undertaken by social and cognitive psychologists shows that in
                many social contexts external rewards, typically monetary ones, affect behavior in a
                direction opposite to that predicted by a standard selfish-rationality argument.
                This evidence strongly supports the view that <italic>external motivations</italic>
                often undermine <italic>intrinsic motivations</italic>, which <italic>per
                    se</italic> sustain effort and performance, resulting ineffective or even
                counterproductive. This phenomenon has been termed “The Hidden Cost of
                Reward” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Lepper1">[1]</xref>,
                “Corruption Effect” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Deci1">[2]</xref> and, more recently, “Cognitive Evaluation
                Theory” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Deci2">[3]</xref> or
                “Motivation Crowding Theory” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Frey1">[4]</xref>.</p>
      <p>This evidence has been largely neglected by economists. However, starting from the
                late Nineties, a growing number of empirical studies have coped with this puzzling
                phenomenon. This body of research substantially confirms the relevance of the
                Motivation Crowding Effect (MCE), both from laboratory experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Fehr1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Bohnet1">[6]</xref> and field
                research <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Gneezy1">[7]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Cardenas1">[9]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Prompted by these empirical results, several studies have attempted to reconcile
                economic and psychological views, developing formal models that clarify the
                conditions under which the MCE may arise. This body of research extends and refines
                along two directions a basic strategic setting, in which contractual relationships
                are vitiated by potential conflict of interests arising from asymmetric information.
                Typically, this class of games consider a principal that contracts another party
                (agent) to perform some action; since the action is costly to the agent and his
                decision is costly to observe the agreement gives the agent the incentive to
                defects. The first approach <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Bnabou1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Bnabou2">[11]</xref> considers an agency game with bilateral asymmetric
                information in which both the principal and the agent do not know something known by
                the other party which is relevant to their decision. For example, an employee (the
                principal) may know better than the worker (the agent) the toil and trouble required
                by the task; in this case the agent may infer from an explicit reward an excessive
                weariness, thus weakening his/her intrinsic motivation. If the reward is viewed as a
                strategic device that conveys information on some hidden, unpleasant, feature of the
                task the external incentive offered by the principal to the agent may reduce
                agent's effort and performance. The second approach assumes that the change in
                behaviour due to an external intervention does not reflect a change in the
                information set of the agent, but is attributed to a change in preference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Frey2">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Frey3">[13]</xref>. Under this
                perspective, intrinsic motivation is modelled as an additional argument within a
                standard specification of agent's utility function. Since intrinsic motivation
                is assumed to adversely responds to explicit monetary reward, the resulting welfare
                loss may cause a lower effort and cooperation on the part of the agent.</p>
      <p>Despite the different interpretations at the basis of the MCE, these two approaches
                share the implicit view that there is no room for intrinsic motivation to be a
                relevant aspect of observed behavior outside a strategic context. From this arise
                two important issues. On the one side this approach may determine the misleading
                view that the relevance of intrinsic motivations is restricted to a specific range
                of social situations. Actually, as pointed out by Aristotle more than 2,300 years
                ago, “man is by nature a social animal”, which, translated into the
                language of modern social sciences, exactly means that individuals are intrinsically
                motivated to social relations. It follows that whatever social interaction may be
                sustained by a motivation, related to the value of social interaction by itself, and
                distinct from the explicit goal that actually prompts the behaviour. Not only this
                implies that the bias of external rewards may arise in social situations not
                involving explicit perspective-taking activity, but also that outside explicit
                social contexts the role of motivations, and their potential conflict with external
                incentives, shouldn't arise as a relevant phenomenon. On the other side, the
                MCE should necessarily be the consequence of cognitively controlled processes
                undertaken by the agent. This issue has never been of any empirical concern by the
                above literature. It follows that it remains unclear, whether the implicit
                assumption that the MCE results from a conscious mental process is grounded on some
                kind of evidence or whether it is the consequence of the effort to formalize the MCE
                within a theoretical framework that retains the basic assumption of rationality.</p>
      <p>Actually, we think that this question has never been considered by the above
                literature, mainly as a consequence of the scarce interaction between research
                undertaken within different social science fields. Indeed, a vast body of research
                in social psychology has demonstrated the importance of uncontrolled processes in
                shaping individuals' behavior <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Kihlstrom1">[14]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Westen1">[16]</xref> and, more recently, the debate
                has focused on the importance of motivation in unconscious processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Gollwitzer1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Barg1">[21]</xref>. However, this
                body of research is mainly concerned with the effectiveness and appropriateness of
                action in response to automatic evaluation, mainly to show how the unconscious
                provides individuals with effortless decision devices able to effectively purse a
                given goal both in individual contexts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Chen1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Neumann1">[23]</xref> and in social contexts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Higgins1">[24]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Dijksterhuis1">[25]</xref>. On the
                contrary, our interdisciplinary perspective motivates a slightly different design,
                in the sense that we investigated under what conditions changes in external
                incentives may interact with social motivations to determine different patterns of
                behaviour, outcomes of an unconscious processing.</p>
      <p>With regards to these considerations, the focus of our experiment was to verify
                whether different ways to distribute a given amount of money, affects effort and
                cooperation within a context where interaction between individuals does not involve
                any explicit process related to emotional cues and/or to strategic or
                “perspective-taking” considerations. Furthermore, since we wanted to
                investigate if different rewarding schemes influence behavior at a very low level,
                we avoid external incentives strictly contingent on performance by modulating a
                fixed amount of money within different experimental conditions, and focusing the
                attention on behavior variations revealed through activity changes in the muscle
                mainly involved during the execution of a motor task. To this purpose, twelve pairs
                of participants, prevented from any visual or verbal exchange, were submitted to a
                simple motor coordination task. Each couple had to cooperatively hold a small sphere
                between their right index fingers and to drop it alternately into one of two
                containers placed below their hands, while electromyography of the right
                    <italic>first dorsal interosseus</italic> (FDI) muscle of each participant was
                recorded. Each successful trial was differently rewarded with a given amount of
                money according to the experimental condition, and the rewarding rules were
                communicated before starting each session. Consequently, for the same action (e.g.,
                pushing the sphere into the left-side container) each participant could receive a
                reward in one session but not in another. The total monetary reward gained by each
                subject in each condition was always the same. Finally, we correlated muscle
                involvement with the scores obtained in a social attitude questionnaire to verify if
                the stock of social capital covertly modulates motor behavior.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Subjects</title>
        <p>Twenty-four female participants were recruited among students of the Law
                    Department of the University of Ferrara (mean age 26+/−3). All of
                    them were naïve to the purpose of the experiment, were right-handed
                    according to the Oldfield questionnaire <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Oldfield1">[26]</xref> and gave their informed
                    consent. They were divided into two subgroups (the “Green” and the
                    “Yellow” group) of 12 participants, and kept in separate rooms after
                    their arrival at the lab. Twelve pairs of subjects were then formed by
                    extracting randomly one partner from each subgroup. Each pair, composed by one
                    Green and one Yellow subject, was submitted to an experimental session lasting
                    approximately 30 minutes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Questionnaire</title>
        <p>In the first stage of the experiment the subjects were asked to answer a written
                    questionnaire based on the Social Capital Community Benchmark Survey (SCCBS)
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Social1">[27]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Following the SCCBS we employed the answers provided by subjects to build several
                    indexes aimed at measuring individual stock of social capital (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0017372.s002">Appendix S2</xref>
                    for details).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Coordination game</title>
        <p>Before entering the lab room, subjects have been invited to remove rings,
                    bracelets, nail enamel, or other kind of decoration, that could have made them
                    recognizable by the other subjects. At the beginning of the experiment, two
                    subjects entered the experimental room from two different doors, standing one in
                    front of the other, their face and trunk hidden by a curtain. Thus, during the
                    experimental session subjects never saw each other. Moreover, they were strictly
                    recommended not to speak to exclude any possible recognition based on
                    subject's voice.</p>
        <p>Subjects were requested to pose their forearms on a Plexiglas surface with a
                    square hole in correspondence of their hands. Twenty centimeters below the
                    Plexiglas was set an apparatus constituted by two adjacent containers of equal
                    size, with the partition side aligned with participants' sagittal plane. At
                    the beginning of each trial a small glass sphere (1 cm diameter) was placed
                    between the extended right index fingers of the two subjects, and subjects were
                    requested to stay on this position (starting position) until the go-signal. In
                    this position the sphere was exactly above the border between the two containers
                    placed 20 centimeters below subjects' hands. Subjects' index fingers
                    were dressed with a soft sponge to avoid finger flexion during the game, and to
                    increase the attrition surface to better keep the sphere in the proper
                    position.</p>
        <p>Each pair of subjects was asked to play 30 trials of a simple motor ability game.
                    The 30 trials were subdivided into three experimental conditions
                        (<italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> and
                        <italic>C</italic><sub>3</sub>) of ten trials each, blocked into three
                    experimental sessions, the presentation of which was pseudo-randomly balanced
                    across pairs. At every trial subjects followed the instruction given by the
                    experimenter indicating to drop the sphere alternately into the two containers.
                    The difference among conditions <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub>,
                        <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>3</sub>. consisted
                    in the monetary incentive associated to each trial successfully performed by
                    subjects. Specifically, in <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub>, putting the sphere
                    into either target container yielded a reward of € 0.50 to each subject
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017372-g001">Figure 1</xref>). In
                        <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>3</sub>, two
                    colored sheets, one green and one yellow, were placed onto the floor of each
                    container, defining the Green and the Yellow container. The allocation of
                    rewards coupled containers and subjects of the same color. When the sphere was
                    successfully dropped into the target container a € 1 reward was received by
                    the correspondent colored subject only. In <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub>, the
                    Green (Yellow) container was placed at the left side of the Green (Yellow)
                    subject: the winning subject had to execute an index finger abduction
                    (contraction of the FDI muscle) to push the sphere towards the container (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017372-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). In
                        <italic>C</italic><sub>3</sub>, the colors of containers were reversed, so
                    that the Green (Yellow) container was placed at the right side of the Green
                    (Yellow) subject: the winning subject had to execute an index finger adduction
                    (FDI muscle not involved) to “pull” the sphere towards the container
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017372-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). The total
                    money reward gained by each subject was € 5 in each condition (€ 15
                    total).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017372-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The experimental apparatus used in the three experimental
                            conditions.</title>
            <p>Subjects' hands laid on a Plexiglas plate (see D) with the two index
                            fingers positioned in correspondence of a square hole (the rectangle
                            shown in the figure). Under the Plexiglas plate, at a distance of 10 cm
                            from it, there were two containers (the two grey areas shown in panel A)
                            where the subjects had to drop the sphere held by their index fingers
                            according to the specific instructions provided for each experimental
                            conditions. The moment at which the sphere touched the floor of the
                            container was detected by a load cell. The monetary incentives
                            associated to the three experimental conditions were the following:
                            Condition 1 (A): each subject (Yellow and Green) get € 0.50 at any
                            trial. Condition 2: the Yellow (Green) subject is coupled with the
                            Yellow (Green) container; the pushing subject gets € 1 while the
                            pulling one gets zero. Condition 3: the container are reversed; the
                            pushing subject gets zero and the pulling one gets € 1.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>EMG Recordings</title>
        <p>Electromyographic potentials (EMG) were recorded from right <italic>first dorsal
                        interosseus</italic> (FDI) muscle by using Ag-AgCl surface electrodes
                    (diameter 6 mm) glued to the subjects' skin according to a tendon-belly
                    configuration. After online rectification and integration (time constant 50 ms)
                    EMG signal was continuously recorded during the experiment and fed to a personal
                    computer for the successive analysis. A custom-made software acquired the two
                    filtered EMG at 25 Hz, a frequency fast enough to correctly sample the
                    integrated - i.e. smoothed - signals. The instant at which the ball touched the
                    bottom of the target container was detected by means of a load cell supporting
                    the container itself. The signal from the load cell, appropriately amplified,
                    was continuously acquired during the experiment by the same acquisition software
                    used for EMG recordings and at the same sampling frequency.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Data Analysis: ANOVA</title>
        <p>For each trial, ten EMG samples, acquired from the pushing subject and concerning
                    the 400 ms before the fall of the sphere into the container, were averaged and
                    considered for the analysis. The averaged data from each subject, acquired
                    during the three experimental conditions, were then normalized (z-score) and
                    submitted to a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). The considered factor was
                    Experimental Condition, a three levels, within-subjects, factor. Post-hoc
                    analysis (Newman-Keuls, p&lt;0.05) was then performed to verify the significant
                    differences between individual conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Data Analysis: Regression Model</title>
        <p>Our data set is distributed along four relevant dimensions: time, trials,
                    subjects and conditions. In particular, since each trial has a different number
                    of observations (i.e a different time length), to perform a regression analysis
                    we had to balance our panel data set. To this purpose, we synchronized all
                    trials with respect to the EMG peak of the pushing subject (i.e the instant at
                    which the sphere was released, starting to drop into the container) and kept 12
                    observations before this point in time. This allowed us to construct a balanced
                    panel data set of a total of 4,320 observations.</p>
        <p>The potential information of our multi dimensional stock of data is not fully
                    exploited by standard analysis of variance, since ANOVA does not control for
                    many potential sources of variability, such as the muscle effort exerted by
                    subject's couplemate, or individual fixed effects. Therefore, we considered
                    the following dynamic multiple regression model:<disp-formula><graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>The dependent
                    variable <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is subject <italic>i</italic>'s EMG signal at time
                        <italic>t</italic>, when involved in pushing the sphere towards the target
                    container. The right-hand side of the equation models the set of explanatory
                    variables. Specifically, <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the lagged EMG
                    of subject <italic>i</italic> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
                        (<italic>n</italic> = 2,5) is the lagged EMG of subject
                        <italic>j</italic> (couplemate of subject <italic>i</italic>). Lags have
                    been set at 2 and 5 time periods (n = 2, 5). This accounts
                    for a period of time ranging from 80 ms (2 * 40 ms, being the sampling
                    frequency 25 Hz) to 200 ms (5 * 40 ms). This choice was based on the
                    observation that when a perturbation is applied during a precision grip a
                    latency of 60–80 ms is required to increase the grip force to restore an
                    adequate safety margin, preventing frictional slips <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Eliasson1">[28]</xref>. Thus, we defined this
                    time range in order to include the minimal reaction time to a change in the load
                    force applied by subject <italic>j</italic>, plus a possible delay determined by
                    the fact that the grasping requires a coordination between two subjects and not
                    only between two fingers of the same hand. To perform successfully the task it
                    is required a continuous exchange of information between subjects, by the
                    pressure exerted by their index fingers. The <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> variables reflect
                    the intention of subject <italic>i</italic> to push the sphere into the target
                    container. At the same time, since the task requires the collaboration of
                    subject <italic>j</italic>, the lagged <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> take into account
                    that subject <italic>i</italic>'s effort depends on the opposition force
                    exerted by subject's <italic>j</italic> finger. Thus, the dynamic part of
                    the regression model represents the motor communication between subjects
                        <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic>. Other factors that might have
                    influenced the motor behavior of subjects could have been determined by strain
                    or stress and learning-by-doing. To account for these factors, we introduced in
                    vector <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the time length of trials and the sequence order of
                    trials over the entire experiment. The reason of our choice is that lengthy
                    trials may have been more expensive in terms of attention, thus affecting the
                    effort spent by subjects. Furthermore, subjects' effort might have been
                    differently modulated over the course of the experiment, due to a better
                    knowledge of her couplemate and/or to the improvement in their motor ability.
                    Several non observable characters of subjects (such that religion, education,
                    family conditions etc..) may influence the dependent variable. The term
                            <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represents a vector of individual dummies, that control
                    the regression model for this individuals' heterogeneity. Finally,
                            <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e010" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are two dummies
                    for condition 2 and 3 respectively, controlling for experimental conditions
                    instructions.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Behavior and Electromyography</title>
        <p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0017372-t001">Table 1</xref>
                    subjects were able to coordinate almost perfectly in all three experimental
                    conditions, with only a negligible proportion of inefficient outcomes
                    (2.7% of total observations), uniformly distributed across
                    conditions.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0017372-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Outcomes of the game for each condition.</title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0017372-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>Condition</italic>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>Green wins</italic>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>Yellow wins</italic>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>Inefficient outcomes</italic>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>Total (12 pairs×10 trials)</italic>
                                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <italic>Total</italic>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">176</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">174</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">360</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017372-g002">Figure 2</xref> depicts the typical
                    EMG traces recorded from both subjects' FDI muscles (blue and red traces)
                    and the signal recorded from the load cell, detecting the instant at which the
                    sphere, after its releasing, touches the floor of the container (black trace),
                    during condition 1 (A) and 3 (B).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017372-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Typical <italic>first dorsal interosseus</italic> electromyographic
                            signal rectified, integrated (time constant, 0.05 s) and intra-subject
                            normalized (z-scores), as recorded from two subjects (red and blue
                            traces) during the interaction game.</title>
            <p>Panel A, Condition 1; panel B, Condition 3. The signal recorded from the
                            load cell is shown in black and indicates the ten times the glass sphere
                            fell into the container, signaling the end of each trial. The figure
                            depicts ten subsequent trials (sampling frequency, 25 Hz). Abscissas,
                            seconds; ordinates, arbitrary normalization units (see text).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>As it appears from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017372-g002">Figure 2</xref>,
                    at the beginning of each trial there is an increase of both subjects' EMG
                    determined by the involvement of subjects' index fingers in maintaining the
                    glass sphere in the starting position. After the go-signal (not indicated in the
                    figure), one of the two subjects starts to exert a phasic effort to push the
                    sphere into the assigned container, as revealed by a clear peak, slightly
                    anticipating the load cell signal. While in panel A the blue and the red peaks
                    clearly alternate, in panel B the trend is less clear, showing some degree of
                    superimposition of the two traces during some of the trials. Note that in both
                    conditions the instructions were exactly the same: “Place the sphere into
                    the target container”. The only difference between the two conditions
                    concerned the monetary reward. In Condition 1, each member of the pair was
                    winning at any trial, while in Condition 3, each member of the pair was winning
                    only when the target container was the one at her right side, requiring the
                    pulling of the sphere towards the container requiring an index finger adduction
                    (FDI muscle not involved).</p>
        <p>This qualitative difference between conditions is quantitatively shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017372-g003">Figure 3</xref>, depicting the
                    average values of FDI muscle EMG, recorded from each subject while pushing the
                    sphere into the target container placed at her left side in the three
                    experimental conditions. EMG data, after normalization, were averaged subject by
                    subject (N = 24) by pooling the last 12 trials before the
                    signal of the load cell signaled the fall of the sphere.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0017372-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Mean values of EMG signals recorded from the FDI muscle for all
                            subjects in the three experimental conditions, when pushing the sphere
                            into the target container placed at her left side.</title>
            <p>Whiskers above each histogram depict the standard error of mean.
                            Ordinates: <italic>z</italic>-score of EMG signals. Asterisks indicate
                            the presence of a significant difference between conditions (*,
                            difference from Condition 1 (C1); **,*** difference
                            from Conditions 2 (C2) and 3 (C3), respectively).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>ANOVA performed on the normalized data with Experimental Condition as three
                    levels within-subjects factor (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017372-g002">Figure 2</xref>) showed that Experimental Condition was statistically
                    significant (F(2,46) = 4.48,
                    <italic>p</italic> = 0.017). Post-hoc analysis
                    (Newman-Keuls) revealed that EMG activity of <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub> was
                    significantly (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.05) stronger than that of
                        <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>3</sub>. However,
                    as indicated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0017372-t001">Table 1</xref>,
                    the game outcome does not reflect this difference, and subjects, interviewed at
                    the end of the experiment, never reported the voluntary use of different
                    strategies in the different conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Questionnaire</title>
        <p>One of the aims of the present work was to verify if different levels of social
                    capital modulates muscle involvement of the pushing subjects, in response to
                    different monetary incentives among conditions. Using the questionnaire's
                    answers, we built up three indicators (<italic>SC1</italic>,
                        <italic>SC2</italic>, <italic>SC3</italic>) to sort subjects according to
                    their attitude to coordinate and cooperate for mutual benefit (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0017372.s002">Appendix S2</xref>
                    for details). For each of these indicators subjects have been divided into two
                    subgroups with respect to the index-related median score, defining the high-
                        (<italic>H</italic> = above median) and the low
                        (<italic>L</italic> = below median) Social Capital
                    groups of subjects.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Regression Results</title>
        <p>The relevant estimation results are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0017372-t002">table (2)</xref> below. The first column (POOL)
                    reports the estimation results for the entire set of subjects (24). The other
                    six columns provide results relative to each high/low prosocial sub-groups
                    according to indicators SC1, SC2 and SC3. In particular, HSC<sub>z</sub> and
                        LSC<sub>z</sub> (z = 1, 2, 3) refer to High and Low
                    prosocial individuals, respectively.</p>
        <p>Even with the rich specification of explanatory variables inside the regression
                    model, all simultaneously engaged to account for the variability of the effort
                    recorded from the pushing subjects, it still emerges that on average subjects
                    exerted a lower pushing effort in condition 3 than in condition 1: only the
                    estimated coefficient of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is negative
                    (−0.0244) and 5% significant
                    (<italic>t</italic> = 2.44). However, once we distinguish
                    between high social capital and low social capital subjects, the estimated
                    coefficients of <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is negative and
                    significant at a 1% level in the low-prosocial sub-sample, only. This
                    pattern arises whatever index of social capital is used. Moreover, the
                    coefficient on the dummy <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> turns out not
                    significant in all regressions, indicating that no difference in effort is
                    detected between Condition 1 and Condition 2. Despite the ANOVA reported that
                    subjects significantly spent a lower effort in Condition 2 than in Condition1,
                    in the light of <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0017372-t002">Table 2</xref>
                    this result appears spurious. Indeed, the regression tells that the EMG
                    difference between conditions 1 and 2 does not reflect any change in external
                    incentives schemes, but more likely the variability in the other set of
                    explanatory variables.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0017372-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>Ordinary Least Squares Regression keeping 12 observations before the
                            maximum EMG level, included. </title>
          </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0017372-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">POOL</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HSC<sub>1</sub></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSC<sub>1</sub></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HSC<sub>2</sub></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSC<sub>2</sub></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HSC<sub>3</sub></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSC<sub>3</sub></td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1121(4.59)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1439(4.22)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0838(2.32)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1840(5.78)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0567(1.56)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1560(4.72)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0924(2.46)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2898(12.69)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2918(8.49)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2634(8.78)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2634(7.67)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2724(8.76)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2294(6.73)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3233(10.54)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0898(3.82)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0405(1.38)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1421(3.79)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0473(1.64)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1552(4.06)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0615(2.11)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1196(3.07)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0330(1.41)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1153(3.61)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0451(1.38)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0748(2.46)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0073(0.21)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0474(1.61)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0281(0.75)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0041(0.40)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0095(0.70)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0003(0.02)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0098(0.72)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0040(0.27)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0079(0.59)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0015(0.10)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                    <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>
                                </td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0244(2.44)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0156(1.10)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0630(4.49)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0105(0.73)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0535(3.82)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0093(0.67)</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.0389(2.72)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Constant</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1044(4.46)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0867(2.66)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1322(0.3.89)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1319(3.71)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1092(2.80)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1748(4.56)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">***</xref></td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0632(2.05)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">**</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Observations</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1755</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">855</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">870</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">885</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">870</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">880</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">875</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R-squared</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3955</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4774</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3455</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4276</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4121</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4472</td>
                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3665</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>Robust t statistics in parentheses:</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>*significant at 10%;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt103">
              <label/>
              <p>**significant at 5%;</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt104">
              <label/>
              <p>***significant at 1%.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nt105">
              <label/>
              <p>Normalization over the entire data set.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>Looking at the dynamic component of the regression, coefficients of lagged
                    variables are positive and significant, suggesting that each couple of subjects
                    successfully tried to coordinate their index fingers as a pair of agonists.
                    However, considering the magnitude of coefficients for different groups of
                    subjects substantial differences emerge between high social capital (High SC)
                    and low social capital (Low SC) individuals. In particular, the following two
                    results appear to be relevant (formal tests are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0017372.s001">Appendix S1</xref>
                    )</p>
        <disp-quote>
          <p>R1) The coefficients of the dynamic part of the regression (autoregressive
                        component) decrease with farther time lags, both in the High SC and Low SC
                        groups</p>
          <p>R2) Result 3 emerges looking at the coefficients describing how
                        subjects' current effort depends on the past effort of her couplemate.
                        In the High SC group the coefficient at lag (−2) is greater than the
                        corresponding coefficient at lag (−5) and the reverse patterns occurs
                        within the Low SC group. Moreover, it appears that coefficient at lag
                        (−2) is higher in the High SC group than in the Low SC group, while
                        the reverse pattern is observed at lag (−5).</p>
        </disp-quote>
        <p>For both high and low social capital subjects the autoregressive component of the
                    regression model (the lagged <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> variables) shows
                    that the current effort <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of subject
                        <italic>i</italic> is positively linked to her own past efforts, and that
                    the magnitude of the coefficients decreases the farther-off are the lags (result
                    R1). This is consistent with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017372-g002">Figure
                        2</xref>, which shows that intensity of muscles effort progressively
                    increases, and reaches its peak at the instant at which the sphere is
                    dropped.</p>
        <p>Result R2 describes how the current reaction of subject <italic>i</italic>
                    depends on past motor behavior of subject <italic>j</italic>. Overall, estimated
                    coefficients are significantly non negative. However, looking at the size of
                    coefficients it emerges a striking difference between high and low social
                    capital individuals. Current muscle effort of high social capital subjects is
                    influenced mainly by the more recent behavior of their couplemates, while
                    current effort of low social capital subjects is better explained by the more
                    distant behavior of their couplemates. Considering high social capital subjects,
                    the estimated coefficients on <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are not
                    significantly different from zero in two of the three regressions
                        (HSC<sub>1</sub> and HSC<sub>2</sub>) and significant at the 5% level
                    but close to zero in the HSC<sub>3</sub> case. On the contrary, coefficients on
                            <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are positive and significant in HSC<sub>1</sub> and
                        HSC<sub>2</sub> and not significant in HSC<sub>3</sub>. Exactly the reverse
                    pattern occurs with low social capital subjects: coefficients on
                            <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are significant at a 1% level, while those on
                            <inline-formula><inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are not significant in all cases (LSC<sub>1</sub>,
                        LSC<sub>2</sub> and LSC<sub>3</sub>). This evidence shows that, compared to
                    high social capital subjects, low social capital participants exhibited a
                    delayed response to stimuli coming from changes in effort in subject's
                    opposing finger. This may suggest that high social capital individuals might
                    have been prompted by a stronger intrinsic motivation, which resulted in a more
                    effective motor coordination.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>An impressive body of social and cognitive psychology studies reports evidence
                supporting the view that external rewards, typically monetary ones, undermine
                intrinsic motivation (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Deci2">[3]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Frey1">[4]</xref> for an extensive survey and meta-analysis). These findings
                contradict the behaviour predicted on the basis of the standard selfish-rationality
                assumption, which is at the core of economic reasoning. As a consequence, since the
                late 90 <italic>s</italic> an increasing number of experimental, empirical and
                theoretical studies have explored this puzzling issue. This body of research shares
                the view that the proper frame in which to consider this phenomenon is a
                principal-agent game context (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Frey1">[4]</xref> for a discussion of the major economic studies identifying
                crowding effects). This approach represents a fruitful context to investigate the
                interaction between extrinsic and intrinsic motivations. However, it is not the
                proper setting to explore if the side effects of external incentives on intrinsic
                motivations might arise as an automatic process, since, due to the strategic
                environment, the crowding out/in of intrinsic motivations necessarily follows from
                an explicit perspective-taking activity undertaken by subjects.</p>
      <p>In the light of these considerations, we set up an experimental framework devoid of
                any complex perspective-taking activity, aimed at investigating whether the
                modulation of a given monetary reward affects effort and performance of
                participants. Pairs of subjects, prevented from any visual or verbal interaction,
                were engaged in a pure motor coordination game divided into three experimental
                conditions, perfectly identical from the point of view of the required motor task.
                Moreover, the monetary stake associated to each condition was exactly the same. Each
                couple of subjects was asked to hold a small sphere between their right index
                fingers and to alternately drop it into one of two containers placed below their
                hands, while electromyography of participants' right FDI muscle was recorded.
                This muscle has the function to abduct the index finger away from the middle finger.
                Thus, it is the muscle more involved in pushing the sphere towards the leftmost
                container, while it remains relaxed when the participant is asked to place the
                sphere into the rightmost container by exerting a finger adduction. Our aim was to
                compare FDI muscle activity when participants were asked to push the sphere into the
                leftmost container under different rewarding schemes. In <italic>C</italic>ondition
                1 the completion of each trial entailed an equal reward assigned to both (pushing
                and opposing) subjects. In <italic>C</italic>ondition 2 at each trial only the
                subject who had pushed the sphere towards the leftmost container obtained the
                reward. Therefore, in Condition 1 and Condition 2 FDI muscle involvement in pushing
                the sphere was coupled with a monetary reward. On the contrary, in Condition 3 the
                reward was assigned to the opposing subject only. Thus, in all trials, FDI muscle
                involvement in pushing the sphere was not associated with any specific monetary
                reward. It should be stressed that, since the total monetary reward allocated to
                both subjects upon completion of the sequence of trials did not change across
                conditions, the overall <italic>external motivation</italic>, that prompted the
                motor performance was the same in each experimental condition. Since subjects were
                able to coordinate almost perfectly their movements across conditions 1, 2 and 3,
                their behavior is consistent with the conscious perceiving of this external
                incentive. Despite from a distributional point of view it does not emerge any
                difference in behavior associated with alternative incentive protocols, substantial
                differences arise from EMG data processing, revealing that not only muscle
                involvement in executing the same motor act is affected by different allocations of
                an identical monetary reward, but also that the modulation of the effort is
                correlated with the degree of prosocial propensity of subjects. To measure the
                social attitude of participants we used the answers to the questionnaire taken from
                Putnam's Social Capital Benchmark Survey to construct three indexes of social
                capital, that we used to split the sample of subjects into high and low social
                capital individuals. With respect to these two groups of individuals our main result
                is that high-prosocial subjects performed the task without any significant
                difference among conditions, while low-prosocial subjects exerted a significant
                lower effort in Condition 3 than in <italic>C</italic>ondition 1.</p>
      <p>When a small object is gripped between the tips of the index finger and thumb and
                held stationary in space, the applied grip force is synchronically balanced to
                optimize the motor behaviour. In addition, the control of the grip force is
                automatically influenced by the weight of the object (load force) and by a safety
                margin factor related to the individual subject <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Johansson1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Edin1">[30]</xref>. Since this is fundamental to
                avoid the accidental drop of the object, within the context of our experiment, the
                level of safety margin set by subjects to avoid errors must be related to the
                    <italic>intrinsic motivations</italic> that sustained action toward the desired
                goal. These considerations highlight the baseline for discussing our results.
                Specifically, we consider that the two index fingers of pair of subjects acted as
                pairs of agonists, and that statistically significative changes in effort detected
                through the EMG recording relates to the intensity intrinsic motivations. We assumed
                that the overall external motivation was the same in all three experimental
                conditions, because each participant received, the same reward in all conditions and
                the motor task was performed following the instructions of the experimenters, to
                avoid any perspective-taking activity. Moreover, upon asking participants at the end
                of the experiment, none of them affirmed to have consciously changed her effort or
                strategy across different conditions. In the light of these considerations, it is
                conceivable that the modulation of the effort in response to different rewarding
                schemes was the consequence of an automatic and unconscious mental process.
                Therefore, the MCE of intrinsic motivations due to external incentives, that
                ultimately determined the level of application and diligence exerted by subjects
                (the safety margin factor), may arise as an unconscious outcome outside a strategic
                context, even in response to “weak” external incentives changes, such as
                a slightly different way to deliver a given amount of money.</p>
      <p>In Condition 1 the completion of each trial entailed an equal reward assigned to both
                subjects. In this respect, the surplus resulting from the cooperation was equally
                divided between subjects. Following an economic terminology, in condition 1 the
                benefit of cooperation was not excludable, in the sense that no individual could be
                excluded from enjoying a slice of the surplus generated by the coordinated efforts.
                In Condition 2 and 3 cooperation is still productive, but within trials only one
                participant was rewarded. This character of excludability in Conditions 2 and 3
                introduced a substantial difference with respect to Condition 1: reciprocity. In
                social psychology (as well as in game theory) reciprocity means that people reward
                kind action and punish unkind ones. In the present context reciprocity has sustained
                in Conditions 2 and 3 an implicit agreement between subjects, in the sense that
                results in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0017372-t001">Table 1</xref> are
                consistent with the statement: “I help you to win €1 if you help me to
                win €1”. However, the excludability of surplus between Conditions 2 and 3
                is asymmetrical, since in Condition 2 it is the pushing subject that it is rewarded,
                while in Condition 3 it is the opposing subject. Actually, this asymmetry introduced
                roles within trials. Specifically, looking at the mechanics of the coordination, it
                is fairly clear that if the opponent's finger started moving before the other
                one started pushing, the sphere would have been fallen in the wrong container. Since
                the event of accidental drop of the sphere has occurred in a negligible proportion,
                we can safely claim that the subject opposite to the pushing one as not started to
                move before the pushing subjects had started to push. Since, at each trial it was
                the pushing subject that decided to start action, while the opposing one waited for
                her couplemate's decision, following the metaphors of the game theory we
                attribute the role of leader to the pushing subject and the role of follower to the
                opposing subject. Following the metaphor outlined above, we can interpret our result
                in the light that Conditions 1 and 2 share the feature that the leader is rewarded,
                while Conditions 2 and 3 share the characteristic that cooperation is sustained by
                reciprocity.</p>
      <p>Our main results are that high social capital participants subjects exhibited no
                significant reaction to the modulation of external reward within conditions. In this
                respect, the intrinsic motivations sustaining cooperation was not affected by
                removing the monetary incentive of the leader (the pushing subject) in Condition 3.
                In this sense, high social capital participants displayed strong reciprocity, which
                caused them to be insensitive to changes in external motivations. On the contrary,
                low social capital participants exerted a significative lower effort in Condition 3
                than in Condition 1, but no difference in effort is detected between Conditions 1
                and 2. Following our line of interpretation, this sample of subjects actually
                perceived a zero monetary incentive as they played as leader in condition 3, causing
                a lower effort spent in the task. In this respect, they actually responded to
                extrinsic motivation consistently with a selfish-rationality argument. However,
                effort spent in condition 1 does not significantly differ from effort recorded in
                condition 2. Thus, it seems that the non excludable character of surplus in
                condition 1 did matter. In condition 1 whatever container did the sphere have been
                dropped subjects were rewarded, thus reciprocity was not relevant. In this sense,
                this group of this group of subjects exhibited only weak reciprocity, since they
                showed some degree of aversion to reciprocate unless they were externally
                rewarded.</p>
      <p>In terms of motivational literature, the above discussion suggests two final
                considerations. First, reciprocity appears a relevant dimension of intrinsic
                motivations in social interaction, and, more interestingly, the propensity to
                reciprocate depends on the stock of social capital. Since the accumulation of social
                capital can be an explicit policy target on the part of public institutions, our
                results suggest a precise channel, micro-founded on the behaviour of the single
                individual, through which investment in social capital might display their effects.
                More specifically, only when individuals are poorly endowed with social capital
                social interaction via market-transactions (i.e. through external motivations
                incentives) is effective. On the contrary, when individuals are integrated by high
                levels of social capital, their behavior may react to changes in relative prices in
                opposition to what is expected on the basis of a standard economic argument. Second
                and more importantly, the effects of extrinsic rewards on intrinsic motivation does
                not rely upon any explicit cost-benefit evaluation, stemming from a controlled
                cognitive process, but may result automatically as an unconscious outcome. This may
                reflect the specific monetary character of the external motivation. It is a well
                established result that several external stimuli may “prime” subjects,
                conditioning in an uncontrolled way their behaviour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Bargh2">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Neely1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Spencer1">[20]</xref>. A more recent study, however,
                has showed the precise behaviour's bias due to the priming of money <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Vohs1">[33]</xref>, which supports
                the interpretation of our results. The main result of this study shows that
                “money brings about a self-orientation, in which people prefer to be free of
                dependency and dependents“ (p. 1154). In this respect the “aversion for
                reciprocity” argument we used in the discussion before may just be reversed by
                using a notion of “preference for the self-supporting”, which is exactly
                the consequence of the priming of money according to Vohs et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0017372-Vohs1">[33]</xref>. On the one side,
                our results find additional supports from the subliminal effects of money
                investigated in this study, on the other side they refine this evidence since we
                show that the “priming” effect of money is modulated by the social
                relevant experiences of individuals (social capital).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0017372.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Appendix S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0017372.s002" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0017372.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Appendix S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This work has been accomplished with the contribution of EC grants Robot-Cub and
                Poeticon. We thank the <italic>Fondazione Cassa di Risparmio</italic> di Ferrara for
                its financial support.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Lepper1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1978</year>
                    <source>The Hidden Cost of Reward: new Perspectives on Psychology of Human
                        Behavior</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, , NY</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Deci1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1975</year>
                    <source>Intrinsic Motivation</source>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Plenum Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Deci2">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koestner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>A Meta-Analytic Review of Experiments Examining the Effects of
                        Extrinsic Rewards on Intrinsic Motivation.</article-title>
                    <source>Psychol Bull</source>
                    <volume>125</volume>
                    <fpage>627</fpage>
                    <lpage>668</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Frey1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jegen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Motivation Crowding theory.</article-title>
                    <source>J Econ Surv</source>
                    <volume>15</volume>
                    <fpage>589</fpage>
                    <lpage>611</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Fehr1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gätcher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Do Incentive Contracts Crowd out Voluntary
                        Cooperation?</article-title>
                    <comment>Institute for Empirical Research in Economics, Working Paper N.
                        34</comment>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Bohnet1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnet</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>More Order with less Law; On Contract Enforcement, Trust and
                        Crowding.</article-title>
                    <source>Am Polit Sci Rev</source>
                    <volume>95</volume>
                    <fpage>131</fpage>
                    <lpage>134</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Gneezy1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gneezy</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rustichini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000a</year>
                    <article-title>Pay Enough or don't Pay At All.</article-title>
                    <source>Q J Econ</source>
                    <volume>115</volume>
                    <fpage>791</fpage>
                    <lpage>810</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Gneezy2">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gneezy</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rustichini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000b</year>
                    <article-title>A Fine is a Price.</article-title>
                    <source>J Legal Stud</source>
                    <volume>29</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>18</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Cardenas1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stranlund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Local Environmental Control and Institutional
                        Crowding-Out.</article-title>
                    <source>World Dev</source>
                    <volume>28</volume>
                    <fpage>1719</fpage>
                    <lpage>1733</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Bnabou1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bénabou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tirole</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Intrinsic and Extrinsic Motivation.</article-title>
                    <source>Rev Econ Stud</source>
                    <volume>70</volume>
                    <fpage>489</fpage>
                    <lpage>520</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Bnabou2">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bénabou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tirole</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Incentives and Prosocial Behavior.</article-title>
                    <source>Am Econ Rev</source>
                    <volume>96</volume>
                    <fpage>1652</fpage>
                    <lpage>1678</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Frey2">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <source>Not just for Money. An Economic Theory of Personal Motivation</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Cheltenham, Uk and Brookfield, USA</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Edward Elgar</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Frey3">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberholzer-Gee</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>The Cost of price Incentives: An Empirical Analysis of Motivation
                        Crowding-out.</article-title>
                    <source>Am Econ Rev</source>
                    <volume>87</volume>
                    <fpage>746</fpage>
                    <lpage>755</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Kihlstrom1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kihlstrom</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1987</year>
                    <article-title>The cognitive unconscious.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>237</volume>
                    <fpage>1445</fpage>
                    <lpage>1452</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Epstein1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1994</year>
                    <article-title>Integration of the cognitive and the psychodynamic
                        unconscious.</article-title>
                    <source>Am Psychol</source>
                    <volume>49</volume>
                    <fpage>709</fpage>
                    <lpage>724</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Westen1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Westen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>The scientific legacy of Sigmund Freud: Toward a
                        psychodynamically informed psychological science.</article-title>
                    <source>Psychol Bull</source>
                    <volume>124</volume>
                    <fpage>333</fpage>
                    <lpage>371</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Gollwitzer1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gollwitzer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moskowitz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Goal effects on action and cognition.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruglanski</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <source>Social psychology: Handbook of basic principles</source>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Bargh1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bargh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chartrand</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>The unbearable automaticity of being.</article-title>
                    <source>Am Psychol</source>
                    <volume>54</volume>
                    <fpage>462</fpage>
                    <lpage>479</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Shah1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruglansk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Goals systems theory: Integrating the cognitive and motivational
                        aspects of self-regulation.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanna</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <source>Motivated social perception: The Ontario symposium</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Mahwah, , NJ</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Spencer1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strahan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>The Role of Motivation in the Unconscious: How Our Motives
                        Control the Activation of Our Thoughts and Shape Our
                        Actions.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forgas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <comment>Social Motivation: Conscious and Unconscious Processes, Cambridge
                        University Press</comment>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Barg1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morsella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>The unconscious mind.</article-title>
                    <source>Perspect Psychol Sci</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>73</fpage>
                    <lpage>79</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Chen1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bargh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Consequences of automatic evaluation: Immediate behavioral
                        predispositions to approach or avoid the stimulus.</article-title>
                    <source>Pers Soc Psychol B</source>
                    <volume>25</volume>
                    <fpage>215</fpage>
                    <lpage>224</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Neumann1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Förster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Motor compatibility: The bidirectional link between behavior and
                        evaluation.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klauer</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <source>The psychology of evaluation: Affective processes in cognition and
                        emotion</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Mahwah, , NJ</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Higgins1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bargh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1987</year>
                    <article-title>Social perception and social cognition.</article-title>
                    <source>Annu Rev Psychol</source>
                    <volume>38</volume>
                    <fpage>369</fpage>
                    <lpage>425</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Dijksterhuis1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijksterhuis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bargh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>The perception-behavior expressway.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <source>Advances in experimental social psychology</source>
                    <publisher-loc>San Diego, , CA</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Oldfield1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oldfield</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1971</year>
                    <article-title>The assessment and analysis of handedness: the Edinburgh
                        inventory.</article-title>
                    <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                    <fpage>97</fpage>
                    <lpage>113</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Social1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">Social Capital Community Benchmark Survey (SCCBS)</collab>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>The John F. Kennedy School of Government of Harvard
                        University.</article-title>
                    <comment>Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cfsv.org/communitysurvey/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cfsv.org/communitysurvey/index.html</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Eliasson1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eliasson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forssberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikuta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westling</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Development of human precision grip. V. anticipatory and
                        triggered grip actions during sudden loading.</article-title>
                    <source>Exp Brain Res</source>
                    <volume>106</volume>
                    <fpage>425</fpage>
                    <lpage>433</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Johansson1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westling</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1984</year>
                    <article-title>Roles of glabrous skin receptors and sensorimotor memory in
                        automatic control of precision grip when lifting rougher or more slippery
                        objects.</article-title>
                    <source>Exp Brain Res</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>550</fpage>
                    <lpage>564</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Edin1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Essick</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trulsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Receptor encoding of moving tactile stimuli in humans. I.
                        Temporal pattern of discharge of individual low-threshold
                        mechanoreceptors.</article-title>
                    <source>J Neurosci</source>
                    <volume>15</volume>
                    <fpage>830</fpage>
                    <lpage>847</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Bargh2">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bargh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lombardy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1985</year>
                    <article-title>The nature of priming effects on categorization.</article-title>
                    <source>J Exp Psychol Learn</source>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                    <fpage>59</fpage>
                    <lpage>69</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Neely1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neely</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1991</year>
                    <article-title>Semantic priming effects in visual word recognition: A selective
                        review of current findings and theories.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Besner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zumphreys</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <source>Basic processes in reading: Visual word recognition</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Hillsdale, , NJ</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Erlbaum</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>264</fpage>
                    <lpage>336</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Vohs1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vohs</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goode</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>The Psychological consequence of Money.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>314</volume>
                    <fpage>1154</fpage>
                    <lpage>1156</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0017372-Brame1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brame</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazerolle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piquero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Using the corrects statistical test for equality of regression
                        coefficients, </article-title>
                    <source>Criminology </source>
                    <volume>36</volume>
                    <fpage>859</fpage>
                    <lpage>866</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>