<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-05069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020101</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal behavior</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Zoology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Animal behavior</subject>
              <subject>Mammalogy</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biological anthropology</subject>
              <subject>Psychological anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Neuroscience</subject>
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>How Abnormal Is the Behaviour of Captive, Zoo-Living Chimpanzees?</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Abnormal Behavior of Zoo-Living Chimpanzees</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Birkett</surname>
            <given-names>Lucy P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Newton-Fisher</surname>
            <given-names>Nicholas E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">          <addr-line>School of Anthropology and Conservation, University of Kent, Canterbury, United Kingdom</addr-line>       </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gursky-Doyen</surname>
            <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Texas A&amp;M University, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">n.e.newton-fisher@kent.ac.uk</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LPB NNF. Analyzed the data: LPB NNF. Wrote the paper: LPB NNF.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e20101</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Birkett, Newton-Fisher</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Many captive chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) show a variety of serious behavioural abnormalities, some of which have been considered as possible signs of compromised mental health. The provision of environmental enrichments aimed at reducing the performance of abnormal behaviours is increasing the norm, with the housing of individuals in (semi-)natural social groups thought to be the most successful of these. Only a few quantitative studies of abnormal behaviour have been conducted, however, particularly for the captive population held in zoological collections. Consequently, a clear picture of the level of abnormal behaviour in zoo-living chimpanzees is lacking.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>We present preliminary findings from a detailed observational study of the behaviour of 40 socially-housed zoo-living chimpanzees from six collections in the United States of America and the United Kingdom. We determined the prevalence, diversity, frequency, and duration of abnormal behaviour from 1200 hours of continuous behavioural data collected by focal animal sampling.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results, Conclusion and Significance</title>
          <p>Our overall finding was that abnormal behaviour was present in all sampled individuals across six independent groups of zoo-living chimpanzees, despite the differences between these groups in size, composition, housing, etc. We found substantial variation between individuals in the frequency and duration of abnormal behaviour, but all individuals engaged in at least some abnormal behaviour and variation across individuals could not be explained by sex, age, rearing history or background (defined as prior housing conditions). Our data support a conclusion that, while most behaviour of zoo-living chimpanzees is ‘normal’ in that it is typical of their wild counterparts, abnormal behaviour is endemic in this population despite enrichment efforts. We suggest there is an urgent need to understand how the chimpanzee mind copes with captivity, an issue with both scientific and welfare implications.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Lucy P. Birkett was supported by the Christine and Ian Bolt Scholarship, University of Kent, and the Universities Federation for Animal Welfare, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ufaw.org.uk/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ufaw.org.uk/</ext-link>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="7"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Captive conditions are known to evoke abnormal behaviour patterns in a variety of species, including non-human primates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Young1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Mason1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Poole1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Hook1">[4]</xref>. Many chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) kept in laboratory housing settings show a variety of serious behavioural abnormalities, such as repetitive rocking, drinking of urine, or self-mutilation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Hook1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Walsh1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bourgeois1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Baker1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bloomsmith1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Fritz1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bradshaw1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bradshaw2">[12]</xref>. Previous work indicates that various abnormal behaviour patterns also occur among chimpanzees held in zoological collections <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Clarke1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Hosey1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Murray1">[16]</xref>, but detailed, quantitative studies on the zoo population are few <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne2">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Abnormal behaviours may indicate psychological suffering <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Rollin1">[18]</xref>, but this is seldom considered directly (cf. Bradshaw and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bradshaw1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bradshaw2">[12]</xref>). Principles of evolutionary psychiatry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne3">[19]</xref> suggest that some abnormal behaviours may be symptomatic of underlying mental illness, a neglected area of research in great apes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne2">[17]</xref>. These possibilities raise serious ethical questions, particularly given the emotional and cognitive abilities of chimpanzees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Goodall1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-deWaal1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Inoue1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Searle1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Mcgrew1">[24]</xref>, although a consistent framework for the study of abnormal behaviour in apes has not yet been achieved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne2">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Social deprivation, and particularly maternal separation, have been suggested as causal factors in the development of abnormal behaviour in captive chimpanzees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Davenport1">[25]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Davenport2">[26]</xref>: such events may be psychologically traumatic, or may deprive individuals of opportunities to learn appropriate behaviour. Persistent effects as a consequence of rearing have been found in some chimpanzees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Murray1">[16]</xref>, but not all <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin2">[27]</xref>. The impact of rearing history, while marked in younger chimpanzees, appears to wane as individuals age, at least in those re-socialised and housed with conspecifics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin2">[27]</xref>. Such findings might suggest that social group housing, with the consequent opportunities for development of appropriate social relationships, will ameliorate the negative effects of early experiences <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Murray1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Lutz1">[28]</xref>. Social housing has been suggested as the most effective means of combating the occurrence and development of abnormal behaviours in primates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Lutz1">[28]</xref>, despite a lack of consensus over the causal roots of such behaviour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nash1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Hosey2">[30]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In this paper we present preliminary findings from a detailed, quantitative investigation of abnormal behaviour in captive (zoo-living) chimpanzees based on extensive and direct observation, comparable with that used for behavioural study of wild chimpanzees (for example: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-NewtonFisher1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-NewtonFisher2">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Muller1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Wrangham1">[34]</xref>). We focus on adult and adolescent individuals housed in social groups, the context in which individuals should be least likely to display abnormal behaviour: our specific aim is to determine the level of abnormal behaviour in zoo-living, socially enriched, captive chimpanzees. We report detailed descriptive data on the occurrence of abnormal behaviour, and test whether performance of abnormal behaviour is related to social group size, rearing history or background (housing prior to entering the study group). As chimpanzee behaviour varies with age and sex, and some sex differences in abnormal behaviour have been reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nash1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Fritz2">[35]</xref>, we also test for the influence of these variables on the occurrence of abnormal behaviour.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>Abnormal behaviours among captive animals are those that are atypical of wild-living individuals, whether absent or occurring only rarely. We used published sources on behaviour in chimpanzees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Walsh1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bloomsmith1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bradshaw1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nash1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Pederson1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nishida1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nishida2">[38]</xref> to compile a list of abnormal behaviours seen in the captive population. As a consequence of our observations (see below), ten further behaviours were added to this list: <italic>bounce</italic>, <italic>groom stereotypically</italic>, <italic>groom stereotypically with object</italic>, <italic>move hand repetitively</italic>, <italic>rub hands repetitively</italic>, <italic>toss head, touch urine stream</italic>, <italic>poke anus</italic>, and <italic>walk on object</italic>; <italic>bite-hit-lick</italic> was added for one individual who performed these behaviours as an integrated pattern. We used the most comprehensive ethogram for wild chimpanzees available <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nishida2">[38]</xref> to determine which of the behaviours have been recorded for wild chimpanzees, and for these, to confirm that they occurred only rarely. Our final list consisted of 37 behaviours (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020101-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0020101-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
          <title>Abnormal behaviours used in this study.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0020101-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abnormal behavioural pattern and summary definition</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Source of definition</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Bang self against surface</italic> - hit own body-part against solid surface.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Bite self</italic> - bite own body-part.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Bite-hit-lick self</italic> - bite, hit, and lick own body-parts in constellation.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Bounce</italic> - bounce body or head, in non-social context.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Clap</italic> - slap palm of hand or sole of foot, making noise.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Clasp self</italic> - clutch own body.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Configure lips</italic> - move lips stereotypically, such as repetitively blowing air through lips or wiping lips over glass.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Display to human</italic> - stylized agonistic display and build-up directed at humans.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Drink urine</italic> - drink own urine.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Eat faeces</italic> - ingest own faeces, both matrix and undigested items (coprophagy).</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Eat faeces of other</italic> - ingest another's faeces, both matrix and undigested items.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Float limb</italic> - entire limb (not just fingers or toes) appears to move independently, as if it does not belong to individual.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1, 5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Fumble nipple</italic> - manipulate own nipple(s) with thumb or fingers. May suck on nipple if breast or nipple is extended.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7, 8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Groom stereotypically</italic> - repetitively groom self on specific body part, seemingly without goal.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Groom stereotypically with object</italic> - groom self seemingly without intention, with stick or other tool. Drag object lightly over hairless body surface in non-focused way.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Hit self</italic> - hit own body-part with hand.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Incest</italic> - copulate with immediate relative.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7, 8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Jerk</italic> - spontaneously jerk body, apparently unprovoked by external stimulus.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Manipulate faeces</italic> - hold, carry, or spread own or other's faeces on surface.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Move hand repetitively</italic> - repetitively move hand in circular fashion in air or through substrate</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Pace</italic> - locomote, usually quadrupedally, on substrate, covering and then re-covering route in stylized fashion, with no clear objective.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Pat genitals</italic> - repetitively touch own genitals, then often lick hand.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Pinch self</italic> - compress own skin between thumb and forefinger.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Pluck hair</italic> - pull out own hair.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Pluck hair of other</italic> - pull out another's hair.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Poke anus</italic> - insert finger into own anus.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Poke eye</italic> - poke one or more fingers into own eye.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Regurgitate</italic> - vomit voluntarily, then usually re-ingest vomitus.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Rock</italic> - sway repetitively and rhythmically, without piloerection. Usually side-to-side movement, but may be forward and backward or full circular motion of torso. Usually whole body, sometimes just the head.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Rub hands</italic> - run one hand over the other, then repeat but reverse the hand order, in stylized fashion.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Spit</italic> - expel saliva through pursed lips, often directed at human observer.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3, 4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Stimulate self stylized, no context</italic> - repetitively stroke or fondle own penis or clitoris in non-mating context.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Toss head</italic> - circular movement of head.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Touch urine stream</italic> - place hand or foot in own urine stream. May wipe hand on body after.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Twirl</italic> - rotate torso on axis for 360 degrees while upright and bipedal.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Twitch body-part</italic> - body-part, often fingers and toes, twitch repetitively, apparently involuntary.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>Walk on object</italic> - locomote bipedally while carrying object (e.g. blanket), stepping on object edges that drag on floor. Individual swaggers to keep feet off ground and to maintain contact with object.</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label/>
            <p>Sources: 1. Walsh et al. (1982); 2. Bloomsmith &amp; Lambert (1995); 3. Nash et al. (1999); 4. Martin (2002); 5. Bradshaw et al. (2008); 6. Pederson et al. (2005); 7. Nishida et al. (2010); 8. This study.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>The first author collected observational data on 40 chimpanzees living in six accredited zoological institutions (accrediting agencies were the American Zoological Association – AZA - and the British and Irish Associations of Zoos and Aquariums - BIAZA). The chimpanzees were all housed in social groups, with one group from each of the six participating zoological gardens contributing to our dataset. We chose the zoos from a master list that gave no information about the chimpanzees' or the institutions' characteristics, housing, or husbandry. Once selected, the participating zoos provided information on the background of their chimpanzees. Zoos often provide a valuable retirement sanctuary for primates and as a result, the backgrounds of the chimpanzees in this study were varied, including “wild caught,” entertainment industry, pet trade, laboratories, other zoological gardens, and sometimes a combination of these. As only partial background information was available in several cases, we classified background as either: <italic>wild</italic>, <italic>laboratory</italic>, <italic>pet-trade/entertainment</italic>, or <italic>zoo</italic>.</p>
      <p>Across the groups there were 17 male and 23 female chimpanzees. Median group size was 6.5 (range = 3–11). Groups were either single-male (two groups) or multi-male (four groups, one of which was male only) and included a wide range of ages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020101-t002">Table 2</xref>). For analysis, we assigned individuals to age categories: 8–15 yrs, 16–23 yrs, 24–31 yrs, 32–39 yrs, and 40+ yrs. Five of the six groups showed a mix of rearing styles (<italic>wild-born</italic>, <italic>mother-reared</italic>, <italic>hand-reared</italic>: reared by human care-giver(s) and bottle fed); the sixth consisted of individuals who were all <italic>hand-reared</italic>. All groups had access to multiple areas (both indoor and outdoor). Only one of the groups had access restricted to a single areas at any one time, typically outside during the day, and inside at night. All enclosures met AZA/BIAZA standards.</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0020101-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
          <title>Study groups: size and composition.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0020101-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group Size</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Males</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Females</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age range (years, category limits)</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8–31</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32–40+</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8–39</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">D</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8–39</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24–39</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8–40+</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt102">
            <label/>
            <p>Groups were drawn from six accredited zoological institutions in the USA and UK; the behaviour of all group members was sampled (n = 40 individuals).</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>Data were collected from December 2008 to May 2010. Thirty hours of continuous focal sampling (a method of data collection in which all activities of a designated individual are recorded <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Altmann1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin3">[40]</xref>) were collected for each chimpanzee, yielding a total of 1200 observation hours (1800 min per individual). Data were collected using pen-and-paper from the public viewing areas at each zoo at distances ranging from 0.1 m (through glass) to about 10 m between observer and subject. Samples lasted 30 min and were collected in randomized rotation among members of each group, except for one zoo where reduced observability of subjects meant that samples lasted 20 min and could not be randomized at some times of the day. Once a focal sample began, recording was continuous unless a subject went out of sight; for every minute of such ‘bad observation’ one minute was added to the end of the sample.</p>
      <p>From these data, we constructed four measures of abnormal behaviour: prevalence (proportion of individuals in a group who show a type of behaviour), diversity (number of types of behaviour), frequency (number of bouts of behaviour), and duration (amount of time spent performing a behaviour). Since our behavioural data were not normally distributed, we used nonparametric statistical tests <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Gibbon1">[41]</xref>. All tests were two-tailed, and following convention, we set α at 0.05. Data were analyzed using SPSS Statistics 19 (SPSS Inc.).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>All 40 chimpanzees showed some abnormal behaviour. Across groups, the most prevalent behaviour (0.83) was <italic>eat faeces</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020101-t003">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0020101-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Six behaviours were present in all six groups (<italic>eat faeces</italic>, <italic>rock</italic>, <italic>groom stereotypically</italic>, <italic>pat genitals</italic>, <italic>regurgitate</italic>, <italic>fumble nipple</italic>) and a further two (<italic>pluck hair</italic> and <italic>hit self</italic>) were present in five of the six groups. <italic>Bite self</italic> was shown by eight individuals across four of the groups. Across groups and behaviours, the median prevalence was 0.1 (range: 0.03–0.83). The number of different abnormal behaviours displayed in each group varied from 15 to 23 (mean = 18) and was not correlated with the number of individuals in the group (r = 0.46; n = 6, p = 0.35).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0020101-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Percentage of chimpanzees from six independent zoological collections displaying each of the indicated abnormal behaviours.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0020101-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
          <title>Abnormal behaviours shown by zoo-living chimpanzees (n = 40).</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0020101-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Duration</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Frequency</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Behavioural Pattern</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prevalence</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Eat faeces</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.83</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–53</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–16</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pluck hair</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–125</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–83</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rock</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–574</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–51</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Groom stereotypically</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.50</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–172</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–152</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pat genitals</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–44</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–46</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poke anus</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–15</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–7</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Regurgitate</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.30</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–33</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–35</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fumble nipple</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–173</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–56</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pluck hair other</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–106</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–24</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bite self</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–55</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–22</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hit self</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–42</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clap</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Manipulate faeces</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–13</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jerk</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–200</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Toss head</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–39</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bang self against surface</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–16</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Configure lips</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–995</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–183</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Display to human</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–13</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–7</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stimulate self stylized</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–15</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–38</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bounce</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–45</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–17</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clasp self</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drink urine</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–7</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Eat faeces other</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incest</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16–26</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pace</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–64</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–124</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spit</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Twirl</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–30</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Twitch body-part</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45–49</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25–41</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bite-hit-lick combination</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Floating limb</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Groom stereotypically w object</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Move hand stereotypically</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">141</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pinch self</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poke eye</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">230</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rub hands</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Touch urine stream</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Walk on object</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt103">
            <label/>
            <p><italic>Prevalence</italic> = number of individuals performing the behaviour/total number of individuals; <italic>duration</italic> = minutes/30 hrs observation; <italic>frequency</italic> = number of performances per 30 hrs observation. Abnormal behaviours were not mutually exclusive categories, and in some cases two or more occurred at the same time; <italic>duration</italic> is specific to each individual behaviour. Range only stated where min. and max. values differ.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>Each of the 40 focal subjects displayed at least 2 abnormal behaviours (median: 5, range: 2–14). The number of different behaviours per individual (diversity) did not differ significantly across groups (Kruskal-Wallis H = 6.28, df = 5, p = 0.28). The lowest-scoring group had a median diversity of 4.5, and the highest-scoring group had a median diversity of 6.5. Similarly, the frequency of abnormal behaviour did not differ across groups (H = 5.75, df = 5, p = 0.33): group (C) with the lowest frequency had a median frequency of 0.6/hr, while group A had the highest median frequency of 3.2/hr (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020101-t004">Table 4</xref>). The median total duration of abnormal behaviour likewise did not differ across groups (H = 1.28, df = 5, p = 0.94).</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0020101-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
          <title>Performance of 37 abnormal behaviour patterns by social group.</title>
        </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0020101-t004-4" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020101.t004" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
            <col align="center" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Diversity</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Frequency per 30 hr</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Duration (%)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Group</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range</td>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5–11</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20–482</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9–62.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–8</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13–320</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.0</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.9–7.7</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5–190</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2–35.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">D</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2–9</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6–109</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1–25.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5–14</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24–105</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.3</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8–5.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3–12</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5–260</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6</td>
              <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1–11.9</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt104">
            <label/>
            <p>Total = number of abnormal behavioural patterns observed in the group; diversity = number of abnormal behaviour patterns per individual; frequency = number of bouts per individual; duration = percentage of observation time spent performing abnormal behaviour per individual.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      <p>In contrast, both frequency and duration of abnormal behaviours varied greatly between individuals. Across individuals, the median frequency was 1.45/hr but this ranged from 0.13/hr to 13.5/hr. The median total duration of abnormal behaviour was 79 min, or 4.4% of 30 hr observation time, but there was great individual variation (0.1–62.4% of activity: <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020101-t004">Table 4</xref>)</p>
      <p>We found no effect of age or sex on the occurrence of abnormal behaviour whether measured by diversity (Sex: Mann-Whitney U = 187, n = 17, 23, p = 0.811; Age: Kruskal-Wallis H = 4.40, df = 4, p = 0.35), frequency (Sex: U = 212, p = 0.652; Age: H = 7.11, df = 4, 0.13) or duration (Sex: U = 147, p = 0.185; Age: H = 5.75, df = 4, p = 0.22). We also found no effect of rearing history (<italic>wild-born</italic>: n = 9, <italic>mother-reared</italic>: n = 17, <italic>hand-reared</italic>: n = 9) on the occurrence of abnormal behaviour, for diversity (H = 1.95, df = 2, p = 0.38), frequency (H = 2.46, df = 2, p = 0.29) or duration (H = 0.05, df = 2, p = 0.97); the ‘unknown’ group (n = 5) was omitted from this analysis. We also found no effect of background (<italic>wild</italic>, <italic>laboratory</italic>, <italic>pet-trade/entertainment</italic>, <italic>zoo</italic>) on diversity (H = 2.92, df = 3, p = 0.40), frequency (H = 0.99, df = 3, p = 0.81), or duration (H = 0.74, df = 3, p = 0.86).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our overall finding was that abnormal behaviour was present in all sampled individuals across six independent groups of zoo-living chimpanzees, despite the differences between these groups in size, composition, housing, etc. We found substantial variation between individuals in the frequency and duration of abnormal behaviour, but all individuals engaged in at least some abnormal behaviour, and variation across individuals could not be explained by sex, age, rearing history or background (defined as prior housing conditions).</p>
      <p>Direct comparison of our results to earlier studies is complicated by differences in methods, particularly the measures used. Some studies coded only presence or absence for a behaviour, limiting any comparison to prevalence. On this measure, we found - across individuals and behaviours - a very similar level (0.10) to that (0.11; calculated from their <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0020101-t003">Table 3</xref>) reported by Fritz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Fritz1">[10]</xref> (also Nash et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nash1">[29]</xref>), although the most prevalent behaviour across these studies - <italic>eat faeces</italic> (<italic>coprophagy</italic>) – is performed by more individuals in our sample (prevalence: 0.85 vs. 0.49). Other studies present the fraction of activity budget spent in abnormal behaviour, calculated from durations or proportion of interval samples. By this measure, the individuals in our sample spent considerably more time behaving abnormally. Martin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin1">[15]</xref> reported a median value of zero; four individuals who spent 5.6% of their time behaving abnormally were described as showing exceptionally high levels of abnormal behaviour. Similarly, Bloomsmith et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bloomsmith1">[9]</xref> reported an average of only 0.3% (see also Hook et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Hook1">[4]</xref>). These figures are substantially lower than our average figure of 4.4%, and maximum of &gt;60%.</p>
      <p>Our study combined a relatively large sample of individuals across multiple populations with detailed, lengthy, direct, and continuous observations of behaviour. We found that some of the abnormal behaviours were performed for only short durations, or at low frequencies; many abnormal behaviours occurred rarely and only in limited contexts, and were often brief. Our choice of sampling method may have allowed us to record behaviours that might have been missed using other approaches. Continuous focal animal sampling allows the determination of prevalence, frequency, and duration, and so provides a more complete picture of the behaviour under investigation. For these reasons, this is the preferred sampling method for observational behavioural studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Altmann1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Martin3">[40]</xref> and we suggest future studies of abnormal behaviour should use this method when logistics allow.</p>
      <p>So how abnormal is the behaviour of captive chimpanzees? In 1023 hours of focal animal sampling of wild chimpanzees in Uganda, none of the abnormal behaviours listed in this study were observed (Newton-Fisher, unpublished data). In contrast, seventeen of 37 behaviours we detailed in this study have been reported to occur (albeit rarely) in wild chimpanzees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Goodall1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nishida2">[38]</xref>. The most prevalent form of ‘abnormal’ behaviour in this and other studies of captive populations – coprophagy – has been reported from at least six wild populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Payne1">[42]</xref> and it may also be transmitted by social learning <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nash1">[29]</xref>. If this – or other – behaviour is ‘abnormal’ in captive chimpanzees, it may be the rate at which it is performed rather than simple occurrence that deviates from the behaviour of wild chimpanzees.</p>
      <p>A formal comparison of rates and durations of these behaviour patterns between captive and wild populations is difficult: few sufficiently detailed quantitative data are available from wild populations, as might be expected for behaviours that are notably rare. The published literature on abnormal behaviour in wild chimpanzees is sparse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Goodall1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Payne1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-HiraiwaHasegawa1">[43]</xref> and rates of abnormality comparable to those that we describe here have never been reported. The hypothetical average individual in our sample of captive chimpanzees had a repertoire of five abnormal behaviours, performed some kind of abnormal behaviour once every forty minutes or so (although in real individuals, performance was more clumped than this figure implies) and spent between four and five percent of their activity in abnormal behaviours. Some individuals were far more extreme (over 60% of activity), and all individuals showed at least 2 different types of abnormal behaviour (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nash1">[29]</xref>).</p>
      <p>Our data support a conclusion that, while most behaviour of captive chimpanzees is ‘normal’ in the sense that it is behaviour seen in their wild counterparts, abnormal behaviour is endemic in captivity. For some individuals it may dominate much of their activity, but for the rest it is a persistent element of their everyday behaviour despite living in social groups in enriched environments. Note that we do not address here whether captive chimpanzees use their normal behaviour in a manner atypical of wild chimpanzees, which may be a further dimension to ‘abnormal’ behaviour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Paquette1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Celli1">[45]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the wild, chimpanzee communities have a fluid social structure in which individuals are free to choose associates, mates, and ranging area (although all of these are subject to competitive effects). Similarly, they choose when, where, and what to eat; their natural diets include many species of flora and fauna, and they use a large variety of foraging, food processing, and hunting methods. Their daily activities vary accordingly, and they range widely over varied landscapes and habitat types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Goodall1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Boesch1">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Nishida3">[47]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-McGrew1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Reynolds1">[49]</xref>. In comparison, zoo-living chimpanzees have little opportunity to adjust association patterns, occupy restricted and barren spaces compared to the natural habitat, and have large parts of their lives substantially managed by humans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Hosey1">[14]</xref>. Controlled diets and provisioned feeding contrast radically with the ever-changing foraging and decision-making processes of daily life in the wild.</p>
      <p>Providing captive apes with more naturalistic enclosures, unpredictable feeding schedules and extractive foraging opportunities, as well as the opportunity to interact with conspecifics through housing in social groups, all appear to decrease the performance of abnormal behaviours <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bloomsmith1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Clarke1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Celli1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bloomstrand1">[50]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Lukas1">[51]</xref>. Even the best zoo environments (which includes all zoos in this study) are limited, however, in what they can provide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Clarke1">[13]</xref>. Some abnormal behaviours persist despite interventions to ‘naturalise’ the captive conditions and we suggest that captivity itself may be fundamental as a causal factor in the presence of persistent, low-level, abnormal behaviour (and potentially more extreme levels in some individuals). The cognitive and behavioural challenges in captivity are fewer than in the wild – stressful and dangerous place that it may be – and many normal behaviours and normal development are precluded. While extreme levels of abnormal behaviour may be explicable by individuals' particular histories, the pattern of low-level, pervasive abnormal behaviour shown by this study suggests that chimpanzee minds struggle to cope with conditions of captivity, despite the best efforts of those charged with their care.</p>
      <p>From the perspective of human psychiatry, some of the behavioural abnormalities demonstrated by chimpanzees might be seen as symptoms of compromised mental health, i.e. mental illness, if they were observed in human primates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bradshaw1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne2">[17]</xref>. As with humans, chimpanzees are self-aware <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Gallup1">[52]</xref> sentient, emotional creatures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Goodall1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Parr1">[53]</xref> with the potential to suffer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Goodall1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Rollin2">[54]</xref>. The apparently pervasive nature of abnormal behaviour, and its persistence in the face of environmental enrichment and social group housing, raises the concern that at least some examples of such behaviour are indicative of possible mental health problems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bradshaw1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Brne2">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Future research should address preventative or remedial actions, whether intervention is best aimed at the environment and/or the individual, and how to best monitor recovery <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Bourgeois1">[7]</xref>. More critically, however, we need to understand how the chimpanzee mind copes with captivity, an issue with both scientific <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0020101-Garner1">[55]</xref> and welfare implications that will impact potential discussions concerning whether such species should be kept in captivity at all.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank all the participating zoological gardens for their help and support throughout the project, especially during data collection. BIAZA gave approval to the project and a letter of support, for which we are very grateful. Mr. E. Thetford gave inspiration at the start of the study, and L.P. Birkett thanks him very much for that.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Young1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <source>Environmental enrichment for captive animals</source>             <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Blackwell Science Ltd</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">240</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Mason1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <source>Stereotypic animal behaviour: fundamentals and applications to welfare. 2nd ed</source>             <publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>CABI</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">384</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Poole1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Granli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Mind and movement: Meeting the interests of elephants.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forthman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancocks</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldau</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>An elephant in the room: The science and well-being of elephants in captivity</source>             <publisher-loc>North Grafton, MA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Tufts University</publisher-name>             <fpage>2</fpage>             <lpage>21</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Hook1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavisky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bloomsmith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Inter-group variation in abnormal behavior in chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) and rhesus macaques (<italic>Macaca mulatta</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Applied Animal Behaviour Science</source>             <volume>76</volume>             <fpage>165</fpage>             <lpage>176</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Brne1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüne-Cohrs</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Psychiatric treatment for great apes?</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>306</volume>             <fpage>2039</fpage>             <lpage>2039</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Walsh1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bramblett</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>A vocabulary of abnormal behaviors in restrictively reared chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>American Journal of Primatology</source>             <volume>3</volume>             <fpage>315</fpage>             <lpage>319</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Bourgeois1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brasky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Combination therapy reduces self-injurious behavior in a chimpanzee (<italic>Pan troglodytes troglodytes</italic>): A case report.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</source>             <volume>10</volume>             <fpage>123</fpage>             <lpage>140</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Baker1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Easley</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <article-title>An analysis of regurgitation and reingestion in captive chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Applied Animal Behaviour Science</source>             <volume>49</volume>             <fpage>403</fpage>             <lpage>415</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Bloomsmith1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bloomsmith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1995</year>             <article-title>Effects of predictable versus unpredictable feeding schedules on chimpanzee behavior.</article-title>             <source>Applied Animal Behaviour Science</source>             <volume>44</volume>             <fpage>65</fpage>             <lpage>74</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Fritz1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matevia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>The relationship between forage material and levels of coprophagy in captive chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Zoo Biology</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>313</fpage>             <lpage>318</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Bradshaw1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capaldo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grow</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Building an inner sanctuary: complex PTSD in chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Trauma and Dissociation</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>9</fpage>             <lpage>34</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Bradshaw2">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capaldo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grow</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Developmental context effects on bicultural posttrauma self repair in chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Developmental Psychology</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>1376</fpage>             <lpage>1388</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Clarke1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juno</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maple</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1982</year>             <article-title>Behavioral effects of a change in the physical environment: a pilot study of captive chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Zoo Biology</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>371</fpage>             <lpage>380</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Hosey1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosey</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skyner</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Self-injurious behavior in zoo primates.</article-title>             <source>International Journal of Primatology</source>             <volume>28</volume>             <fpage>1431</fpage>             <lpage>1437</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Martin1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Early life experiences: Activity levels and abnormal behaviours in resocialised chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Animal Welfare</source>             <volume>11</volume>             <fpage>419</fpage>             <lpage>436</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Murray1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <article-title>The effects of group structure and rearing strategy on personality in Chimpanzees <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> at Chester, London ZSL and Twycross Zoos.</article-title>             <source>International Zoo Yearbook</source>             <volume>36</volume>             <fpage>97</fpage>             <lpage>108</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Brne2">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüne-Cohrs</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preuschoft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Psychopathology in great apes: concepts, treatment options and possible homologies to human psychiatric disorders.</article-title>             <source>Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews</source>             <volume>30</volume>             <fpage>1246</fpage>             <lpage>1259</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Rollin1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <source>Science and ethics</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">304</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Brne3">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brüne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <source>Textbook of evolutionary psychiatry</source>             <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">380</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Goodall1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1986</year>             <source>The chimpanzees of Gombe: Patterns of behaviour</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Belknap Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">673</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-deWaal1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Waal</surname><given-names>FBM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1989</year>             <article-title>Food sharing and reciprocal oligations among chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Human Evolution</source>             <volume>18</volume>             <fpage>433</fpage>             <lpage>459</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Inoue1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuzawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Working memory of numerals in chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Current Biology</source>             <volume>17</volume>             <fpage>R1004</fpage>             <lpage>1005</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Searle1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <source>Consciousness and language</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">280</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Mcgrew1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcgrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1981</year>             <article-title>Social and cognitive capabilities of non-human primates: Lessons from the wild to captivity.</article-title>             <source>International Journal for the Study of Animal Problems</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>138</fpage>             <lpage>149</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Davenport1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1979</year>             <article-title>Some behavioral disturbances of great apes in captivity.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamburg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCown</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>The great apes</source>             <publisher-loc>Menlo Park, CA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Benjamin Cummings</publisher-name>             <fpage>341</fpage>             <lpage>357</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Davenport2">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>RK</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzel</surname><given-names>EW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>             <year>1963</year>             <article-title>Stereotyped behavior of the infant chimpanzee.</article-title>             <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>             <volume>8</volume>             <fpage>99</fpage>             <lpage>104</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Martin2">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>The influence of rearing on personality ratings of captive chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Applied Animal Behaviour Science</source>             <volume>90</volume>             <fpage>167</fpage>             <lpage>181</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Lutz1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Environmental enrichment for nonhuman primates: theory and application.</article-title>             <source>ILAR Journal</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>178</fpage>             <lpage>191</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Nash1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Variables influencing the origins of diverse abnormal behaviors in a large sample of captive chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Americal Journal of Primatology</source>             <volume>48</volume>             <fpage>15</fpage>             <lpage>29</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Hosey2">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosey</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>How does the zoo environment affect the behaviour of captive primates?</article-title>             <source>Applied Animal Behaviour Science</source>             <volume>90</volume>             <fpage>107</fpage>             <lpage>129</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-NewtonFisher1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton-Fisher</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2004</year>             <article-title>Hierarchy and social status in Budongo chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Primates</source>             <volume>45</volume>             <fpage>81</fpage>             <lpage>87</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-NewtonFisher2">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton-Fisher</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2011</year>             <article-title>Grooming reciprocity in wild male chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Animal Behaviour</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>439</fpage>             <lpage>446</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Muller1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Agonistic relations among Kanyawara chimpanzees.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boesch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Behavioural diversity in chimpanzees and bonobos</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>112</fpage>             <lpage>124</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Wrangham1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wrangham</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1986</year>             <article-title>Ecology and social relationships in two species of chimpanzee.</article-title>             <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wrangham</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>             <source>Ecology and social evolution: Birds and mammals</source>             <publisher-loc>Princeton, USA</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>             <fpage>352</fpage>             <lpage>378</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Fritz2">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1992</year>             <article-title>Abnormal behaviors, with a special focus on rocking, and reproductive competence in a large sample of captive chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>).</article-title>             <source>American Journal of Primatology</source>             <volume>27</volume>             <fpage>161</fpage>             <lpage>176</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Pederson1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pederson</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landau</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Chimpanzee (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) personality predicts behavior.</article-title>             <source>Journal of Research in Personality</source>             <volume>39</volume>             <fpage>534</fpage>             <lpage>549</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Nishida1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1999</year>             <article-title>Ethogram and ethnography of Mahale chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Anthropological Science</source>             <volume>107</volume>             <fpage>141</fpage>             <lpage>188</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Nishida2">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsusaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <source>Chimpanzee behavior in the wild: An audio-visual encyclopedia</source>             <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">247</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Altmann1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1974</year>             <article-title>Observational study of behaviour: Sampling methods.</article-title>             <source>Behaviour</source>             <volume>49</volume>             <fpage>227</fpage>             <lpage>265</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Martin3">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <source>Measuring behaviour: An introductory guide</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">176</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Gibbon1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbon</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1997</year>             <source>Nonparametric methods for quantitative analysis</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>American Sciences Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">537</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Payne1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>CLR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2008</year>             <article-title>Coprophagy by the semi-habituated chimpanzees of Semliki, Uganda.</article-title>             <source>Pan Africa News</source>             <volume>15</volume>             <fpage>29</fpage>             <lpage>32</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-HiraiwaHasegawa1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiraiwa-Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>A case of offspring desertion by a female chimpanzee and the behavioral-changes of the abandoned offspring.</article-title>             <source>Primates</source>             <volume>29</volume>             <fpage>319</fpage>             <lpage>330</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Paquette1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paquette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paquette</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1988</year>             <article-title>Use of novel objects to enhance environments of captive chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Zoo Biology</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>15</fpage>             <lpage>23</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Celli1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Celli</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomonaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Udono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teramoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Tool use task as environmental enrichment for captive chimpanzees.</article-title>             <source>Applied Animal Behaviour Science</source>             <volume>81</volume>             <fpage>171</fpage>             <lpage>182</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Boesch1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boesch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boesch-Achermann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2000</year>             <source>The chimpanzees of the Taï forest</source>             <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">316</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Nishida3">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1990</year>             <source>The chimpanzees of the Mahale Mountains: sexual and life history strategies</source>             <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>University of Tokyo Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">328</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-McGrew1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGrew</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1996</year>             <source>Great ape societies</source>             <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">352</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Reynolds1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <source>The chimpanzees of the Budongo forest: Ecology, behaviour and conservation</source>             <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>             <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name> <comment>xv, 297 p.</comment>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Bloomstrand1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bloomstrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alford</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maple</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1986</year>             <article-title>Objective evaluation of a behavioral enrichment device for captive chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>).</article-title>             <source>Zoo Biology</source>             <volume>5</volume>             <fpage>293</fpage>             <lpage>300</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Lukas1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lukas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boesch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigilant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>To what extent does living in a group mean living with kin?</article-title>             <source>Molecular Ecology</source>             <volume>14</volume>             <fpage>2181</fpage>             <lpage>2196</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Gallup1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallup</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1970</year>             <article-title>Chimpanzees: Self recognition.</article-title>             <source>Science</source>             <volume>167</volume>             <fpage>86</fpage>             <lpage>87</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Parr1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parr</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Understanding chimpanzee facial expression: Insights into the evolution of communication.</article-title>             <source>Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>221</fpage>             <lpage>228</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Rollin2">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1998</year>             <comment>The unheeded cry: Animal consciousness, animal pain, and science</comment> <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">330</size>           </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0020101-Garner1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Stereotypies and other abnormal repetitive behaviors: Potential impact on validity, reliability, and replicability of scientific outcomes ILAR</article-title>             <source>Journal</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>106</fpage>             <lpage>117</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>