<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-06421</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Agriculture</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Agricultural production</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Agroecology</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Crops</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Soil science</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Soil ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Anthropology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biological anthropology</subject>
              <subject>Ethnobiology</subject>
              <subject>Social anthropology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Archaeology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Ethnoarchaeology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Plant Biology</subject>
          <subject>Ecology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Convergent Adaptations: Bitter Manioc Cultivation Systems in Fertile Anthropogenic Dark Earths and Floodplain Soils in Central Amazonia</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Convergent Adaptations</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Fraser</surname>
            <given-names>James Angus</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Alves-Pereira</surname>
            <given-names>Alessandro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Junqueira</surname>
            <given-names>André Braga</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Peroni</surname>
            <given-names>Nivaldo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Clement</surname>
            <given-names>Charles Roland</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Departamentos de Antropología e Historia, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Cundinamarca, Colombia</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Anthropology, University of Sussex, East Sussex, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Post-graduate Program in Genetics and Plant Breeding, Universidade de São Paulo, Piracicaba, Estado de São Paulo, Brazil</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Laboratório de Evolução Aplicada, Universidade Federal do Amazonas, Manaus, Amazonas, Brazil</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff5">
        <label>5</label>
        <addr-line>Coordenação de Tecnologia e Inovação, Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia, Manaus, Amazonas, Brazil</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff6">
        <label>6</label>
        <addr-line>Centre for Crop Systems Analysis/Technology and Agrarian Development Group Wageningen University, Wageningen, Gelderland, The Netherlands</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff7">
        <label>7</label>
        <addr-line>Departamento de Ecologia e Zoologia, Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina, Florianópolis, Santa Catarina, Brazil</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Newsom</surname>
            <given-names>Lee A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>The Pennsylvania State University, United States of America</addr-line>
      </aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">james.angus.fraser@gmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JAF AAP CRC NP. Performed the experiments: JAF AAP NP ABJ. Analyzed the data: JAF AAP NP ABJ CRC. Wrote the paper: JAF AAP NP ABJ CRC.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e43636</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
        
        <copyright-holder>Fraser et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions><abstract>
        <p>Shifting cultivation in the humid tropics is incredibly diverse, yet research tends to focus on one type: long-fallow shifting cultivation. While it is a typical adaptation to the highly-weathered nutrient-poor soils of the Amazonian <italic>terra firme</italic>, fertile environments in the region offer opportunities for agricultural intensification. We hypothesized that Amazonian people have developed divergent bitter manioc cultivation systems as adaptations to the properties of different soils. We compared bitter manioc cultivation in two nutrient-rich and two nutrient-poor soils, along the middle Madeira River in Central Amazonia. We interviewed 249 farmers in 6 localities, sampled their manioc fields, and carried out genetic analysis of bitter manioc landraces. While cultivation in the two richer soils at different localities was characterized by fast-maturing, low-starch manioc landraces, with shorter cropping periods and shorter fallows, the predominant manioc landraces in these soils were generally not genetically similar. Rather, predominant landraces in each of these two fertile soils have emerged from separate selective trajectories which produced landraces that converged for fast-maturing low-starch traits adapted to intensified swidden systems in fertile soils. This contrasts with the more extensive cultivation systems found in the two poorer soils at different localities, characterized by the prevalence of slow-maturing high-starch landraces, longer cropping periods and longer fallows, typical of previous studies. Farmers plant different assemblages of bitter manioc landraces in different soils and the most popular landraces were shown to exhibit significantly different yields when planted in different soils. Farmers have selected different sets of landraces with different perceived agronomic characteristics, along with different fallow lengths, as adaptations to the specific properties of each agroecological micro-environment. These findings open up new avenues for research and debate concerning the origins, evolution, history and contemporary cultivation of bitter manioc in Amazonia and beyond.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group>
        <funding-statement>The research was funded by Leverhulme Trust (Grant F/00 230/W) and the CNPq (Brazilian National Research Council) (CT Amazonia 575588/08-0). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Shifting cultivation has been a predominant mode of traditional agriculture in the rainforests of the lowland Neotropics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-ArroyoKalin1">[1]</xref>, humid Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Neumann1">[2]</xref>, the Indian subcontinent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-KingwellBanham1">[3]</xref> and parts of South East Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Barker1">[4]</xref> and Oceania <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Denham1">[5]</xref> for thousands of years. Shifting cultivation in the humid tropics is incredibly diverse <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Brookfield1">[6]</xref>, yet both empirical studies and theoretical discussions tend to focus on one type: long-fallow shifting cultivation (LFSC). LFSC is an <italic>extensive</italic> form of crop production, which entails a relatively short cropping period of 1–3 years, followed by a longer fallow period (normally 10–20 years), with land cleared by slashing and burning fallow vegetation (or sometimes mature forest) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Conklin1">[7]</xref>. The long fallow period is necessary because soils of the <italic>terra firme</italic> (non-flooded upland plateaus) in the tropical world tend to be highly-weathered infertile Oxisols and Ultisols (US classification system). Hence, this form of land-use is spatially (fields must shift frequently) and temporally (fields must be fallowed for years before they can be cultivated again) <italic>extensive</italic>. Extensive systems are widely held to be well adapted to such soils because a nutrient flush provided by the burning of secondary or mature forest is used for a single cropping period, before swidden fields are left to fallow in order to restore fertility via the growth of secondary forest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Nye1">[8]</xref>. It has long been assumed that any intensification of LFSC (i.e., a reduction of fallow periods) in the humid tropics will cause crop yields to decline, as infertile Oxisols and Ultisols are not capable of withstanding a sustained reduction of fallow periods, leading to the eventual collapse of the system. These assumptions about the prevalence and precariousness of extensive shifting cultivation have influenced theories of cultural development in Amazonia, where Steward <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Steward1">[9]</xref> and Meggers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Meggers1">[10]</xref> held that the small scattered Amerindian settlements practicing LFSC found in the interfluvial <italic>terra firme</italic> today represent an optimal adaptation to a low productivity environment. While their theories have long since gone out of fashion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Stahl1">[11]</xref>, studies of the cultivation of the Amazonian staple bitter manioc (<italic>Manihot esculenta</italic> Crantz) continue to focus almost exclusively on LFSC practiced by current Native Amazonian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Rival1">[12]</xref> and other traditional populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Emperaire1">[13]</xref> in the poor soils of marginal interfluvial <italic>terra firme</italic> environments.</p>
      <p>In Amazonia, however, the most populated areas – both today and in the late pre-Columbian period – are along major white-water rivers, such as the Solimões, Amazon and Madeira, all of which have nutrient-rich floodplain soils used for agriculture and adjacent paleo-floodplains that are somewhat more nutrient-rich than the typical Oxisols and Ultisols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Irion1">[14]</xref>, as well as areas of Anthropogenic Dark Earths <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Glaser1">[15]</xref>. These regions are among the most suitable for human habitation and population growth, since they are characterized by an abundance of fish as well as fertile soils. Students of pre-Columbian Amazonia have long emphasized the agricultural potential of these regions. Lathrap <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Lathrap1">[16]</xref> argued that the productivity of the white-water floodplains underwrote the growth of large and dense human settlements, sparking competition and warfare between groups for these rich but spatially and temporally limited areas. However, although the flood pulse provides a yearly flush of nutrients, extreme floods once every decade or so can destroy crops, settlements and even the high floodplain itself, which makes these environments relatively unpredictable. Denevan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Denevan1">[17]</xref> argued that agriculture began as multi-cropping in floodplain environments and developed later in forested uplands as intensive multi-cropping systems with short fallow. For him, long fallow, extensive cultivation is a late development associated with the introduction of efficient forest clearance tools, especially metal axes and machetes.</p>
      <p>Denevan recognized that large scale settlements could not have been supported exclusively by seasonal floodplain cultivation, given the riskiness of producing food in areas subjected to floods. He proposed that settlements would preferentially be located on bluffs along the river margins, allowing the exploitation of both the fertile floodplain zones and the <italic>terra firme</italic> areas that were safe from flooding but located on less fertile soils <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Denevan1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Denevan2">[18]</xref>. This occupation pattern would ultimately result in the transformation of upland soils: many bluffs in central Amazonia feature fertile anthropogenic soils known as Anthropogenic Dark Earths (ADE) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Glaser2">[19]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Woods1">[21]</xref>. These soils are associated with Native Amazonian settlements of the late pre-Columbian period (2000–500 years before present) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Neves1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Heckenberger1">[23]</xref>, and are most abundant and largest in whitewater regions, because these are where the largest populations were located in pre-Columbian times <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Petersen1">[24]</xref>. Amazonian ADE form through human inputs of organic and inorganic matter [e.g., biomass wastes, manure, bones, ash, charcoal and ceramics] <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Glaser1">[15]</xref>. Amazonian ADE are enduringly fertile in part due to their historical enrichment in highly stable black carbon, which has a half-life of 1000 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Kuzyakov1">[25]</xref>. ADE exhibit much higher levels of chemical elements essential for plant growth, such as phosphorous, calcium, magnesium, zinc and manganese, than the weathered and infertile soils in which they were formed. ADE sites exhibit a highly fertile ‘core area’, which grades into more subtly modified soils, with a continuum of fertility between them and surrounding soils <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Schmidt1">[27]</xref>. It is likely that ADE were appreciated for plant cultivation by pre-Columbian Native Amazonian peoples, just as they are by Amazonian people today <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Erickson1">[28]</xref>.</p>
      <p>These historical arguments point to the possibility that local people may also intensify shifting cultivation when circumstances permit today. Fertile soils, such as ADE and floodplain soils, provide farmers with the opportunity to intensify shifting cultivation, increasing both crop productivity and frequency of cultivation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-German1">[29]</xref>, raising the carrying capacity of the landscape <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Smith1">[30]</xref>. Therefore, the study of swidden systems on fertile soils allows us to examine the extent to which fallow lengths, bitter manioc landraces, and other aspects of swidden systems vary on different soils. While numerous studies have addressed many dimensions of shifting cultivation, few have compared swidden systems on different soils and in different ecological contexts within a circumscribed geographical area <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-German2">[31]</xref>.</p>
      <sec id="s1a">
        <title>The Amazonian Staple: Bitter Manioc</title>
        <p>Manioc landraces are classified as either bitter or sweet depending on cyanogenic glucoside (CG) content. In Central Amazonia, bitter manioc is the staple crop today, whilst sweet manioc is only of secondary importance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-ArroyoKalin2">[32]</xref>. Sweet manioc has low CG content in their tuberous roots (&lt;100 ppm fresh weight), while bitter manioc has larger amounts of cyanogenic glycosides (&gt;100 ppm fresh weight) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-McKey1">[33]</xref>. There are an estimated 7000 landraces of manioc worldwide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Hershey1">[34]</xref>, but this is surely an underestimate given farmers' continual selection and propagation of new landraces. Differences in the color, form and size of leaves and stems, in the size, number, color and cyanide content of roots, and in the rate of growth of tuberous roots are determined by genetic differences, although the environmental conditions in which plants grow also affect manioc phenotypes, including CG content <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-McKey1">[33]</xref>. Farmers comprehend a “landrace” as a set of individuals sharing particular morphological characteristics that differentiate them from other landraces; they also distinguish them by giving them a particular name <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Boster1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Elias1">[36]</xref>. These morphological characteristics are shaped by genotype-environment interactions that can result in different phenotypic expressions of the same genotype, and create morphotypes that are identified as distinct landraces <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Emperaire2">[37]</xref>. Landraces are the result of generations of farmer selection in local environments, and are therefore well adapted to local growing conditions, which has been demonstrated in South America <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Emperaire1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Salick1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Elias2">[39]</xref>, in humid Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Deltre1">[40]</xref> and Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Ellen1">[41]</xref>. Several students of manioc have asserted that bitter manioc does not yield well in fertile soils <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Jones1">[42]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Ohly1">[44]</xref>, perhaps because it has been so thoroughly studied on nutrient-poor soils. However, about 30% of Central Amazonian manioc, both bitter and sweet, is produced in the floodplain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Gutjahr1">[45]</xref>. It was observed that on highly fertile soils manioc plants tend to invest more in aboveground biomass than in the tubers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-German1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Roosevelt1">[43]</xref>. However, there are bitter manioc landraces that yield well in the floodplain and in ADE, possibly even better than in Oxisols and Ultisols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser2">[46]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Manioc is vegetatively propagated via stem cuttings, which grow into plants that are genetically identical to the mature plants from which they were cut. However, manioc retains its ability to reproduce sexually and produces seeds that lie dormant in fallow vegetation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-McKey2">[47]</xref>. When fallows are cleared for cultivation, seeds are stimulated to germinate by increasing temperatures caused by both soil exposure and the heat of the burn phase in swidden-fallow systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Pujol1">[48]</xref>, and seedlings appear <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Elias3">[49]</xref>. When cuttings from seedlings are incorporated into a landrace, its genetic diversity is increased because it becomes a polyclonal landrace <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Elias1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Pujol1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Elias4">[50]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Peroni1">[52]</xref>. This increased genetic diversity provides the raw material for adaptation to new conditions, such as ADE and the floodplain, as different clones in the landrace have different possibilities for adaptation to different agro-ecosystems. The extent to which volunteer seedlings are incorporated is variable in modern bitter manioc cultivation in the Neotropics. Studies in Guyana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Elias5">[53]</xref>, French Guiana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Pujol3">[54]</xref> and the Atlantic Forest in Brazil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Peroni2">[55]</xref> found a relatively high level of incorporation. However, Stocker found only a small amount of seedling incorporation amongst farmers in Pará, in eastern Brazilian Amazonia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Stocker1">[56]</xref>:162–63). Nonetheless, this is a recurring pattern in many traditional farming systems in Amazonia and beyond <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Emperaire1">[13]</xref>.</p>
        <p>This article examines the hypothesis that contemporary Amazonian people have developed divergent bitter manioc cultivation systems as adaptations to the properties of different soils in the landscapes that they inhabit. We test this hypothesis by comparing swidden systems in fertile (ADE and floodplain) and infertile (Oxisols and Ultisols) soils with respect to their assemblages of manioc landraces, the performance (from the farmer's point of view) and productivity of the most common landraces in different soils, along with the genetic relationships between the most common landraces, and length of fallow periods. Hence, we will examine both the adaptations of manioc landraces and of swidden-fallow systems. In earlier publications <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser2">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser3">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser4">[58]</xref>, we hypothesized, based on initial interpretations of ethnobotanical data, that “weak” bitter manioc landraces grown in ADE originated in the floodplain, given farmers' knowledge and similar adaptations (fast maturation and low starch content).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Farmer theory and practice</title>
        <p>In the preliminary stage of research we conducted multi-sited participant observation in numerous communities of the study region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Subsequent quantitative work was driven by hypotheses generated during this stage. While qualitative data have been presented at length elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser3">[57]</xref>, here we summarize major findings and their interplay with quantitative data. We found that, contrary to what was expected from the literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-German1">[29]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-German2">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Roosevelt1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Hiraoka1">[59]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-German4">[61]</xref>, bitter manioc was widely cultivated in ADE. More specifically, farmers stated that not only did they <italic>i</italic>) perceive that certain landraces yield better in certain soils (the basis for our <italic>pri</italic> index and yield observations, see below), but that this informed their <italic>ii</italic>) selection of different landraces for planting in different soils (the basis for the <italic>la</italic> index), and <italic>iii</italic>) that fertile soils (ADE/floodplain) could be farmed with much shorter fallow periods than infertile soils (the basis for our fallow length data).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0043636-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Map of the middle Madeira River region, Amazonas State, Brazil, showing communities where research was carried out.</title>
            <p>The inset map shows the location of the middle Madeira River in Northern South America. Map by Victoria Frausin.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Most intriguingly, however, was the finding that farmers expressed these perceptions and behaviors in the form of a local theory of strength and weakness (the categories strong and weak are present in traditional agriculture in other areas of the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Harlan1">[62]</xref>:148)). Along the middle Madeira River, the categories weak and strong express the suitability of different landraces for planting in different soil-successional scenarios. Briefly, weak landraces are fast yielding (5 months–1 year), but rot if left too long in the ground, and produce less starch than stronger landraces. Strong landraces, on the other hand, are slow yielding (1–3 years), but produce more starch than weaker landraces. Farmers claim that weak landraces are best suited to planting in “weak” land (land with young fallow), whilst strong landraces are said to be suited to “strong” land (land with older fallow). Elsewhere, we reported that landraces described as weak were planted more frequently in ADE and the floodplain, whilst those described as strong were planted more frequently in Oxisols and Ultisols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser5">[63]</xref>:400). The specifics of this local theory have been elaborated at length <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser2">[46]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser3">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser4">[58]</xref>, and here we would just emphasize two points. This local theory would appear to provide evidence of the cognitive aspects of adaptation – local people have theorized the emergent properties of their adaptive knowledge and practices – and express these using the simple yet powerful metaphors of strength and weakness. Secondly, this theory is not limited to the middle Madeira; an independent study recently found an identical theory of weak and strong manioc amongst floodplain and <italic>terra firme</italic> manioc farmers in and around the Brazilian Sustainable Development Reserves of Mamirauá and Amanã, close to the town of Tefé on the middle Solimões River <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Lima1">[64]</xref>. The fact that the same local theory exists in two localities hundreds of kilometers apart suggests that this theory is likely to inform adaptive aspects of manioc farming in various locations throughout Amazonia.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Diversity of manioc landraces</title>
        <p>A total of 50 landraces were found, with 29 in ADE, 20 in Oxisols, 20 in Ultisols and 23 in the floodplain. Most of the landraces cultivated on the <italic>terra firme</italic> are planted in more than one type of soil: among the 29 landraces cultivated in ADE, 18 (62%) are also planted in Ultisols and 19 (65.5%) in Oxisols. Ultisols and Oxisols shared 75% (15) of their landraces. On the other hand, most of the landraces that occurred in the floodplains (19, or 82.6%) only occurred in this environment, with only four landraces shared with other types of soil (one shared with Ultisols and ADE, and three that occurred in all four types of soil). The number of landraces cultivated in each village varied between 5 (Verdum) and 21 (Vista Alegre), and tended to be lower in floodplain villages (N = 5; mean ± standard deviation: 8.2±3.1) than villages located on the <italic>terra firme</italic> (N = 4; 15.7±5.0), principally because villages on the <italic>terra firme</italic> have access to more than one type of soil (and, in the case of Água Azul, even cultivate in the floodplain). The average number of landraces cultivated in each manioc field was similar among the different types of soil (ADE: 2.8±1.9; Oxisols: 3.4±1.5; Ultisols; 3.2±2.0; Floodplain: 3.1±1.3) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043636.s001">Dataset S1</xref>).</p>
        <p>Along the Upper Negro River, communities commonly have 60 to 89 landraces, somewhat higher when compared to other local communities in Amazonia and in the Atlantic Forest in Brazil (53–58; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Emperaire1">[13]</xref>). The diversity of bitter manioc landraces on the <italic>terra firme</italic> along the middle Madeira is quite low, although higher than what Grenand reported along the Cuieiras River near Manaus (six) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Grenand1">[65]</xref>. Perhaps this is due to a greater market orientation in the Madeira River communities, and higher population pressure. By contrast, the number of landraces we registered on the floodplain is much higher than reports for Careiro Island (three; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Grenand1">[65]</xref>) at the confluence of the Negro and Solimões Rivers, and for communities between Santarém and Óbidos (maximum of four), along the middle Amazon River <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Castro1">[66]</xref>, although Pereira <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Pereira1">[67]</xref> reported 43 bitter manioc landraces at the confluence of the Solimões and Japurá Rivers. The generally low numbers in the literature most likely reflect the lack of attention to manioc in the floodplain compared to the <italic>terra firme</italic>, as pointed out by Denevan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Denevan3">[68]</xref> for studies of agriculture in the floodplain in general. Various studies mention fast maturing manioc in the floodplain, without reporting the number of landraces <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Smith2">[69]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Lima2">[71]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Landrace composition of manioc fields in different soils</title>
        <p>The composition of manioc landraces in fields on different types of soil is significantly different, which is shown both in the general model (NPMANOVA; F = 16.46, p = 0.01) and also in all possible pairwise comparisons (six) between the four different soil types (all with p values lower than 0.05, corrected for multiple comparisons) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g002">Figure 2</xref>). In general, manioc fields in Oxisols and Ultisols cluster together, while in Floodplains they form an almost completely separate group, with fields in ADE occupying an intermediate area in the ordination space (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Also, fields in Oxisols and Ultisols are more homogeneous, while in Floodplains and ADE they are more heterogeneous, especially in the latter case. The areas of overlap and the dispersion of some points through the figure indicate that the composition of manioc landraces is very heterogeneous and highlights the practice of landrace exchange between soils. Within-field heterogeneity is commonly reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Rival1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Emperaire1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Salick1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Boster2">[72]</xref>, as is exchange among farmers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Boster1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Elias1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Salick1">[38]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Deltre1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Pujol1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Pujol4">[73]</xref>, but exchange among farmers on different soil types has not been reported previously, perhaps because the heterogeneity of soils has been less carefully studied than that of bitter manioc landraces.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0043636-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) showing the composition of bitter manioc landraces sampled in fields on Ultisols, Oxisols, Anthropogenic Dark Earths (ADE) and on floodplains along the middle Madeira River (percentage of explanation of the bidimensional model: 35.8%).</title>
            <p>Each point represents a bitter manioc field, and its position in the graph is a bidimensional representation of the Bray-Curtis dissimilarity between the fields.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Farmer perceptions of landrace performance</title>
        <p>A Performance Ranking Index (<italic>pri</italic>) for each landrace in each type of soil on the <italic>terra firme</italic> was calculated. Most of the landraces mentioned by the farmers in the interviews in all three soils on the <italic>terra firme</italic> (ADE, Oxisol and Ultisol) have a very low <italic>pri</italic> score, either because they are rarely cited in that specific soil or because farmers do not rank them among the best performers in that soil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g003">Figure 3</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043636.s001">Dataset S1</xref>). <italic>Roxinha</italic>, <italic>Tartaruga</italic>, <italic>Arroz</italic> and <italic>Aruari</italic> are among the five landraces with higher <italic>pri</italic> in all three soils. However, while the landraces <italic>Jabuti</italic> and <italic>Arroz</italic> are considered the best performers in Oxisols and Ultisols, in ADE this place is occupied by <italic>Tartaruga</italic>, <italic>Pirarucu Branco</italic> and <italic>Roxinha Branca</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0043636-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Farmer perceptions of performance for the six most frequent manioc landraces cultivated in Oxisols, Ultisols and Anthropogenic Dark Earths (ADE) along the middle Madeira River.</title>
            <p>Numbers in the axis indicate the Performance-Rank Index (<italic>pri</italic>) of each landrace in each type of soil, calculated based on the perception of 162 farmers interviewed on the Middle Madeira. Dots indicate the value of <italic>pri</italic> for each variety in the three types of soil.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>There were strong positive correlations between the area occupied by each landrace in the fields (<italic>la</italic>) and their performance (<italic>pri</italic>) in the soils (Pearson's Correlation - Ultisol: ρ = 0.901; Oxisol: ρ = 0.912; ADE: ρ = 0.898). This high degree of correlation between <italic>pri</italic> and <italic>la</italic> supports the notion that farmers' planting behavior is shaped by their perceptions of the performance of different landraces in different types of soil. While this pattern is common and has been mentioned elsewhere (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Lebot1">[74]</xref>:50), the correlations between this pair of indices permits a quantitative demonstration of this behavior.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Farmer estimates of manioc yields</title>
        <p>Our farmer yield observations reveal that there are significant differences between yields in five of the six most popular landraces when planted in different soils along the middle Madeira River (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0043636-t001">Table 1</xref>). These findings support our inference of a high degree of adaptation in bitter manioc systems found on different soils, since landraces that perform better in particular soils tend to be more predominant in those soils, as farmers respond positively to good yields by planting more of specific landraces. This is reflected in the <italic>la</italic> and <italic>pri</italic> indices: <italic>Jabuti</italic> and <italic>Roxinha</italic> are significantly more predominant in Oxisols and Ultisols than in ADE, while <italic>Tartaruga</italic> and <italic>Pirarucu Branco</italic> are more predominant in ADE than in Oxisols or Ultisols.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0043636-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
            <title>Farmer-recorded production of 50 kg sacks of manioc flour that would be obtained from approximately 0.5 ha of swidden plot at various localities along the Middle Madeira River, Central Amazonia, Brazil, in 2007–2008.</title>
          </caption><alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0043636-t001-1" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Manioc landrace</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">ADE</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Oxisol/Ultisol</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Floodplain</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">ANOVA</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(avg ± SD)</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(avg ± SD)</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(avg ± SD)</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jabuti</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.2±5.1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.2±8.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arroz</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31±2.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.5±4.2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ns</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tartaruga</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.4±6.1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.7±3.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.0</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Roxinha</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.2±3.11</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40.1±4.3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43.5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pirarucu Branco</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.2±7.0<sup>a</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.7±4.6<sup>b</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55±11.2<sup>a</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.8</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pirarucu Amarelo</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.7±24.9<sup>a</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.5±4.4<sup>b</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.5±11.3<sup>a</sup></td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.012</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt101">
              <label/>
              <p>Superscript characters indicate significant differences in pairwise comparisons using Tukey's HSD test (p&lt;0.05).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2f">
        <title>Fallow length and the intensification of swidden systems</title>
        <p>Intensification in swidden-fallow systems refers, among other factors, to a shortening of fallow length <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Boserup1">[75]</xref>. Intensification on infertile soils can result in exhaustion of fertility and breakdown of the system. Fertile soils provide opportunities for sustainable reduction of fallow lengths. The average fallow length for 55 fields on Ultisols was 13.2±8.1 years and for 64 Oxisol fields the average length was 21.3±15.4 years, while for 71 ADE fields it was 6.5±6.8 years and for 59 floodplain fields it was 1.6±4.0. There were significant differences between fallow lengths in different soils (ANOVA, F = 44.51, p&lt;0.001, while Tukey's post hoc test revealed significant differences between all possible pairwise comparisons except ADE vs Floodplain). It is important to emphasize that local factors, such as population density, also play important roles in shaping fallow lengths, and these are discussed at length for each locality in the Supporting Information, along with other factors (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043636.s003">Text S1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2g">
        <title>Generation, selection and exchange of landrace diversity</title>
        <p>Local farmers identify and exchange genetic diversity of bitter manioc landraces <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Salick1">[38]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Boster2">[72]</xref>. Along the middle Madeira River, we observed that certain people that we categorized as “key individuals” play an important role in the exchange of new landraces originating from seedlings, conservation of existing landraces and knowledge associated with them. Key individuals were identified as being the individuals who most informants mentioned during open interviews as being responsible for introducing new landraces and keeping a stock of all landraces present in each community. Interviews with these key individuals revealed that they consciously recognize new phenotypes and are always intentionally experimenting with new landraces from seedlings and with clonal material from their kin in other communities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Emperaire1">[13]</xref>. These key individuals perform a vital role in the identification and distribution of new manioc genetic diversity, because they try out new landraces in local micro-environments and, if they prove to be exceptional, are responsible for their distribution within communities, and to kin in other communities. The fact that each locality only has a few key individuals points to the critical role that they play in the circulation of exceptional landraces throughout the region, but some new genotypes can circulate unconsciously mixed with other individuals that are morphologically similar.</p>
        <p>At the six localities examined in this study, both the incorporation of seedlings into pre-existing landraces and the creation of new landraces from seedlings are relatively common practices. Farmers recognize that seedlings often appear in the newly burnt fields <italic>before</italic> cuttings have been planted and are morphologically different from the planted landraces, as they tend to grow taller and only have a single tuberous root growing straight downwards. Most farmers (53–66% across communities) interviewed simply ignore or weed out the seedlings, while others (11–32%, including, but not restricted to key individuals) take cuttings from mature seedlings and plant them separately (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0043636-t002">Table 2</xref>). When mature, these volunteers are either: i) incorporated into an existing landrace, e.g., <italic>Jabuti</italic>; ii) incorporated as a sub-landrace of an existing landrace (such as <italic>Jabuti</italic>-<italic>Preto</italic>); iii) named as a combination of two landraces (such as <italic>Jabuti</italic>-<italic>Arroz</italic>); or iv) established as a new landrace with a different name.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0043636-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
            <title>Number of informants, both total and key individuals for manioc management, number of landraces cultivated, and the ways that farmers manage seedlings at six communities along the middle Madeira River, municipality of Manicoré, Amazonas, Brazil.</title>
          </caption><alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0043636-t002-2" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Informants</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of landraces</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Seedling Management</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Key</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intentionally incorporate</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Incorporate at random</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Remove</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barro Alto</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barreira do Capanã/Boa Vista</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.66</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Água Azul</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vista Alegre</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.55</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Água Azul floodplain</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.55</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genipapo floodplain</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives></table-wrap>
        <p>All the landraces analyzed with microsatellite markers had observed heterozygosities (<italic>H<sub>O</sub></italic>) higher than expected heterozygosities (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0043636-t003">Table 3</xref>), which appears to be related to both the incorporation of seedlings and the selection of heterozygous individuals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-AlvesPereira1">[76]</xref>. For example, the landrace <italic>Arroz</italic> from ADE at Barreira do Capanã had an observed heterozygosity of 0.495 and 5 different multi-locus genotypes (MLGs) in the 20 individuals examined. The landraces <italic>Jabuti</italic> from Oxisols and <italic>Tartaruga</italic> from floodplain had 7 and 6 different MLGs, and <italic>H<sub>O</sub></italic> of 0.567 and 0.707, respectively. The number of MLGs reflects either the incorporation of seedlings or the unintentional “mixing” of landraces (which may happen, for example, when they are morphologically similar), both of which contribute to increasing heterozygosity. Incorporation of seedlings into recognized landraces increases intra-landrace heterogeneity, because farmers tend to select the largest and healthiest volunteers, which tend to be the most heterozygous <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Elias5">[53]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Pujol3">[54]</xref>. These practices are critical in maintaining and amplifying the genetic diversity of manioc landraces, and in adapting landraces to new environmental conditions, such as different soils.</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0043636-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
            <title>Indices of intra-varietal genetic diversity [Observed (<italic>H<sub>O</sub></italic>) and expected (<italic>H<sub>E</sub></italic>) heterozygosities, and number of multi-locus genotypes (No. MLGs)] for five bitter manioc landraces cultivated in different soil types in the middle Madeira River region, based on variation detected with 10 microsatellite markers.</title>
          </caption><alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0043636-t003-3" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
            <table>
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Landrace</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Soil</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Locality</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>H<sub>O</sub></italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>H<sub>E</sub></italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. MLGs</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MLGs</td>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Pirarucu Branco</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADE</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barreira do Capanã</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.495</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.250</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>A</bold>, g</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FP</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pau Queimado</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.505</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.255</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>B</bold>, h</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Tartaruga</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADE</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barro Alto</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.503</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.268</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>B</bold>,F</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OX</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barro Alto</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.507</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.276</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>B</bold>, F, i, j</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FP</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Verdum</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.707</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.361</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>C</bold>, k, l, m, n</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Arroz</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADE</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barreira do Capanã</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.495</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.460</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A, <bold>D</bold>, o, p, q</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OX</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Água Azul</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.503</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.257</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>D</bold>, r</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Jabuti</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OX</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Barreira do Capanã</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.567</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.445</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">D, <bold>E</bold>, s, t, u, v</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <italic>Pirarucu Amarelo</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADE</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Água Azul</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.607</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.306</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>F</bold>, x</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FP</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Água Azul</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.607</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.307</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                  <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                    <bold>F</bold>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nt102">
              <label/>
              <p>Capital letters indicate the MLGs that were present in more than one landrace. Boldfaced letters indicate the most common MLG for a given landrace, while small letters indicate MLGs present at low frequencies.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
        <p>Along the middle Madeira River the performance in different soils is a major factor in varietal selection by farmers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The selection of distinct traits in different environments where the landraces are cultivated may be correlated to the genetic differentiation found among the bitter manioc landraces grown in different soil types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g005">Figure 5</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-AlvesPereira2">[77]</xref>). Evidence of genetic divergence among landraces cultivated in floodplain from those cultivated in ADE and infertile soils was also found when analyzing intra-varietal genetic diversity. In all examples the landraces grown in ADE and infertile soils had the same most common MLGs. On the other hand, landraces grown in the floodplain, except <italic>Pirarucu Amarelo</italic>, had distinct MLGs from those with the same landrace name but grown in ADE or infertile soils. Additionally, in the floodplain some farmers observed that volunteers occur more frequently in higher areas of the floodplain. These areas are not flooded every year and the seeds have time to be acted upon by agro-ecological management. The planting of manioc in different zones, the flood regime, farmer perceptions and the combination of landraces they select drive the generation of new landraces in the floodplain. This is consistent with the somewhat higher number of landraces from the floodplain observed in this study, and may be related to the genetic differentiation among the landraces grown in the floodplain from those grown in upland soils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0043636-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Principal Coordinates Analysis based on diversity revealed by 10 microsatellites markers showing the dispersion of 48 swiddens from three soil types (17 in ADE soils, 14 in floodplain soils and 17 in Oxisols/Utilsols) in six communities along the middle Madeira River.</title>
            <p>The two coordinates together explain 65.4% of the variation in the matrix.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0043636-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Schematic representation of floodplain zones relative to the main channel, lakes and <italic>terra firme</italic> (non-flooded upland plateaus).</title>
            <p><italic>Vazante</italic> is the local term on the middle Madeira for the banks of the main channel, <italic>Restinga</italic> for the high levee floodplain and <italic>Cacaia</italic> for the back-swamp area. Drawn by Victoria Frausin.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2h">
        <title>Farmer selection for agronomic performance? Comparative perspectives</title>
        <p>Our findings call for re-evaluation of the widespread notion that farmer identification and selection of manioc landraces is weakly associated with agronomic performance. This notion is based on Boster's research on the perceptual distinctiveness of manioc amongst the Aguaruna Jivaro of the Peruvian Amazon. Boster concluded that “there are significant differences between the [manioc] cultivars in their responses to environmental factors…”, but “the Aguaruna are generally unaware of or unconcerned with these differences” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Boster2">[72]</xref>:40). Boster's own garden experiments did, however, show that “some cultivars grow well in sandy alluvial soils on river islands and do poorly on other sites, while other cultivars yield about the same regardless of soil conditions.” Boster also noted that the Cashinahua, another Native Amazonian group that resides in Peru and Brazil, do appear to select particular landraces for planting in certain kinds of soil, according to their well-known ethnographer, Ken Kensinger <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Kensinger1">[78]</xref>. The Aguaruna Jivaro reside in hill country, where there is certainly a lot of soil variation and there will be some high quality soils, and the Cashinauhua live along the fertile whitewater Juruá River (Tarauacá, Jordão, Breu, Muru, Envira) and in the Purus basin (Upper Purus and its affluent the Curanja) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Aquino1">[79]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Ricardo1">[80]</xref>. Each of these areas offers a variety of very different soils to the manioc farmer. However, even in the Upper Negro Region, an area notorious for infertile soils, according to Wilson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Wilson1">[81]</xref>, there appears to be non-random planting of sweet manioc in more fertile soils by Tukanoan manioc farmers. Heckler and Zent, on the other hand, describing research amongst the Piaroa in Venezuela, found that “specific genotype-micro-condition interactions were demonstrably not a significant factor in determining planting patterns” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Heckler1">[82]</xref>:684). Similarly, Salick and colleagues, reporting on a study amongst the Amuesha in Peruvian Amazonia, found that “soil seemed to have little predictive power for cassava phenotype occurrence.” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Salick1">[38]</xref>:11).</p>
        <p>The findings of Boster, Heckler and Zent, and Salick et al. explain the persistence of the notion that farmer identification and selection of manioc landraces is weakly associated with agronomic performance. Our findings, however, when combined with those of Kensinger and Wilson, support the conclusion that the way in which <italic>at least some</italic> Amazonian farmers consciously identify and select landraces <italic>is</italic> shaped by agronomic performance. Indeed, the perceptual weak-strong theory of manioc detailed above and elsewhere appears to be built upon and indeed express in schematic/metaphoric form local knowledge of selection for agronomic performance. This raises questions regarding the distribution of practices of selection for agronomic performance, and which factors (such as the presence/absence of fertile soils, indigenous/non-indigenous farmers etc.) contribute to the presence of these practices and associated knowledge in different parts of Amazonia. We conjecture that selection for agronomic performance would be more likely to emerge amongst people inhabiting areas with greater heterogeneity of soil types.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We examined manioc cultivation in four different soil types at six localities, and found that farmers plant different assemblages of bitter manioc landraces in different soils and that shorter fallow lengths were strongly associated with more fertile soils. Most popular landraces were shown to exhibit significantly different yields when planted in different soils. From this we can infer that farmers have selected different sets of landraces with different perceived agronomic characteristics, along with different fallow lengths, as adaptations to the specific properties of each agroecological micro-environment. On the <italic>terra firme</italic>, intentional selection of certain landraces for cultivation in certain soils was demonstrated by the close relationship between <italic>Performance Ranking Index</italic> and <italic>Landrace Area</italic> for landraces in different soil types. These findings suggest that the local theory revolving around metaphors of strength and weakness may represent a cognitive manifestation of adaptive farming behavior: a way to express in simple terms local knowledge of the relationship between different sets of bitter manioc landrace traits and soil properties and fallow stages. Although landraces grown in ADE and the floodplain share similar phenotypical characteristics, specifically fast maturation and low starch content, and are both described as “weak” by farmers, these groups of landraces were not genetically more related to each other, as we had predicted from ethnobotanical observation. Rather, the landraces grown in upland soils (ADE and Oxisols/Ultisols) are more related to each other and genetically differentiated from floodplain landraces. For landraces cultivated in the floodplain and in ADE, the selection for convergent adaptive traits appears to be associated with the similar ecological adaptations to nutrient-rich soils and short periods for rapid growth and yield before stress. The stresses are quite different, however: floods in the floodplain and enhanced weed pressure in ADE. Nonetheless, they yield convergent adaptive results.</p>
      <p>If the similar ecological adaptations observed for ADE and floodplain landraces are outcomes of adaptive convergence of traits directed by farmer's selection, what drives that selection? On ADE, farmer selection for fast maturing landraces coupled with a reduction in fallow periods is likely to be driven by population pressure and permitted by ADE's high nutrient availability. When ADE is cultivated at Barro Alto and Água Azul, where population pressure exerts more of an influence, the most intensive swidden-fallow systems were found (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043636.s003">Text S1</xref>). These intensive systems were associated with a reduction in the diversity of landraces in general, suggesting that when farmers reduce fallow lengths they may select only the fastest maturing landrace that is widely available for planting. In the floodplain, selection for fast maturing landraces is certainly a strategy to cope with the high seasonality of the floodplain determined by the flood pulse. Hence two different swidden-fallow systems have developed as convergent adaptations to intensification in nutrient-rich anthropogenic and floodplain soils. This intensification may be driven by population pressure (<italic>terra firme</italic>) and the flood pulse (floodplain); alternatively, owing to their greater fertility, it may be that the floodplain and ADE are the only places that offer the opportunity to produce food and/or money in a shorter time period – and this could also be a driver for the selection of these common traits.</p>
      <p>Our findings broaden our understanding of the diversity of bitter manioc swidden-fallow systems in contemporary Amazonia, and allow some ethnographic projection. Firstly, the intensive short-fallow shifting cultivation in the floodplain and on bluffs with ADE that we reported along the middle Madeira are clearly modern analogs of Denevan's <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Denevan1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Denevan2">[18]</xref> hypothesis that pre-conquest food production systems were much more intensive than the extensive long-fallow shifting cultivation common today, which he argues is a post-conquest adaptation. Secondly, Arroyo-Kalin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-ArroyoKalin2">[32]</xref> recently hypothesized that during the pre-Columbian period manioc was selected for high toxicity in swiddens in the infertile agricultural hinterland further from settlements, but farmers were selecting for lower toxicity in fertile ADE soils forming in and around homegardens. The phenomenon of farmer selection being driven by landrace agronomic performance in different soils would support the possibility that farmer selection in the pre-Columbian period for planting in different environments was a key driver in the emergence of “bitter” and “sweet” manioc and the continuum of toxicity that underlie them. Given the importance of bitter manioc cultivation to our understanding of pre-Columbian and contemporary populations in Central Amazonia, we hope that this study will encourage further research into the under-investigated area of intensified bitter manioc cultivation in fertile soils.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Study area and sampling design</title>
        <p>We focus on the middle Madeira River, Amazonas State, Brazil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g001">Figure 1</xref>), where traditional farmers plant their staple crop, bitter manioc, in infertile Oxisols and Ultisols of the <italic>terra firme</italic>, and in fertile ADE and floodplain soils. Amazonian Dark Earths are easily recognizable by their very dark brown or black coloring, high fertility, and pottery shards. The other <italic>terra firme</italic> soils were classified in the field according to local ethnopedological knowledge and physical properties (color, presence of potsherds, etc.). It was found that the local ethnopedological category “<italic>barro</italic>” (clay), recognized by its red/yellow coloring and high clay content in the A horizon, is broadly coterminous with Oxisols, while the local category “<italic>areia</italic>” (sand), recognized by dark brown, grey or black coloring and highly friable and “sandy” (although probably pseudosands) A horizon is broadly coterminous with Ultisols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser1">[26]</xref>. Along the Madeira River, farmers recognize three major zones in the floodplain: i) the highly fertile sides of the main channel, locally known as the <italic>vazante</italic>; ii) the high floodplain, known as the <italic>restinga</italic>; iii) and the back-swamp area, known as the <italic>cacaia</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g005">Figure 5</xref>). These terms are local and identify fewer categories than Denevan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Denevan3">[68]</xref> observed along the floodplain of the Ucayali River, in eastern Peru, between the towns of Pucallpa and Panaillo.</p>
        <p>Both the collection of plant material and the interviews took place after prior informed consent was obtained at each community. Anthropological fieldwork was authorized by a scientific expedition (EXC 022/05) granted by the Brazilian National Research Council (CNPq). Four <italic>terra firme</italic> localities (the second and third comprised of several communities) were selected for semi-structured quantitative interviews on bitter manioc cultivation on ADE, Oxisols and Ultisols: Barro Alto, Barreira do Capanã/Boa Vista, the Água Azul Coast, and Vista Alegre (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0043636-g001">Figure 1</xref>). These localities were selected because they had the greatest numbers of farmers cultivating this crop on ADE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser6">[83]</xref>. All farmers cultivating bitter manioc on ADE in these localities at the time of research were interviewed. We selected an equivalent number of families farming Oxisols and Ultisols using the snowball method whereby new families were enrolled through those who had already been interviewed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Bryman1">[84]</xref>:184–85). Two floodplain localities, each comprising several communities, were selected. Upstream from Manicoré families resident in the floodplain communities Fortaleza and Pau Queimado, and a few families at Água Azul and Monte Sião who had fields in the floodplain were selected. Downstream from Manicoré are the communities Verdum, Amparo and Delícia. These communities are among the longest established floodplain communities on the middle Madeira River. All farmers present at these floodplain communities during visits were interviewed. Key individuals who maintained the highest number of bitter manioc landraces were identified through open-interviews with different community members. In order to minimize gender/age biases, and to verify information from multiple sources, interviews were conducted in the household, normally with all of the family present, as family members would often intervene to correct the orator or provide additional information.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Participant observation and open interviews</title>
        <p>JAF conducted extensive participant observation in all communities of the study area prior to and during subsequent quantitative work (from September 2006 to March 2008), in order to build rapport and open up areas of interest that cannot be gleaned from close reading of the literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Bernard1">[85]</xref>. This entailed engaging in daily activities, including planting, harvesting and processing manioc, and conducting open, unstructured interviews with local people. The advantage of this type of initial qualitative approach is that it places no limitations on and is non-reductive in relation to reality. This open-ended approach led to the generation of the hypothesis that this paper addresses (that there are different adaptive manioc systems in different soils) and facilitated the discovery of the local theory of weakness and strength. The disadvantage of such an unstructured qualitative approach is that it cannot test the hypotheses it generates, and this is why we generated various novel quantitative indicators to measure aspects of bitter manioc cultivation systems from which adaptability could be inferred (planting behaviour, perceptions of landrace performance in different soils, yields and fallow lengths).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Ethnobotanical Data, Indices and Analyses</title>
        <p>In total, we conducted 249 semi-structured interviews at the six localities between May 2007 and March 2008. Quantitative ethnobotanical data were gathered on a) the area occupied by each manioc landrace (landrace area – <italic>la</italic> – see below) in fields on four soil types (ADE, Ultisols, Oxisols and Floodplain), b) perceptions of relative performance (performance ranking index – <italic>pri</italic> – see below) of the same landraces in the three different <italic>terra firme</italic> soils, c) fallow lengths, and d) incorporation of seedlings. In order to test if fields on different soils exhibit different compositions of landraces, data on <italic>la</italic> were ordered through a Non-Metric Multidimensional Scaling (NMDS) based on the Bray-Curtis dissimilarity, followed by non-parametric multivariate analyses of variance (MANOVA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-McCune1">[86]</xref>). Non-parametric MANOVAs were performed for the general model (i.e., including all soil types simultaneously) and also for the six possible pairwise comparisons between the soil types. Critical p-values were adjusted by the Holm correction for multiple comparisons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Wright1">[87]</xref>. The relationship between <italic>la</italic> and <italic>pri</italic> was investigated using simple correlations. Composite soil samples were collected in each field and the results from chemical analysis were used for an <italic>a posteriori</italic> classification of soil types <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser1">[26]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Landrace Area Index and Fallow Lengths</title>
        <p>In order to identify the different landraces cultivated and quantify their abundance in the fields, we relied on the local nomenclature for the landraces and on numerical estimates provided by each farmer, using a local unit commonly used for quantifying manioc stem cuttings. In general, farmers along the middle Madeira recall the amount of each landrace they plant in terms of the number of bundles (“<italic>feixes</italic>”) of each landrace they planted in their fields. We asked each farmer (a) which landraces he/she cultivated, (b) how many bundles of each landrace he had planted in his/her current manioc field and (c) how big was his/her field. Using this information we calculated the area occupied by each landrace in each field (<italic>la</italic>) through the formula:<disp-formula id="pone.0043636.e001"><graphic orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <italic>la</italic> is the <italic>landrace area</italic> index, <italic>nbv</italic> is the number of bundles of a given landrace planted in a given field, <italic>nbT</italic> is the total number of bundles planted in that field, and <italic>arf</italic> is the area of the field. Since we did not observe differences in the spacing used to plant the landraces, we regard the area occupied by each landrace (<italic>la</italic>) as a good estimator of the abundance of each landrace in the field. When all landraces are taken into account, we interpret this data as the varietal composition of the fields. We collected data on fallow lengths by asking each farmer how old the fallow was that he/she had cleared in order to establish the field. Data for the calculation of <italic>la</italic> and on fallow lengths were collected with 249 farmers at all six localities, of which 190 farmers on the <italic>terra firme</italic> and 59 on the floodplain.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Performance Ranking Index and seedling management</title>
        <p>During participant observation it emerged that farmers claimed that certain landraces performed better in particular soils <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser6">[83]</xref>. In order to quantify this, we asked all 190 <italic>terra firme</italic> farmers (a) to name all landraces that they cultivated in each type of soil and then (b) to rank the landraces mentioned according to their performance in that specific soil. Based on Sutrop's “Cognitive Salience Index” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Sutrop1">[88]</xref>, we combined data on the frequency with which a given landrace was cited, its mean position in the performance ranking and calculated a Performance Ranking Index (<italic>pri</italic>) of each landrace in each type of soil, using the formula:<disp-formula id="pone.0043636.e002"><graphic orientation="portrait" position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula>where <italic>pri</italic> is the Performance Ranking index, <italic>F</italic> is the frequency of citations of the landrace, <italic>N</italic> is the number of farmers interviewed who cultivate in this specific type of soil, and <italic>mP</italic> is the mean position of the landrace in the rankings.</p>
        <p>Participant observation also revealed that some farmers purposefully separate cuttings from volunteer seedlings for later planting, others simply harvest them together with other landraces (resulting in their random incorporation into pre-existing landraces), and others purposefully exclude volunteers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Fraser6">[83]</xref>. Once these three categories were established, the incorporation of seedlings was measured by asking 114 farming families if they: a) <italic>separated</italic> seedlings, that is took cuttings from seedlings and planted them apart to see how they did; b) <italic>randomly</italic> incorporated seedlings, where they do plant cuttings of seedlings volunteers, but randomly mixed up with the other landraces; or c) <italic>removed</italic> them, cutting the volunteers out as weeds when they appeared in the field.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Farmer landrace yield estimates</title>
        <p>Thirty one farmers were selected to record the production of different bitter manioc landraces in mono-varietal patches within 43 fields on the four different soil types. They were selected on the basis of literacy, their expressed interest in participating in the study (i.e., willingness to commit to recording production), and, crucially, the fact that they had mono-varietal patches within manioc fields during the study period. Bitter manioc fields are harvested bit by bit depending on labor availability and demand for manioc flour for subsistence consumption and sale. Amazonian farmers also do not tend to have accurate scales. They take a great interest in the amount of manioc flour produced, however, since it is equivalent to, as one woman put it, their “daily bread” (e.g., carbohydrate staple) and additionally an important product for sale in markets. In order to measure production therefore we asked farmers to record how many sacks of manioc flour (each sack is 50 kg) they produced from each mono-varietal-landrace patch. Fields were visited and we did not record significant differences in spacing, so we consider them to be all planted at similar density (around 1 meter between plants – c. 5000 plants per 0.5 ha). The size of mono-varietal patches varied (mean 0.286 ha±0.123 SD), so we corrected each one up to 0.5 ha in order to make the data commensurate and comparable using ANOVA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0043636-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Collection of genetic data</title>
        <p>The collection of plant material for genetic analyses was carried out in 2009. Authorization for interviewing farmers was obtained from <italic>Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia</italic>'s Committee for Research Ethics (protocol 235/09) and our collecting was registered in the System for Authorization and Information on Biodiversity, coordinated by the Chico Mendes Institute for Biodiversity, of the Ministry of the Environment (number of register: 10020-5). No proprietary traditional knowledge was accessed, allowing us to meet Resolution 21 requirements for basic research that does not require authorization from Brazil's Council for Genetic Patrimony (CGEN in the Brazilian acronym), which was consulted before field work.</p>
        <p>To investigate how the genetic diversity of bitter manioc was organized in different environments of cultivation we collected leaf samples of each landrace present in each of a total of 48 swiddens in all the localities except Vista Alegre: 17 in ADE soils, 14 in floodplain soils and 17 in Oxisols/Utilsols. A total of 184 individuals were sampled, representing 43 different bitter manioc landraces. The genetic variation of landraces was accessed using ten microsatellite loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-ChavarriagaAguirre1">[89]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Mba1">[90]</xref>, which are short sequences of repetitive DNA. Seven of them (GA21, GA126, GA131, GA134, GA136, GA140, GAGG5) were described by Chavarriaga-Aguirre <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-ChavarriagaAguirre1">[89]</xref> and three (SSRY13, SSRY89, SSRY 164) by Mba <italic>et al.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Mba1">[90]</xref>. Each microsatellite locus refers to a unique genomic region and the genetic variation results from differences in the number of repetitive units among individuals.</p>
        <p>To investigate the extent of genetic variation within landraces and the genetic identity of landraces with the same name but grown in different soil types, some of the most commonly cultivated bitter manioc landraces in the region (<italic>Pirarucu Branco</italic>, <italic>Tartaruga</italic>, <italic>Arroz</italic>, <italic>Jabuti</italic> and <italic>Pirarucu Amarelo</italic>) had 20 or 30 individuals sampled (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043636.s002">Dataset S2</xref>). To evaluate the dispersion of bitter manioc swiddens along the genetic diversity revealed by microsatellites, a Principal Coordinate Analysis (PCoA), based on Euclidian distances, was carried out with GenAlEx v.6.4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-Peakall1">[91]</xref>. Among the parameters used to describe intra-varietal genetic diversity, we estimated the observed (<italic>H<sub>O</sub></italic>) and expected (<italic>H<sub>E</sub></italic>) heterozygotes with GenAlEx v.6.4, while the number of multi-locus genotypes (MLGs) was analysed with GenClone v.2.0 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-ArnaudHaond1">[92]</xref>. <italic>H<sub>O</sub></italic> varies from 0 to 1, and corresponds to the probability that a given microsatellite locus has two different numbers of repetitions in a given individual. <italic>H<sub>E</sub></italic> also varies from 0 to 1, and corresponds to the proportion of heterozygote individuals that were expected under the Hardy-Weinberg Equilibrium based on the number of different microsatellite forms found for a given landrace. The MLGs describe the number of different microsatellite combinations present in a given group of individuals (in this case, the landraces). The detailed sampling strategy, material and methods and other genetic results are described elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-AlvesPereira1">[76]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0043636-AlvesPereira2">[77]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0043636.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Dataset S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Landrace area and performance ranking index.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0043636.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Dataset S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Intra-varietal genotypes and soil differentiation genotypes.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(XLSX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0043636.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0043636.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Text S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Manioc cultivation at the community level.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(DOCX)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We extend our heartfelt thanks to the people of the Middle Madeira River for participating in our research. JAF thanks the CNPq (Brazilian National Research Council) for granting research permission (EXC 022/05). AAP thanks the <italic>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior</italic>—CAPES for a master's scholarship. CRC thanks CNPq for a research fellowship (<italic>bolsas de produtividade</italic>). NP thanks CAPES for a research fellowship (PRODOC).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-ArroyoKalin1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arroyo-Kalin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Slash-burn-and-churn: Landscape history and crop cultivation in pre-Columbian Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Quaternary International</source> <volume>249</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Neumann1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bostoen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Höhn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kahlheber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ngomanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>First farmers in the Central African rainforest: A view from southern Cameroon</article-title>. <source>Quaternary International</source> <volume>249</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-KingwellBanham1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingwell-Banham</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>DQ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Shifting cultivators in South Asia: Expansion, marginalisation and specialisation over the long term</article-title>. <source>Quaternary International</source> <volume>249</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Barker1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Barker G, Gilbertson D, Reynolds T, editors (2012) Rainforest Foraging and Farming in Island Southeast Asia: The Archaeology and Environmental History of the Niah Caves, Sarawak. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Denham1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haberle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Agricultural emergence and transformation in the Upper Wahgi valley, Papua New Guinea, during the Holocene: theory, method and practice</article-title>. <source>Holocene</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>496</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Brookfield1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brookfield</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Padoch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Appreciating agrodiversity: A look at the dynamism and diversity of indigenous farming practices</article-title>. <source>Environment</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Conklin1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conklin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1961</year>) <article-title>The study of shifting cultivation</article-title>. <source>Current Anthropology</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Nye1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Nye PH, Greenland DJ (1960) The Soil under Shifting Cultivation. Harpenden, UK: Technical Communication 51, Commonwealth Bureaux of Soils. 156 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Steward1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Steward JH, editor (1948) Handbook of South American Indians. Volume 3: The Tropical Forest Tribes. Washington, D.C: Bulletin 143, Bureau of American Ethnology, Smithsonian Institution. 567 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Meggers1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Meggers BJ (1971) Amazonia: Man and Culture in a Counterfeit Paradise. Washington: Smithsonian Institution Press. 194 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Stahl1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Paradigms in paradise: revising standard Amazonian prehistory</article-title>. <source>The Review of Archaeology</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Rival1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rival</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Domestication and diversity in manioc (Manihot esculenta Crantz ssp. esculenta, Euphorbiaceae)</article-title>. <source>Current Anthropology</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1119</fpage>–<lpage>1128</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Emperaire1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emperaire</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peroni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Traditional management of agrobiodiversity in Brazil: A case study of manioc</article-title>. <source>Human Ecology</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>761</fpage>–<lpage>768</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Irion1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Irion G (1984) Sedimentation and sediments of Amazon rivers and evolution of the Amazon landscape since Pliocene times. In: Sioli H, editor. The Amazon - Limnology and Landscape Ecology of a Mighty Tropical River and its Basin. The Hague: Springer. pp. 201–204.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Glaser1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birk</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>State of the scientific knowledge on properties and genesis of Anthropogenic Dark Earths in Central Amazonia (terra preta de Indio)</article-title>. <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Lathrap1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Lathrap DW (1970) The Upper Amazon. Southampton: Thames &amp; Hudson. 256 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Denevan1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Denevan WM (2001) Cultivated Landscapes of Native Amazonia and the Andes; Clark G, Goudie A, Peach C, editors. Oxford: Oxford University Press. 400 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Denevan2">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Denevan</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>A bluff model of riverine settlement in prehistoric Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Annals of the Association of American Geographers</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>654</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Glaser2">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Glaser B, Woods WI, editors (2004) Amazonian Dark Earths: Explorations in Space and Time. Berlin: Springer. 216 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Lehmann1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Lehmann J, Kern DC, Glaser B, Woods WI, editors (2003) Amazonian Dark Earths. Origins, Properties and Management. Dordrecht: Kluwer Press. 523 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Woods1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Woods WI, Teixeira WG, Lehmann J, Steiner C, WinklerPrins AMGA, et al.. (2009) Amazonian Dark Earths: Wim Sombroek's Vision. Berlin: Springer. 504 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Neves1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Neves EG (2008) Ecology, ceramic chronology and distribution, long-term history, and political change in the Amazonian floodplain. In: Silverman H, Isbell WH, editors. Handbook of South American Archaeology: Springer. pp. 359–403.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Heckenberger1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckenberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Amazonian archaeology</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Anthropology</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Petersen1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Petersen JB, Neves EG, Heckenberger MJ (2001) Gift from the past: <italic>terra preta</italic> and prehistoric occupation in Amazonia. In: McEwan C, Barreto C, Neves EG, editors. Unknown Amazon Culture in Nature in Ancient Brazil. 1st ed. London: The British Museum Press. pp. 86–107.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Kuzyakov1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzyakov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Subbotina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bogomolova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Black carbon decomposition and incorporation into soil microbial biomass estimated by <sup>14</sup>C labeling</article-title>. <source>Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Fraser1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falcão</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Anthropogenic soils in the Central Amazon: From categories to a continuum</article-title>. <source>Area</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Schmidt1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Schmidt MJ (2010) Reconstructing tropical nature: Prehistoric and modern anthrosols (<italic>terra preta</italic>) in the Amazon rainforest, upper Xingu river, Brazil [PhD Dissertation]: Department of Geography, University of Florida. 1594 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Erickson1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Erickson CL (2008) Amazonia: The Historical Ecology of a Domesticated Landscape. In: Silverman H, Isbell WH, editors. The Handbook of South American Archaeology. New York: Springer. pp. 157–183.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-German1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>German</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Historical contingencies in the coevolution of environment and livelihood: contributions to the debate on Amazonian Black Earth</article-title>. <source>Geoderma</source> <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Smith1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NJH</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Anthrosols and human carrying capacity in Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Annals of the Association of American Geographers</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-German2">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>German</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Ecological praxis and blackwater ecosystems: A case study from the Brazilian Amazon</article-title>. <source>Human Ecology</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-ArroyoKalin2">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arroyo-Kalin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The Amazonian formative: Crop domestication and anthropogenic soils</article-title>. <source>Diversity</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-McKey1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavagnaro</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cliff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gleadow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Chemical ecology in coupled human and natural systems: people, manioc, multitrophic interactions and global change</article-title>. <source>Chemoecology</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>133</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Hershey1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Hershey CH (1994) Manihot Genetic Diversity: International network for cassava genetic resources. International Crop Network Series, IPGRI 10.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Boster1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boster</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Selection for perceptual distinctiveness: evidence from Aguaruna cultivars of Manihot esculenta</article-title>. <source>Economic Botany</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Elias1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The unmanaged reproductive ecology of domesticated plants in traditional agroecosystems: An example involving cassava and a call for data</article-title>. <source>Acta Oecologica-International Journal of Ecology</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Emperaire2">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emperaire</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Second</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Gestion dynamique de la diversité varie tale du manioc en Amazonie du nord-ouest</article-title>. <source>Nature, Science et Societé</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Salick1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cellinese</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Indigenous diversity of cassava: Generation, maintenance, use and loss among the Amuesha, Peruvian Upper Amazon</article-title>. <source>Economic Botany</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Elias2">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rival</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Perception and management of cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) diversity among Makushi Amerindians of Guyana (South America)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ethnobiology</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Deltre1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delêtre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hodkinson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Marriage exchanges, seed exchanges, and the dynamics of manioc diversity</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>18249</fpage>–<lpage>18254</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Ellen1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellen</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soselisa</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A Comparative Study of the Socio-ecological Concomitants of Cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) Diversity, Local Knowledge and Management in Eastern Indonesia</article-title>. <source>Ethnobotany Research &amp; Applications</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Jones1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Jones W (1959) Manioc in Africa: Stanford University Press. 315 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Roosevelt1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Roosevelt AC (1980) Parmana: Prehistoric Maize and Manioc Susbistence along the Amazon and Orinoco. New York: Academic Press. 320 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Ohly1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Ohly J, Junk W (1999) Multiple Use of Central Amazon Floodplains: Reconciling Ecological Conditions, Requirements for Environmental Protection, and Socioeconomic Needs. In: Padoch C, Ayres JM, Pinedo-Vasquez M, Henderson A, editors. Varzea: Diversity, Development and Conservation of Amazonias's whitewater floodplains. New York: New York Botanical Garden. pp. 283–299.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Gutjahr1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Gutjahr E (2000) Prospects for arable farming in the floodplains of the Central Amazon. In: W. J Junk, J. J Ohly, Piedade MTF, Soares MGM, editors. The Central Amazon Floodplain: Actual Use and Options for a Sustainable Management. Leiden: Backhuys. pp. 141–170.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Fraser2">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The diversity of bitter manioc (Manihot esculenta Crantz) cultivation in a whitewater Amazonian landscape</article-title>. <source>Diversity</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>586</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-McKey2">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Emperaire</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Local management and regional dynamics of varietal diversity of cassava in Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Genetics Selection Evolution</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>S465</fpage>–<lpage>S490</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Pujol1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gigot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro-Kluppel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Germination ecology of cassava, Manihot esculenta Crantz, Euphorbiaceae, in traditional agroecosystems: Seed and seedling biology of a vegetatively propagated domesticated plant</article-title>. <source>Economic Botany</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Elias3">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vindry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panaud</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Unmanaged sexual reproduction and the dynamics of genetic diversity of a vegetatively propagated crop plant, cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz), in a traditional farming system</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1895</fpage>–<lpage>1907</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Elias4">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muhlen</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roa</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tohme</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genetic diversity of traditional south american landraces of cassava (Manihot esculeatta Crantz): An analysis using microsatellites</article-title>. <source>Economic Botany</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Pujol2">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Renoux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rival</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The unappreciated ecology of landrace populations: Conservation consequences of soil seed banks in Cassava</article-title>. <source>Biological Conservation</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>551</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Peroni1">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Peroni N (1998) Taxonomia folk e diversidade intraespecíıfica de mandioca (Manihot esculenta Crantz) em roças de agricultura tradicional em áreas de Mata Atlântica, São Paulo. [Masters Dissertation]. São Paulo: University of São Paulo.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Elias5">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panaud</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anstett</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Traditional management of cassava morphological and genetic diversity by the Makushi Amerindians (Guyana, South America): Perspectives for on-farm conservation of crop genetic resources</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Pujol3">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Microevolution in agricultural environments: how a traditional Amerindian farming practice favours heterozygosity in cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz, Euphorbiaceae)</article-title>. <source>Ecology Letters</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Peroni2">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peroni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kageyama</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Begossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molecular differentiation, diversity, and folk classification of “sweet” and “bitter” cassava (Manihot esculenta) in Caicara and Caboclo management systems (Brazil)</article-title>. <source>Genetic Resources and Crop Evolution</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>1333</fpage>–<lpage>1349</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Stocker1">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Stocker P (2006) Family farmers and manioc in contemporary Brazil: The management of agrobiodiversity and change [PhD Dissertation]: University of Edinburgh. 359 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Fraser3">
        <label>57</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Caboclo horticulture and Amazonian dark earths along the middle Madeira River, Brazil</article-title>. <source>Human Ecology</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Fraser4">
        <label>58</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dark earths and manioc cultivation in Central Amazonia: A window on pre-Colombian agricultural systems?</article-title> <source>Boletim do Museu Paraense Emílio Goeldi Ciências Humanas</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Hiraoka1">
        <label>59</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Hiraoka M, Yamamoto S, Matsumoto E, Nakamura S, Falesi I, et al.. (2003) Contemporary use and management of Amazonian Dark Earths. In: Lehmann J, Kern D, Glaser B, Woods W, editors. Amazonian Dark Earths: Origin, properties, and management. Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic Publishers. pp. 387–406.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-German3">
        <label>60</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">German LA (2001) The dynamics of <italic>Terra Preta</italic>: an integrated study of human-environmental interaction in a nutrient-poor Amazonian ecosystem [Unpublished Ph.D Dissertation]: University of Georgia. 312 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-German4">
        <label>61</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">German LA (2003) Ethnoscientific understandings of Amazonian Dark Earths. In: Lehmann J, Kern D, Glaser B, Woods WI, editors. Amazonian Dark Earths: Origin, Properties and Management. Dordrecht: Kluwer. pp. 179–201.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Harlan1">
        <label>62</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Harlan J (1992) Crops and Man. Madison, Wisconsin.: American Society of Agronomy Inc. Crop Science Society of America Inc. 284 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Fraser5">
        <label>63</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Junqueira</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawa</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Crop Diversity on Anthropogenic Dark Earths in Central Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Human Ecology</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Lima1">
        <label>64</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Lima D, Steward A, Richers BT (2012) Trocas, experimentações e preferências: um estudo sobre a dinâmica da diversidade da mandioca no Médio Solimões, Amazonas. Boletim do Museu Paraense Emílio Goeldi: Ciências Humanas.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Grenand1">
        <label>65</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Grenand F (1993) Bitter manioc in the lowlands of Tropical America: from myth to commercialization. In: C. MHladik, AHladik, O. FLinares, HPagezy, Semple A et al.., editors. Tropical Forests and Food: Biocultural Interactions and Applications to Development. Paris: UNESCO and Parthenon.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Castro1">
        <label>66</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Castro F (2009) Patterns of Resource Use by Caboclo Communities in the Middle-Lower Amazon. In: C. RAdams, RMurrieta, WNeves, Harris M, editors. Amazon peasant societies in a changing environment: Political ecology, invisibility and modernity in the rainforest. New York: Springer. pp. 157–177.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Pereira1">
        <label>67</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Pereira KJC (2008) Agricultura tradicional e manejo da agrobiodiversidade na Amazônia Central: Um estudo de caso nos roçados de mandioca das Reservas de Desenvolvimento Sustentável Amanã e Mamirauá, Amazonas [PhD Dissertation]. São Paulo: University of São Paulo. 223 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Denevan3">
        <label>68</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Denevan W (1984) Ecological heterogeneity and horizontal zonation of agriculture in the Amazon floodplain. In: M Schmink and C Wood, editor. Frontier Expansion in Amazonia. Gainsville: University of Florida Press. pp. 311–336.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Smith2">
        <label>69</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Smith NJH (1999) The Amazon River Forest: A Natural History of Plants, Animals, and People. Oxford: Oxford University Press. 208 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Noda1">
        <label>70</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Noda SN, Noda H, Santos HP (2000) Family farming systems in the floodplains of the State of Amazonas. In The Central Amazon Floodplain: Actual Use and Options for a Sustainable Management. In: W. JJunk, J. JOhly, Piedade MTF, Soares MGM, editors. The Central Amazon Floodplain: Actual Use and Options for a Sustainable Management. Leiden: Backhuys. pp. 215–242.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Lima2">
        <label>71</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Lima RMB, Saragoussi M (2000) Floodplain home gardens on the Central Amazon in Brazil. In: Junk WJ,J. JOhly, Piedade MTF, Soares MGM, editors. The Central Amazon Floodplain: Actual Use and Options for a Sustainable Management. Leiden: Backhuys. pp. 243–268.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Boster2">
        <label>72</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boster</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Classification, cultivation and selection of Aguaruna cultivars of Manihot esculenta (Euphorbiaceae)</article-title>. <source>Advances in Economic Botany</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Pujol4">
        <label>73</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gigot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro-Kluppel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Germination ecology of cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz, Euphorriaceae) in traditional agroecosystems: Seed and seedling biology of a vegetatively propagated domesticated plant</article-title>. <source>Economic Botany</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Lebot1">
        <label>74</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Lebot V (2009) Tropical Root and Tuber Crops: Cassava, Sweet Potato, Yams and Aroids. Oxford, UK: CAB International.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Boserup1">
        <label>75</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Boserup E (1993 (1965)) The conditions of agricultural growth. The economics of agrarian change under population pressure. London: Earthscan Publications Ltd.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-AlvesPereira1">
        <label>76</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Alves Pereira A (2011) Dinâmica evolutiva de mandioca (Manihot esculenta Crantz) em três tipos de solos manejados por Caboclos na região do Médio Rio Madiera, Amazonas. Manaus, Brazil: Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia. 87 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-AlvesPereira2">
        <label>77</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves-Pereira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peroni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gribel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genetic structure of traditional varieties of bitter manioc in three soils in Central Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Genetica</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1259</fpage>–<lpage>1271</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Kensinger1">
        <label>78</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Kensinger KM (1975) Studying the Cashinahua. In: Kensinger KM, editor. The Cashinahua of Eastern Peru Studies in Anthropology and Material Culture, vol 1. Providence, Rhode Island: Brown University. pp. 9–85.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Aquino1">
        <label>79</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Aquino TVd, Iglesias MP (2002) Habitantes: Os Kaxinawá. In: Carneiro da Cunha M, Almeida MBd, editors. Enciclopédia da floresta O alto juruá: práticas e conhecimentos das populações. São Paulo: Companhia das Letras. pp. 147–160.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Ricardo1">
        <label>80</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Ricardo CA, editor (2000) Povos Indígenas no Brasil, 1996–2000. São Paulo: Instituto Socioambiental.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Wilson1">
        <label>81</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Soils Utilized for Gardens by Tukanoans in Northwestern Amazonia and their Impact on Cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) Cultivar Selection</article-title>. <source>Culture &amp; Agriculture</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Heckler1">
        <label>82</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Piaroa Manioc Varietals: Hyperdiversity or Social Currency?</article-title> <source>Human Ecology</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>679</fpage>–<lpage>697</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Fraser6">
        <label>83</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Fraser JA (2009) Amazonian dark earths and <italic>Caboclo</italic> subsistence on the Middle Madeira River, Brazil [PhD Dissertation]: University of Sussex.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Bryman1">
        <label>84</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Bryman A (2008) Social Research Methods. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press. 800 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Bernard1">
        <label>85</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Bernard HR (2006) Research methods in anthropology: qualitative and quantitative approaches. Oxford: Altamira Press. 803 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-McCune1">
        <label>86</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">McCune B, Grace JB (2002) Analysis of Ecological Communities: MjM Software Design. 304 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Wright1">
        <label>87</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Adjusted p-values for simultaneous inference</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>1005</fpage>–<lpage>1013</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Sutrop1">
        <label>88</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutrop</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>List task and a cognitive salience index</article-title>. <source>Field Methods</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-ChavarriagaAguirre1">
        <label>89</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavarriaga-Aguirre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maya</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonierbale</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kresovich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fregene</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Microsatellites in cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz): discovery, inheritance and variability</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Mba1">
        <label>90</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mba</surname><given-names>REC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melzer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nkumbira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Simple sequence repeat (SSR) markers survey of the cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) genome: towards an SSR-based molecular genetic map of cassava</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-Peakall1">
        <label>91</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peakall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smouse</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genalex 6: Genetic analysis in Excel. Population genetic software for teaching and research</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0043636-ArnaudHaond1">
        <label>92</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnaud-Haond</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belkhir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>GENCLONE: a computer program to analyse genotypic data, test for clonality and describe spatial clonal organization</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>