<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-07422</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic polymorphism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physical anthropology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Genetic Structure of Qiangic Populations Residing in the Western Sichuan Corridor</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Genetic Origin of Sino-Tibetan Populations</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Chuan-Chao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Ling-Xiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>Rukesh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Manfei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Xiu-Yuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Kang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>State Key Laboratory of Genetic Engineering and MOE Key Laboratory of Contemporary Anthropology, School of Life Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Key Laboratory of High Altitude Environment and Genes Related to Diseases of Tibet Autonomous Region, School of Medicine, Tibet University for Nationalities, Xianyang, Shaanxi, China</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>CAS-MPG Partner Institute for Computational Biology, SIBS, CAS, Shanghai, China</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>Luísa M. Sousa Mesquita</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>IPATIMUP (Institute of Molecular Pathology and Immunology of the University of Porto), Portugal</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">LHCA@FUDAN.edu.cn</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: HL LJ. Performed the experiments: CCW LXW RS MZ XYH. Analyzed the data: CCW HL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CCW KH LJ HL. Wrote the paper: CCW HL.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e103772</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Wang et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The Qiangic languages in western Sichuan (WSC) are believed to be the oldest branch of the Sino-Tibetan linguistic family, and therefore, all Sino-Tibetan populations might have originated in WSC. However, very few genetic investigations have been done on Qiangic populations and no genetic evidences for the origin of Sino-Tibetan populations have been provided. By using the informative Y chromosome and mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) markers, we analyzed the genetic structure of Qiangic populations. Our results revealed a predominantly Northern Asian-specific component in Qiangic populations, especially in maternal lineages. The Qiangic populations are an admixture of the northward migrations of East Asian initial settlers with Y chromosome haplogroup D (D1-M15 and the later originated D3a-P47) in the late Paleolithic age, and the southward Di-Qiang people with dominant haplogroup O3a2c1*-M134 and O3a2c1a-M117 in the Neolithic Age.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Excellent Youth Science Foundation of China (31222030), National Natural Science Foundation of China (91131002), Shanghai Rising-Star Program (12QA1400300), China Ministry of Education Scientific Research Major Project (311016,113022A), MOE University Doctoral Research Supervisor’s Funds (20120071110021), and Shanghai Professional Development Funding (2010001). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The Sino-Tibetan languages are a family of some 460 languages, including two subfamilies, namely Chinese and Tibeto-Burman. They are spoken by over a billion people all over East Asia and Southeast Asia, and second only to the Indo-European languages in terms of the population size of native speakers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Martisoff1">[1]</xref>. The linguistic connection between Chinese and Tibeto-Burman are well established. There are over 300 cognates between Old Chinese and Proto-Tibeto-Burman, grouping them into the same language family <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Martisoff1">[1]</xref>. Based on lexical evidence and cladistic methods, Wang estimated that Chinese split away from Tibeto-Burman around 6 thousand years ago (kya) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang1">[2]</xref>. The Qiangic languages in western China were believed to be the oldest type of Sino-Tibetan languages, and have given birth to all other Sino-Tibetan languages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Martisoff1">[1]</xref>. Archaeological evidence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Martisoff1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-CavalliSforza1">[3]</xref> also indicated that the ancestors of Sino-Tibetan populations lived around at least 6 kya in western China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Martisoff1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-CavalliSforza1">[3]</xref>.</p>
<p>Despite intense linguistic and archaeological researches, little has been known about how the Sino-Tibetan people dispersed from western China? During the past two decades, the characterization of genetic diversity has shed light on the history of Sino-Tibetan populations, especially the diversity defined by the maternal mtDNA and the paternal Y chromosome. In the maternal side, mtDNA evidence suggested a northern Asian origin of Tibetans, due to the high frequencies of northern Asian specific haplogroup A, D, G, and M8 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qi1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhao1">[8]</xref>. However, that evidence has been contradicted by another work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wen1">[9]</xref>, which showed that the southern Tibeto-Burman populations exhibited sex-biased admixture with a stronger influence of northern immigrants on the male lineages and a more extensive contribution of southern natives to the female lineages. Likewise, the southern natives made a greater contribution to the maternal gene pool of southern Han Chinese <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wen2">[10]</xref>.</p>
<p>Given that a correlation is emerging that suggests language change in an already-populated region may require a minimum proportion of immigrant males, while mtDNA types represent more ancient settlement <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Forster1">[11]</xref>, the Y chromosome characterization in the Sino-Tibetan populations may provide valuable insights into its origins. From the Y chromosome perspective, Su et al. found that almost all the modern Sino-Tibetan populations shared a common genetic signature, the high frequencies of O3-M122 lineages, including O3*-M122, O3a2c1*-M134, and O3a2b-M7. They postulated that the ancient Di-Qiang people (Proto-Sino-Tibetan speakers) with the dominant O3-lineages in the upper-middle Yellow River basin were the ancestors of present Sino-Tibetan populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Su1">[12]</xref>. However, they did not give a convincing explanation about the high frequency of Y chromosomal Alu insertion (YAP) in Tibetan populations. The YAP polymorphism was also enriched in Japan and Andaman islands, but basically absent in almost all the other East Asian populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qian1">[13]</xref>. Haplogroup D-M174 is one subhaplogroups of YAP+. Shi et al. proposed that D-M174 had a southern origin and then started its northward expansion about 60 kya. The current fragmented distribution of D-M174 was likely due to the later Neolithic expansion of Han culture carrying O3-lineages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Shi1">[14]</xref>. In addition, one of O3-M122 lineages in the study of Su et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Su1">[12]</xref>, haplogroup O3a2b-M7, was found out to be the characteristic lineage of Mon-Khmer and Hmong-Mien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Cai1">[15]</xref>. Haplogroup O3a1c-002611, which was included in the O3*-M122 haplogroup in the study of Su et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Su1">[12]</xref>, comprises almost 17% of Han Chinese <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Yan1">[16]</xref>. However, haplogroup O3a1c was found at very low frequencies in Tibeto-Burman populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang2">[17]</xref>, suggesting that this lineage might not have participated in the establishment of the Tibeto-Burman populations. Recently, we have found that Qiang people have the highest Y chromosomal short tandem repeats (STRs) diversity among the Sino-Tibetan populations in the eastern Himalayas, indicating the Qiangic group to be the origin of the Sino-Tibetan expansion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Kang1">[18]</xref>. However, the highest genetic diversity of Qiang people might also be the result of repeated migrations from all directions.</p>
<p>Y chromosome evidence indicates that Qiang people might be the origin source for the Sino-Tibetan populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Su1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Kang1">[18]</xref>. Qiang people refer to the populations speaking Qiangic languages, a group of the northeastern Tibeto-Burman branch, spoken mainly in Southwestern China (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g001">Figure 1</xref>), especially in western Sichuan (WSC). Qiangic has more than ten sub-branches, such as Horpa, Lavrung, Ersu and Zhaba <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Sun1">[19]</xref>. The differentiation of the various Qiangic languages makes WSC a very important place for studying the origin of Sino-Tibetan. Furthermore, WSC is located between the upper-middle Yellow River basin and the eastern Himalayas, probably serving as a conduit for gene flow during the origin of the Sino-Tibetan populations. Here, we integrate Y chromosome and mtDNA diversity in Qiangic populations located in the WSC corridor to provide a broader framework for reconstructing the history of Sino-Tibetan.</p>
<fig id="pone-0103772-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Geographic locations of Qiangic and other referenced East Asian populations in this study.</title>
<p>(a). Geographic location of WSC and distributions of the East Asian populations used in data analysis; (b). Detailed geographic location of studied Qiangic speaking populations. The number of individual sampled in each population is enclosed in parentheses.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Population samples</title>
<p>We collected blood samples of 407 healthy and unrelated individuals from four Qiaingic populations in western Sichuan province (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Our study was approved by the Ethnic Committee of School of Life Sciences, Fudan University. All individuals were adequately informed and signed their informed content before their participation. The populations were labeled as follows: Horpa-Danba (DB), 47 Horpa individuals from Danba County of Sichuan; Horpa-Daofu (DF), 43 Horpa individuals from Bamei Town, Daofu County of Sichuan; Tibetan-Xinlong (XL), 124 Khams Tibetans from Xinlong County of Sichuan; Tibetan-Yajiang (YJ), 193 Khams Tibetans from Hekou Town, Yajiang County of Sichuan. Genomic DNA was extracted using DP-318 Kit (Tiangen Biotechnology, Beijing).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Y chromosome markers</title>
<p>The samples were typed through seven panels of 100 SNPs as listed in the latest Y chromosome phylogenetic tree <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Yan1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Karafet1">[20]</xref>.</p>
<p>Haplogroup O panel: M175, M119, P203, M110, M268, P31, M95, M176, M122, M324, M121, P201, M7, M134, M117, 002611, P164, L127 (rs17269396), and KL1 (rs17276338).</p>
<p>Corset Panel: M130, P256, M1, M231, M168, M174, M45, M89, M272, M258, M242, M207, M9, M96, P125, M304, M201 and M306.</p>
<p>Haplogroup C panel: P54, M105, M48, M208, M407, P33, M93, P39, P92, P53.1, M217, M38, M210, M356, P55, and M347.</p>
<p>Haplogroup D panel: P47, N1, P99, M15, M125, M55, M64.2, M116.1, M151, N2, and 022457.</p>
<p>Haplogroup N panel: M214, LLY22g, M128, M46/Tat, P63, P119, P105, P43, and M178.</p>
<p>Haplogroup R panel: M306, M173, M124, M420, SRY10831.2, M17, M64.1, M198, M343, V88, M458, M73, M434, P312, M269, and U106/M405.</p>
<p>Haplogroup Q panel: P36.2, M3, M120, MEH2, M378, N14/M265, M25, M143, M346, L53, and M323.</p>
<p>Those binary markers were hierarchically genotyped by SNaPshot (ABI SNaPshot Multiplex Kit) and fluorescent allele-specific PCR. PCR products were electrophoresed on a 3730xl Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA).</p>
<p>Seventeen Y chromosomal STRs (DYS19, DYS389I, DYS389II, DYS390, DYS391, DYS392, DYS393, DYS385a, DYS385b, DYS438, DYS439, DYS437, DYS448, DYS456, DYS458, DYS635 and YGATAH4) were amplified using the AmpFlSTR Yfiler PCR Amplification kit (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Amplified products were separated and detected using the ABI 3730xl Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s recommended protocol. The data were analyzed using GeneMapper ID v3.2 (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). For use in the analyses, DYS389II was calculated by subtracting the DYS389I allele size.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Mitochondrial DNA markers</title>
<p>The hypervariable segment I (HVS-I) of the control region was amplified by primers L15974 and H16488 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Yao1">[7]</xref>. Purified PCR products were sequenced using the BigDye terminator cycle sequencing kit and an ABI 3730XL genetic analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). A SNaPshot assay was used for typing SNPs in the coding regions to confirm haplogroup identity. This assay was designed as a multiplex panel including 21 coding region SNPs and one length variation marker <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>. Both the HVS-I motif and the coding region variations were used to infer haplogroups. In addition, three representative mtDNA (BM024, DBB005, and DBB006) have been completely sequenced using the method as described in our previous work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>. The nomenclature of mtDNA follows van Oven and Kayser <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-vanOven1">[21]</xref>, with several latest new modifications (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phylotree.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.phylotree.org/</ext-link>). The mtDNA sequences have been deposited in Genbank with accession numbers KJ783504-KJ783899.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>Principal component analysis (PCA) was performed using SPSS 18.0 software (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Networks of Y chromosomal STR data and the mtDNA HVS-I motifs were constructed by reduced median-joining method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Bandelt1">[22]</xref> using NETWORK v. 4.5.1.6 (Fluxus-engineering.com). Molecular diversity, population structure estimates and Y-STR genetic distances between populations were calculated using Arlequin v. 3.11 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Excoffier1">[23]</xref>. Classical frequency spectrum tests, such as Tajima’s D, Fu and Li’s D, D*, F and F*, were calculated using DnaSP5.0 to detect deviation from neutrality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Fu1">[24]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Tajima1">[27]</xref>. Coalescence times of mtDNA haplogroups of interest were calculated by ρ statistic method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Forster2">[28]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Saillard1">[29]</xref> using recently corrected calibrated mutation rate: 18,845 years per mutation in HVS-I (16090–16365) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Soares1">[30]</xref>. Reference population data on the Y chromosomes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Shi1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Kang1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Deng1">[31]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Xue1">[44]</xref> and mtDNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhao1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wen2">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Black1">[45]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zimmermann1">[69]</xref> were retrieved from the literature. Time estimations for main Y chromosomal lineages were made using 15 STRs (excluding DYS385a and DYS385b) in BATWING <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wilson1">[70]</xref> under a model of exponential growth from an initially constant-sized population. The parameters used in estimation were following Xue et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Xue1">[44]</xref>. Four sets of Y-STR mutation rates were applied in time estimations as Wei et al did <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wei1">[71]</xref>. These are a widely used evolutionary mutation rate (EMR) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhivotovsky1">[72]</xref>, two observed genealogical mutation rates (OMRB and OMRS) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Burgarella1">[73]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Shi3">[74]</xref>, and a genealogical mutation rate adjusted for population variation using logistic model (lmMR) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Burgarella1">[73]</xref>. A total of 10<sup>4</sup> samples of the program’s output representing 10<sup>6</sup> MCMC cycles were taken after discarding the first 3×10<sup>3</sup> samples as burn-in. The Time to the Most Recent Common Ancestor (TMRCA) is calculated using the product of the estimated population size N and the height of the tree T (in coalescent units) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wilson1">[70]</xref>. A generation time of 25 years was used to produce a time estimate in years. The geographic distributions of Y chromosome haplogroup D1 and D3a are presented by generation of contour maps using Surfer 8.0 Software (Golden Software).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Y chromosome</title>
<sec id="s3a1">
<title>Y chromosome haplogroup profile</title>
<p>According to the nomenclature of Y Chromosome Consortium (YCC) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Yan1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Karafet1">[20]</xref>, 23 SNP haplogroups were determined from the 127 male individual samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g002">Figure 2a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s001">Table S1</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s002">Table S2</xref>). Haplogroup D1-M15 and its subhaplogroups, which are widely distributed across East Asia including most of the Tibeto-Burman, Tai-Kadai and Hmong-Mien speaking populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qi1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Shi1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang4">[75]</xref> (Figure S1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s005">Doc S1</xref>), are also prevalent in the four studied populations (44.44% and 12.50% in Horpa-Danba and Horpa-Daofu, respectively; 8.70% in Tibetan-Xinlong and 6.38% in Tibetan-Yajiang). Haplogroup D3a-P47 is almost exclusively distributed in Tibeto-Burman populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qi1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Shi1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang4">[75]</xref> (Figure S1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s005">Doc S1</xref>) and also found highly frequent in Horpa-Daofu, Tibetan-Xinlong and Tibetan-Yajiang, but absent in Horpa-Danba. Haplogroup O1a1-P203, which occurs at high frequencies in Tai-Kadai speaking people along the southeast coast of China and Taiwan aborigines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Yan1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang4">[75]</xref>, is also observed at a high frequency in Yajiang (21.28%) and moderate frequencies in Daofu and Xinlong (6.25% and 8.70%, respectively), but absent in Danba. The major lineages in the Indo-China Peninsula, O2a1-M95 and its subhaplogroups, are also found at moderate or relatively low levels in the four studied populations. Haplogroup O3-M122 is the most common haplogroup in China and prevalent throughout East and Southeast Asia, comprising roughly 25–37% of the studied Qiangic populations. O3a1c-002611, O3a2c1-M134, and O3a2c1a-M117 are three main subclades of O3, each accounting for 12–17% of the Han Chinese <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Yan1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang4">[75]</xref>. However, their frequencies vary a lot in Qiangic populations. O3a1c-002611 comprises 15.22% of Xinlong Tibetans, but absent in three other populations. O3a2c1*-M134 accounts for about 6% of the Horpa-Danba and Tibetans of Xinlong and Yajiang, but absent in Horpa-Daofu. Haplogroup O3a2c1a-M117, which exhibits high frequencies in other Tibeto-Burman populations, is also observed at high frequencies in Horpa-Danba and Tibetan-Yajiang (22.22% and 19.15%, respectively), and moderate frequencies in Horpa-Daofu and Tibetan-Xinlong (12.50% and 10.87%, respectively). Haplogroup C-M130 has a very wide distribution and might represent one of the earliest settlements in East Asia. Haplogroup C* (M130+, M105−, M38−, M217−, M347−, and M356−) has been found at low frequencies along the southern coast of mainland East Asia as well as throughout the islands of Southeast Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang4">[75]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhong1">[76]</xref>. In spite of the wide distribution of C*, they all have similar STR haplotypes (DYS19, 15; DYS389I, 12; DYS389b, 16; DYS390, 21; DYS391, 10; DYS392, 11; DYS393). There are two C* individuals detected in this study, one in Horpa-Danba and the other in Tibetan-Xinlong. Those two individuals also have the same STR haplotype as mentioned above. Haplogroup C3-M217 is the most widespread subclade of C-M130, and reaches the highest frequencies among the populations of Northern East Aisa, especially in Mongolians <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang4">[75]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zerjal1">[77]</xref>. Haplogroup C3-M217 has also been found in Tibetan-Yajiang at a frequency of 10.64%, but totally absent in other three populations. Haplogroup N-M231 has both a unique and widespread distribution throughout northern Eurasia and reaches highest frequency among most of the Uralic populations as well as some Altaic populations. Haplogroup N1c1a-M178 is the most common subclade of N-M231 and thought to be originated in China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang4">[75]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Rootsi1">[78]</xref>. N1c1a-M178 has also been detected in Horpa-Daofu and Tibetan-Xinlong at 12.50% and 2.17%, respectively. The 17-STR haplotype of N1c1a individuals in Horpa-Daofu is exactly the same with some Komi people in Russia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Mirabal1">[79]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Roewer1">[80]</xref>. However, the haplotype of N1c1a individual in Xinlong shows more similarity with samples of its surrounding populations (unpublished data). It is particularly noteworthy that Central-South Asia related haplogroups J-M304 and R2-M124 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhong2">[81]</xref> have also been detected at low frequencies in Qiangic populations.</p>
<fig id="pone-0103772-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Y chromosome and mtDNA haplogroup frequencies of studied Qiangic populations.</title>
<p>(a). Y chromosome haplogroup frequencies of the four Qiangic populations; (b). mtDNA haplogroup frequencies of the four Qiangic populations.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3a2">
<title>PCA and STR genetic distance analysis</title>
<p>The paternal genetic relationships among Qiangic, Tibeto-Burman, and other East Asian populations were discerned with the aid of additional published Y chromosome datasets. We used a PCA based on the distribution of Y chromosome haplogroup frequencies of 51 populations to show the overall clustering pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g003">Figure 3a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s003">Table S3</xref>). Results of PCA are presented by the plots of the first two principal components (PCs), which together account for 31.31% of the Y chromosome variation in these populations. The first PC revealed a clear north-south geographic division between Altaic and Sino-Tibetan, Tai-Kadai &amp; Hmong-Mien. Haplogroup C3-M217, G-M201, J-P209, and R-M207 were found to contribute most to the northern pole of Altaic. Haplogroup O-M175 contributed most to the southern pole. Sino-Tibetan, Tai-Kadai and Hmong-Mien populations showed different distributions of the second PC. Horpa-Danba, Horpa-Daofu, Tibetan-Xinlong, and Tibetan-Yajiang were clustered within Sino-Tibetan group, which reflected a clear linguistic clustering pattern. Haplogroups O3a1c-002611, O3a2c1*-M134, and O3a2c1a-M117 contributed most to the Sino-Tibetan pole. Contrastingly, haplogroups O3a2b*-M7 and O2a1-M95 were concentrated at the Tai-Kadai and Hmong-Mien pole. The four western Sichuan populations clustered tightly together with other Tibeto-Burman populations, such as Qiang, Tibetan-Yunnan, Yi, and Tujia, mostly due to high frequencies of haplogroup D3a-P47, O3a2c1a-M117, D1-M15, and O3a2c1*-M134. In the STR genetic distance based neighbor-joining tree, Horpa-Daofu, Tibetan-Yajiang, and Tibetan-Xinlong also clustered tightly with Tibeto-Burman populations. However, Horpa-Danba was close related to Han and Hmong-Mien populations (Figure S2 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s005">Doc S1</xref>). As PCA was performed from frequencies of haplogroups and genetic distance was obtained from only 6 STR markers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s004">Table S4</xref>), the results are suggestive but not conclusive.</p>
<fig id="pone-0103772-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Phylogenetic relationship between Qiangic and reference populations analyzed by PCA with the frequencies of haplogroups.</title>
<p>(a). PCA plot based on Y chromosome haplogroup frequencies of 51 populations; (b). PCA plot based on mtDNA haplogroups frequencies of 72 populations.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3a3">
<title>Network analysis and time estimation</title>
<p>To discern the detail relationship between the D3a-P47, O3a2c1a-M117, D1-M15, and O3a2c1*-M134 haplogroups in Tibeto-Burman and other related populations, a median-joining network was constructed based on Y-STR haplotypes of those haplogroups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g004">Figure 4</xref>). A clear Sino-Tibetan vs. Tai-Kadai and Hmong-Mien divergence can be inferred from the network of D1-M15 though sporadic haplotype sharing exists. Furthermore, within the Sino-Tibetan populations, haplogroup D1-M15 contains distinct STR haplotypes between Qiangic populations, Northern Han, and Tibetan-Tibet, implying that D1-M15 experienced a serial of founder effects or strong bottlenecks and a secondary expansion in Sino-Tibetan populations. In the network of D3a-P47, the divergence between Qiang and Tibetan with other Tibeto-Burman populations has been observed. Other Tibeto-Burman populations only have a subset of the Qiang and Tibetan haplotypes. The star-like network of D3a-P47 also suggests population expansion in Tibetans. The network of O3a2c1*-M134 shows a clear divergence between Tibetan and northern populations (Northern Han and Altaic). Southern Han and Tai-Kadai samples constitute the center of the network and act as a bridge connected Tibetan and northern populations, which supports the southern origin and northern expansion of O3a2c1*-M134. Most of the Qiangic samples belonging to haplogroup O3a2c1*-M134 share haplotypes with northern populations, indicating a recent gene flow from northern populations to Qiangic populations. A population expansion has also been observed in the star-like network of haplogroup O3a2c1a-M117. o However, the haplotypes of O3a2c1a-M117 are extensively shared among all the East Asia populations.</p>
<fig id="pone-0103772-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Reduced Median joining network of Y chromosome haplogroups.</title>
<p>Reduced Median-joining network based on six Y-STR data (DYS19, DYS389I, DYS390, DYS391, DYS392, and DYS393) of haplogroup D1-M15, D3a-P47, O3a2c1*-M134, and O3a2c1a-M117.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We then estimated the coalescence and expansion time of Y chromosome lineages in Qiangic populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t001">Table 1</xref>). The ages estimated using evolutionary rate are about two or three times higher than using genealogical rates. As the times using genealogical rates fit well with sequence-based estimates in Y chromosome lineage dating <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang5">[82]</xref>, we present results from the genealogical calculations in the following section. Haplogroup D can trace back to late Palaeolithic period, while other subhaplogroups coalescence more likely in Neolithic Time. The lineage expansion times all fall into Neolithic Time ranging from 4.2 to 7.5 kya.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0103772-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Estimates of the coalescence time of selected Y chromosome haplogroups within Qiangic populations using Batwing.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0103772-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutation rate</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D1a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D3a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O1a1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O3a1c</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O3a2c1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O3a2c1a</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMRB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMRCA (years BP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16828</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9552</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7284</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5393</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8054</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11364</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12087</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7167</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13807</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8070</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5625</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4113</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6683</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8198</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8892</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5491</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3804</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1836</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2161</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1633</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1698</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4342</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4385</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2158</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expansion (years BP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7928</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6862</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6295</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5820</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6609</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10788</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10169</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7117</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5548</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5103</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4589</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4975</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7490</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7050</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5205</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3031</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2261</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2345</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2139</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2170</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4896</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4628</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2666</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMRS</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMRCA (years BP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14657</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7699</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6499</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4432</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7009</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9408</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9749</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6097</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12065</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6509</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5069</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3425</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5837</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6799</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7158</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4717</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3268</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1459</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1865</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1273</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1432</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3579</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3580</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1768</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expansion (years BP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7302</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5827</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5728</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5789</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9448</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8974</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6412</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5165</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4373</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4209</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3864</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4367</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6560</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6242</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4738</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2732</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1874</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2080</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1843</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1870</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4325</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4081</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2336</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lmMR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMRCA (years BP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16339</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9493</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7019</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5461</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7592</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11724</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7163</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13368</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7997</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5403</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4162</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6280</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8576</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5441</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3788</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1857</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2081</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1663</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1633</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4288</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4352</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2217</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expansion (years BP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7828</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6898</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6326</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5899</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6638</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10734</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10098</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7180</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5509</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5141</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4627</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4319</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5017</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7437</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6973</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5217</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2285</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2326</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2171</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2184</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4892</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4656</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2734</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMRCA (years BP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61245</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37303</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23989</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19642</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31365</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47036</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42244</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26666</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50014</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30316</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18544</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15078</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24777</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34581</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31205</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20191</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13963</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8828</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6950</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5825</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8457</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16827</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14929</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8404</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expansion (years BP)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17964</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17671</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16601</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15520</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19721</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34503</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30242</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19886</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11959</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11379</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12060</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11355</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13753</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24220</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21250</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14185</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7870</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6352</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5817</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8648</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15101</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13198</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8162</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Abbreviations: BP, before present; SD, standard deviation; Expansion: population expansion time; TMRCA: Time to the Most Recent Common Ancestor; EMR: evolutionary mutation rate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhivotovsky1">[72]</xref>; OMRB and OMRS: two observed genealogical mutation rates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Burgarella1">[73]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Shi3">[74]</xref>; lmMR: genealogical mutation rate adjusted for population variation using logistic model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Burgarella1">[73]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>*is a part of the haplogroup name.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>MtDNA</title>
<sec id="s3b1">
<title>MtDNA haplogroup profiles, Population summary statistics, and PCA analysis</title>
<p>MtDNA HVS-I sequences of 396 individuals from the four studied Qiangic populations have been successfully typed. A total of 214 different haplotypes were defined by 134 polymorphic sites in the HVS-I dataset. The haplotype diversity of those Qiangic groups ranged from 0.978 to 0.994, with the lowest haplotype diversity observed in Horpa-Daofu (0.978) and the highest in Horpa-Danba (0.994). The mean number of pairwise differences (MNPD) and nucleotide diversity (ND) show a similar pattern with the haplotype diversity, as the highest diversity was observed in Horpa-Danba and the lowest in Horpa-Daofu. However, Tibetan-Yajiang has a higher diversity in haplotype but lower diversity in MNPD and ND than Tibetan-Xinlong. Measures of population growth (Tajima’s D, Fu’s Fs, Fu and Li’s D*, and Fu and Li’s F*) all gave the negative values for each population, but Tajima’s D, Fu &amp; Li’s D* and F* were not statistically significant in Horpa-Daofu (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t002">Table 2</xref>). The not significant growth factor values and the lowest diversities of Horpa-Daofu might be the result of small sample sizes and/or genetic drift.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0103772-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Molecular diversity indices and growth summary statistics for Qiangic populations.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0103772-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Diversity Indices</td>
<td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1">Growth Statistics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HaplotypeDiversity(SD)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNPD(SD)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NucleotideDiversity(SD)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tajima’s D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu’s Fs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu and Li’s D<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu andLi’s F<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DB</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.994±0.00005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.468±3.121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0140±0.0075</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.927</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.174</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.515</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DF</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.978±0.00012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.126±2.534</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0111±0.0061</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.443</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.500</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.187</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.312</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.993±0.00001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.698±2.749</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0123±0.0066</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.081</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.187</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.437</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.434</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YJ</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.980±0.00001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.027±2.884</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0130±0.0069</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.906</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.916</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.729</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.863</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSC</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">396</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.990±0.00000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.917±2.831</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0128±0.0068</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.119</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.594</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0020</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.612</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.423</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.02</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Abbreviations: N, number of sequences; h, number of haplotypes; S, number of polymorphic sites; MNPD, mean number of pairwise differences; SD, standard deviation; P, probability value.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>*is a part of the parameter name.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>397 samples were successfully assigned to mtDNA haplogroups using a combination of HVS-I sequence motifs and single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) distributed around the coding region of the mtDNA genome. A total of 79 haplogroups or paragroups (unclassified lineages within a clade marked with an asterisk [*]) were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g002">Figure 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s001">Table S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s002">Table S2</xref>), all within the two principal out-Africa macrohaplogroups: M and N (including R). Macrohaplogroup M and its subhaplogroups comprise 59.70% of the Qiangic maternal gene pool, and macrohaplogroup N and its subhaplogroups comprise the left 49.30%. The most prevalent haplogroups within macrohaplogroup M, haplogroup D and G represent 18.14% and 13.60% of all the samples. Within macrohaplogroup N, haplogroup A and F are the most common lineages, accounting for 13.60% and 10.58% of Qiangic, respectively. The majority of the mtDNA lineages belong to eastern Eurasian specific groups, including those from Northeast Asia (A, D4, D5, G, C, and Z) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Tanaka1">[83]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Derenko2">[85]</xref> and Southern China or Southeast Asia (B, F, M7, and R9) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Li4">[54]</xref>. Only two U samples in Yajiang might be traced for their origins to western or southern Eurasia, comprising 0.5% of Qiangic. The frequencies of Southern China or Southeast Asia specific haplogroups in Horpa-Danba, Horpa-Daofu, Tibetan-Xinlong, and Tibetan-Yajiang are 26.09%, 22.50%, 27.73%, and 21.35%, respectively. However, Tibetan-Yajiang, Horpa-Danba, Horpa-Daofu and, to a lesser extent, Tibetan-Xinlong, display a considerable Northeast Asian proportion of lineages (56.77%, 56.52%, 55.00%, and 43.70%, respectively). Consistent with other studied Tibetan populations on the Tibetan Plateau, Qiangic populations also showed a strong similarity with Northeast Asian populations.</p>
<p>We performed a PCA using the mtDNA haplogroup frequencies of Qiangic groups in this study and other 68 populations to see the detailed genetic patterns of those populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g003">Figure 3b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s003">Table S3</xref>). The first PC revealed a clear geographic division between northern populations (Altaic and Northern Han) and southern populations (Southern Han, Tai-Kadai, and Hmong-Mien). Qiangic groups were clustered in the northern pole due to the high frequencies of haplogroup A and G. Han Chinese and Tibeto-Burman populations showed significantly different distributions in the second PC. Qiangic populations were clustered within Tibeto-Burman group due to the existence of haplogroup M9a’b and M13.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b2">
<title>Phylogeography of Macrohaplogroup M</title>
<p>Macrohaplogroup M and its subhaplogroups represent the majority of the Qiangic maternal lineages, with frequencies ranging from 65.22% in Horpa-Danba to 57.98% in Tibetan-Xinlong. Haplogroup D4 and G are the most frequent sub-clades of macrohaplogroup M in Qiangic populations, each comprising 13.60%. Haplogroup D4, which is prevalent throughout Central Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Derenko2">[85]</xref>, Northeast Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Lee1">[86]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Nohira1">[87]</xref>, and Southwest China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhao1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wang3">[65]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wen3">[66]</xref>, represents the majority of haplogroup D samples in Horpa-Danba (17.39%), Tibetan-Yajiang (13.54%), Tibetan-Xinlong (13.45%), and Horpa-Daofu (10.00%). The haplotypes of D4* were extensively shared among Qiangic, Tibetan, Han Chinese, and Altaic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Specifically, sub-haplogroup D4j3 was detected in Horpa-Danba and Horpa-Daofu with considerable frequencies (4.35% and 5.00%, respectively). The age estimates generated for D4* and D4j3 in Qiangic were about 15 kya (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t003">Table 3</xref>). In addition, the population growth factor, Fu’s Fs values of haplogroups D4* and D4j3, were significantly negative (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t004">Table 4</xref>), implying post-LGM expansions of those two lineages in Qiangic.</p>
<fig id="pone-0103772-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Reduced Median-joining network based on the HVRI data of mtDNA.</title>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0103772-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Estimates of the coalescence time of selected mtDNA haplogroups inferred from the ρ statistic within Qiangic populations.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0103772-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haplogroup</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4j3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D5a2a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2a</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time(years BP ± SD)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8510±3647</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27220±11372</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41728±14806</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14722±5167</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16152±6594</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12563±9932</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20558±7661</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5139±2098</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45228±16855</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18845±7123</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34263±11234</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haplogroup</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2b1b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M7b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M9a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M9a1a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M9a1b1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M13a1b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N9a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time(years BP ± SD)</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20558±8392</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21985±7328</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28267±9422</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7067±4080</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13302±6651</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12563±6282</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12563±7693</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5653±4214</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30152±11919</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58248±15608</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12563±7693</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>Abbreviations: BP, before present; SD, standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>*is a part of the haplogroup name.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0103772-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption>
<title>Growth summary statistics and frequency spectrum tests for deviation from neutrality.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0103772-t004-4" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haplogroup</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tajima’s D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu’s Fs</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu and Li’s D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu and Li’s D<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu and Li’s F</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fu and Li’s F<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.118</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.491</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.200</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.814</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.578</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.020</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.184</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>6.181</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.304</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.020</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.927</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.237</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.431</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>6.724</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.030</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.165</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.124</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.264</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B5b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.065</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.793</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.479</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.420</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.679</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.125</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.572</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.176</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.079</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>5.692</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.457</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.423</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.576</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.519</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4j3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>1.576</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.082</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.619</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.651</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.899</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.812</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.035</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.262</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.042</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.083</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.264</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D5a2a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.462</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.776</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.498</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.581</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.773</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.762</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.324</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.409</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.430</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.637</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.593</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.781</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F1a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.599</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.964</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.078</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.598</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.649</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>1.809</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.637</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.253</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>1.940</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.478</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.119</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.915</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>3.027</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.748</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.275</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.771</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.344</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2b1b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.270</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.583</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.995</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.581</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.161</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.705</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>4.928</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.926</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.405</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.529</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.707</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M7b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.590</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.138</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.246</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.525</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.426</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.592</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M9a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.541</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.911</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.888</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.596</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.194</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.766</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M9a1a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>1.680</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.588</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.672</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.492</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.767</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.614</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M9a1b1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.043</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.207</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.971</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.516</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.081</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.963</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.943</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.320</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.871</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.190</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.975</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M13a1b</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>1.766</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.505</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.410</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>1.942</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.555</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.145</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N9a</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.886</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.774</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.419</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.851</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.526</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.927</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">*</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.534</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>7.523</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.170</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.787</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>2.371</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.960</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label>a</label><p>means P&lt;0.01,</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label>b</label><p>means P&lt;0.05,</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label>c</label><p>means 0.05&lt;P&lt;0.1. A haplotype L3e is used as an out group when calculating Fu and Li’s D and F.</p></fn><fn id="nt110"><label/><p>*is a part of the parameter name or haplogroup name.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>Haplogroup G is found at high frequencies in northeastern Siberia but it is also common among populations of Japanese Archipelago and Korean Peninsula. This haplogroup also comprises an average of 20% of the maternal gene pool of the Tharus from Nepal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Fornarino1">[88]</xref> and accounts for more than 10% in the Tibetan populations of Nagqu, Chamdo, Lhasa, Garze, and Monba <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>. In this study, haplogroup G and subhaplogroups G2a, G2b1b, G3, and G3a1 account for 20% of Horpa-Daofu and reach frequencies greater than 10% in three other Qiangic populations. Subhaplogroup G2a is represented as four distinct HVS-I motif types: 16129–16223–16278–16362 (I), frequent in Tibetan and Southern Han but nearly absent in Altaics; 16223–16227–16278–16362 (II), frequent in all the above three populations and probably experienced population expansion in Altaics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g005">Figure 5</xref>); 16193–16223–16278–16362 (III), exclusive in South Asia. All of the G2a samples in Horpa-Daofu harbor haplotype II but add one more mutation at site 16304. However, most of Tibetan-Xinlong samples belong to haplotype I (50%). Subhaplogroup G2b1b was first reported as a novel haplogroup in northeast India and has low frequency distribution in Tibet and surrounding regions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Soares2">[89]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Chandrasekar1">[90]</xref>. This haplogroup accounts for 4.69%, 2.50%, and 0.84 of Tibetan-Yajiang, Horpa-Daofu, and Tibetan-Xinlong. Compared with other Tibetan samples, 72.73% of Qiangic G2b1b samples were detected with a mutation at site 16356, thus forming some exclusive clades in the network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Subhaplogroup G3 comprises 6.77%, 5.00%, 3.36%, and 2.17% of Tibetan-Yajiang, Horpa-Daofu, Tibetan-Xinlong, and Horpa-Danba, respectively. Two Yajiang samples are further defined as G3a1 by a mutation at site 16215. In addition, we have found two Horpa-Danba G2a samples bearing both G2a (16278) and G3 (16274) characteristic mutations and thus we could not tell the exact haplogroup classification of those two samples. The coalescence time estimates of G*, G2b1b, and G3 were all around 20 kya and the age of G2a even reached about 34 kya (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t003">Table 3</xref>). However, it is noteworthy that the arrival time of these haplogroups at the Tibetan Plateau might be somewhat more recent than their coalescent ages would indicate, because nearly all these haplogroups (except G2b1b) had already differentiated before their arrival on the plateau (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The exclusive clades in the network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g005">Figure 5</xref>) and the significant negative Fu’s Fs values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t004">Table 4</xref>) of G2a and G3 suggest the probable isolation and secondary population expansion of the two lineages.</p>
<p>Haplogroup M8 has two sublineages, haplogroup C and Z. Haplogroup C is a common lineage, which is widespread in East Asia and Siberia and is one of the founder lineages among Native Americans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Torroni1">[6]</xref>. Haplogroup C comprises 8–10% of Horpa-Danba and Tibetan-Yajiang, but was detected at a very low frequency or even absent in Tibetan-Xinlong and Horpa-Daofu. Almost 60% of the C samples in present study harbored a specific HVS-I motif 16093–16298–16327 and were assigned as C4d. One Horpa-Danba individual with HVS-I motif 16298–16327 is also classified as C4d through complete sequencing (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0103772.s006">Doc S2</xref>). Haplogroup C4d has been supposed to be Tibetan specific, frequencies ranging from 1.6% to 5.0% in populations of Tibet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>. However, the frequency of C4d in Tibetan-Yajiang even reaches 6.25%. In addition, all the reported C4d samples in Tibet and Qinghai have the same motif as above mentioned. However, 25% of the C4d samples in Yajiang share another mutation at site 16111. About 23% of C samples in Qiangic with a mutation at site 16357 might be assigned as C4a2′3′4, which is also restricted to Tibeto-Burman populations. Haplogroup Z is observed at relatively low frequencies in Qiangic populations.</p>
<p>M9a’b is widely distributed in mainland East Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Soares2">[89]</xref> and Japan, and reaches its greatest frequency and diversity in Tibet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhao1">[8]</xref> and its surrounding regions, including Nepal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Fornarino1">[88]</xref> and northeast India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Chandrasekar1">[90]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Reddy1">[91]</xref>. It has been proposed recently that haplogroup M9’b had most likely originated in southern China and/or mainland Southeast Asia. After the LGM, M9a’b might be involved in some northward migrations in mainland East Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Peng2">[60]</xref>. In the present study, the frequencies of M9a’b in Horpa-Danba, Horpa-Daofu, Tibetan-Xinlong, and Tibetan-Yajiang are 4.35%, 10%, 13.45%, and 6.77%, respectively. Most M9a* samples (62.5%) of Qiangic shared the main haplotype that clustered in the central largest clade with other Tibeto-Burman populations in the network. However, the estimated age of M9a* is relatively young at about 7 kya. M9b is largely restricted to the non-Tibetans in southern China and southwest China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Peng2">[60]</xref>. We have detected low frequencies of M9b in Horpa-Danba and Tibetan-Xinlong (2.17% and 0.84%, respectively). In the networks of M9a1a and M9a1b, most of the Qiangic samples shared the descent types, giving a clear signal of out of Tibet migrations of those haplogroups. The age estimates generated for M9a1a and M9a1b1 in Qiangic were around 12–13 kya (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t003">Table 3</xref>), consistent with proposed post-glacial dispersal of the M9a’b lineages.</p>
<p>Haplogroup M13a has been found at its greatest frequency and diversity in Tibet, but it has also been detected at very low frequencies in Siberian Buryat, Yakut, Altaian Kazakh, and Ewenki <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Derenko2">[85]</xref>, and central Asian Kirghizs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Irwin2">[92]</xref> as well as Barghuts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Derenko1">[84]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Gokcumen1">[93]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Pakendorf1">[94]</xref>. The frequency of haplogroup M13a in Qiangic populations is remarkable, accounting for 3.27% of all samples. In the network of haplogroup M13a1 and M13a2, Qiangic and Tibetan-Burman samples formed some almost exclusive clades. This strongly suggests that these specific lineages have de novo origins within Tibetans. Specially, 70% of subhaplogroup M13a1b samples in Qiangic share the same haplotype. A coalescence time estimate for M13a1b corresponded to 5.7 kya (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t003">Table 3</xref>), suggesting a relatively recent Neolithic expansion out of Tibet and even more recent arrival into northern Asia of this lineage.</p>
<p>Qiangic populations also exhibit some basal Eurasian mtDNA lineages. Haplogroup M62, for example, was first reported in Northeast India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Chandrasekar1">[90]</xref> and since then has been reported in several populations at low frequency throughout Tibet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Zhao1">[8]</xref>. Zhao et al. suggested that M62 might represent the genetic relics of the initial Late Paleolithic settlers (&gt;21 kya) on the Tibetan Plateau. In this study, we observed haplogroup M62b in three Yajiang Tibetans. The haplotype of those three individuals is different from all other reported M62 samples with a mutation at site 16305. Likewise, haplogroup M74a was detected in one Xinlong Tibetan, and the haplotype of which bearing a distinctive mutation at site 16274 only shared with one Maonan individual, one Zhuang individual, and one Hainan Han Chinese <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Kong1">[52]</xref>. Haplogroup M33c was found in a Tibetan sample from Yajiang with a similar haplotype as some Hmong-Mien samples <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Kong1">[52]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b3">
<title>Phylogeography of Macrohaplogroup N</title>
<p>Haplogroup R and its subhaplogroups (B and F) represent the majority of the lineages branching from the basal N trunk, accounting for 26.09%, 22.50%, 28.57%, and 23.44% of the maternal diversity in Horpa-Danba, Horpa-Daofu, Tibetan-Xinlong, and Tibetan-Yajiang, respectively. Subhaplogroup B4* is the most frequent lineage of haplogroup B in Qiangic, comprising 4.53% of all the samples. In the network of B4*, the root clade composed almost exclusively of non-Tibetan-Burman samples, however, the Tibetan-Burman samples only formed some small clusters or shared the terminal types, suggesting that B4* had already differentiated before its arrival in Tibet. Subhaplogroup F1* is the most frequent lineage of haplogroup F in Qiangic, accounting for 5.54% of all the samples, and even comprising as high as 12.5% of Horpa-Daofu. Age estimate generated for F1* in Qiangic was around 5 kya (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t003">Table 3</xref>). The exclusive Qiangic cluster of F1* in the network suggests a strong bottleneck or founder effect in its Neolithic migration towards the plateau. The significant negative values of the growth factor estimates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t004">Table 4</xref>) suggest a secondary expansion and probable selection of F1* lineage during its adaptation in the plateau.</p>
<p>Haplogroup N* is almost exclusively represented by haplogroup A in our samples. Haplogroup A is widely distributed in northern and eastern Asia, occurring at frequencies of 5%–10% in different populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Derenko2">[85]</xref>. Haplogroup A also has an average frequency of nearly 9% on the plateau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>. Subhaplogroup A4*, which is mainly found in Central, Northeast and Southwest Asia, is the most frequent sublineage of haplogroup A in Qiangic, accounting for 2.17%, 5.00%, 4.20%, and 12.50% of Horpa-Danba, Horpa-Daofu, Tibetan-Xinlong, and Tibetan-Yajiang, respectively. Network analysis of haplogroup A4* revealed a star-like pattern and thus showed a signal of population expansion on the plateau (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g005">Figure 5</xref>). The probable population expansion was also confirmed by growth summary statistics in this lineage (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0103772-t004">Table 4</xref>). Subhaplogroup A11 split from the root of haplogroup A very early and formed a distinct lineage. A11a and A11b, the two sublineages of A11, have the different distribution pattern. Most of the A11 samples in Tibet belong to A11* or A11a and only a few have a control-region substitution at site 16234, assigned as A11b. However, almost all the A11 samples in the Tibetan-Burman and Han Chinese of Yunnan belong to A11b. In the present study, three of five A11 samples belonged to A11* and the other two were assigned as A11b.</p>
</sec></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The Sino-Tibetan linguistic family comprises some 460 languages distributed in East Asia, Southeast Asia, and parts of South Asia, including the Chinese and Tibeto-Burman subfamilies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Martisoff1">[1]</xref>. Despite intense linguistic, archaeological, and genetic researches, where the Sino-Tibetan speakers came from, how they dispersed remain major open questions. One widely accepted hypothesis states that the ancestors of the Sino-Tibetan population were originally from the Neolithic Age Di-Qiang people in the upper and middle Yellow River basin. Di people have gradually developed into Han Chinese and Qiangic populations since the collapse of Later Liang dynasty (one of the Sixteen Kingdoms dynasty, AD 386–403). Here, we integrated the Y chromosome and mtDNA evidence of Qiangic populations to provide a broader framework for reconstructing the history of Sino-Tibetan.</p>
<p>From the paternal Y chromosome perspective, haplogroup D1-M15 originated from D*-M174 during its migration into mainland East Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wei2">[95]</xref>. Around 50–60 kya, a subgroup of haplogroup D*-M174 and D1-M15 started their northward migration through WSC corridor into nowadays Qinghai province, and then probably moved along the well-known route, called the Tibeto-Burman corridor, to enter the Himalayas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wei2">[95]</xref>. Haplogroup D*-M174 probably gave birth to D3a-P47 in Tibet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wei2">[95]</xref>. Haplogroup D3a-P47 experienced recent population expansion on the Tibetan Plateau, and then probably migrated southward via the WSC corridor and gradually became the main genetic component of Tibeto-Burman populations in nowadays Sichuan, Yunnan, and Guangxi province. Y chromosome haplogroup D might give the evidences of the late Palaeolithic human activity on the plateau. The genetic relics of late Palaeolithic age have also been detected in the maternal side, for example, haplogroup M62b. In addition, a number of Paleolithic sites have been excavated crossing the Tibetan Plateau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Brantingham1">[96]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Yuan1">[99]</xref>, documenting the earliest human presence on the plateau dated to 20–30 kya.</p>
<p>Around 20–40 kya, a population with dominant haplogroup O3-M122 Y chromosomes (haplogroup O3a1c-002611, O3a2c1*-M134, O3a2c1a-M117, and probably other O3 lineages) finally reached the upper and middle Yellow River basin and formed the Di-Qiang populations. During the Neolithic period, the Di-Qiang people experienced relatively huge population expansion. A subgroup of the Di-Qiang people with dominant haplogroup O3a2c1*-M134 and O3a2c1a-M117, now called the Proto-Tibeto-Burman people left their Yellow River homeland, probably also moved along the Tibeto-Burman corridor, embarking on large-scale westward migrations to nowadays Qinghai province and then southward to the Himalayas, or southward migration directly via the WSC corridor to Yunnan and Guangxi, where they mixed with D-M174 linages and developed into Tibeto-Burman populations. However, haplogroup O3a2c1*-M134 might have already reached Tibet predated the above southward migration together with O3a2c1a-M117, judging from the high diversity in the network of O3a2c1*-M134 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0103772-g004">Figure 4</xref>). In addition, another branch of the Di-Qiang people, the proto-Chinese, with dominant haplogroup O3a1c-002611 migrated eastward to the central China plain area, the middle and lower Yellow River Valley, and integrated gradually with the natives (probably populations with haplogroup C-M130 or D-M174) around 5–6 kya. Subsequently, the Di-Qiang people that resided in upper and middle Yellow River basin with haplogroup O3a2c1*-M134 and O3a2c1a-M117 formed the well-known Yan-Huang tribe (Hot Emperor and Yellow Emperor), and the eastward branch with O3a1c-002611 developed into the Dong Yi tribe. The Yan-Huang tribe together with the Dong Yi tribe gradually developed into a large population known as Han Chinese. With the expansion of Han Chinese, especially southward, this group became the largest one of the 56 officially recognized ethnic populations in China.</p>
<p>The role of haplogroup O3-M122 lineages played in the origin of Tibeto-Burman populations has suggested extensive genetic input from northern Asians. This suggestion has been supported by previous studies employing autosomal STR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Gayden2">[100]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Kang2">[101]</xref>, Y chromosome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Gayden1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Hammer1">[34]</xref>, and mtDNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Qin1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Wen1">[9]</xref>. It is not surprising that the maternal variation of Qiangic populations was also largely contributed by northern Asian-prevalent haplogroups, including haplogroups A, C, D, and G. In addition, cultural features of the upper Yellow River basin, such as painted pottery, millet agriculture, and urn burial, are prevalent in the Neolithic sites of WSC, probably due to the demic diffusion via the genetic corridor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0103772-Shi4">[102]</xref>. However, we still could not rule out the possibility that the complex genetic structure of Qiangic populations might be due to repeated admixture from surrounding populations, which provides directions for future work.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0103772.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Y chromosome and mtDNA haplogroup frequencies of Qiangic populations.</bold></p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0103772.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Y chromosome SNP and STR data, mtDNA haplogroups and HVS-I motif of Qiangic</bold> <bold>populations.</bold></p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0103772.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Y chromosome and mtDNA haplogroup frequencies used in PCA plot and haplogroup</bold> <bold>contributions to each PC.</bold></p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0103772.s004" mimetype="application/vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Shared Y-STR haplotypes between Qiangic populations and other East Asian populations.</bold></p>
<p>(XLS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0103772.s005" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Doc S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Geographic distribution of Y chromosome haplogroup D1 and D3a, Y-STR neighbor-joining tree based on genetic distance.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0103772.s006" mimetype="application/msword" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0103772.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Doc S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Three representative complete mtDNA haplotypes compared to rCRS.</bold></p>
<p>(DOC)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Martisoff1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martisoff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Sino-Tibetan linguistics: present state and future prospects</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Anthropol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>504</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wang1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wang WSY (1998) In the Bronze Age and Early Iron Age peoples of Eastern Central Asia. University of Pennsylvania Museum Publications, 508–534.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-CavalliSforza1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cavalli-Sforza LL, Piazza MP (1994) The history and geography of human genes. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Qi1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Genetic evidence of paleolithic colonization and neolithic expansion of modern humans on the tibetan plateau</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1761</fpage>–<lpage>1778</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Qin1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A mitochondrial revelation of early human migrations to the Tibetan Plateau before and after the last glacial maximum</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>–<lpage>569</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Torroni1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torroni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zamudio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA analysis in Tibet: implications for the origin of the Tibetan population and its adaptation to high altitude</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Yao1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>QP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kivisild</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Phylogeographic differentiation of mitochondrial DNA in Han Chinese</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>–<lpage>651</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Zhao1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>QP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial genome evidence reveals successful Late Paleolithic settlement on the Tibetan Plateau</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>21230</fpage>–<lpage>21235</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wen1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Analyses of genetic structure of Tibeto-Burman populations reveals sex-biased admixture in southern Tibeto-Burmans</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>856</fpage>–<lpage>865</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wen2"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genetic evidence supports demic diffusion of Han culture</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>431</volume>: <fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Forster1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Mother Tongue and Y Chromosomes</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>333</volume>: <fpage>1390</fpage>–<lpage>1391</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Su1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seielstad</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kangwanpong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Y chromosome haplotypes reveal prehistorical migrations to the Himalayas</article-title>. <source>Hum Genet</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>582</fpage>–<lpage>590</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Qian1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Multiple origins of Tibetan Y chromosomes</article-title>. <source>Hum Genet</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>454</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Shi1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Y chromosome evidence of earliest modern human settlement in East Asia and multiple origins of Tibetan and Japanese populations</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Cai1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Human migration through bottlenecks from Southeast Asia into East Asia during Last Glacial Maximum revealed by Y chromosomes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e24282</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Yan1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>An updated tree of Y-chromosome Haplogroup O and revised phylogenetic positions of mutations P164 and PK4</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1013</fpage>–<lpage>1015</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wang2"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Late Neolithic expansion of ancient Chinese revealed by Y chromosome haplogroup O3a1c-002611</article-title>. <source>J Syst Evol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>286</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Kang1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Y-chromosome O3 haplogroup diversity in Sino-Tibetan populations reveals two migration routes into the eastern Himalayas</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Genet</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Sun1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>The nationality languages in the six valleys and their language branches</article-title>. <source>Yunnan Minzuxuebao</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Karafet1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karafet</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meilerman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zegura</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>New binary polymorphisms reshape and increase resolution of the human Y chromosomal haplogroup tree</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>830</fpage>–<lpage>838</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-vanOven1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Oven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Updated comprehensive phylogenetic tree of global human mitochondrial DNA variation</article-title>. <source>Hum Mutat</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>E386</fpage>–<lpage>E394</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Bandelt1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Median-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Excoffier1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laval</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Arlequin ver. 3.0: An integrated software package for population genetics data analysis</article-title>. <source>Evol Bioinform Online</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Fu1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations against population growth, hitchhiking and background selection</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>915</fpage>–<lpage>925</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Fu2"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>709</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Librado1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Librado</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>DnaSP v5: a software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1451</fpage>–<lpage>1452</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Tajima1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Statistical-method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Forster2"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torroni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Origin and evolution of Native American mtDNA variation: a reappraisal</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>945</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Saillard1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saillard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lynnerup</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bandelt</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>mtDNA variation among Greenland Eskimos: the edge of the Beringian expansion</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>718</fpage>–<lpage>726</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Soares1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ermini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mormina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Correcting for purifying selection: An improved human mitochondrial molecular clock</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>740</fpage>–<lpage>759</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Deng1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Genetic affinity between the Kam-Sui speaking Chadong and Mulam people</article-title>. <source>J Syst Evol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Gan1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mustavich</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Pinghua population as an exception of Han Chinese’s coherent genetic structure</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>313</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Gayden1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gayden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cadenas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Regueiro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhivotovsky</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Himalayas as a directional barrier to gene flow</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>884</fpage>–<lpage>894</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Hammer1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karafet</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Omoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Dual origins of the Japanese: common ground for hunter-gatherer and farmer Y chromosomes</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Li1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pramoonjago</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Paternal genetic affinity between Western Austronesians and Daic populations</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>146</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Li2"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Paternal genetic structure of Hainan aborigines isolated at the entrance to East Asia</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e2168</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Li3"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013b</year>) <article-title>Substitution of Hainan indigenous genetic lineage in the Utsat people, exiles of the Champa kingdom</article-title>. <source>J Syst Evol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Lu1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Genetic evidence for the multiple origins of Pinghua Chinese</article-title>. <source>J Syst Evol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Nonaka1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nonaka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takezaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Y-chromosomal binary haplogroups in the Japanese population and their relationship to 16 Y-STR polymorphisms</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Genet</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>480</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Park1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Understanding the Y chromosome variation in Korea–relevance of combined haplogroup and haplotype analyses</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>599</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Sengupta1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhivotovsky</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehdi</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Polarity and temporality of high-resolution y-chromosome distributions in India identify both indigenous and exogenous expansions and reveal minor genetic influence of Central Asian pastoralists</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Shi2"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Y-chromosome evidence of southern origin of the East Asian-specific haplogroup O3-M122</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Tan1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Y-chromosome polymorphisms define the origin of the Mang, an isolated population in China</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Biol</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>581</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Xue1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zerjal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Male demography in East Asia: a north-south contrast in human population expansion times</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>172</volume>: <fpage>2431</fpage>–<lpage>2439</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Black1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dufall</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sulliva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bittles</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genetic ancestries in northwest Cambodia</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Biol</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>620</fpage>–<lpage>627</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Dancause1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dancause</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arunotai</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Origins of the Moken Sea Gypsies inferred from mitochondrial hypervariable region and whole genome sequences</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Fucharoen1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fucharoen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fucharoen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA polymorphisms in Thailand</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Hill1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mormina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meehan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Phylogeography and ethnogenesis of aboriginal Southeast Asians</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2480</fpage>–<lpage>2491</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Hill2"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mormina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A mitochondrial stratigraphy for Island Southeast Asia</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Irwin1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saunier</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strouss</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diegoli</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sturk</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial control region sequences from a Vietnamese population sample</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Jin1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyler-Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The peopling of Korea revealed by analyses of mitochondrial DNA and Y-chromosomal markers. PLoS One</article-title>. <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e4210</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Kong1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>QP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Large-scale mtDNA screening reveals a surprising matrilineal complexity in east Asia and its implications to the peopling of the region</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Lertrit1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lertrit</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poolsuwan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thosarat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanpachudayan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boonyarit</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genetic history of Southeast Asian populations as revealed by ancient and modern human mitochondrial DNA analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Li4"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winograd-Cort</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA diversity and population differentiation in southern East Asia</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Li5"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013a</year>) <article-title>Three phases for the early peopling of Hainan Island viewed from mitochondrial DNA</article-title>. <source>J Syst Evol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>680</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Maruyama1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nohira-Koike</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nambiar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>mtDNA control region sequence polymorphisms and phylogenetic analysis of Malay population living in or around Kuala Lumpur in Malaysia</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Mona1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grunz</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pakendorf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castrì</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genetic admixture history of eastern Indonesia as revealed by Y chromosome and mitochondrial DNA analysis</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1865</fpage>–<lpage>1877</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Oota1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oota</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Extreme mtDNA homogeneity in continental Asian populations</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>118(2)</volume>: <fpage>146</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Peng1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trieu</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Tracing the Austronesian footprint in Mainland Southeast Asia: a perspective from mitochondrial DNA</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>2417</fpage>–<lpage>2430</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Peng2"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palanichamy</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Inland post-glacial dispersal in East Asia revealed by mitochondrial haplogroup M9a’b</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Tabbada1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabbada</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trejaut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Philippine mitochondrial DNA diversity: a populated viaduct between Taiwan and Indonesia?</article-title> <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Tajima2"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tokunaga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Juji</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genetic origins of the Ainu inferred from combined DNA analyses of maternal and paternal lineages</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Trivedi1"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sitalaximi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sircar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Molecular insights into the origins of the Shompen, a declining population of the Nicobar archipelago</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Tsai1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linacre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sequence polymorphism of mitochondrial D-loop DNA in the Taiwanese Han population</article-title>. <source>Forensic Sci Int</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wang3"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA copy number, but not haplogroup, confers a genetic susceptibility to leprosy in Han Chinese from Southwest China</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e38848</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wen3"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genetic structure of Hmong-Mien speaking populations in East Asia as revealed by mtDNA lineages</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>734</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wong1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Budowle</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Syn</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Sequence polymorphism of the mitochondrial DNA hypervariable regions I and II in 205 Singapore Malays</article-title>. <source>Legal Med (Tokyo)</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Yang1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farina</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Positive selection on mitochondrial M7 lineages among the Gelong people in Hainan</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Zimmermann1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bodner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amory</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fendt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Forensic and phylogeographic characterization of mtDNA lineages from northern Thailand (Chiang Mai)</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wilson1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weale</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balding</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Inferences from DNA data: population histories, evolutionary processes and forensic match probabilities. J. R. Stat. Soc</article-title>. <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wei1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayub</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyler-Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A comparison of Y-chromosomal lineage dating using either resequencing or Y-SNP plus Y-STR genotyping. Forensic Sci Int Genet</article-title>. <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>572</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Zhivotovsky1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhivotovsky</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cinnioğlu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The effective mutation rate at Y chromosome short tandem repeats, with application to human population-divergence time. Am J Hum Genet</article-title>. <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Burgarella1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgarella</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Navascués</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Mutation rate estimates for 110 Y-chromosome STRs combining population and father-son pair data. Eur J Hum Genet</article-title>. <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Shi3"><label>74</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayub</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zuniga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A worldwide survey of human male demographic history based on Y-SNP and Y-STR data from the HGDP-CEPH populations. Mol Biol Evol</article-title>. <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wang4"><label>75</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Inferring Human History in East Asia from Y Chromosomes</article-title>. <source>Investig Genet</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Zhong1"><label>76</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Global distribution of Y-chromosome haplogroup C reveals the prehistoric migration routes of African exodus and early settlement in East Asia</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Zerjal1"><label>77</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zerjal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertorelle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The genetic legacy of the Mongols. Am J Hum Genet</article-title>. <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>721</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Rootsi1"><label>78</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rootsi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhivotovsky</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baldovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kutuev</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A counter-clockwise northern route of the Y-chromosome haplogroup N from Southeast Asia towards Europe</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Mirabal1"><label>79</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirabal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Regueiro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cadenas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalli-Sforza</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Underhill</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Y-chromosome distribution within the geo-linguistic landscape of northwestern Russia</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1260</fpage>–<lpage>1273</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Roewer1"><label>80</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willuweit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krüger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rychkov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Analysis of Y chromosome STR haplotypes in the European part of Russia reveals high diversities but non-significant genetic distances between populations</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Zhong2"><label>81</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Extended Y chromosome investigation suggests postglacial migrations of modern humans into East Asia via the northern route</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>717</fpage>–<lpage>727</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wang5"><label>82</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wang CC, Li H (2014) Comparison of Y-chromosomal lineage dating using either evolutionary or genealogical Y-STR mutation rates. bioRxiv doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/004705" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/004705</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Tanaka1"><label>83</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larruga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takeyasu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial genome variation in eastern Asia and the peopling of Japan</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1832</fpage>–<lpage>1850</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Derenko1"><label>84</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derenko</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grzybowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malyarchuk</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dambueva</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denisova</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Diversity of mitochondrial DNA lineages in South Siberia</article-title>. <source>Ann Hum Genet</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Derenko2"><label>85</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derenko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malyarchuk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grzybowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denisova</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dambueva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Phylogeographic analysis of mitochondrial DNA in northern Asian populations</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1025</fpage>–<lpage>1041</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Lee1"><label>86</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA control region sequences in Koreans: identification of useful variable sites and phylogenetic analysis for mtDNA data quality control</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Nohira1"><label>87</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nohira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic classification of Japanese mtDNA assisted by complete mitochondrial DNA sequences</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Fornarino1"><label>88</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fornarino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maranta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Achilli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial and Y-chromosome diversity of the Tharus (Nepal): a reservoir of genetic variation</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Soares2"><label>89</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trejaut</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mormina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Climate change and postglacial human dispersals in southeast Asia</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1209</fpage>–<lpage>1218</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Chandrasekar1"><label>90</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrasekar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sreenath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urade</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Updating phylogeny of mitochondrial DNA macrohaplogroup M in India: dispersal of modern human in South Asian corridor</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e7447</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Reddy1"><label>91</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langstieh</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>ANS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Austro-Asiatic tribes of Northeast India provide hitherto missing genetic link between South and Southeast Asia</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e1141</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Irwin2"><label>92</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ikramov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saunier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bodner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amory</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The mtDNA composition of Uzbekistan: a microcosm of Central Asian patterns</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Gokcumen1"><label>93</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gokcumen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dulik</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhadanov</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genetic variation in the enigmatic Altaian Kazakhs of South-Central Russia: insights into Turkic population history</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Pakendorf1"><label>94</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pakendorf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tarskaia</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spitsyn</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soodyall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA evidence for admixed origins of central Siberian populations</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Wei2"><label>95</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Distribution of Y chromosome Haplogroup D in East Asia and its Anthropological Implications. COM. on C. A</article-title>. <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e11</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Brantingham1"><label>96</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brantingham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Lithic assemblages from the Chang Tang region, northern Tibet</article-title>. <source>Antiquity</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Aldenderfer1"><label>97</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldenderfer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The prehistory of the Tibetan Plateau to the seventh century AD: Perspectives and research from China and the West since 1950</article-title>. <source>J World Prehist</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Zhang1"><label>98</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Optical dating of Tibetan human hand- and footprints: An implication for the palaeoenvironment of the last glaciation of the Tibetan Plateau</article-title>. <source>Geophys Res Lett</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1072</fpage>–<lpage>1074</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Yuan1"><label>99</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>HuangW</surname><given-names>ZhangD</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>New evidence for human occupation of the northern Tibetan Plateau, China during the Late Pleistocene</article-title>. <source>Chin Sci Bull</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>2675</fpage>–<lpage>2679</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Gayden2"><label>100</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gayden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirabal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cadenas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lacau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genetic insights into the origins of Tibeto-Burman populations in the Himalayas</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Kang2"><label>101</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genetic structures of the Tibetans and the Deng people in the Himalayas viewed from autosomal STRs</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0103772-Shi4"><label>102</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Population migration from the upper Yellow River basin to Zang-Yi corridor viewed from Neolithic cultural evidence (in Chinese)</article-title>. <source>J Southwest University for Nationalities</source> <volume>29(10)</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>