<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-00947</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064539</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy and physiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Diagnostic medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer detection and diagnosis</subject><subject>Cancers and neoplasms</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Radiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Diagnostic radiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Social and behavioral sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological anthropology</subject><subject>Paleoanthropology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Fibrous Dysplasia in a 120,000+ Year Old Neandertal from Krapina, Croatia</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Krapina Neandertal Tumor</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monge</surname><given-names>Janet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kricun</surname><given-names>Morrie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radovčić</surname><given-names>Jakov</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radovčić</surname><given-names>Davorka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frayer</surname><given-names>David W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>University of Pennsylvania Museum, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Radiology, University of Pennsylvania Museum, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Croatian Natural History Museum, Zagreb, Croatia</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Anthropology, Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><addr-line>Department of Anthropology, University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelso</surname><given-names>Janet</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">frayer@ku.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors state that Monge and Frayer are Academic Editors. This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JM MK JR AM DWF. Performed the experiments: JM MK DR AM. Analyzed the data: MK DR AM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JM MK DR. Wrote the paper: JM MK AM DWF.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<elocation-id>e64539</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Monge et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We describe the first definitive case of a fibrous dysplastic neoplasm in a Neandertal rib (120.71) from the site of Krapina in present-day Croatia. The tumor predates other evidence for these kinds of tumor by well over 100,000 years. Tumors of any sort are a rare occurrence in recent archaeological periods or in living primates, but especially in the human fossil record. Several studies have surveyed bone diseases in past human populations and living primates and fibrous dysplasias occur in a low incidence. Within the class of bone tumors of the rib, fibrous dysplasia is present in living humans at a higher frequency than other bone tumors. The bony features leading to our diagnosis are described in detail. In living humans effects of the neoplasm present a broad spectrum of symptoms, from asymptomatic to debilitating. Given the incomplete nature of this rib and the lack of associated skeletal elements, we resist commenting on the health effects the tumor had on the individual. Yet, the occurrence of this neoplasm shows that at least one Neandertal suffered a common bone tumor found in modern humans.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="4"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Tumors are seldom documented in the human skeletal record in part because of their overall rarity. They are even more infrequent in the human fossil record, an effect of much younger age-at-death profiles and the fragmentary nature of most fossil remains. Here, we describe a Krapina Neandertal rib, which preserves bony indications of a fibrous dysplastic tumor.</p>
<p>The Krapina rock shelter is located on Hušnjakovo Hill, in the city of Krapina, some 55 km north of Zagreb, Croatia. Under the direction of Gorjanović-Kramberger, excavations at the site began in 1899 and continued until 1905, when almost 900 human bones were recovered, along with stone tools and thousands of faunal remains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-GorjanoviKramberger1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Miracle1">[4]</xref>. ESR and U-Series dating suggest a date between 120–130 kyr for the site with the entire stratigraphic sequence accumulating over a short 20 kyr time period or less <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Rink1">[5]</xref>. The lithic collection has been characterized as Mousterian with side scrapers as the most common tool <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Simek1">[6]</xref>. Krapina has yielded one of the largest samples of human skeletal remains accumulated from any Upper Pleistocene site. These human bones were recovered in a fragmentary condition, intermixed with the faunal and archeological sample. Only a few articulated bones have been found and there is no evidence of deliberate burial. Rather, cut marks and other evidence of bone processing suggest postmortem manipulation of the bones by other humans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Russell1">[7]</xref>. Among this sample of fragmentary cranial and postcranial elements, a number of pathologies have been identified, with most involving degenerative disease, blunt force trauma and dental hypoplasia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-GorjanoviKramberger2">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-HuttonEstabrook1">[16]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Krapina 120.71 is a 30mm long, left rib fragment containing about 2/3rds of the neck, most of the tubercular facet and a small section of the shaft. It appears to be a rib 3–6 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Kricun1">[12]</xref> and matches up well with adult rib K120.1, a left 4–6 rib. It shares identical areas of preservation with 120.1 and both show deep muscular impressions on the neck. (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0064539.s001">Table S1</xref> for comparable ribs.) On K120.71 just lateral from the tubercular facet, the inferior surface shows a fresh break, exposing cortical bone and a large chamber (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064539-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). External dimensions of the cavity are 18 mm in medial-lateral length and 7.6 mm at the maximum anterior-posterior breadth across the inferior, broken surface. The cavity’s internal aspect forms a smooth surface at the ceiling and on the anterior and posterior walls of the lesion. On the lateral-most portion of the bone where the rib narrows, two tiny bone spicules run across the medullary cavity in an anterior-posterior orientation. There are also some tiny spicules deep on the dorsal-most portion of the cavity, but for the most part the internal cavity is smooth and the cortical bone around it dense. Compared to Krapina 120.6, a left rib 3–5, where the cavity is packed with cancellous bone above the facet and continuing into the medullary fossa, the empty Krapina 120.71 medullary chamber is striking.</p>
<fig id="pone-0064539-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064539.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Krapina 120.71 in a caudal view (a).</title>
<p>The large lesion is located above the tubercular facet and extends laterally. The trabeculae have been destroyed and the cortex appears expansive. The thin cortical bone forming the superior surface of the cavern was broken away postmortem. (b) Krapina 120.6 shows the normal pattern of bony trabeculae in the medullary space. The surface irregularities are post-mortem.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064539.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>A conventional radiograph of the rib shows an osteolytic lesion with a geographic pattern of bone destruction arising in the posterior-medial aspect of the shaft of the rib and showing a sharp non-sclerotic margin. The lesion is eccentrically expansive with a shell of periosteal bone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064539-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). From the µ-CT scans we calculated an internal maximum length of 24 mm, maximum breadth of 16 mm and a maximum depth of 10 mm. Using Analyze [R], contour outline measures of the internal void, taken every.5 mm from individual slice µ-CT scan projections, give a volume for the tumor of 78 mm<sup>3</sup>. Since the inferior most portion of the rib is broken away, the tumor must have been larger than this. The opposing cortex shows mild erosion, but no adjacent periosteal reaction. The original matrix forming the tumor disintegrated over time, and a µ-CT examination shows soil infiltration within the lesion. The µ-CT also shows a portion of the lesion that appears loculated with vertical septations. There has been erosion beneath the facet of the tubercle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064539-g003">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0064539-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064539.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Radiograph of 120.71.</title>
<p>Two views of Krapina 120.71 rib fragment: a: Superior/inferior radiograph view of Krapina 120.71 in position matching illustration in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064539-g001">Figure 1</xref>; b: Lateral view in position matching the µ-CT scan series in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0064539-g003">Figure 3</xref>. The radiograph shows the full extent of the bony cavern excavated by the growth of the dysplastic mass. The lesion occupies most of the length of the fragment, but does not extend beyond the medial and distal borders. The full extent of the lesion is visible within this small rib fragment.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064539.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0064539-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064539.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Krapina 120.71 was µ-CT scanned at 20 micron intervals (voxel size, 20 microns) across the long axis of the curved bone producing 495 individual images.</title>
<p>Four slices are illustrated here showing the changing architectural detail of the internal tumor compartment. Loculations and vertical septations are clearly visible on each slice. Radiodense particles represent areas of adhering soil matrix that were part of the sedimentary environment.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064539.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The radiographic appearance of the lesion, the location of the lesion within the shaft of the rib and the estimated adult age of the individual suggest the most likely diagnosis is fibrous dysplasia. Fibrous dysplasia is a developmental disorder of bone in which lesions develop fibrous tissue and spicules of woven bone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Mirra1">[17]</xref>. The medullary cancellous bone is replaced by fibrous tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Rodenberg1">[18]</xref>. There may be one lesion (monostotic), several lesions, or multiple bone lesions (polyostotic). The monostotic form is the most common. The polyostotic form is often associated with skin pigmentation, may be associated with endocrine abnormalities and precocious puberty in females and rarely can have sarcomatous transformations. Rib lesions are often unilateral in the polyostotic form <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Schajowicz1">[19]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Fibrous dysplasia is the most common benign tumor/tumor–like lesion of ribs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-The1">[20]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Pascuzzi1">[21]</xref>, accounting for 17% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Hochberg1">[22]</xref> to 33% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-The1">[20]</xref> of primary rib lesions other than myeloma. In the monostotic form of fibrous dysplasia, 5.4% to 25% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Mirra1">[17]</xref> of lesions occur in the ribs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Mirra1">[17]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Rodenberg1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Gibson1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Kricun2">[24]</xref>. In the polyostotic form of fibrous dysplasia, 55% of individuals have rib lesions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Harris1">[25]</xref> and the rib lesions are often unilateral <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Schajowicz1">[19]</xref>. Fibrous dysplasia occurs anywhere along the rib except at the ends <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Kricun2">[24]</xref>.</p>
<p>The radiographic appearance of fibrous dysplasia of a rib is that of a slow-growing lesion with a geographic pattern of bone destruction that may appear round, elongated, or lobulated. It is centrally located in the marrow space, although it may appear eccentric as well <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Schajowicz1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Kricun2">[24]</xref>. Bone “expansion” is common as the rib is a thin flat bone and the distortion may be symmetric or asymmetric. The margin of fibrous dysplasia is sharp and may be sclerotic or non-sclerotic. The matrix may appear radiolucent, may show peripheral trabeculae and appear loculated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Hochberg1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Gibson1">[23]</xref>, may show mineralization with amorphous, faint, homogeneous increase in density (“ground glass”) appearance and on occasion may appear sclerotic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Gibson1">[23]</xref>. The degree of radiographic density of the matrix depends upon the degree of spicules of woven bone within the fibrous matrix <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Mirra1">[17]</xref>.</p>
<p>An enchondroma (chondroma) may have a similar radiographic appearance as the lesion presented, however, enchondromas develop at the sternal ends of ribs with 81.6% of rib enchondromas developing in the anterior aspect of the rib <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Hochberg1">[22]</xref>. The matrix may show punctate, ring or arc-like calcifications indicative of cartilage matrix <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Kricun2">[24]</xref>. Enchondroma is the second most common benign rib lesion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Hochberg1">[22]</xref>.</p>
<p>A post-traumatic lesion is unlikely as there is no evidence of a fracture and the expansive aspect of the lesion protrudes anteriorly. Any trauma to the rib would have occurred posterior. Chronic osteomyelitis is highly unlikely due to the lack of a sclerotic margin and the lack of periosteal reaction along the cortex opposing the expansive aspect of the lesion.</p>
<p>Chronic osteomyelitis is highly unlikely due to the lack of a sclerotic margin and the lack of periosteal reaction along the cortex opposing the expansive aspect of the lesion. Metastasis and myeloma are not likely since the relatively thick base of the periosteal shell suggests an underlying benign process <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Kricun3">[26]</xref>. In addition, it is unlikely that metastasis or myeloma existing in the medullary space, as seen in solitary hot spots (27) would have “expanded” the anterior cortex to such a degree without destroying or “expanding” the opposing cortex in this thin bone.</p>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Neoplastic bone disease, of both primary and secondary origin, is an exceptionally rare occurrence in the evolutionary fossil and archaeological record of human prehistory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Ortner1">[28]</xref>, until now extending back in time only 1,000–4,000 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Capasso1">[29]</xref>. Additionally, not only are primary bone neoplasms relatively rare in comparison to other neoplasms (accounting for a mere 7% of all soft and hard tissue forms of the disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-American1">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Hauber1">[31]</xref>), but several other factors confound the study of bone disease in past populations. Osteolytic lesions on bone are difficult to classify without the accompanying soft tissue analysis (primarily, but not exclusively histologic) that is part of the medical process of the study of disease etiology. Compounding this are the processes associated with decomposition of the body after burial or deposition that serves to fragment, erode, distort, or completely destroy parts of the remaining bony tissues.</p>
<p>The frequency of neoplastic disease is strongly correlated with the relatively recent expansion of the human life span. This increases the frequency of neoplastic diseases, many of which are age-dependent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Aufderheide1">[32]</xref>. Neandertals had average life spans that were at best half those modern populations, especially of people in developed countries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Caspari1">[33]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Monge1">[34]</xref>. Finally, it is recognized that environmental changes wrought by humans, compounded by population expansion, have resulted in an increase the types and the intensification of the pollutants within the environment, many of which are directly associated with neoplastic disease and were not part of environments in the past <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Halperin1">[35]</xref>.</p>
<p>Given these factors, most argue that cases of neoplastic bone disease are rare in prehistoric human populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Baxter1">[27]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Ortner1">[28]</xref>. It is against this background that the identification of a 120,000+ year old Neandertal with a primary osteolytic lesion is surprising and one that provides insights into the nature and history of the association of humans to neoplastic disease.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0064539.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0064539.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>A table of adult rib measurements for comparative Neandertal ribs from Krapina.</bold></p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The rib was discovered in the faunal collection by TD White (University of California, Berkeley) and N Toth (Indiana University, Bloomington) and preliminarily identified as a pathological specimen in 1986 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0064539-Gardner1">[11]</xref>. L Mjeda (Zagreb) produced Figure 1. We thank V Butković (University of Zagreb, Croatia) for the radiographs presented in Figure 2. We are grateful to GW Weber (University of Vienna, Austria) for the high resolution µ-CT images on the Viscom X8060 scanner (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.micro-ct.at/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.micro-ct.at/</ext-link>).</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0064539-GorjanoviKramberger1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gorjanović-Kramberger G (1906) Der diluviale Mensch von Krapina in Kroatien. Ein Beitrag zur Paläoanthropologie. In: Walkhoff, O, editor. <italic>Studien über die Entwicklungsmechanik des Primatenskelletes, Volume II</italic>. Wiesbaden: Kreidel, 59–277.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Radovi1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Radovčić J, Smith FH, Trinkaus E, Wolpoff MH (2008) The Krapina hominids: An illustrated catalog of the skeletal collection. Zagreb: Mladost and the Croatian Natural History Museum. 118p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Radovi2"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Radovčić J (1988) Dragutin Gorjanović-Kramberger and Krapina early man. Zagreb: Mladost and the Croatian Natural History Museum. 176 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Miracle1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Miracle PT (2007) The Krapina Paleolithic site. Zooarchaeology, taphonomy and catalog of the faunal remains. Zagreb: Croatian Natural History Museum. 345p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Rink1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rink</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarcz</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radovčić</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>ESR dates for Krapina hominids</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>378</volume>: <fpage>24</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Simek1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Chronological changes in stone tool assemblages from Krapina (Croatia)</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>575</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Russell1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Bone breakage in the Krapina Neandertal site</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Anthropol</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-GorjanoviKramberger2"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorjanović-Kramberger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1908</year>) <article-title>Anomalien und pathologische Erscheinungen am Skelett des Urmenschen von Krapina</article-title>. <source>Korres Deutsch Gesell Anthropol, Ethnol Urgesch</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-GorjanoviKramberger3"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorjanović-Kramberger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1908</year>) <article-title>Anomalien und Krankhafte Erscheinungen am Skelett des Urmenschen von Krapina</article-title>. <source>Die Umschau</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>623</fpage>–<lpage>662</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Molnar1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molnar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molnar</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>The incidence of enamel hypoplasia among the Krapina Neandertals</article-title>. <source>Am Anthropol</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>536</fpage>–<lpage>549</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Gardner1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gardner JC, Smith FH (2008) The paleopathology of the Krapina Neandertals. In: Monge J, Mann A, Frayer DW, Radovčić J, editors. New insights on the Krapina Neandertals. Zagreb: Croatian Natural History Museum. 237–251.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Kricun1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kricun M, Monge J, Mann A, Finkel G, Lampl M, <etal>et al</etal>.. (1999) The Krapina hominids. A radiographic atlas of the skeletal collection. Zagreb: Croatian Natural History Museum. 137p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Hutchinson1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Stressed to the max?: Physiological perturbation in the Krapina Neandertals</article-title>. <source>Curr Anthropol</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>904</fpage>–<lpage>914</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-GuatelliSteinberg1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guatelli-Steinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Prevalence and duration of linear hypoplasia: A comparative study of Neandertals and Inuit foragers</article-title>. <source>J Hum Evol</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Mann1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mann A, Monge J (2008) A Neandertal parietal fragment from Krapina (Croatia) with a serious cranial trauma. In: Monge J, Mann A, Frayer DW, Radovčić J, editors. New insights on the Krapina Neandertals. Zagreb: Croatian Natural History Museum. 261–268.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-HuttonEstabrook1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hutton Estabrook V, Frayer DW (2013) Trauma in the Krapina Neandertals: Violence in the Middle Paleolithic? In: Knüsel C, Smith M, editors. The bioarchaeology of human conflict: Traumatized bodies from early prehistory to the present. London: Routledge. in press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Mirra1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mirra JM (1980) Bone Tumors: Diagnosis and treatment. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott. 125–126.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Rodenberg1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bünger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Fibrous dysplasia of the spine, costae and hemipelvis with sarcomatous transformation</article-title>. <source>Skel Radiol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>682</fpage>–<lpage>684</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Schajowicz1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Schajowicz F (1994) Tumors and tumorlike lesions of bone. Pathology, radiology, and treatment. 2nd ed. Berlin: Springer-Verlag. 567–569.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-The1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">The Netherlands Committee on Bone Tumors (1973) Radiological atlas of bone tumors. Vol. 2. The Hague: Mouton and Co. pp. X, XII–XIII.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Pascuzzi1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascuzzi</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlin</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clagett</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name> (<year>1957</year>) <article-title>Primary tumors of the ribs and sternum</article-title>. <source>Surg Gynecol Obstet</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Hochberg1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>Primary tumors of the rib. Review of the literature and presentation of eleven cases not reported previously</article-title>. <source>Arch Surg</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Gibson1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Middlemiss</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Fibrous dysplasia of bone</article-title>. <source>Br J Radiol</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Kricun2"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kricun ME (1993) Tumors of the ribs. In: Kricun ME, editor. Imaging of bone tumors. Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders Company. 311–312.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Harris1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>HR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>The natural history of fibrous dysplasia. An orthopaedic, pathological, and roentgenographic study</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg</source> <volume>44A</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Kricun3"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kricun ME (1993) Parameters of diagnosis. In: Kricun ME, editor. Imaging of bone tumors. Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders Company. 6–7.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Baxter1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coakley</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The aetiology of solitary hot spots in the ribs on planar bone scans</article-title>. <source>Nucl Med Commun</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>834</fpage>–<lpage>837</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Ortner1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ortner DJ, Putschar WGJ (1981) Identification of pathological conditions in human skeletal remains. Washington DC: Smithsonian Contributions to Anthropology, #28. p.365.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Capasso1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capasso</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Antiquity of cancer</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-American1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">American Cancer Society (2012) Bone cancer overview. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.org/acs/groups/cid/documents/webcontent/003034-pdf.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.cancer.org/acs/groups/cid/documents/webcontent/003034-pdf.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Hauber1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hauber EJ, Hogendoorn PCW (2009) Epidemiology of primary bone tumors and economical aspects of bone metastases. In: Heymann D, editor. Bone cancer: Progression and therapeutic approaches. New York: Academic Press. 3–8.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Aufderheide1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Aufderheide AC, Rodriguez-Martin C (1998) The Cambridge encyclopedia of human paleopathology. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 478p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Caspari1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Older age becomes more common late in human evolution</article-title>. <source>PNAS USA</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>10895</fpage>–<lpage>10900</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Monge1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Monge JM, Mann AE (2007) Paleodeography of extinct hominin populations. In: Henke W, Tattersall I, editors. Handbook of paleoanthropology. Berlin: Springer-Verlag. 673–700.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0064539-Halperin1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halperin</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Paleo-oncology: The role of ancient remains in the study of cancer</article-title>. <source>Pers Biol Med</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>