<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171650</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-15651</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject><subj-group><subject>Infants</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Families</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject><subj-group><subject>Infants</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Endocrinology</subject><subj-group><subject>Diabetic endocrinology</subject><subj-group><subject>Insulin</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Hormones</subject><subj-group><subject>Insulin</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Families</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological tissue</subject><subj-group><subject>Adipose tissue</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological tissue</subject><subj-group><subject>Adipose tissue</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Birth weight</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physiological parameters</subject><subj-group><subject>Body weight</subject><subj-group><subject>Birth weight</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pediatrics</subject><subj-group><subject>Child development</subject><subj-group><subject>Child growth</subject><subj-group><subject>Growth restriction</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropometry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropometry</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pediatrics</subject><subj-group><subject>Neonatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Neonatal care</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Neonatal care</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>IGF-I and relation to growth in infancy and early childhood in very-low-birth-weight infants and term born infants</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">IGF-I and growth in VLBW and term infants</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>de Jong</surname>
<given-names>Miranda</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Cranendonk</surname>
<given-names>Anneke</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Twisk</surname>
<given-names>Jos W. R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>van Weissenbruch</surname>
<given-names>Mirjam M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Pediatrics, Albert Schweitzer Hospital, Dordrecht, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Neonatology, VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff003"><label>3</label> <addr-line>Department of Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics, VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Samocha-Bonet</surname>
<given-names>Dorit</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Garvan Institute of Medical Research, AUSTRALIA</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con">
<p><list list-type="simple"> <list-item><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> MdJ MvW.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> JT MdJ MvW.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> AC MdJ MvW.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> MdJ MvW.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> AC MdJ MvW.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Resources:</bold> AC MvW.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> MvW.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Visualization:</bold> MdJ MvW.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Writing – original draft:</bold> MdJ.</p></list-item> <list-item><p><bold>Writing – review &amp; editing:</bold> MdJ JT MvW AC.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">m.vanweissenbruch@vumc.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>9</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<elocation-id>e0171650</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>30</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>23</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>de Jong et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0171650"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Background</title>
<p>In very-low-birth-weight infants IGF-I plays an important role in postnatal growth restriction and is probably also involved in growth restriction in childhood. We compared IGF-I and its relation to growth in early childhood in very-low-birth-weight infants and term appropriate for gestational age born infants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>We included 41 very-low-birth-weight and 64 term infants. Anthropometry was performed at all visits to the outpatient clinic. IGF-I and insulin were measured in blood samples taken at 6 months and 2 years corrected age (very-low-birth-weight children) and at 3 months, 1 and 2 years (term children).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Over the first 2 years of life growth parameters are lower in very-low-birth-weight children compared to term children, but the difference in length decreases significantly. During the first 2 years of life IGF-I is higher in very-low-birth-weight children compared to term children. In both groups there is a significant relationship between IGF-I and (change in) length and weight over the first 2 years of life and between insulin and change in total body fat.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Considering the relation of IGF-I to growth and the decrease in difference in length, higher IGF-I levels in very-low-birth-weight infants in early childhood probably have an important role in catch-up growth in length.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="0"/>
<table-count count="5"/>
<page-count count="10"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Insulin-like growth factor I (IGF-I) is important for fetal and postnatal growth and development. In contrast to term infants, IGF-I levels in preterm infants decrease after birth and only increase gradually during the early postnatal period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref001">1</xref>]. Studies in preterm infants show that IGF-I levels during the first postnatal weeks are positively related to early postnatal growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref002">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref006">6</xref>]. IGF-I not only plays an important role in postnatal growth restriction; studies in older children (between 5 and 10 years of age) suggest that IGF-I also is involved in prolonged growth restriction in very-low-birth-weight (VLBW) infants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref007">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref008">8</xref>]. IGF-I levels in mid-childhood in preterm infants compared to term born children were found lower in one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref008">8</xref>], but higher in another study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref009">9</xref>].</p>
<p>The aim of the present study was to compare IGF-I and its relation to growth parameters in infancy and early childhood in VLBW infants (birth weight &lt; 1500 g) to term appropriate for gestational age (AGA) born infants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Study population</title>
<p>The VLBW infants were part of the Neonatal Insulin Replacement Therapy in Europe (NIRTURE) trial, an international multicenter randomized controlled trial investigating the role of early insulin therapy in VLBW infants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref010">10</xref>]. After written informed consent was obtained from both parents VLBW infants younger than 24 hours of age and requiring intensive care were randomized to receive continuous intravenous infusion of insulin for the first seven days of life or standard neonatal care with insulin treatment only in case of hyperglycemia. Exclusion criteria included maternal diabetes and major congenital anomalies. All infants participating in the NIRTURE trial in our neonatal intensive care unit (inclusion period from 2006 to 2007) were eligible for the present study. Therefore the sample size of the VLBW infants in the present study was determined by the number of infants we included in the NIRTURE trial.</p>
<p>The term infants were born between 2000 and 2005 from a low-risk population of pregnant women included in the first trimester in a prospective longitudinal study (Trophoblast study) which aimed to investigate the use of circulating trophoblast for prenatal diagnosis of pregnancy-associated diseases such as preeclampsia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref011">11</xref>]. Only term infants born AGA were included in the present study. AGA was defined as a birth weight above the 10th percentile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref012">12</xref>]. Standard deviation scores (SDS) of birth weight were calculated according to Niklasson [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref013">13</xref>].</p>
<p>Approval from the ethics committee of the VU University Medical Center was obtained.</p>
<p>During the inclusion period of the NIRTURE trial in our neonatal intensive care unit (21 months) 165 VLBW infants were admitted and the parents of 69 infants were approached regarding participation in the study. The most common reasons for not approaching parents were infants not requiring intensive care or no opportunity to obtain informed consent within the first 24 hours after birth. In our unit 47 VLBW infants participated in the NIRTURE trial. Five infants died and one child was excluded because parents refused blood sampling at the follow-up visits; 41 VLBW children were included in the present study. At 2 years corrected age one of these 41 children was lost to follow-up. Four (10%) of the VLBW children were SGA (defined as a birth weight below the 10th percentile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref012">12</xref>]). Seventeen infants (9 male/8 female) were assigned to the early-insulin group and 24 infants (12 male/12 female) received standard neonatal care. During the first week of life 6 infants in the standard care group were treated with insulin for 1 or 2 days because of hyperglycemia due to sepsis.</p>
<p>90 term born infants were included in the follow-up part of the Trophoblast study of whom 72 were AGA. Eight AGA children were excluded from the present study because they were lost to follow-up after the first visit at 3 months of age; 64 children were included in the present study. At 2 years of age 6 children were lost to follow-up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Data collection</title>
<p>The VLBW infants visited the outpatient clinic at expected date of delivery and at the corrected ages of 3 and 6 months, 1 year and 2 years, the term born infants at 3 months, 1 year and 2 years of age, according to the protocol of the NIRTURE trial and Trophoblast study respectively. At each visit anthropometry according to Dauncey et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref014">14</xref>] was performed by the same trained research nurse in all children. Body weight was measured using an electronic scale to the nearest 0.1 kg, standing height was measured to the nearest 0.1 cm and all lengths and circumferences were measured using a measuring tape to the nearest 0.1 cm. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated. Total body fat was calculated according to Dauncey from skinfold thickness measurements and body dimensions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref014">14</xref>]. Standard deviation scores of weight, height, head circumference and BMI were calculated according to Dutch references [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref015">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref016">16</xref>]. Blood samples for IGF-I and insulin measurement were taken at 6 months and 2 years corrected age in the VLBW infants and at 3 months, 1 and 2 years of age in the term born infants, according to the specific study protocol. All blood samples were taken early in the afternoon after a fasting period of at least 3 hours. Samples were stored at -80°C and were all analysed at the same time.</p>
<p>Study population and data collection also have been previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref017">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref019">19</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Assays</title>
<p>IGF-I in serum was measured by chemiluminescence immunoassay (Liaison, DiaSorin, Saluggia, Italy). Intra-assay coefficient of variation is 8% at both 10.3 nmol/l and 17.5 nmol/l and 9% at 23.8 nmol/l. Inter-assay coefficient of variation is 10% at 6.9 nmol/l, 7.4% at 30.8 nmol/l and 16% at 59.4 nmol/l.</p>
<p>Insulin in serum was measured by immunometric assay (Advia Centaur, Siemens Medical Solutions Diagnostics, Malvern, Pennsylvania). Lower limit of quantitation is 10 pmol/l. Intra-assay coefficient of variation is 4% at 20 pmol/l, 3% at 500 pmol/l and 4% at 1500 pmol/l. Inter-assay coefficient of variation is 8% at 24 pmol/l and 7% at both 780 pmol/l and 3000 pmol/l.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Statistical analyses were performed using the Statistical Package of Social Sciences software for Microsoft Windows version 19 (SPSS inc., Chicago, Illinois) and Stata version 14 (StataCorp, College Station, Texas). Differences in characteristics between VLBW children and term AGA children were evaluated using Student's t-test for normally distributed values and Mann-Whitney test and Wilcoxon signed-rank test for not normally distributed values.</p>
<p>Longitudinal differences in anthropometry, IGF-I and insulin between the two groups were analysed with linear mixed model analyses. In a first analysis, growth parameters at different time-points were compared between the groups and by adding an interaction between group and time to the model it was evaluated whether the difference between the groups changed over time. In a second analysis, the differences in IGF-I and insulin between the groups on average over time were investigated. Because both IGF-I and insulin were highly skewed to the right, both variables were log transformed before analyses. Finally the longitudinal relationship between IGF-I and insulin on the one hand and growth parameters on the other hand was investigated. This was done for the absolute growth parameters as well as for the changes in growth parameters between subsequent time-points. Group differences in the observed relationships between IGF-I and insulin and growth parameters were investigated by adding an interaction between group and IGF-I and insulin to the linear mixed models. All analyses were (if possible) adjusted for gestational age, gender and target height.</p>
<p>For insulin levels below the limit of quantitation a value of 1 pmol/l was used. P values &lt; 0.05 were considered as significant.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t001">Table 1</xref> shows the characteristics of the VLBW infants and term AGA infants including parental background information.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0171650.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Characteristics of the VLBW and term AGA children.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0171650.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">VLBW (n = 41)</th>
<th align="left">Term AGA (n = 64)</th>
<th align="left">p-value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Sex</bold></td>
<td align="left">21 M / 20 F</td>
<td align="left">35 M / 29 F</td>
<td align="left">0.728</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Gestational age (wks)</bold></td>
<td align="left">27.9 ± 1.3</td>
<td align="left">39.3 ± 1.2</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Birth weight (g)</bold></td>
<td align="left">1059 ± 231</td>
<td align="left">3529 ± 393</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Birth weight SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.06 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">0.3 ± 0.7</td>
<td align="left">0.019</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Maternal age (years)</bold></td>
<td align="left">31.3 ± 4.7</td>
<td align="left">33.7 ± 4.4</td>
<td align="left">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Maternal weight (kg)</bold></td>
<td align="left">68.2 ± 13.7</td>
<td align="left">71.7 ±13.2</td>
<td align="left">0.206</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Maternal smoking</bold></td>
<td align="left">5/41 (12%)</td>
<td align="left">6/64 (9%)</td>
<td align="left">0.747</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Racial group</bold></td>
<td align="left">26 Caucasian, 10 black, 3 Moroccan, 2 Asian</td>
<td align="left">55 Caucasian, 4 black, 5 Asian</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Highest level of parental education</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td>
<td align="left">3 low, 18 medium, 20 high</td>
<td align="left">l 1ow, 19 medium, 35 high, 9 unknown</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Target height SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.2 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">0.5 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">0.181</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Breast feeding</bold></td>
<td align="left">31/41 (76%)</td>
<td align="left">45/64 (70%)</td>
<td align="left">0.554</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">- duration of exclusive breast feeding (months)</td>
<td align="left">3 (0–8)</td>
<td align="left">3 (0–6)</td>
<td align="left">0.207</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">- total duration of breast feeding (months)</td>
<td align="left">5 (1–23)</td>
<td align="left">4 (1–24)</td>
<td align="left">0.924</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight (g) at expected date of delivery</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004"><sup><bold>b</bold></sup></xref></td>
<td align="left">3154 ± 579</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight SDS at expected date of delivery</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004"><sup><bold>b</bold></sup></xref></td>
<td align="left">-1.2 ± 1.3</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p>Data are expressed as mean ± standard deviation, percentages or numbers; duration of breast feeding is presented as median (range).</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p>VLBW infants are compared to term AGA infants.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p><sup>a</sup>Highest level of education completed by either parent was used as an indicator of socioeconomic status and classified as low (primary school, low occupational training), medium (high school, medium occupational training) or high (high occupational training, university).</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn004"><p><sup>b</sup>Weight (SDS) at expected date of delivery of the VLBW infants was compared to birth weight (sds) of the term AGA infants.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Anthropometry</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t002">Table 2</xref> shows the weight (SDS), length (SDS), head circumference (SDS), BMI (SDS) and total body fat at 3 months, 1 year and 2 years of (corrected) age for the VLBW and term AGA children. Longitudinal analysis showed that on average over the first 2 years of life all these growth parameters were significantly lower in VLBW children compared to term AGA children. The difference in length (SDS) between the VLBW children and term AGA children decreased significantly in the course of these 2 years. For the other growth parameters, the difference between the VLBW children and term AGA children increased or did not change over time.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0171650.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Anthropometry of the VLBW (n = 41) and term AGA (n = 64) children.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0171650.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">VLBW</th>
<th align="left">Term AGA</th>
<th align="left">VLBW</th>
<th align="left">Term AGA</th>
<th align="left">VLBW</th>
<th align="left">Term AGA</th>
<th align="left">Difference<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left">p-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
<th align="left">Interaction with time<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003"><sup>b</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left" colspan="2"><italic>At 3 months (corrected) age</italic></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2"><italic>At 1 year (corrected) age</italic></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2"><italic>At 2 years (corrected) age</italic></th>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight (kg)</bold></td>
<td align="left">5.6 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">6.2 ± 0.6</td>
<td align="left">9.1 ± 1.2</td>
<td align="left">10.1 ± 1.0</td>
<td align="left">11.5 ± 1.3</td>
<td align="left">13.0 ± 1.5</td>
<td align="left">-1.3 (-1.9 to -0.8)</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left">negative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.6 ± 1.4</td>
<td align="left">0.5 ± 0.7</td>
<td align="left">-0.9 ± 1.1</td>
<td align="left">0.1 ± 0.8</td>
<td align="left">-0.9 ± 1.0</td>
<td align="left">0.1 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">-1.0 (-1.3 to -0.7)</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Length (cm)</bold></td>
<td align="left">58.2 ± 2.7</td>
<td align="left">61.4 ± 2.0</td>
<td align="left">74.5 ± 2.9</td>
<td align="left">76.5 ± 2.4</td>
<td align="left">86.0 ± 3.7</td>
<td align="left">87.7 ± 3.3</td>
<td align="left">- 3.7 (-6.1 to -1.5)</td>
<td align="left">0.001</td>
<td align="left">positive</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Length SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">-1.1 ± 1.1</td>
<td align="left">0.4 ± 0.7</td>
<td align="left">-0.6 ± 1.0</td>
<td align="left">0.1 ± 0.8</td>
<td align="left">-0.7 ± 1.1</td>
<td align="left">-0.3 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">-0.9 (-1.2 to -0.5)</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left">positive</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Head circumference (cm)</bold></td>
<td align="left">40.4 ± 1.5</td>
<td align="left">41.3 ± 1.3</td>
<td align="left">46.1 ± 1.6</td>
<td align="left">47.2 ± 1.5</td>
<td align="left">48.3 ± 1.7</td>
<td align="left">49.4 ± 1.5</td>
<td align="left">-1.3 (-2.1 to -0.6)</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Head circumference SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.1 ± 1.0</td>
<td align="left">0.6 ± 0.8</td>
<td align="left">-0.4 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">0.4 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">-0.2 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">0.4 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">-0.7 (-1.0 to -0.4)</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left">no</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BMI (kg/m2)</bold></td>
<td align="left">16.3 ± 1.8</td>
<td align="left">16.4 ± 1.2</td>
<td align="left">16.3 ± 1.5</td>
<td align="left">17.2 ± 1.3</td>
<td align="left">15.5 ± 1.5</td>
<td align="left">16.9 ± 1.1</td>
<td align="left">-0.6 (-1.1 to -0.2)</td>
<td align="left">0.004</td>
<td align="left">negative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BMI SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.1 ± 1.3</td>
<td align="left">0.3 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">-0.7 ± 1.1</td>
<td align="left">0.1 ± 0.9</td>
<td align="left">-0.7 ± 1.2</td>
<td align="left">0.5 ± 0.8</td>
<td align="left">-0.6 (-1.0 to -0.3)</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left">negative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Total body fat (kg)</bold></td>
<td align="left">1.0 ± 0.5</td>
<td align="left">1.3 ± 0.3</td>
<td align="left">1.6 ± 0.6</td>
<td align="left">2.3 ± 0.7</td>
<td align="left">1.8 ± 0.6</td>
<td align="left">2.6 ± 1.0</td>
<td align="left">-0.5 (-0.7 to -0.4)</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left">negative</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>TBF/Weight</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.18 ± 0.06</td>
<td align="left">0.20 ± 0.04</td>
<td align="left">0.18 ± 0.06</td>
<td align="left">0.22 ± 0.05</td>
<td align="left">0.16 ± 0.05</td>
<td align="left">0.20 ± 0.06</td>
<td align="left">-0.03 (-0.05 to -0.015)</td>
<td align="left">&lt;0.001</td>
<td align="left">no</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>Data are expressed as mean ± standard deviation. TBF: total body fat.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p><sup>a</sup>Differences and p-values were based on the comparison between VLBW children and term AGA children on average over time adjusted for gender.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn003"><p><sup>b</sup>Negative interaction indicates that the differences between the groups became stronger over time; positive interaction indicates that the differences between the groups became less strong over time.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec013">
<title>IGF-I and insulin</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t003">Table 3</xref> shows IGF-I and insulin for the VLBW and term AGA children.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0171650.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>IGF-I and insulin.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0171650.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">VLBW (n = 41)</th>
<th align="left">Term AGA (n = 64)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="3"><italic>At 3 months (corrected) age</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>IGF-I (nmol/l)</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">7.7 (3.7–14.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="3"><italic>At 6 months (corrected) age</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>IGF-I (nmol/l)</bold></td>
<td align="left">10.2 (2.3–30.9)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Insulin (pmol/l)</bold></td>
<td align="left">23.0 (1.0–256.7)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="3"><italic>At 1 year (corrected) age</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>IGF-I (nmol/l)</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">6.8 (2.0–19.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Insulin (pmol/l)</bold></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left">15.7 (1.0–179.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="3"><italic>At 2 years (corrected) age</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>IGF-I (nmol/l)</bold></td>
<td align="left">11.6 (3.5–26.8)</td>
<td align="left">9.5 (4.2–21.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Insulin (pmol/l)</bold></td>
<td align="left">21.0 (1.0–190.9)</td>
<td align="left">17.9 (1.0–181.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="3"><italic>Difference between the VLBW and term AGA children on average over time adjusted for gender</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>IGF-I</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2">1.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref> (1.19 to 1.56); p &lt;0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Insulin</bold></td>
<td align="left" colspan="2">1.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002"><sup>a</sup></xref> (0.86 to 2.17); p = 0.182</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p>Data are expressed as median and range.</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p><sup>a</sup>Difference expressed as a ratio (e.g. VLBW children have 1.36 higher concentration of IGF-I compared to term AGA children).</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Longitudinal analysis showed that on average over the first 2 years of life IGF-I was significantly higher in VLBW children compared to term AGA children. Insulin did not differ between the VLBW and term AGA children over time.</p>
<p>In the VLBW children we also compared the early-insulin group to the standard care group and the SGA born children to the AGA born children and did not find significant differences.</p>
<p>In VLBW children IGF-I at 2 years corrected age was significantly higher than at 6 months corrected age (p = 0.023). In term AGA children IGF-I at 2 years of age was significantly higher than at 1 year of age (p&lt;0.001).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec014">
<title>Relation of IGF-I and insulin to growth parameters</title>
<p>Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t004">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t005">5</xref> show the longitudinal relationship over the first 2 years of life between IGF-I and insulin on the one hand and growth parameters on the other hand. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t004">Table 4</xref> the relationship with the absolute growth parameters is shown and in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t005">Table 5</xref> the relationship with the changes in growth parameters between subsequent time-points. In both groups there was a significant relationship between IGF-I and (change in) length and weight over the first 2 years of life and between IGF-I and total body fat. The relationship between IGF-I and (change in) head circumference and BMI SDS was only significant in the term AGA children.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0171650.t004" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t004</object-id>
<label>Table 4</label> <caption><title>Longitudinal relationship between IGF-I and insulin and growth parameters.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0171650.t004g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t004" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">VLBW</th>
<th align="left">Term AGA</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="3"><bold>IGF-I</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn003"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.14 (0.04 to 0.24); p = 0.004</td>
<td align="left">0.23 (0.15 to 0.32); p &lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.05 (0.01 to 0.10); p = 0.01</td>
<td align="left">0.05 (0.01 to 0.08); p = 0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Length</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.58 (0.15 to 1.02); p = 0.009</td>
<td align="left">0.75 (0.46 to 1.04); p &lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Length SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.06 (0.02 to 0.10); p = 0.007</td>
<td align="left">-0.02 (-0.06 to 0.01); p = 0.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Head circumference</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.04 (-0.08 to 0.17); p = 0.49</td>
<td align="left">0.15 (0.06 to 0.24); p = 0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Head circumference SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.02 (-0.01 to 0.04); p = 0.24</td>
<td align="left">0.002 (-0.03 to 0.03); p = 0.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BMI</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.01 (-0.05 to 0.08); p = 0.69</td>
<td align="left">0.04 (-0.02 to 0.09); p = 0.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BMI SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.02 (-0.03 to 0.07); p = 0.41</td>
<td align="left">0.08 (0.04 to 0.12); p &lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Total body fat</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.03 (0.01 to 0.06); p = 0.006</td>
<td align="left">0.06 (0.02 to 0.09); p = 0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="3"><bold>Insulin</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn004"><sup><bold>b</bold></sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.01 (-0.02 to 0.003); p = 0.16</td>
<td align="left">0.003 (-0.007 to 0.01); p = 0.56</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Weight SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.001 (-0.01 to 0.004); p = 0.75</td>
<td align="left">0.003 (-0.001 to 0.006); p = 0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Length</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.05 (-0.11 to 0.01); p = 0.12</td>
<td align="left">0.01 (-0.03 to 0.04); p = 0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Length SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.01 (-0.01 to 0.00); p = 0.05</td>
<td align="left">0.006 (0.002 to 0.01); p = 0.003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Head circumference</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.01 (-0.03 to 0.003); p = 0.13</td>
<td align="left">-0.002 (-0.012 to 0.009); p = 0.71</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Head circumference SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.002 (-0.01 to 0.00); p = 0.06</td>
<td align="left">0.001 (-0.02 to 0.004); p = 0.55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BMI</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.01 (-0.002 to 0.01); p = 0.19</td>
<td align="left">-0.001 (-0.01 to 0.005); p = 0.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>BMI SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.003 (-0.003 to 0.01); p = 0.27</td>
<td align="left">-0.001 (-0.006 to 0.003); p = 0.62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Total body fat</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.002 (-0.001 to 0.005); p = 0.26</td>
<td align="left">0.008 (0.004 to 0.01); p &lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t004fn001"><p>All analyses were adjusted for target height, gestational age and gender.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn002"><p>For example, in VLBW children a difference of 1 unit in IGF-I is associated with a difference of 0.14 units in weight on average over time.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn003"><p><sup>a</sup>Regarding IGF-I, there were significant group differences for length SDS and BMI SDS.</p></fn>
<fn id="t004fn004"><p><sup>b</sup>Regarding insulin there were significant group differences for length SDS.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="pone.0171650.t005" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t005</object-id>
<label>Table 5</label> <caption><title>Longitudinal relationship between IGF-I and insulin and changes in growth parameters.</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0171650.t005g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.t005" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">VLBW</th>
<th align="left">Term AGA</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="3"><bold>IGF-I</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t005fn003"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Weight</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.03 (0.003 to 0.06); p = 0.03</td>
<td align="left">-0.01 (-0.06 to 0.04);p = 0.63</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Weight SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.01 (-0.01 to 0.04); p = 0.50</td>
<td align="left">0.06 (0.02 to 0.10); p &lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Length</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.15 (0.03 to 0.26); p = 0.01</td>
<td align="left">0.15 (-0.30 to -0.004); p = 0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Length SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.01 (-0.02 to 0.04); p = 0.36</td>
<td align="left">0.01 (-0.02 to 0.05); p = 0.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Head circumference</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.02 (-0.05 to 0.02); p = 0.32</td>
<td align="left">-0.19 (-.29 to -0.09); p &lt; 0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Head circumference SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.009 (-0.01 to 0.03); p = 0.39</td>
<td align="left">0.03 (-0.0036 to 0.06); p = 0.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ BMI</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.03 (-0.08 to 0.02); p = 0.25</td>
<td align="left">-0.03 (-0.10 to 0.04); p = 0.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ BMI SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.001 (-0.04 to 0.04); p = 0.95</td>
<td align="left">0.06 (0.02 to 0.11); p = 0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Total body fat</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.008 (-0.01 to 0.03); p = 0.47</td>
<td align="left">-0.02 (-0.06 to 0.02); p = 0.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" colspan="3"><bold>Insulin</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t005fn004"><sup><bold>b</bold></sup></xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Weight</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.002 (-0.19 to 0.03); p = 0.16</td>
<td align="left">0.005 (-0.001 to 0.01); p = 0.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Weight SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.001 (-0.002 to 0.005); p = 0.50</td>
<td align="left">0001 (-0.004 to 0.006); p = 0.64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Length</bold></td>
<td align="left">-0.01 (-0.03 to 0.004); p = 0.14</td>
<td align="left">0.02 (-0.001 to 0.03); p = 0.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Length SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.001 (-0.003 to 0.005); p = 0.66</td>
<td align="left">0.003 (-0.02 to 0.04); p = 0.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Head circumference</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.002 (-0.003 to 0.006); p = 0.41</td>
<td align="left">0.004 (-0.008 to 0.02); p = 0.50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Head circumference SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.001 (-0.002 to 0.004); p = 0.59</td>
<td align="left">0.0003 (-0.003 to 0004); p = 0.87</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ BMI</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.004 (-0.003 to 0.01); p = 0.28</td>
<td align="left">0.000 (-0.008 to 0.008); p = 0.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ BMI SDS</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.001 (-0.004 to 0.007); p = 0.66</td>
<td align="left">-0.001 (-0.01 to 0.004); p = 0.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Δ Total body fat</bold></td>
<td align="left">0.004 (0.001 to 0.006); p = 0.02</td>
<td align="left">0.007 (0.002 to 0.01); p = 0.003</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t005fn001"><p>All analyses were adjusted for target height, gestational age and gender.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn002"><p>For example, in VLBW children a difference of 1 unit in IGF-I is associated with a change of 0.03 units in weight between two subsequent measurements on average over time.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn003"><p><sup>a</sup>Regarding IGF-I, there were significant group differences for <bold>Δ</bold> weight SDS, <bold>Δ</bold> head circumference, <bold>Δ</bold> BMI SDS and <bold>Δ</bold> total body fat.</p></fn>
<fn id="t005fn004"><p><sup>b</sup>Regarding insulin there were significant group diffences for <bold>Δ</bold> weight and <bold>Δ</bold> length.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>There was no significant relationship between insulin and (change in) length and weight over the first 2 years of life, but only between insulin and change in total body fat in both groups.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec015" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The present study shows that during the first 2 years of life VLBW infants have significantly higher IGF-I levels than term AGA children. In both VLBW and term born children there is a significant relationship between IGF-I and (change in) length and weight over the first 2 years of life.</p>
<p>The majority of studies concerned with IGF-I levels in VLBW infants have focused on the early postnatal period. Studies of IGF-I levels in older VLBW children are limited.</p>
<p>Patel et al. showed a significant correlation between IGF-I output and both weight and length, during the first two years in infants born between 24 and 33 weeks gestational age, which is in accordance with our results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref020">20</xref>]. They did not compare IGF-I levels with a control group of term born children.</p>
<p>Two previous studies in mid-childhood suggest that IGF-I is involved in prolonged growth restriction in preterm born infants. Kwinta et al. showed that 7-year-old extremely-low-birth-weight children with short stature have lower IGF-I levels than those with normal stature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref007">7</xref>]. Cutfield et al. showed that VLBW children between 5 and 10 years of age did not reach their mid-parental height SDS and had low IGF-I levels compared to term born AGA children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref008">8</xref>].</p>
<p>Our present study confirms the role of IGF-I in childhood growth in VLBW infants. The VLBW children in our study were shorter than term AGA children, but the difference in length between the VLBW and term AGA children decreased during the first 2 years of life. Therefore our finding of significantly higher IGF-I levels during the first 2 years of life in VLBW children compared to term AGA children together with the longitudinal relationship between IGF-I and growth suggests that IGF-I has an important role in the catch-up growth in length in early childhood in VLBW infants. Our results are in accordance with the study of Rajaram et al., showing higher IGF-I levels in preterm infants compared to term born infants from 2 through 12 months of (corrected) age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref021">21</xref>]. Kistner et al. found higher IGF-I levels in 9-year-old preterm born children compared to term born controls; as the preterm children were significantly shorter than the term born children, they hypothesize that preterm born children may have reduced sensitivity in the IGF-I receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref009">9</xref>].</p>
<p>During early postnatal life and at 1 year corrected age IGF-I levels in preterm infants are positively correlated to head circumference and brain volume [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref022">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref024">24</xref>]. In the present study we only found a significant relationship between IGF-I and head circumference in the term AGA children. The absence of this relationship in the VLBW children is probably caused by the small size of the group. We could not explain the inverse relation between IGF-I and change in head circumference in the term AGA children.</p>
<p>In the study of van de Lagemaat et al. in preterm infants between term age and 6 months corrected age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0171650.ref025">25</xref>], both IGF-I and insulin were correlated to growth parameters. At 6 months corrected age the correlation between insulin and IGF-I had disappeared, indicating the shift from insulin dependency to growth hormone (GH) dependency of IGF-I with increasing postnatal age. In the present study we did not measure insulin before 6 months of (corrected) age; this explains why we could not explore any relationship between insulin and growth in our study. We hypothesize that the association between insulin and total body fat could be caused by the influence of body composition on insulin sensitivity.</p>
<p>We found some differences between the VLBW and term born children in the relationships between IGF-I and insulin and (changes in) growth parameters (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t004">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0171650.t005">5</xref>), but the groups are too small to draw any conclusions from these differences.</p>
<p>The most important limitation of our study is the small number of children. The results have to be confirmed in larger groups of VLBW children. Including serial IGF-I measurements from the early postnatal period until late childhood in both VLBW infants and term born controls at the same time points could contribute to the knowledge about the role of IGF-I in growth of VLBW infants during childhood, its relation to catch-up growth and about the meaning of the higher IGF-I levels in preterm born children compared to term born children.</p>
<p>Another limitation is the amount of statistical tests performed. Because of this, individual significant results should be interpreted with caution.</p>
<p>In conclusion, as IGF-I is related to growth in length and the difference in length compared to term born children decreases during early childhood, the higher IGF-I levels in VLBW infants during the first 2 years of life probably have an important role in catch-up growth in length.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec016">
<title>Supporting information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0171650.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0171650.s001" xlink:type="simple">
<label>S1 Protocol</label>
<caption>
<title>Protocol local amendment to Nirture study.</title>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lineham</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlenburg</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haslam</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stuart</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Circulating insulin-like growth factor I levels in newborn premature and full-term infants followed longitudinally</article-title>. <source>Early Hum Dev</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3956421</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohkawa</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shoji</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitamura</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suganuma</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshikawa</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>IGF-I, leptin and active ghrelin levels in very low birth weight infants during the first 8 weeks of life</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1651-2227.2009.01516.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1651-2227.2009.01516.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19785636</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hikino</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ihara</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahata</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakayama</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kinukawa</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Physical growth and retinopathy in preterm infants: involvement of IGF-I and GH</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>732</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1203/00006450-200112000-00017" xlink:type="simple">10.1203/00006450-200112000-00017</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11726732</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajantie</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunkel</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rutanen</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seppala</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koistinen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarnesto</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>IGF-I, IGF binding protein (IGFBP)-3, phosphoisoforms of IGFBP-1, and postnatal growth in very low birth weight infants</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>2171</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1210/jcem.87.5.8457" xlink:type="simple">10.1210/jcem.87.5.8457</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11994360</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen-Pupp</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lofqvist</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polberger</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niklasson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fellman</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellstrom</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Influence of insulin-like growth factor I and nutrition during phases of postnatal growth in very preterm infants</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>448</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1203/PDR.0b013e3182115000" xlink:type="simple">10.1203/PDR.0b013e3182115000</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21263374</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsao</surname> <given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname> <given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Changes in serum insulin-like growth factors, not leptin, are associated with postnatal weight gain in preterm neonates</article-title>. <source>JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15772385</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwinta</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klimek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wojcik</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grudzien</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drozdz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pietrzyk</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1) serum concentration among 7-year-old extremely low birth weight children—an indicator of growth problems</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22145451</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutfield</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Regan</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname> <given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jefferies</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The endocrine consequences for very low birth weight premature infants</article-title>. <source>Growth Horm IGF Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>14</volume> <issue>Suppl A</issue>:<fpage>S130</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deschmann</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Legnevall</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanpee</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Preterm born 9-year-olds have elevated IGF-1 and low prolactin, but levels vary with behavioural and eating disorders</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>1198</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/apa.12751" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/apa.12751</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25040495</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beardsall</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhaesebrouck</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogilvy-Stuart</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhole</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Weissenbruch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Early insulin therapy in very-low-birth-weight infants</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>359</volume>:<fpage>1873</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa0803725" xlink:type="simple">10.1056/NEJMoa0803725</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18971490</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tjoa</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Vugt</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Go</surname> <given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blankenstein</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oudejans</surname> <given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Wijk</surname> <given-names>IJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Elevated C-reactive protein levels during first trimester of pregnancy are indicative of preeclampsia and intrauterine growth restriction</article-title>. <source>J Reprod Immunol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12892901</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollack</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Divon</surname> <given-names>MY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Intrauterine growth retardation: definition, classification, and etiology</article-title>. <source>Clin Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1544253</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niklasson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ericson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fryer</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karlberg</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karlberg</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>An update of the Swedish reference standards for weight, length and head circumference at birth for given gestational age (1977–1981)</article-title>. <source>Acta Paediatr Scand</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>756</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1957592</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dauncey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gandy</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gairdner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of total body fat in infancy from skinfold thickness measurements</article-title>. <source>Arch Dis Child</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">849001</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fredriks</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Buuren</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burgmeijer</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meulmeester</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beuker</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brugman</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Continuing positive secular growth change in The Netherlands 1955–1997</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709729</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fredriks</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Buuren</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wit</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verloove-Vanhorick</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Body index measurements in 1996–7 compared with 1980</article-title>. <source>Arch Dis Child</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/adc.82.2.107" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/adc.82.2.107</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10648362</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cranendonk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Weissenbruch</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Components of the metabolic syndrome in early childhood in very-low-birth-weight infants and term small and appropriate for gestational age infants</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/pr.2015.118" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/pr.2015.118</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26086641</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cranendonk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Weissenbruch</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Salivary and serum cortisol and relation to blood pressure in infancy and early childhood in very-low-birth-weight infants</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>476</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/pr.2015.128" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/pr.2015.128</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">26151494</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lafeber</surname> <given-names>HN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cranendonk</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Weissenbruch</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Components of the metabolic syndrome in early childhood in very-low-birth-weight infants</article-title>. <source>Horm Res Paediatr</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000355597" xlink:type="simple">10.1159/000355597</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24281139</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavazzoni</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whatmore</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carney</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wales</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname> <given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The contributions of plasma IGF-I, IGFBP-3 and leptin to growth in extremely premature infants during the first two years</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1203/01.pdr.0000250036.34522.f1" xlink:type="simple">10.1203/01.pdr.0000250036.34522.f1</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17211149</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajaram</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koo</surname> <given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rangachari</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname> <given-names>DP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Insulin-like growth factor (IGF)-I and IGF-binding protein 3 during the first year in term and preterm infants</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1203/00006450-199505000-00004" xlink:type="simple">10.1203/00006450-199505000-00004</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7541522</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen-Pupp</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hovel</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellstrom</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellstrom-Westas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lofqvist</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Postnatal decrease in circulating insulin-like growth factor-I and low brain volumes in very preterm infants</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1129</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1210/jc.2010-2440" xlink:type="simple">10.1210/jc.2010-2440</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21289247</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lofqvist</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engstrom</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sigurdsson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hard</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niklasson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ewald</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Postnatal head growth deficit among premature infants parallels retinopathy of prematurity and insulin-like growth factor-1 deficit</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>1930</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1542/peds.2005-1926" xlink:type="simple">10.1542/peds.2005-1926</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740833</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okuma</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname> <given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avila</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavada</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Microstructural brain and multivoxel spectroscopy in very low birth weight infants related to insulin-like growth factor concentration and early growth</article-title>. <source>Horm Res Paediatr</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000348517" xlink:type="simple">10.1159/000348517</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23594793</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0171650.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van de Lagemaat</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rotteveel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heijboer</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lafeber</surname> <given-names>HN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Weissenbruch</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Growth in preterm infants until six months postterm: the role of insulin and IGF-I</article-title>. <source>Horm Res Paediatr</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1159/000351710" xlink:type="simple">10.1159/000351710</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23817055</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>