<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149250</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-23766</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Sedation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Quality of life</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Palliative care</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health care</subject><subj-group><subject>Patients</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Drugs</subject><subj-group><subject>Sedatives</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cultural anthropology</subject><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Religion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental health and psychiatry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and analysis methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research design</subject><subj-group><subject>Survey research</subject><subj-group><subject>Questionnaires</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>No Negative Impact of Palliative Sedation on Relatives’ Experience of the Dying Phase and Their Wellbeing after the Patient’s Death: An Observational Study</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">No Negative Impact of PS on Relatives' Wellbeing after Patient's Death</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Bruinsma</surname>
<given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>van der Heide</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>van der Lee</surname>
<given-names>M. L.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="econtrib001"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Vergouwe</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="econtrib001"><sup>‡</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Rietjens</surname>
<given-names>J. A. C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Public Health, Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Helen Dowling Institute, Bilthoven, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Simeoni</surname>
<given-names>Umberto</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois, FRANCE</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001">
<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SB JR AvdH MvdL. Performed the experiments: SB. Analyzed the data: SB JR YV AvdH. Wrote the paper: SB JR YV AvdH MvdL.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001">
<p>‡ These authors also contributed equally to this work.</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">s.m.bruinsma@erasmusmc.nl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>12</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2016</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<elocation-id>e0149250</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>2</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2015</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>28</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2016</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Bruinsma et al</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149250"/>
<abstract>
<sec id="sec001">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Palliative sedation is the widely-used intervention of administering sedating agents to induce a state of unconsciousness to take away a dying patient’s perception of otherwise irrelievable symptoms. However, it remains questionable whether this ethically complex intervention is beneficial for patients and whether the associated lack of communication in the last phase of life has a negative impact on relatives’ wellbeing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>An observational questionnaire study was conducted among relatives of a consecutive sample of patients who died a non-sudden death in the Erasmus MC Cancer Institute or in the hospice ‘Laurens Cadenza’ (both in Rotterdam) between 2010 and 2013.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec003">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Relatives filled in questionnaires regarding 151 patients who had been sedated and 90 patients who had not been sedated. The median time since all patients had passed away was 21 (IQR 14–32) months. No significant differences were found in relatives´ assessments of the quality of end-of-life care, patients´ quality of life in the last week before death and their quality of dying, between patients who did and did not receive sedation, or in relatives’ satisfaction with their own life, their general health and their mental wellbeing after the patient’s death.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The use of sedation in these patients appears to have no negative effect on bereaved relatives’ evaluation of the patient’s dying phase, or on their own wellbeing after the patient’s death.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<funding-statement>The research on which this paper is based is linked to a larger project, the 'UNBIASED' study (UK - Netherlands - Belgium InternAtional SEDation study) is a collaboration between research teams in the UK, Belgium and the Netherlands with funding from the Economic and Social Research Council (UK), the Research Foundation Flanders (BE), the Flemish Cancer Association (BE), the Research Council of Ghent University (BE), the Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research (NL) and the Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and Development (NL) (grant number: 11510006). Dr. Rietjens was supported by the Innovational Research Incentives Scheme Veni of the Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research (NWO) and the ‘For Women in Science’ fellowship of UNESCO and L'Oréal. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="2"/>
<table-count count="3"/>
<page-count count="13"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec005" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>A frequently-used last resort intervention in end-of-life care is palliative sedation, i.e. the administration of sedating drugs to induce a state of unconsciousness to take away a dying patient’s perception of symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref001">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref003">3</xref>]. A European study undertaken in 6 countries in 2001/2 reported that continuous deep sedation until death was used for 2.5–8.5% of all dying patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref002">2</xref>]. Subsequent studies indicate that sedation was used for 15% of deceased persons in Flanders [Belgium] in 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref004">4</xref>], in 12% of all deceased persons in the Netherlands in 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref005">5</xref>], and in 17% of all deceased persons in the UK in 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref007">7</xref>]. Palliative sedation is used in all settings where patients die, but most often in hospitals and for patients with cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref002">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref008">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref010">10</xref>]. While palliative sedation is often seen as an indispensable intervention to alleviate severe suffering in the dying phase, it is also heavily criticized for its resemblance to euthanasia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref011">11</xref>], and for depriving patients of the ability to communicate when many of them strongly endorse the importance of being mentally aware [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref012">12</xref>]. Moreover, its use can be disturbing for the patient’s relatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref013">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref014">14</xref>]. For example, the start of sedation may be the moment at which the family becomes aware that the patient’s death is imminent and/or the intimacy of family care may be disrupted by the introduction of a medical technology, such as sedation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref001">1</xref>].</p>
<p>Professionals working in palliative care stress the importance of good care for the relatives of the patient, because they are often present during the last period of the patient’s life and are closely involved with the patient. However, a literature review revealed that few studies have examined the experience of relatives with palliative sedation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref015">15</xref>]; this review also showed that relatives’ experiences were mainly studied from the perspective of the professional caregivers. The authors conclude that most of the relatives had positive feelings regarding the use of palliative sedation, e.g. because palliative sedation helped to decrease the patient’s symptom distress. Finally, although most relatives reported to be comfortable with the use of sedation, some experienced the use of sedation as distressing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref015">15</xref>].</p>
<p>The reasons for such distress include: i) the feeling that the patient still suffers while receiving sedation, ii) the inability to interact with the patient after the start of sedation, iii) feeling the burden of responsibility for the decision to start sedation, iv) concerns about a possibly hastened death, v) the (long) duration of the sedation, vi) the fact that information about the sedation cannot easily be obtained, and vii) the idea that there might be more appropriate ways to provide symptom relief [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref014">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref017">17</xref>]. As a result, sedation may negatively influence relatives’ experience of the patient’s dying phase, as well as their wellbeing after the patient’s death.</p>
<p>Insight into the potential consequences of the use of palliative sedation can support the development of evidence-based care strategies to improve the death experience for terminally ill patients and their relatives. Although most palliative care efforts focus on assessing and improving quality of life and quality of care for patients, many studies also emphasize the importance of taking good care of the patient’s relatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref018">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref020">20</xref>].</p>
<p>Therefore, this study examines whether the relatives of patients who receive palliative sedation differ in their experience of the dying phase and their wellbeing after the patient’s death compared to the relatives of patients who died a non-sudden death without the use of palliative sedation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Study population and recruitment of participants</title>
<p>An observational study was conducted among relatives of a consecutive sample of 564 patients who had died a non-sudden death at the Erasmus MC Cancer Institute (a large academic hospital in the Netherlands with a specialized inpatient unit for palliative cancer care), or at the hospice ‘Laurens Cadenza’ (with 20 beds, the largest inpatient palliative care center in the Netherlands for patients for whom death is imminent) in Rotterdam between 2010 and 2013.</p>
<p>Relatives were not necessarily restricted to family members, but could also include significant others (e.g. close friends, etc.). Relatives who were registered as the contact person of the patient in the medical file were invited to take part in the study via an information letter sent by a senior clinical staff member of the two participating locations. If the relatives were willing to participate they were asked to fill in the questionnaire. If the relatives were not willing to participate they were asked to inform the research team via an answering sheet, or to ignore the invitation. When the relatives did not respond within six weeks, they received a reminder.</p>
<p>The study was approved by the Medical Ethical committee of the Erasmus MC (No. NL33327.078.10, v03). All participants gave written informed consent before participation in the study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Questionnaire</title>
<p>The questionnaire covered several topics shown to be important based on a systematic review on the experiences of relatives with palliative sedation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref015">15</xref>]. Further, main themes relating to relatives’ experiences were identified in a focus group study among 14 relatives of patients who received palliative sedation until death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref021">21</xref>] and in an interview study among 38 relatives of 32 cancer patients who received continuous sedation until death in three European countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref022">22</xref>]. The study questionnaire was based on several validated questionnaires [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref023">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref030">30</xref>]; all instruments have adequate psychometric properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref024">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref027">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref030">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref034">34</xref>].</p>
<p>To assess whether or not the patient had received sedation prior to death, relatives were asked the self-constructed question: ‘Has your relative been brought to sleep with medication prior to death?’ (yes/no/don’t know).</p>
<p>Relatives’ experience of the dying phase was assessed with three items that were derived from the Quality of Death and Dying questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref023">23</xref>]: ratings on a 0–10 scale of 1) the patient’s quality of life in the last week before death, 2) their quality of dying, and 3) the quality of end-of-life care. On these scales, 0 represented a ‘terrible experience’ and 10 an ‘almost perfect experience’.</p>
<p>Relatives’ wellbeing after the patient’s death was assessed with several items. Relatives’ satisfaction with life 3 months after the patient’s death and at the time of the survey was measured with the Cantril Ladder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref024">24</xref>], i.e. a picture of a ladder numbered from 0 on the bottom rung (worst possible life) to 10 on the top rung (best possible life). Relatives’ general health was assessed with a single item from the Short Form 36 Health Survey (SF-36), a self-report questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref025">25</xref>] on which a score of 1 indicates poor health and a score of 5 excellent health. Mental wellbeing in the 4 weeks prior to the survey was assessed with the SF-36, which includes 5 items about mental health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref025">25</xref>]; scores were linearly transformed from a 1–6 to a 0–5 scale. The sum score had a minimum of 0 and a maximum of 25. A low score indicates poor mental wellbeing (feelings of nervousness and depression all the time), and a high score implies excellent mental wellbeing (feels peaceful, happy, and calm all the time).</p>
<p>Questions on the sociodemographic characteristics of the deceased person and the relative were added by the research team [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref026">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref027">27</xref>]. These included questions about age, sex, relatives’ relationship to the patient (Married or partner/Child/ Other), highest level of education (Low = primary education + lower vocational education + lower secondary education; Intermediate = intermediate vocational education + upper secondary education; High = higher vocational education or university) and religion [Catholic/Christian/Other (e.g. Buddhism, Hinduism, Judaism)/No religion]. Items on relatives’ involvement in the care for the patient and the decision-making process, and the provision of information were based on the VOICES questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref028">28</xref>]. Relatives were asked: 1) if they were involved in the care for the patient by the professional caregivers in the last week of life (Yes/No); 2) if they perceived the degree of involvement in care for the patient by the professional caregivers in the last week of life as sufficient (Yes/No, would have preferred more involvement/No, would have preferred less involvement); 3) if they perceived the amount of information received from professional caregivers about the situation of the patient and care for the patient during the last week of life as sufficient (Yes/No, received too much information/No, received too little information); 4) if they had the opportunity to say goodbye to the patient (Yes/More or less/No); 5) if they were present at the death of the patient (Yes/No, but another relative was present/No, and no other relatives were present); 6) if the professional caregivers could have done something to make the period before the death of the patient more bearable for the relative (Yes/No); and 7) if the professional caregivers could have done something for them to make the period after the death of the patient more bearable for the relative (Yes/No). The severity of the patient’s symptoms during the last week of life was assessed using items from the Edmonton Symptom Assessment System (ESAS) and the Structured Interview for Symptoms and Concerns (SISC) questionnaire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref029">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref030">30</xref>]. The scale comprised 15 items, including 7 physical symptoms (i.e. pain, nausea/vomiting, dyspnea, confusion, restlessness, consciousness, fatigue) and 8 psychological symptoms (i.e. depression, anxiety, loss of control, loss of dignity, burden for environment, loss of interest, hopelessness, longing for death). Scores per item ranged from 1–5; the sum score had a minimum of 15 (not severe) and a maximum of 75 (very severe). The cause of death was recorded as ‘cancer’ or ‘other’ (cerebrovascular accident, respiratory diseases, dementia, heart failure and other diseases).</p>
<p>The content of the questionnaire was piloted among five respondents; this led to some minor changes in the formulation of the questions. In July and August 2013, 564 questionnaires were sent to potential participants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>Data analyses</title>
<p>Multivariable linear regression analysis was performed to assess whether the relatives of patients who received sedation differed in their experience of the dying phase and their wellbeing after the patient’s death from the relatives of patients who had died a non-sudden death without the use of palliative sedation. Because the error of the variance varied for several models (heteroscedasticity), robust estimates of standard errors and confidence intervals were assessed with bootstrapping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref035">35</xref>]. To be consistent, this method was used for all models. Logistic regression was used to assess the association between the use of sedation (yes/no) and personal and care characteristics. Those variables that showed an association (p-value ≤ 0.30) were included in the main multivariable linear regression model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149250.g001">Fig 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0149250.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Model analyses.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Of the 564 relatives who were approached, 243 (45%) were willing to participate. Because two relatives did not answer the question on whether sedation had been administered 241 relatives (43%) were included, of which 151 (63%) concerned relatives of patients who had died after the use of palliative sedation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149250.g002">Fig 2</xref> presents an overview of the inclusion of the relatives in the present study.</p>
<fig id="pone.0149250.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Flowchart of the inclusion of study participants.</title>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>The characteristics of the deceased patients and their relatives are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0149250.t001">Table 1</xref>. The median age at death of the non-sedated patients was slightly higher [77 (IQR 70–86) years] than that of the sedated patients [71 (IQR 62–81)] years (p = 0.002). Patients who received sedation prior to death more often died of cancer (92%) than patients who did not receive sedation (77%) (p = 0.002). Further, the median score for severity of symptoms during the last week of life was slightly higher (worse) for sedated patients [42 (IQR 34–52)] than for non-sedated patients [38 (IQR 30–46)] (p = 0.008). No significant differences were found with regard to patient’s sex, religion and place of death. Relatives of sedated patients were more often female (68%) than relatives of non-sedated patients (51%) (p = 0.007). No significant differences were found between both groups with regard to relatives’ relationship to the patient, age, education, religion, and time elapsed since bereavement.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0149250.t001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.t001</object-id>
<label>Table 1</label> <caption><title>Characteristics of the deceased patients and their relatives (n = 241).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0149250.t001g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="center"/>
<th align="center">No sedation (n = 90 patients)</th>
<th align="center">Sedation (n = 151 patients)</th>
<th align="center">p-value of difference<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001"><sup>A</sup></xref> Unadjusted</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Deceased patients</italic></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Sex</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Female</italic></td>
<td align="center">50 (56%)</td>
<td align="center">71 (47%)</td>
<td align="center">0.187</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Male</italic></td>
<td align="center">39 (44%)</td>
<td align="center">79 (53%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Age in years</bold> median (IQR) (n = 228)</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center">77 (70–86)</td>
<td align="center">71 (62–81)</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Religion</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Catholic</italic></td>
<td align="center">17 (22%)</td>
<td align="center">22 (17%)</td>
<td align="center">0.338</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Christian</italic></td>
<td align="center">21 (28%)</td>
<td align="center">31 (23%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Other</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn002"><sup>B</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">6 (8%)</td>
<td align="center">23 (17%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No religion</italic></td>
<td align="center">32 (42%)</td>
<td align="center">57 (43%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="center">14</td>
<td align="center">18</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Cause of death</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Cancer</italic></td>
<td align="center">62 (77%)</td>
<td align="center">133 (92%)</td>
<td align="center">0.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Other</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003"><sup>C</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">19 (23%)</td>
<td align="center">12 (8%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="center">9</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Place of death</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Hospice</italic></td>
<td align="center">83 (92%)</td>
<td align="center">138 (91%)</td>
<td align="center">0.821</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Hospital</italic></td>
<td align="center">7 (8%)</td>
<td align="center">13 (9%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Severity of symptoms during last week of life</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn004"> <sup>D</sup></xref> <italic>median (IQR)</italic> (n = 201)</td>
<td align="left"><italic>Overall score</italic></td>
<td align="center">38 (30–46)</td>
<td align="center">42 (34–52)</td>
<td align="center">0.008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><italic>Relatives</italic></td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Relatives’ relationship to patient</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Married/ partner</italic></td>
<td align="center">24 (27%)</td>
<td align="center">51 (36%)</td>
<td align="center">.581</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Child</italic></td>
<td align="center">42 (48%)</td>
<td align="center">54 (38%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Parent</italic></td>
<td align="center">5 (6%)</td>
<td align="center">12 (8%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Other</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn005"><sup>E</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">17 (19%)</td>
<td align="center">26 (18%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Sex</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Male</italic></td>
<td align="center">44 (49%)</td>
<td align="center">47 (32%)</td>
<td align="center">0.007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Female</italic></td>
<td align="center">45 (51%)</td>
<td align="center">101 (68%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Age in years</bold> median (IQR) (n = 237)</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center">57 (49–66)</td>
<td align="center">59 (50–65)</td>
<td align="center">0.465</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Education</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn006"><sup>F</sup></xref></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Low</italic></td>
<td align="center">37 (44%)</td>
<td align="center">43 (31%)</td>
<td align="center">0.400</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Intermediate</italic></td>
<td align="center">18 (21%)</td>
<td align="center">55 (39%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>High</italic></td>
<td align="center">29 (35%)</td>
<td align="center">43 (31%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Religion</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Catholic</italic></td>
<td align="center">10 (13%)</td>
<td align="center">15 (12%)</td>
<td align="center">0.132</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Protestant</italic></td>
<td align="center">20 (25%)</td>
<td align="center">33 (25%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Other</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn002"><sup>B</sup></xref></td>
<td align="center">5 (6%)</td>
<td align="center">19 (15%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No religion</italic></td>
<td align="center">44 (56%)</td>
<td align="center">63 (48%)</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="center">11</td>
<td align="center">21</td>
<td align="center"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Time in months since bereavement</bold> median (IQR) (n = 234)</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="center">20 (14–31)</td>
<td align="center">22 (15–32)</td>
<td align="center">0.592</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t001fn001"><p><sup>A</sup> Difference test is based on logistic regression analysis (univariable). Reference group is ‘no sedation’.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn002"><p><sup>B</sup> E.g. Buddhism, Hinduism, Judaism</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn003"><p><sup>C</sup> cerebrovascular accident, respiratory diseases, dementia, heart failure and other diseases</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn004"><p><sup>D</sup> Scale consisting of 15 items with range 1–5. Total scale score with a minimum of 15 (not severe) and a maximum of 75 (very severe). Symptoms: pain, nausea/vomiting, dyspnea, confusion, restlessness, depression, anxiety, consciousness, fatigue, loss of control, loss of dignity, burden for environment, loss of interest, hopelessness, longing for death.</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn005"><p><sup>E</sup> Sibling, grandchild, cousin, family-in-law, aunt/uncle</p></fn>
<fn id="t001fn006"><p><sup>F</sup> Low = primary education + lower vocational education + lower secondary education; Intermediate = intermediate vocational education + upper secondary education; High = higher vocational education or university</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Relatives of sedated patients more often stated that the professional caregivers could have done more to make the period before the death of the patient more bearable (n = 31, 20%) than relatives of non-sedated patients (n = 7, 8%) (p = 0.013). Such statements included suggestions to provide ‘more information’, e.g. regarding the drugs that were administered and the duration of the sedation, to provide ‘more compassioned care’, e.g. by being more attentive to relatives or offering a listening ear when needed, and general suggestions to provide ‘better care’. Otherwise, we found no significant differences between the groups in the characteristics of the care provided during the last week of life (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0149250.t002">Table 2</xref>). Relatives of non-sedated patients were involved in the care for the patient in 74% of the cases, and relatives of sedated patients in 83% of the cases (p = 0.093). Relatives perceived the degree of their involvement as sufficient in 84% and 88% of the cases, respectively (p = 0.357). For those relatives who perceived the degree of their involvement to be insufficient, all except one would have preferred more involvement. Relatives of non-sedated patients perceived the amount of information they received from professional caregivers about the patient’s situation and care during the last week of life as sufficient in 82% of the cases, compared to 88% of the relatives of sedated patients (p = 0.191). All relatives who did not perceive the amount of information as sufficient wished they had received more information. Relatives of non-sedated patients had had the opportunity to say goodbye to the patient in 53% of the cases and they had ‘more or less’ had the opportunity in 30%, versus 66% and 24% of relatives of sedated patients, respectively. Relatives of non-sedated patients were present at the patient’s death in 56%, compared to 60% of the relatives of sedated patients. In all cases where the relative was not present at the death of the patient, they indicated that another relative had been present. In total, 6% of the relatives of non-sedated patients stated that the professional caregivers could have done ‘something’ for them to make the period <italic>after</italic> the death of the patient more bearable, compared to 5% of the relatives of sedated patients (p = 0.700).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0149250.t002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.t002</object-id>
<label>Table 2</label> <caption><title>Care characteristics (n = 241 relatives).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0149250.t002g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">No sedation (n = 90)</th>
<th align="left">Sedation (n = 151)</th>
<th align="left">Total</th>
<th align="left">p-value <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Relative was involved in the care for the patient by the professional caregivers in the last week of life</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Yes</italic></td>
<td align="left">67 (74%)</td>
<td align="left">126 (83%)</td>
<td align="left">193 (80%)</td>
<td align="left">.093</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No</italic></td>
<td align="left">23 (26%)</td>
<td align="left">25 (17%)</td>
<td align="left">48 (20%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Relative perceived the degree of involvement in care for the patient by the professional caregivers in the last week of life as sufficient</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Yes</italic></td>
<td align="left">72 (84%)</td>
<td align="left">132 (88%)</td>
<td align="left">204 (86%)</td>
<td align="left">.357</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No</italic></td>
<td align="left">14 (16%)</td>
<td align="left">18 (12%)</td>
<td align="left">32 (14%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="left">4</td>
<td align="left">1</td>
<td align="left">5</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Relative perceived the amount of information received from professional caregivers about the patient’s situation and care during the last week of life as sufficient</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Yes</italic></td>
<td align="left">72 (82%)</td>
<td align="left">132 (88%)</td>
<td align="left">204 (86%)</td>
<td align="left">.191</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No</italic></td>
<td align="left">16 (18%)</td>
<td align="left">18 (12%)</td>
<td align="left">34 (14%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="left">2</td>
<td align="left">1</td>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Relative had the opportunity to say goodbye to the patient</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Yes</italic></td>
<td align="left">48 (53%)</td>
<td align="left">98 (65%)</td>
<td align="left">146 (61%)</td>
<td align="left">.200</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>More or less</italic></td>
<td align="left">27 (30%)</td>
<td align="left">36 (24%)</td>
<td align="left">63 (26%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No</italic></td>
<td align="left">14 (16%)</td>
<td align="left">15 (10%)</td>
<td align="left">29 (12%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="left">1</td>
<td align="left">2</td>
<td align="left">3</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Relative was present at the death of the patient</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Yes</italic></td>
<td align="left">50 (56%)</td>
<td align="left">91 (60%)</td>
<td align="left">141 (58%)</td>
<td align="left">.473</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No</italic></td>
<td align="left">40 (44%)</td>
<td align="left">60 (40%)</td>
<td align="left">100 (42%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Professional caregivers could have done something to make the period <italic>before</italic> the death of the patient more bearable for the relative</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Yes</italic></td>
<td align="left">7 (8%)</td>
<td align="left">31 (20%)</td>
<td align="left">38 (16%)</td>
<td align="left">.013</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No</italic></td>
<td align="left">81 (92%)</td>
<td align="left">120 (80%)</td>
<td align="left">201 (84%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="left">2</td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left">2</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Professional caregivers could have done something to make the period <italic>after</italic> the death of the patient more bearable for the relative</bold></td>
<td align="left"><italic>Yes</italic></td>
<td align="left">5 (6%)</td>
<td align="left">7 (5%)</td>
<td align="left">12 (5%)</td>
<td align="left">.700</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>No</italic></td>
<td align="left">81 (94%)</td>
<td align="left">143 (95%)</td>
<td align="left">224 (95%)</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"/>
<td align="left"><italic>Missing</italic></td>
<td align="left">4</td>
<td align="left">1</td>
<td align="left">5</td>
<td align="left"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t002fn001"><p>a. Difference test is based on logistic regression analysis (univariable). Reference group is ‘no sedation’.</p></fn>
<fn id="t002fn002"><p>* Variable was dichotomized for the logistic regression analysis</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0149250.t003">Table 3</xref> presents relatives’ experience of the dying phase and relatives’ wellbeing after the patient’s death for non-sedated and sedated patients. We found no significant differences between both groups in univariable analyses and multivariable models that controlled for the characteristics of the patients, relatives and care. The median score for the quality of end-of-life care was 9 in both groups, and the median score for quality of life was 4 for non-sedated and 3 for sedated patients. The median score for quality of dying was 8 in both groups. Relatives’ satisfaction with their own life 3 months after the patient’s death was rated at a median of 6 in both groups; at the time of the survey the median scores were 8 and 7, respectively. The median scores on the general health scale were 3 in both groups, and the median scores on mental health were 11 and 12, respectively.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone.0149250.t003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.t003</object-id>
<label>Table 3</label> <caption><title>Experience of the dying phase and wellbeing after the patient’s death: differences between relatives of patients who received no sedation and relatives of patients who died with the use of palliative sedation (n = 241).</title></caption>
<alternatives>
<graphic id="pone.0149250.t003g" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0149250.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
<col align="left" valign="middle"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left">No sedation (n = 90)</th>
<th align="left">Sedation (n = 151)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Univariable regression<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001"><sup>A</sup></xref></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Multivariable regression<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002"><sup>B</sup></xref></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"/>
<th align="left"><italic>Median (IQR)</italic></th>
<th align="left"><italic>Median (IQR)</italic></th>
<th align="right"><italic>p-value</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>β (95% CI)</italic></th>
<th align="right"><italic>p-value</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>β (95% CI)</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="7"><bold><italic>Relatives’ experience of the dying phase</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Quality end of life care</bold><sup><bold>C</bold></sup> (n = 241)</td>
<td align="left">9 (8–9)</td>
<td align="left">9 (8–10)</td>
<td align="center">0.808</td>
<td align="center">0.06 (-0.43–0.52)</td>
<td align="left">0.888</td>
<td align="left">0.04 (-0.57–0.66)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Quality of life of patient last week before death</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003"><sup>C</sup></xref> (n = 241)</td>
<td align="left">4 (2–7)</td>
<td align="left">3 (2–7)</td>
<td align="center">0.356</td>
<td align="center">-0.35 (-1.12–0.30)</td>
<td align="left">0.818</td>
<td align="left">-0.13 (-1.21–0.96)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Quality of dying</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003"><sup>C</sup></xref> (n = 239)</td>
<td align="left">8 (6–8)</td>
<td align="left">8 (6–8)</td>
<td align="center">0.324</td>
<td align="center">0.31 (-0.32–0.99)</td>
<td align="left">0.273</td>
<td align="left">0.46 (-0.37–1.28)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="7"><bold><italic>Relatives’ wellbeing after the patient’s death</italic></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Life satisfaction 3 months after death of the patient</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003"><sup>C</sup></xref> (n = 241)</td>
<td align="left">6 (4–8)</td>
<td align="left">6 (4–7)</td>
<td align="center">0.082</td>
<td align="center">-0.51 (-1.06–0.09)</td>
<td align="left">0.970</td>
<td align="left">0.01 (-0.74–0.77)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Current life satisfaction</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003"><sup>C</sup></xref> (n = 241)</td>
<td align="left">8 (7–8)</td>
<td align="left">7 (6–8)</td>
<td align="center">0.268</td>
<td align="center">-0.26 (-0.67–0.19)</td>
<td align="left">0.581</td>
<td align="left">-0.20 (-0.90–0.51)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>General health</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004"><sup>D</sup></xref> (n = 236)</td>
<td align="left">3 (3–4)</td>
<td align="left">3 (3–3)</td>
<td align="center">0.742</td>
<td align="center">-0.39 (-2.69–1.92)</td>
<td align="left">0.288</td>
<td align="left">1.62 (-1.38–4.62)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left"><bold>Mental health</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn005"><sup>E</sup></xref> (n = 232)</td>
<td align="left">11 (9–14)</td>
<td align="left">12 (12–14)</td>
<td align="center">0.204</td>
<td align="center">0.59 (-0.37–1.50)</td>
<td align="left">0.371</td>
<td align="left">0.61 (-0.73–1.95)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="t003fn001"><p><sup>A</sup> Linear regression (univariable)</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn002"><p><sup>B</sup> Linear regression (multivariable). Adjusted for sex patient, age patient, cause of death, severity symptoms, religion relative, sex relative, involvement relative in care for patient, satisfaction relative with information from caregivers, opportunity to say goodbye to patient and care for relative before the death of the patient (p&lt;0.30)</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn003"><p><sup>C</sup> Range 0–10 (0 = terrible experience, 10 = almost perfect experience)</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn004"><p><sup>D</sup> Range 1–5 (1 = poor health, 5 = excellent health)</p></fn>
<fn id="t003fn005"><p><sup>E</sup> Mental wellbeing 4 weeks before questionnaire. Scale with 5 items. The sum score had a minimum of 0 (low mental wellbeing) and a maximum of 25 (excellent mental wellbeing)</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="sec011" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The aim of this study was to assess whether the relatives of patients who receive palliative sedation differ in their experience of the dying phase and their wellbeing after the patient’s death compared to the relatives of patients who died a non-sudden death without the use of palliative sedation. No significant differences were found in relatives´ assessments of the quality of end-of-life care, patients´ quality of life in the last week before death and their quality of dying. Further, no significant differences were found in relatives’ satisfaction with their own life, and their general health and their mental wellbeing after the patient’s death. It appears that the use of sedation may not have a negative effect on bereaved persons’ experience of the dying phase of their deceased relative or on their own wellbeing after the patient’s death, despite that relatives of sedated patients sometimes state that they lack support from professional caregivers before the death of the patient and that some relatives may experience the use of sedation as distressing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref017">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref036">36</xref>].</p>
<p>Adequate symptom relief is a key to the experience of a ‘good’ death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref037">37</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref039">39</xref>]. Many relatives evaluated the provision of palliative sedation to their severely suffering family member positively because the patient’s suffering is finally alleviated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref021">21</xref>]. The benefit of palliation could explain why no differences were found in relatives’ experience of the dying phase and wellbeing after the patient’s death, despite the fact that relatives of sedated patients report significantly more severe symptoms in the last week of life than relatives of non-sedated patients; this has also been reported by others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref009">9</xref>]. Further, the loss of the ability to communicate with the patient during the sedation, sometimes referred to as a ‘social death’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref040">40</xref>], and a potential life- shortening effect are often considered to be key drawbacks of the use of palliative sedation by healthcare professionals, ethical and legal experts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref011">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref012">12</xref>]. However, in the evaluation of relatives, adequate symptom relief possibly outweighs these drawbacks. The wellbeing of the patient is known to be a crucial factor for the health and welfare of the patient’s relatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref041">41</xref>]. Therefore, adequate symptom relief for the patient might also benefit the wellbeing of relatives.</p>
<p>Providing information to family members and involving them in discussions about medical care and interventions is known to reduce symptoms of post-traumatic stress, anxiety, and depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref042">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref043">43</xref>]. Our study shows that most relatives experienced the amount of information they received from caregivers as sufficient, which might have been an important determinant of their wellbeing after the patient’s death. However, these findings are not fully in line with other studies that highlighted inadequate provision of information and poor communication in end-of-life care in general [19)], or with palliative sedation in particular [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref021">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref022">22</xref>]. One explanation for this could be that our study mainly concerned relatives of patients who were cared for in a hospice (91%), which is a place of care where bereaved family members have relatively few unmet needs regarding information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref044">44</xref>].</p>
<p>The World Health Organization’s definition of palliative care incorporates a support system to help relatives to cope during the patient’s illness and during their own bereavement process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref045">45</xref>]. Indeed, relatives need support for their own wellbeing as well as to enable them to be close to and support the patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref046">46</xref>]. In the present study, most relatives were satisfied with the support provided to them by the professional caregivers before and after the death of the patient. However, 1 in 5 relatives of sedated patients stated that the professional caregivers could have done something to make the period before the death of patient more bearable for them. Since palliative sedation is a far-reaching intervention that often follows a trajectory of intense suffering for the patient, caregivers should specifically focus on comforting, supporting and providing continuous information to the patient’s family when palliative sedation is being considered and while it is being administered.</p>
<p>The present study has several strengths and limitations. Since we conducted a study among relatives of consecutive patients, this implies that the senior clinical staff members could not have made a specific selection of patients or relatives; in addition, the large sample enhances the generalizability of our findings. On the other hand, non-response may have influenced our findings. For instance, persons with more severe feelings of grief are more prone to non-response than those with less feelings of grief [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref047">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref048">48</xref>]. Also, relatives may differ in their interpretation of the question ‘Has your relative been brought to sleep with medication prior to death’. Nevertheless, we think that this descriptive definition is less ambiguous than use of the term ‘palliative sedation’. Moreover, because lay persons have different notions about what this latter term entails [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref049">49</xref>], future studies should provide respondents with a clear definition of palliative sedation at the start of the study. Further, most relatives were recruited via a hospice and the quality of hospice care is generally rated higher than that of hospital care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref050">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref051">51</xref>], also by relatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0149250.ref028">28</xref>]. However, when we corrected the analysis for the place of death, the results remained unchanged. Therefore, regarding comparisons between the patient groups, the place of death is unlikely to have influenced the results. Also, heterogeneity within the investigated population (such as variability in the cause of death), may have lowered the power to find differences between the two patient groups. In the Netherlands, from 2002 onwards both euthanasia and physician-assisted suicide are legally allowed under certain conditions. It seems likely that legalizing euthanasia has an influence on both care practices and perceptions of what is important in end-of-life care. Thus, it should be noted that the present study was conducted within a specific context and that this might diminish the generalizability of our results to, for example, other countries. Finally, estimating the true effect of palliative sedation on relatives’ experiences of the dying phase and their wellbeing after the patient’s death would require an experimental study; however, this is of course not an option for this patient group.</p>
<p>In this study, although selection bias was probably limited, certain groups were not included in our sample, such as young caregivers and ethnic minorities (e.g. Turkish and Moroccan patients). Also, our study focused mainly on the experiences of relatives of cancer patients. Future studies should also include other patient populations, such as patients with dementia.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Based on these findings, the use of sedation does not appear to have a negative influence on bereaved persons’ experience of the dying phase of their deceased relative or on their own wellbeing after the patient’s death. This finding might be attributed to relief of the patient’s severe suffering, or to relatives receiving sufficient information from their caregivers about palliative sedation. Nevertheless, palliative sedation is a far-reaching and ethically complex intervention that requires caregivers to focus on providing comfort, support and continuous information to both the patient and the patient’s family. Future research is necessary to gain a deeper understanding of the factors that contribute to the wellbeing of relatives prior to and after the patient’s death.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors thank the senior clinical staff members of the participating settings for recruitment of the bereaved participants, as well as the bereaved persons who participated in this study. Dr Rietjens was supported by the Innovational Research Incentives Scheme Veni of the Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research (NWO) and the ‘For Women in Science’ fellowship of UNESCO and L'Oréal.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Royal Dutch Medical Association. Guideline for palliative sedation (in Dutch). 2009. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://knmg.artsennet.nl/Publicaties/KNMGpublicatie/Guideline-for-palliativesedation-2009.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://knmg.artsennet.nl/Publicaties/KNMGpublicatie/Guideline-for-palliativesedation-2009.htm</ext-link>. Accessed March, 2014.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miccinesi</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deliens</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paci</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bosshard</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nilstun</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Continuous deep sedation: physicians’ experiences in six European countries</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16488345</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherny</surname> <given-names>NI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Radbruch</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <collab>Board of the European Association for Palliative C</collab>. <article-title>European Association for Palliative Care (EAPC) recommended framework for the use of sedation in palliative care</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0269216309107024" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/0269216309107024</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19858355</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chambaere</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bilsen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onwuteaka-Philipsen</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Continuous deep sedation until death in Belgium: a nationwide survey</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>170</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>490</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2009.542" xlink:type="simple">10.1001/archinternmed.2009.542</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20212190</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onwuteaka-Philipsen</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brinkman-Stoppelenburg</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penning</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong-Krul</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Delden</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trends in end-of-life practices before and after the enactment of the euthanasia law in the Netherlands from 1990 to 2010: a repeated cross-sectional survey</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>380</volume>(<issue>9845</issue>): <fpage>908</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61034-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61034-4</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22789501</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seale</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Continuous deep sedation in medical practice: a descriptive study</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2009.06.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2009.06.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854611</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anquinet</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seale</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seymour</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deliens</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The practice of continuous deep sedation until death in Flanders (Belgium), the Netherlands, and the U.K.: a comparative study</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2011.07.007" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2011.07.007</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22652134</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilsen</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vander Stichele</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broeckaert</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deliens</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Changes in medical end-of-life practices during the legalization process of euthanasia in Belgium</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>65</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17490798</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Delden</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onwuteaka-Philipsen</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buiting</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Maas</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Continuous deep sedation for patients nearing death in the Netherlands: descriptive study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>336</volume>(<issue>7648</issue>): <fpage>810</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.39504.531505.25" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/bmj.39504.531505.25</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18344245</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seale</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>End-of-life decisions in the UK involving medical practitioners</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0269216308102042" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/0269216308102042</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19318459</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billings</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Block</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Slow euthanasia</article-title>. <source>J Palliat Care</source>. <year>1996</year> Winter; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9019033</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinhauser</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christakis</surname> <given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clipp</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McNeilly</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tulsky</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Factors considered important at the end of life by patients, family, physicians, and other care providers</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>284</volume>(<issue>19</issue>): <fpage>2476</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11074777</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ikenaga</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adachi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narabayashi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kizawa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honke</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Concerns of family members of patients receiving palliative sedation therapy</article-title>. <source>Support Care Cancer</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15372223</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ikenaga</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adachi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narabayashi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kizawa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honke</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Family experience with palliative sedation therapy for terminally ill cancer patients</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>28</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15645586</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruinsma</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seymour</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anquinet</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The experiences of relatives with the practice of palliative sedation: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2011.09.006" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2011.09.006</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22658470</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercadante</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Intravaia</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villari</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrera</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casuccio</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Controlled sedation for refractory symptoms in dying patients</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>37</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>771</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2008.04.020" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2008.04.020</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19041216</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dooren</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Veluw</surname> <given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Zuylen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passchier</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Rijt</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Exploration of concerns of relatives during continuous palliative sedation of their family members with cancer</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>452</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2008.11.011" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2008.11.011</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19559563</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinhauser</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voils</surname> <given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bosworth</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tulsky</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>What constitutes quality of family experience at the end of life? Perspectives from family members of patients who died in the hospital</article-title>. <source>Palliat Support Care</source> <year>2014</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andershed</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relatives in end-of-life care- part 1: a systematic review of the literature the five last years, January 1999-February 2004</article-title>. <source>J Clin Nurs</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1158</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911057</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aranda</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Melbourne Family Support Program: evidence-based strategies that prepare family caregivers for supporting palliative care patients</article-title>. <source>BMJ Support Palliat Care</source> <year>2014</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmjspcare-2013-000500" xlink:type="simple">10.1136/bmjspcare-2013-000500</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24644195</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruinsma</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Palliative sedation: a focus group study on the experiences of relatives</article-title>. <source>J Palliat Med</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/jpm.2012.0410" xlink:type="simple">10.1089/jpm.2012.0410</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23421537</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruinsma</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deliens</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anquinet</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Making sense of continuous sedation in end-of-life care for cancer patients: an interview study with bereaved relatives in three European countries</article-title>. <source>Support Care Cancer</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>3243</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00520-014-2344-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00520-014-2344-7</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25022759</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engelberg</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Norris</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asp</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byock</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>A measure of the quality of dying and death. Initial validation using after-death interviews with family members</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12183092</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantril</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <source>The pattern of human concern</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, New Jersey, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>; <year>1965</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names> <suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sherbourne</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name>. <article-title>The MOS 36-item short-form health survey (SF-36). I. Conceptual framework and item selection</article-title>. <source>Medical care</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>30</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>473</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1593914</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veerbeek</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Vogel-Voogt</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Bakker</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Rijt</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Swart</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Using the LCP: bereaved relatives’ assessments of communication and bereavement</article-title>. <source>Am J Hosp Palliat Care</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1049909108315515" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/1049909108315515</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18403578</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Claessen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francke</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sixma</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Putten</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Veer</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <chapter-title>Op weg naar een CQ-index Palliatieve Zorg: meetinstrumentenontwikkeling (in Dutch)</chapter-title>. <publisher-loc>Utrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NIVEL</publisher-name> <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Addington-Hall</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O’Callaghan</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comparison of the quality of care provided to cancer patients in the UK in the last three months of life in in-patient hospices compared with hospitals, from the perspective of bereaved relatives: results from a survey using the VOICES questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>190</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0269216309102525" xlink:type="simple">10.1177/0269216309102525</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19251834</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruera</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuehn</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selmser</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macmillan</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Edmonton Symptom Assessment System (ESAS): a simple method for the assessment of palliative care patients</article-title>. <source>J Palliat Care</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1714502</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viola</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chater</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Faye</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Structured interview assessment of symptoms and concerns in palliative care</article-title>. <source>Can J Psychiatry</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>49</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>350</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15283529</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name>: <article-title>Applying the Cantril methodology to study self-esteem: psychometrics of the self-anchoring self-esteem scale</article-title>. <source>J Nurs Measur</source> <year>1996</year>, <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>189</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snow</surname> <given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kosinski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gandek</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>. <source>SF-36® Health Survey Manual and Interpretation Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New England Medical Center, The Health Institute</publisher-name>, <year>1993</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkova</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>The psychometric properties of cancer multisymptom assessment instruments: a clinical review</article-title>. <source>Support Care Cancer</source> <year>2015</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2189</fpage>–<lpage>2202</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00520-015-2732-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00520-015-2732-7</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25894883</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Addington-Hall</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karlsen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>A randomised controlled trial of postal versus interviewer administration of a questionnaire measuring satisfaction with and use of services received in the year before death</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>802</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10396521</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Efron</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tibshirani</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <source>Introduction to the bootstrap</source>. <publisher-name>Hall/CRC C</publisher-name>, ed <year>1993</year>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ikenaga</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adachi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Narabayashi</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kizawa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honke</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Concerns of family members of patients receiving palliative sedation therapy</article-title>. <source>Support Care Cancer</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>885</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15372223</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierson</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name>. <article-title>A good death: a qualitative study of patients with advanced AIDS</article-title>. <source>AIDS care</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12419108</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onwuteaka-Philipsen</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Maas</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Wal</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Preferences of the Dutch general public for a good death and associations with attitudes towards end-of-life decision-making</article-title>. <source>Palliat Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17060267</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teno</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname> <given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname> <given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edgman-Levitan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Patient-focused, family-centered end-of-life medical care: views of the guidelines and bereaved family members</article-title>. <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>738</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11532587</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seale C</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruinsma</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sterckx</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mathers</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rietjens</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <collab>on behalf of the UNBIASED consortium</collab>. <article-title>The language of sedation in end-of-life care: the ethical reasoning of care providers in three countries</article-title>. <source>Health</source> <year>2014</year> (accepted for publication).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Astedt-Kurki</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paunonen</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehti</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Family members’ experiences of their role in a hospital: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Adv Nursing</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>908</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lautrette</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Darmon</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Megarbane</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joly</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chevret</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adrie</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>A communication strategy and brochure for relatives of patients dying in the ICU</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>356</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17267907</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mack</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trice</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balboni</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Associations between end-of-life discussions, patient mental health, medical care near death, and caregiver bereavement adjustment</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>300</volume>(<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>1665</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/jama.300.14.1665" xlink:type="simple">10.1001/jama.300.14.1665</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18840840</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krawczyk</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Family members’ perceptions of end-of-life care across diverse locations of care</article-title>. <source>BMC Palliat Care</source> <year>2013</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>25</fpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1472-684X-12-25" xlink:type="simple">10.1186/1472-684X-12-25</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23870101</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization. ‘Definition of palliative care’, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/cancer/palliative/definition/en" xlink:type="simple">http://www.who.int/cancer/palliative/definition/en</ext-link> (2008, accessed January 2015).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andershed</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ternestedt</surname> <given-names>BM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Involvement of relatives in care of the dying in different care cultures: development of a theoretical understanding</article-title>. <source>Nursing Sci Quarter</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stroebe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stroebe</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name>. <article-title>Who participates in bereavement research? A review and empirical study</article-title>. <source>J Death Dying</source> <year>1989</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swarte</surname> <given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Lee</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Bom</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Bout</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heintz</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of euthanasia on the bereaved family and friends: a cross sectional study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>327</volume>(<issue>7408</issue>):<fpage>189</fpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12881258</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">van Delden JJM, Van Der Heide A, van de Vathorst S, Weyers H, van Tol D. Knowledge and opinions of the general public and professionals on medical decision making and treatment in the end of life, the KOPPEL-research (in Dutch). ZonMw 2011. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zonmw.nl/uploads/tx_vipublicaties/ZonMw_A4_RapportKOPPELDEF_klein.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.zonmw.nl/uploads/tx_vipublicaties/ZonMw_A4_RapportKOPPELDEF_klein.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 13 Sep 2013).</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greer</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mor</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwood</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kidder</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Birnbaum</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>An alternative in terminal care: results of the National Hospice Study</article-title>. <source>J Chronic Dis</source> <year>1986</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3511081</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0149250.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kane</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wales</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernstein</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leibowitz</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>A randomised controlled trial of hospice care</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>1984</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>8382</issue>):<fpage>890</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6143195</object-id></mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>